<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03823365</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EudraCT Nr 2018-000086-36</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03823365</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blinatumomab Expanded T-cells (BET) in Indolent Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas/Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>BET2017</acronym>
  <official_title>Immune Reconstitution With Blinatumomab Expanded T-cells (BET) After First-line Treatment With Fludarabine-Cyclophosphamide-Rituximab or Bendamustine-Rituximab in CD20+ Indolent Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas/Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia: a Phase I Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>A.O. Ospedale Papa Giovanni XXIII</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>A.O. Ospedale Papa Giovanni XXIII</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Non-Hodgkin CD20 + Indolent Lymphoma (iNHL) and Chronic Lymphatic Leukemia (CLL) are the most
      frequent neoplasms of B lymphocytes. They include various histologies (follicular NHL,
      marginal zone NHL and Lymphocytic NHL/ CLL) characterized by a chronic course and prolonged
      survival, but while patients with a limited disease could be cured, those with advanced
      disease or relapsed after localized radiation therapy are generally considered untreatable
      through standard treatments. The options for first-line therapy include the use of the FCR
      scheme, based on Fludarabine, Cyclophosphamide and Rituximab or the BR, with Bendamustine and
      Rituximab. Despite good results, treatment with these two regimens (FCR or BR) is associated
      with severe immunosuppression which worsens the immunological dysfunction already present at
      diagnosis in several patients. It has been shown previously that the adoptive transfer of ex
      vivo anti-CD3/CD28 co-stimulated autologous T cells can successfully accelerate a robust
      early recovery of T cells after autologous transplantation in multiple myeloma. These
      CD3/CD28 expanded T cells cannot however be used in NHLi and CLL due to the presence of
      contaminating tumor cells in the preparation. Polyclonal T cells can also be expanded in
      vitro in presence of Blinatumomab and recombinant human IL2 (rhIL2) and have been called BET
      (Blinatumomab-expanded T cells). They are a product of Advanced Therapeutic Medicinal Product
      (ATMP) composed of polyclonal CD8 and CD4 T cells that are still functional and devoid of
      contaminating CD19+ neoplastic cells. Based on these data, it was hypothesized that infusion
      of BET in patients with iNHL/CLL, after the first treatment line (with FCR or BR), could
      induce adequate immunological recovery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Indolent non-Hodgkin lymphomas (iNHL) and chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) are among
           the most frequent B-cell neoplasms. They include different histologies (i.e. follicular
           NHL, marginal zone NHL and lymphocytic NHL/CLL) characterized by chronic course and
           prolonged survival. While some patients with limited stage disease may be cured, those
           presenting with advance stage or relapsing after local radiotherapy are generally
           considered not curable with standard treatments.

        -  First-line treatment of CLL/LL is currently based on the biologic profile of the
           disease. Excluding high risk patients harboring the del(17p) and/or TP53 mutations,
           first line chemoimmunotherapy options includes the use of either fludarabine,
           cyclophosphamide and rituximab (FCR) or BR. Despite the good results, treatment with FCR
           or BR regimens is associated with severe immunosuppression that worsens the immune
           dysfunctions already present at diagnosis in several patients. In the CLL phase III
           trial, high frequency of grade 3/4 infections was reported in FCR and BR, being observed
           in 39% and 25% of the patients, respectively. In iNHL, infections have been observed in
           37-55% of the patients treated with BR, with grade 3/4 events in 7-12% of the cases.

        -  Blinatumomab-expanded T cells (BET) are an Advanced Therapeutic Medicinal Product (ATMP)
           composed of autologous polyclonal activated T cells expanded in vitro using blinatumomab
           and rhIL-2, to be used for somatic cell therapy in an autologous setting. Indeed the
           investigators have developed a method using blinatumomab and rhIL2 to expand and
           activate ex vivo the T lymphocytes present in the peripheral blood from CLL and iNHL
           patients, while at the same time eliminating contaminating CD19+ neoplastic cells. The
           resulting polyclonal T cells can be used for immuno-reconstitution purposes. The Cell
           Factory &quot;Centro di Terapia Cellulare G. Lanzani&quot; showed the functionality of BET in a
           mouse B-cell NHL xenograft model. Upon in vivo inoculation, BET retain functional
           activity: upon engagement with blinatumomab in vivo, BET were able to efficiently kill
           the B-cell NHL cells. Importantly, BET did not showed any toxicity in animals, even at
           high doses and in presence of blinatumomab.

        -  About clinical experience, it has been previously shown that adoptive transfer of ex
           vivo (anti-CD3/anti-CD28) co-stimulated autologous T cells can successfully accelerate a
           robust T-cell recovery early after autologous transplant for multiple myeloma. However,
           the invariable presence of clonal disease in cell product of iNHL/CLL patients hampered
           this possibility up to now. In contrast BET cell expansion leads to lysis of
           contaminating neoplastic cells. BET can therefore be expanded from CLL patients
           peripheral blood in GMP (Good Manufacturing Practice) conditions for adoptive therapy.
           Starting from only 10 mL of peripheral blood, a mean 5.15x108 CD3+ cells can be expanded
           in 3 weeks with a rapid clearance of CLL contamination. The resulting
           blinatumomab-expanded T cells (BET) were polyclonal CD4+ and CD8+ T cells and mostly
           effector and central memory cells. They showed a normalized expression of the synapse
           inhibitors CD272 and CD279 compared with starting T cells and were functionally active,
           showing cytotoxicity against CD19+ targets in presence of Blinatumomab in vitro and in
           vivo.

        -  On the basis of these data the investigators hypothesize that BET infusion after
           first-line treatment of iNHL/CLL with either FCR or BR could lead to an adequate immune
           recovery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 17, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>CD20+ Indolent Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas/Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Patients After First-line Treatment with Fludarabine-Cyclophosphamide-Rituximab or Bendamustine-Rituximab.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>This study is a phase I open-label, single center study. The patient population will consist of adults diagnosed with indolent non-Hodgkin lymphomas (iNHL) or chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) in need of first line treatment consisting of either FCR or BR as per investigator assessment. Chemotherapy treatment will consist of a minimum of 4 to a maximum of 6 cycles of standard FCR or BR.Patients will be enrolled in the study after the last planned cycle of chemo-immunotherapy and, if eligibility criteria are met, BET dose level will be assigned.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of grade 3 or 4 adverse events (AE) possibly related to therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>The period of observation is during 14 days after BET infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Description and grading of all adverse events will be based on the NCI -CTCAE v4.03 and MedDra code (current version).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse event (AE) and laboratory abnormalities.</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of study start up to 180 days after BET infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Number, causality and intensity of all adverse events will be evaluated according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) V4.03 and MedDRA code (current version).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Optimal Biological Dose (ODB) of BET cells</measure>
    <time_frame>+90 days after infusion</time_frame>
    <description>OBD of BET will be defined as the absolute number of BET cell that will allow a CD3+ count of &gt; 600 x106/L at +90 days after infusion in at least 70% of the patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of general Immune Reconstitution after BET infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>at +0 (4 hours), +30, +90 and +180 days after infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute numbers of B, T, and NK cells reconstitution and its correlation with BET cell infused and its composition (in terms of T-cell subsets and NK cells)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of ex vivo transfer of anti-viral immunity</measure>
    <time_frame>at +0 (4 hours), +30, +90 and +180 days after infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Ex vivo transfer of anti-viral immunity in terms of tetramer-based quantification of CMV-specific CD8+ T lymphocytes (this will be done only for CMV positive patients for whom CMV specific tetramers stain positive in starting peripheral blood or BET).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Indolent Non-Hodgkin Lymphomas/Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indolent NHL or CLL patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults diagnosed with indolent non-Hodgkin lymphomas (iNHL) or chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) in need of first line treatment consisting of either FCR or BR as per investigator assessment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blinatumomab Expanded T-cells (BET)</intervention_name>
    <description>Two to five days after the last chemotherapy infusion, BET will be administered. An accelerated titration dose escalation design will be used. During dose escalation, up to four dose levels (see table) will be evaluated or until (Maximum Tolerated Dose) MTD is reached.
Dose level BET dose(Counted on CD3+ cells)
(starting dose) 3.0 x 109
6.0 x 109
9.0 x 109
12.0 x 109</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indolent NHL or CLL patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Male or female patients 18 years or older 2. Confirmed diagnosis of the following
             CD20+ iNHL or CLL according to (World Health Organization ) WHO criteria:

               -  Follicular NHL

               -  Marginal zone NHL (splenic, extranodal or nodal)

               -  Lymphocytic lymphoma/CLL without del(17p) or TP53 mutations 3. No previous
                  chemotherapy. Previous radiotherapy for localized disease is admitted 4.
                  Requirement for treatment:

               -  For CLL, active disease is defined as meeting at least one of the International
                  Workshop on CLL guidelines (Hallek et al., 2008)

               -  For iNHL, active disease is defined as meeting at least one of the Groupe
                  d'Etudes des Lymphomes Folliculaires (GELF) criteria (Brice et al., 1997) 5.
                  Indication to treatment with either fludarabine, cyclophosphamide and rituximab
                  or bendamustine and rituximab 6. Presence of peripheral blood clone ≥10% of total
                  lymphocytes (with absolute lymphocyte count &gt;800 x106/L) at study entrance 7.
                  Written informed consent prior to any study procedures being performed

        Additional inclusion criteria to be met at study entry (i.e. before BET infusion):

        8. Achieving at least a partial response after three chemo-immunotherapy cycles 9. Absence
        of any serious therapy-related complications that might affect interpretation of the
        results of the study or render the subject at high risk from treatment complications 10.
        Production of adequate BET numbers (counted on CD3+ cells: ≥0.5 x 109) 11. For female
        patients:

          1. being postmenopausal for at least 1 year before the screening visit, OR

          2. being surgically sterile, OR

          3. if they are of childbearing potential, must agree to practice highly effective method
             of contraception and one additional effective (barrier) method from the time of
             signing the informed consent until the end of study. Highly effective method of
             contraception includes: (i) combined (estrogen and progestogen containing) hormonal
             contraception associated with inhibition of ovulation: oral, intravaginal,
             transdermal; (ii) progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition
             of ovulation: oral, injectable, implantable (intrauterine device (IUD), intrauterine
             hormone-releasing system (IUS), bilateral tubal occlusion, vasectomized partner,
             sexual abstinence) OR

          4. must agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
             usual lifestyle of the subject from the time of signing the informed consent until the
             end of study. [Periodic abstinence (eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
             postovulation methods), withdrawal, spermicides only, and lactational amenorrhea are
             not acceptable methods of contraception. Female and male condoms should not be used
             together.]

        For male patients, even if surgically sterilized (i.e., status postvasectomy):

          1. with female partners of childbearing potential: must agree to practice barrier
             contraception (condom with or without spermicide) from the time of signing the
             informed consent until the end of study and his female partner must agree to practice
             method of contraception including one of the following: estrogen and progestogen
             containing hormonal contraception; inhibition of ovulation: oral, intravaginal,
             transdermal; progestogen-only hormonal contraception associated with inhibition of
             ovulation: oral, injectable, implantable (intrauterine device (IUD), intrauterine
             hormone-releasing system (IUS), bilateral tubal occlusion) from the time of signing
             the informed consent until the end of study.

          2. must agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
             usual lifestyle of the subject from the time of signing the informed consent until the
             end of study. [Periodic abstinence (eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
             postovulation methods), withdrawal, spermicides only, and lactational amenorrhea are
             not acceptable methods of contraception. Female and male condoms should not be used
             together.]

          3. must agree to refrain from donating sperm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) Performance Status &gt;2

          2. Active central nervous system (CNS) disease

          3. Calculated creatinine clearance (by Cockroft-Gault) of &lt; 50 ml/min or serum creatinine
             &gt; 1.5x ULN (Upper Limit of Normal )

          4. Concomitant or previous diagnosis of autoimmune hemolytic anemia or thrombocytopenia

          5. Subjects with active, known or suspected autoimmune disease. Subjects with vitiligo,
             type I diabetes mellitus, residual hypothyroidism due to autoimmune condition
             requiring the sole hormone replacement are allowed to participate. Psoriasis requiring
             systemic treatment, or conditions expected to recur at the presence of an external
             trigger are excluded.

          6. Known infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or treponema

          7. Active hepatitis B virus (HBV) and/or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infections

          8. Any suspected or known active infection

          9. History of other diseases, metabolic dysfunctions, physical examination findings, or
             clinical laboratory findings giving reasonable suspicion of a disease or condition
             that contraindicates use of an investigational drug or that might affect
             interpretation of the results of the study or render the subject at high risk from
             treatment complications

         10. Residual CD19+ B cells in BET final cell product ≥0.5%
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alessandro Rambaldi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ASST - Papa Giovanni XXIII</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alessandro Rambaldi, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 035 2673683</phone>
    <phone_ext>3683</phone_ext>
    <email>arambaldi@asst-pg23.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Giuseppe Gritti, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+39 035 2673679</phone>
    <phone_ext>3679</phone_ext>
    <email>g.gritti@asst-pg23.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST - Papa Giovanni XXIII</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergamo</city>
        <zip>24127</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alessandro Rambaldi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 035 2673683</phone>
      <phone_ext>3683</phone_ext>
      <email>arambaldi@asst-pg23.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Giuseppe Gritti, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+39 035 2673679</phone>
      <phone_ext>3679</phone_ext>
      <email>g.gritti@asst-pg23.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Federico Lussana, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Martino Introna, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Josee Golay, Biol. Sc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ardeshna KM, Smith P, Norton A, Hancock BW, Hoskin PJ, MacLennan KA, Marcus RE, Jelliffe A, Vaughan G, Hudson, Linch DC; British National Lymphoma Investigation. Long-term effect of a watch and wait policy versus immediate systemic treatment for asymptomatic advanced-stage non-Hodgkin lymphoma: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2003 Aug 16;362(9383):516-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12932382</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berdeja JG, Hess A, Lucas DM, O'Donnell P, Ambinder RF, Diehl LF, Carter-Brookins D, Newton S, Flinn IW. Systemic interleukin-2 and adoptive transfer of lymphokine-activated killer cells improves antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity in patients with relapsed B-cell lymphoma treated with rituximab. Clin Cancer Res. 2007 Apr 15;13(8):2392-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17438098</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bomberger C, Singh-Jairam M, Rodey G, Guerriero A, Yeager AM, Fleming WH, Holland HK, Waller EK. Lymphoid reconstitution after autologous PBSC transplantation with FACS-sorted CD34+ hematopoietic progenitors. Blood. 1998 Apr 1;91(7):2588-600.</citation>
    <PMID>9516161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brice P, Bastion Y, Lepage E, Brousse N, Haïoun C, Moreau P, Straetmans N, Tilly H, Tabah I, Solal-Céligny P. Comparison in low-tumor-burden follicular lymphomas between an initial no-treatment policy, prednimustine, or interferon alfa: a randomized study from the Groupe d'Etude des Lymphomes Folliculaires. Groupe d'Etude des Lymphomes de l'Adulte. J Clin Oncol. 1997 Mar;15(3):1110-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9060552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Fisher RI, Barrington SF, Cavalli F, Schwartz LH, Zucca E, Lister TA; Alliance, Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group; European Mantle Cell Lymphoma Consortium; Italian Lymphoma Foundation; European Organisation for Research; Treatment of Cancer/Dutch Hemato-Oncology Group; Grupo Español de Médula Ósea; German High-Grade Lymphoma Study Group; German Hodgkin's Study Group; Japanese Lymphorra Study Group; Lymphoma Study Association; NCIC Clinical Trials Group; Nordic Lymphoma Study Group; Southwest Oncology Group; United Kingdom National Cancer Research Institute. Recommendations for initial evaluation, staging, and response assessment of Hodgkin and non-Hodgkin lymphoma: the Lugano classification. J Clin Oncol. 2014 Sep 20;32(27):3059-68.</citation>
    <PMID>25113753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chemotherapeutic options in chronic lymphocytic leukemia: a meta-analysis of the randomized trials. CLL Trialists' Collaborative Group. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 May 19;91(10):861-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10340906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cockcroft DW, Gault MH. Prediction of creatinine clearance from serum creatinine. Nephron. 1976;16(1):31-41.</citation>
    <PMID>1244564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Darwish M, Bond M, Hellriegel E, Robertson P Jr, Chovan JP. Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile of bendamustine and its metabolites. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol. 2015 Jun;75(6):1143-54. doi: 10.1007/s00280-015-2727-6. Epub 2015 Apr 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25829094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grupp SA, Kalos M, Barrett D, Aplenc R, Porter DL, Rheingold SR, Teachey DT, Chew A, Hauck B, Wright JF, Milone MC, Levine BL, June CH. Chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells for acute lymphoid leukemia. N Engl J Med. 2013 Apr 18;368(16):1509-1518. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1215134. Epub 2013 Mar 25. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2016 Mar 10;374(10):998.</citation>
    <PMID>23527958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hallek M, Cheson BD, Catovsky D, Caligaris-Cappio F, Dighiero G, Döhner H, Hillmen P, Keating MJ, Montserrat E, Rai KR, Kipps TJ; International Workshop on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia. Guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of chronic lymphocytic leukemia: a report from the International Workshop on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia updating the National Cancer Institute-Working Group 1996 guidelines. Blood. 2008 Jun 15;111(12):5446-56. doi: 10.1182/blood-2007-06-093906. Epub 2008 Jan 23. Erratum in: Blood. 2008 Dec 15;112(13):5259.</citation>
    <PMID>18216293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Introna M, Borleri G, Conti E, Franceschetti M, Barbui AM, Broady R, Dander E, Gaipa G, D'Amico G, Biagi E, Parma M, Pogliani EM, Spinelli O, Baronciani D, Grassi A, Golay J, Barbui T, Biondi A, Rambaldi A. Repeated infusions of donor-derived cytokine-induced killer cells in patients relapsing after allogeneic stem cell transplantation: a phase I study. Haematologica. 2007 Jul;92(7):952-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17606446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Introna M, Pievani A, Borleri G, Capelli C, Algarotti A, Micò C, Grassi A, Oldani E, Golay J, Rambaldi A. Feasibility and safety of adoptive immunotherapy with CIK cells after cord blood transplantation. Biol Blood Marrow Transplant. 2010 Nov;16(11):1603-7. doi: 10.1016/j.bbmt.2010.05.015. Epub 2010 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20685246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalamasz D, Long SA, Taniguchi R, Buckner JH, Berenson RJ, Bonyhadi M. Optimization of human T-cell expansion ex vivo using magnetic beads conjugated with anti-CD3 and Anti-CD28 antibodies. J Immunother. 2004 Sep-Oct;27(5):405-18.</citation>
    <PMID>15314550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kochenderfer JN, Dudley ME, Feldman SA, Wilson WH, Spaner DE, Maric I, Stetler-Stevenson M, Phan GQ, Hughes MS, Sherry RM, Yang JC, Kammula US, Devillier L, Carpenter R, Nathan DA, Morgan RA, Laurencot C, Rosenberg SA. B-cell depletion and remissions of malignancy along with cytokine-associated toxicity in a clinical trial of anti-CD19 chimeric-antigen-receptor-transduced T cells. Blood. 2012 Mar 22;119(12):2709-20. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-10-384388. Epub 2011 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22160384</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levine BL, Bernstein WB, Connors M, Craighead N, Lindsten T, Thompson CB, June CH. Effects of CD28 costimulation on long-term proliferation of CD4+ T cells in the absence of exogenous feeder cells. J Immunol. 1997 Dec 15;159(12):5921-30.</citation>
    <PMID>9550389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levine BL, Cotte J, Small CC, Carroll RG, Riley JL, Bernstein WB, Van Epps DE, Hardwick RA, June CH. Large-scale production of CD4+ T cells from HIV-1-infected donors after CD3/CD28 costimulation. J Hematother. 1998 Oct;7(5):437-48.</citation>
    <PMID>9829318</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Löffler A, Gruen M, Wuchter C, Schriever F, Kufer P, Dreier T, Hanakam F, Baeuerle PA, Bommert K, Karawajew L, Dörken B, Bargou RC. Efficient elimination of chronic lymphocytic leukaemia B cells by autologous T cells with a bispecific anti-CD19/anti-CD3 single-chain antibody construct. Leukemia. 2003 May;17(5):900-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12750704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Long-Boyle JR, Green KG, Brunstein CG, Cao Q, Rogosheske J, Weisdorf DJ, Miller JS, Wagner JE, McGlave PB, Jacobson PA. High fludarabine exposure and relationship with treatment-related mortality after nonmyeloablative hematopoietic cell transplantation. Bone Marrow Transplant. 2011 Jan;46(1):20-6. doi: 10.1038/bmt.2010.53. Epub 2010 Apr 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20383215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mackall CL. T-cell immunodeficiency following cytotoxic antineoplastic therapy: a review. Oncologist. 1999;4(5):370-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10551553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maus MV, Thomas AK, Leonard DG, Allman D, Addya K, Schlienger K, Riley JL, June CH. Ex vivo expansion of polyclonal and antigen-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes by artificial APCs expressing ligands for the T-cell receptor, CD28 and 4-1BB. Nat Biotechnol. 2002 Feb;20(2):143-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11821859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagorsen D, Baeuerle PA. Immunomodulatory therapy of cancer with T cell-engaging BiTE antibody blinatumomab. Exp Cell Res. 2011 May 15;317(9):1255-60. doi: 10.1016/j.yexcr.2011.03.010. Epub 2011 Mar 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21419116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rapoport AP, Stadtmauer EA, Aqui N, Badros A, Cotte J, Chrisley L, Veloso E, Zheng Z, Westphal S, Mair R, Chi N, Ratterree B, Pochran MF, Natt S, Hinkle J, Sickles C, Sohal A, Ruehle K, Lynch C, Zhang L, Porter DL, Luger S, Guo C, Fang HB, Blackwelder W, Hankey K, Mann D, Edelman R, Frasch C, Levine BL, Cross A, June CH. Restoration of immunity in lymphopenic individuals with cancer by vaccination and adoptive T-cell transfer. Nat Med. 2005 Nov;11(11):1230-7. Epub 2005 Oct 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16227990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rapoport AP, Stadtmauer EA, Aqui N, Vogl D, Chew A, Fang HB, Janofsky S, Yager K, Veloso E, Zheng Z, Milliron T, Westphal S, Cotte J, Huynh H, Cannon A, Yanovich S, Akpek G, Tan M, Virts K, Ruehle K, Harris C, Philip S, Vonderheide RH, Levine BL, June CH. Rapid immune recovery and graft-versus-host disease-like engraftment syndrome following adoptive transfer of Costimulated autologous T cells. Clin Cancer Res. 2009 Jul 1;15(13):4499-507. doi: 10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-09-0418. Epub 2009 Jun 9.</citation>
    <PMID>19509133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robak T, Lech-Maranda E, Korycka A, Robak E. Purine nucleoside analogs as immunosuppressive and antineoplastic agents: mechanism of action and clinical activity. Curr Med Chem. 2006;13(26):3165-89.</citation>
    <PMID>17168705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rummel MJ, Niederle N, Maschmeyer G, Banat GA, von Grünhagen U, Losem C, Kofahl-Krause D, Heil G, Welslau M, Balser C, Kaiser U, Weidmann E, Dürk H, Ballo H, Stauch M, Roller F, Barth J, Hoelzer D, Hinke A, Brugger W; Study group indolent Lymphomas (StiL). Bendamustine plus rituximab versus CHOP plus rituximab as first-line treatment for patients with indolent and mantle-cell lymphomas: an open-label, multicentre, randomised, phase 3 non-inferiority trial. Lancet. 2013 Apr 6;381(9873):1203-10. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61763-2. Epub 2013 Feb 20. Erratum in: Lancet. 2013 Apr 6;381(9873):1184.</citation>
    <PMID>23433739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saito H, Maruyama D, Maeshima AM, Makita S, Kitahara H, Miyamoto K, Fukuhara S, Munakata W, Suzuki T, Kobayashi Y, Taniguchi H, Tobinai K. Prolonged lymphocytopenia after bendamustine therapy in patients with relapsed or refractory indolent B-cell and mantle cell lymphoma. Blood Cancer J. 2015 Oct 23;5:e362. doi: 10.1038/bcj.2015.86. Erratum in: Blood Cancer J. 2017 Nov 3;7(11):e620.</citation>
    <PMID>26495859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Solal-Céligny P, Bellei M, Marcheselli L, Pesce EA, Pileri S, McLaughlin P, Luminari S, Pro B, Montoto S, Ferreri AJ, Deconinck E, Milpied N, Gordon LI, Federico M. Watchful waiting in low-tumor burden follicular lymphoma in the rituximab era: results of an F2-study database. J Clin Oncol. 2012 Nov 1;30(31):3848-53. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.33.4474. Epub 2012 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23008294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stadtmauer EA, Vogl DT, Luning Prak E, Boyer J, Aqui NA, Rapoport AP, McDonald KR, Hou X, Murphy H, Bhagat R, Mangan PA, Chew A, Veloso EA, Levine BL, Vonderheide RH, Jawad AF, June CH, Sullivan KE. Transfer of influenza vaccine-primed costimulated autologous T cells after stem cell transplantation for multiple myeloma leads to reconstitution of influenza immunity: results of a randomized clinical trial. Blood. 2011 Jan 6;117(1):63-71. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-07-296822. Epub 2010 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20864577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Pileri SA, Harris NL, Stein H, Siebert R, Advani R, Ghielmini M, Salles GA, Zelenetz AD, Jaffe ES. The 2016 revision of the World Health Organization classification of lymphoid neoplasms. Blood. 2016 May 19;127(20):2375-90. doi: 10.1182/blood-2016-01-643569. Epub 2016 Mar 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26980727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong R, Pepper C, Brennan P, Nagorsen D, Man S, Fegan C. Blinatumomab induces autologous T-cell killing of chronic lymphocytic leukemia cells. Haematologica. 2013 Dec;98(12):1930-8. doi: 10.3324/haematol.2012.082248. Epub 2013 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23812940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ysebaert L, Gross E, Kühlein E, Blanc A, Corre J, Fournié JJ, Laurent G, Quillet-Mary A. Immune recovery after fludarabine-cyclophosphamide-rituximab treatment in B-chronic lymphocytic leukemia: implication for maintenance immunotherapy. Leukemia. 2010 Jul;24(7):1310-6. doi: 10.1038/leu.2010.89. Epub 2010 May 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20463751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>A.O. Ospedale Papa Giovanni XXIII</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rambaldi Alessandro</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head Hematology and Bone Marrow Transplant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blinatumomab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

