<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03829579</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108572</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>54135419TRD3012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03829579</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-Approval Access to Esketamine Nasal Spray for the Treatment of Treatment-Resistant Depression (TRD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Esketamine Single Patient Request</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pre-approval access program (PAAP) for eligible participants. The main purpose of
      this program is to provide access to esketamine nasal spray to eligible participant with
      treatment-resistant depression (TRD), who have exhausted all other treatment options,
      including all alternative treatment options with marketed therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Approved for marketing</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <expanded_access_info>
    <expanded_access_type_individual>Yes</expanded_access_type_individual>
  </expanded_access_info>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Treatment-Resistant</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will self-administer esketamine nasal spray, under the supervision of the healthcare professional at the site of care. A starting dose of 56 milligram (mg) will be administered intranasally into each nostril on Day 1 with subsequent doses of 56 mg or 84 mg administered during Weeks 1-4 (2 treatment sessions per week). For participants who respond, treatment is continued as follows: 56 mg or 84 mg of esketamine nasal spray during Weeks 5-8 (once weekly), and Week 9 onwards (every 2 weeks or once weekly), with period re-evaluation to determine the need for continued treatment. Doses will be adjusted based on efficacy and tolerability to the previous dosing.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have an unmet medical need to treat treatment-resistant depression (TRD) with
             esketamine nasal spray, an investigational compound, that has not been approved by any
             health authority. This means no other treatment options are available and the
             participant must be unable to participate in a clinical trial; for example, because
             they do not fulfill the eligibility criteria of the protocol or there are no trial
             sites within a reasonable distance of where they reside

          -  Must not participate in a clinical trial or be concurrently treated with an
             investigational drug when being treated with esketamine nasal spray

          -  Participants must have TRD with the diagnosis verified by a psychiatrist, and have
             exhausted all other options including all alternative treatment options with marketed
             therapies, specifically:

               1. Participant must meet the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders
                  (DSM)-5 diagnostic criteria for single-episode major depressive episode (major
                  depressive disorder [MDD]) (if single-episode MDD, the duration must be greater
                  than [&gt;]2 years) or recurrent MDD, without psychotic features.

               2. Participant must have had nonresponse to 2 or more oral antidepressant treatments
                  in the current episode of depression confirmed by documented medical history
                  and/or pharmacy/prescription records to meet criteria for TRD and have failed at
                  least one augmentation strategy (for example, atypical antipsychotics such as
                  aripiprazole or quetiapine, lithium, thyroid hormones, bupropion, etc) and have
                  failed an adequate course (greater than or equal to [&gt;=] 7 unilateral [UL]
                  sessions) of, or have a contraindication to electro-convulsive therapy (ECT) and
                  transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS)

          -  Participants must have exhausted clinical trials, early access programs or named
             patient programs that may be available in their region

          -  Participants must have moderate to severe depression per clinical judgment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The participant's depressive symptoms have previously demonstrated nonresponse to
             Esketamine Nasal Spray or ketamine in the current major depressive episode per
             clinical judgment

          -  Participant has a current or prior DSM-5 diagnosis of a psychotic disorder or MDD with
             psychosis, bipolar or related disorders, comorbid obsessive- compulsive disorder,
             intellectual disability (only DSM-5 diagnostic code 319), borderline personality
             disorder, antisocial personality disorder, histrionic personality disorder, or
             narcissistic personality disorder

          -  Participant has homicidal ideation/intent or has suicidal ideation with some intent to
             act within 6 months or a history of suicidal behavior within the past year, per the
             requesting psychiatrist's clinical judgment

          -  Participant has a history of moderate or severe substance or alcohol use disorder
             according to DSM-5 criteria, except nicotine or caffeine, within 6 months before the
             start of the first dose.

             a) A history (lifetime) of ketamine, phencyclidine (PCP), lysergic acid diethylamide
             (LSD), or 3, 4-methylenedioxy-methamphetamine (MDMA) hallucinogen-related use disorder
             is exclusionary

          -  Participants with a current or past history of seizures (uncomplicated childhood
             febrile seizures with no sequelae are not exclusionary)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Treatment-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

