<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03820947</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MDT18034</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03820947</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VenaSeal Spectrum: Global Post-Market Randomized Controlled Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Global, Post-Market, Prospective, Multi-Center, Randomized Controlled Trial of the VenaSeal™ Closure System vs. Surgical Stripping or Endothermal Ablation (ETA) for the Treatment of Early &amp; Advanced Stage Superficial Venous Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medtronic Endovascular</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medtronic Endovascular</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Global, Post-Market, Prospective, Multi-Center, Randomized Controlled Trial of the VenaSeal™
      Closure System vs. Surgical Stripping or Endothermal Ablation (ETA) for the Treatment of
      Early and Advanced Stage Superficial Venous Disease
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed with two randomized studies and one single arm study.

      Two randomized studies are for CEAP 2-5 subjects:

        1. VenaSeal vs. Surgical Stripping Study (outside of the United States only)

        2. VenaSeal vs. ETA Study

      The single arm study is for CEAP 6 subjects with active venous leg ulcers (VLU):

      1. VLU Study
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire-early (VenousTSQe)(For Randomized studies, VenaSeal vs. ETA and VenaSeal vs. Surgical Stripping Study)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Peri-procedural patient satisfaction as measured by a validated, patient-centered venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire (VenousTSQe).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire- status (VenousTSQs) (For Randomized studies, VenaSeal vs. ETA and VenaSeal vs. Surgical Stripping Study)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction as measured by a validated, patient-centered venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire (VenousTSQs).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of target vein treated (For Randomized studies, VenaSeal vs. ETA and VenaSeal vs. Surgical Stripping Study)</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Elimination of clinically relevant superficial truncal disease in each target vein at the time of index procedure as measured by the percentage of target vein length successfully treated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to ulcer healing (For VLU study)</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time to ulcer healing, calculated through healing confirmation and verified by an independent core laboratory.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomic closure of the primary target superficial truncal vein</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Duplex Ultrasound showing primary target vein closure along the entire treated vein segment with no discrete segments of patency exceeding 5 cm after VenaSeal™ system and ETA procedures, or the absence of refluxing or residual primary target vein after surgical stripping procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to return to work</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomic closure of primary target vein</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, and 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Duplex Ultrasound showing primary target vein closure along the entire treated vein segment with no discrete segments of patency exceeding 5 cm after VenaSeal™ system and ETA procedures, or the absence of refluxing or residual primary target vein after surgical stripping procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anatomic closure of target vein</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, and 6, 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Duplex Ultrasound showing target vein closure along the entire treated vein segment with no discrete segments of patency exceeding 5 cm after VenaSeal™ system and ETA procedures, or the absence of refluxing or residual target vein after surgical stripping procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success of each target vein</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via Duplex Ultrasound showing target vein (including primary target vein) closure along the entire treated vein segment with no discrete segments of patency exceeding 5 cm after VenaSeal™ system and ETA procedures, or the absence of refluxing or residual target vein after surgical stripping procedures.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reintervention of any target vein</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed via number of the target veins requiring retreatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reintervention of any target vein</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AEs) occurring in the target limb</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events occurring in target limb, evaluated from index procedure through 12 months are hypersensitivity to VenaSeal™ adhesive, phlebitis, granuloma, endovenous glue induced thrombosis (EGIT) or endovenous heat induced thrombosis (EHIT), symptomatic deep vein thrombosis (DVT) events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Additional adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Additional adverse events that will be evaluated through 60 months are symptomatic pulmonary embolism (PE) and serious adverse events (SAEs).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and type of adjunctive treatment conducted</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of healthcare resources utilized for target limb venous reflux disease</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of healthcare resources utilized for adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU study only: Number of ulcer related healthcare resources utilized</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to return to normal activities</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-procedural and post-procedural pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure, and 7 days and 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by using numeric rating scale (NRS) with a scale of 0-10, with '0' indicating no pain and '10' indicating worst pain imaginable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in venous disease symptoms compared to baseline measured by the revised Venous Clinical Severity Score (rVCSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>7 and 30 days, and at 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>rVCSS score ranges from 0 to 30, with higher score indicating severe venous disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in venous disease symptoms compared to baseline as measured by subject self-reporting symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>7 and 30 days, and at 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Aberdeen Varicose Vein Questionnaire (AVVQ) score compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, and 6, 12, 24, 36, 48, and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>The total score ranges from 0-100 points, with '0' point indicating the best quality of life and '100' points indicating worst quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EuroQoL Group 5-Dimension Self-Report Questionnaire (EQ-5D-5L) compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, and 6, 12, 24, 36, 48 and 60 months</time_frame>
    <description>Items are scored on a 1-5 scale, 5 being a worse outcome. Each of the 5 dimensions are scored separately to obtain a 5-digit code which is converted into a standard value by country. Max &amp; min values vary by country.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36) compared to baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days, and 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The total score ranges from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating better general health perception.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Provider experience evaluating overall satisfaction with the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by a 5 point Likert scale ranging from 0-5, with 5 indicating the best outcome (extremely satisfied with the treatment).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU study: Ulcer healing rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure through 24 months or until ulcer healing has been confirmed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU Study: Ulcer recurrence on the target limb</measure>
    <time_frame>Following ulcer healing through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU Study: Ulcer-free time</measure>
    <time_frame>Through 60 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU Study: Venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire-early (VenousTSQe)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Peri-procedural patient satisfaction as measured by a validated, patient-centered venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire (VenousTSQe).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU Study: Venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire- status (VenousTSQs)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction as measured by a validated, patient-centered venous treatment satisfaction questionnaire (VenousTSQs).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For VLU Study: Percentage of target vein treated</measure>
    <time_frame>Index procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Elimination of clinically relevant superficial truncal disease in each target vein at the time of index procedure as measured by the percentage of target vein length successfully treated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">806</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VenaSeal™ Closure System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CEAP 2-5 subjects will be randomized to VenaSeal™ Closure System vs. ETA or Surgical Stripping</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Endothermal Ablation (ETA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CEAP 2-5 subjects will be randomized to either VenaSeal™ Closure System or ETA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Stripping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>CEAP 2-5 subjects will be randomized to either VenaSeal™ Closure System or surgical stripping (outside of the United States only)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VenaSeal™ Closure System VLU Study</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>CEAP 6 active leg ulcer subjects will not be randomized to a comparator, all subjects will be treated with VenaSeal™ Closure System</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VenaSeal™ Closure System</intervention_name>
    <description>The VenaSeal™ closure system is the non-tumescent, non-thermal, non-sclerosant device that uses a proprietary medical adhesive delivered endovenously to close the vein.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VenaSeal™ Closure System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VenaSeal™ Closure System VLU Study</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endothermal Ablation (ETA)</intervention_name>
    <description>ETA includes EVLA that uses laser or RFA that uses radiofrequency heating to close the vein. Heat is applied in both EVLA and RFA therapies to close the vein.
Subject can be treated with either EVLA or RFA if randomized to ETA arm per site's standard practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Endothermal Ablation (ETA)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Endovenous laser ablation(EVLA)</other_name>
    <other_name>Radiofrequency ablation (RFA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical Stripping</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical stripping involves stripping (removal) of the diseased vein via surgical procedures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical Stripping</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient is ≥18 years of age

          2. Patient has venous reflux in superficial truncal vein(s) (e.g., GSV, SSV, accessory
             saphenous veins) with CEAP 2 (symptomatic) or CEAP 3, 4a, 4b, 5, 6, appropriate for
             treatment, as confirmed by DUS

          3. Eligibility for treatment:

               -  VenaSeal vs ETA Study: Patient is eligible for treatment with the VenaSeal™
                  system and ETA

               -  VenaSeal vs Surgical Stripping Study: Patient is eligible for treatment with the
                  VenaSeal™ system and surgical stripping

               -  VLU Study: patients should be eligible for treatment with the VenaSeal™ system

          4. Treatable refluxing segment of target vein(s) 10 cm in length or longer

          5. Patient has a target vein diameter of ≥3 mm throughout the intended treated segment of
             the target vein as measured by DUS while patient is standing

          6. Patient is willing and capable of complying with specified follow-up evaluations at
             the specified times

          7. Patient has an ability to understand the requirements of the study and to provide
             informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient has a known history of allergic sensitivities (including but not limited to
             cyanoacrylate adhesives), or any other condition, which in the opinion of the
             investigator may make the patient more susceptible to cyanoacrylate adhesive
             hypersensitivity

          2. Patient has known deep vein obstruction in the target limb, as identified by the
             site's standard of care

          3. Patient has abnormal pulse exam or ABI &lt;0.8

          4. Patient has acute superficial thrombophlebitis

          5. Patient requires any non-target vein treatments in the contralateral or ipsilateral
             limb, or any other surgical procedure up tp 30 days pre-procedure and through 3 months
             post-procedure

          6. Patient has any co-morbid conditions, which in the investigator's opinion may
             interfere with the patient's compliance with study visits and procedures, or may
             confound interpretation of study data (e.g., congestive heart failure Class III and
             IV, non-ambulatory patients, severe hepatic dysfunction, life expectancy &lt; 1 year)

          7. IFU contraindications:

               -  VenaSeal vs. ETA Study: Patient has VenaSeal™ system and/or ETA product's IFU
                  contraindication(s)

               -  VenaSeal vs Surgical Stripping Study: Patient has surgical stripping and/or
                  VenaSeal™ system IFU contraindication(s)

               -  VLU Study: Patient has VenaSeal™ system IFU contraindication(s)

          8. Patient is non-ambulatory

          9. Patient is a female of childbearing potential who may be pregnant or breastfeeding at
             the time of the index procedure

         10. Patient belongs to a vulnerable population per investigator's judgment or patient has
             any kind of disorder that compromises his/her ability to give written informed consent
             and/or to comply with study procedures

         11. Patient is currently participating in an investigational drug or device study when the
             data collected could be conflicting or biased due to participation in another study

         12. VLU Study: Patient has target ulceration identified to be of non-venous etiology, as
             confirmed by the independent core laboratory

         13. VLU Study: Patient has target circumferential ulceration that cannot be captured in a
             single photograph (any ulcer curvature around the leg that goes out of sight)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen Gibson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lake Washington Vascular, US</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manjit Gohel</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Addenbrooke's Hospital, UK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara Ortiz</last_name>
    <phone>+1 7075432216</phone>
    <email>sara.o.ortiz@medtronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shital Patel</last_name>
    <phone>+1 7075413256</phone>
    <email>shital.r.patel@medtronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lake Washington Vascular</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bellevue</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98004-4623</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathleen Gibson, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kim Glorieux</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Venous reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous leg ulcer</keyword>
  <keyword>Varicose Veins</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Venous Insufficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>VenaSeal</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothermal Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgical Stripping</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiofrequency Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Great Saphenous Vein</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Saphenous Vein</keyword>
  <keyword>Anterior Accessory Saphenous Vein</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

