<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03821064</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00077402</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03821064</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single-arm Phase II Study of NDURE for Patients With HNC</brief_title>
  <acronym>NDURE</acronym>
  <official_title>Single-arm, Phase II Study Evaluating the Clinical Impact of Navigation on Delays and Racial Disparities Starting Postoperative Radiation Therapy for Adults With Locally Advanced Head and Neck Cancer: The NDURE Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate whether a new patient navigation intervention can decrease delays
      starting post-operative radiation therapy after surgery for white and African-American head
      and neck cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the feasibility, acceptability, preliminary clinical impact, and
      preliminary behavioral impact of NDURE (Navigation for Disparities and Untimely Radiation
      thErapy), our multi-level, theory-based navigation intervention to improve timely, equitable
      post-operative radiation treatment (PORT) among Head and Neck Cancer (HNC) patients. We
      hypothesize that NDURE will be feasible, acceptable, improve the timeliness of PORT for white
      and African American (AA) HNC patients and decrease disparities in delay between the two
      groups by improving system-, interpersonal-, and individual-level health behavior constructs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 21, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 21, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Delays Starting Post-Operative Radiation Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients (overall, African American, white) who start PORT &gt;6 weeks after surgery. Initiation of postoperative PORT &gt; 6 weeks after surgery is defined as more than 42 calendar days from the time of the definitive surgical resection to the initiation of radiation therapy. In situations in which the surgical management of the primary tumor and the neck are staged (i.e. occur on two different calendar days), the date of the surgery for the primary tumor will be used. In situations in which an additional surgical resection is required (e.g. re-resection of positive margins to clear residual disease), the date of the earlier (i.e. attempted definitive) surgical procedure will be used to determine the target start date for PORT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Racial Disparities Starting PORT, Rate of Delay</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The difference in the rate of initiation of PORT &gt; 6 weeks after surgery between white and AA HNC patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Racial Disparities Starting PORT, Number of Days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in number of days from surgery to PORT start (overall, white, AA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time-to-PORT</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Days between surgery and the start of PORT is defined as the time, in days, between the date of definitive surgical resection to the initiation of radiation therapy. All of the criteria used to adjudicate the date of the definitive surgical procedure described for the primary outcome measure will be applied to this measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, Pre-Surgical Radiation Consultation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with pre-surgical radiation consultation. Pre-Surgical Radiation Consultation is defined as the attendance by the patient at a consultation with a radiation oncologist (at MUSC or elsewhere) prior to surgery to discuss RT in the definitive or adjuvant setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, Pre-Radiation Therapy Dental Extractions</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with on-time dental extractions. Pre-Radiation Therapy Dental Extractions is defined as the extraction of teeth prior to discharge from the index hospitalization for the definitive surgical procedure. Patients who are edentulous are not evaluable for this measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, Surgery to Pathology Reports &lt;/= 7 days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Surgery to Pathology Report &lt;/= 7 days is defined as the production of the pathology report from the definitive surgical procedure within the electronic medical record (EMR) within 7 calendar days of the definitive surgical procedure. Addenda to the pathology report at the request of the HNC team (e.g. tumor p16 status) are not counted in this measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, Surgery to PORT Referral &lt;10 days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with surgery to PORT referral &lt; 10 days. Surgery to PORT Referral &lt;/= 10 days is defined as the placement of a referral for PORT, at MUSC or elsewhere, within 10 calendar days of the definitive surgical procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, RT Referral to RT Consult &lt;10 days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with RT Referral to Consult &lt; 10 days. RT Referral to Consult &lt;/= 10 days is defined as the evaluation of the patient at a postoperative consultation with a radiation oncologist within 10 calendar days of the referral being placed (or postoperative appointment being scheduled in cases in which care has been established and the return visit is no longer a consultation). The consultation may occur in the clinic or the hospital depending upon clinical circumstances.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PORT Timeline and Care Processes, RT Consult to Initiation &lt;/= 21 days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with RT Consult to Initiation &lt;/= 21 days. RT Consult to Initiation &lt;/= 21 days is defined as the initiation of PORT within 21 calendar days of the patient being evaluated by a radiation oncologist for PORT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barriers Resolved</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of barriers identified by the navigator that are resolved during the NDURE intervention, as determined by the navigator log.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanisms of Barrier Reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PN Log (type of navigator action for barrier reduction, number of navigator actions for barrier reduction).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Efficacy in Cancer Care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Communication and Attitudinal Self-Efficacy Scale for Cancer-12 (CASE-cancer) measures self-efficacy within the context of productive communication and positive attitude for cancer patients. It is a psychometrically sound tool that may provide new information on important mediating factors of cancer care. The response scale ranges from 1 to 4 points (1= strongly disagree, 2=slightly disagree, 3=slightly agree, 4=strongly disagree). The twelve question scale is divided into 3 domains with 4 questions each. Scores from these subscales are added to compute a total score. Higher values represent a more positive attitude.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barriers Unresolved</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of barriers identified by the navigator that are not resolved during the NDURE intervention, as determined by the navigator log.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NDURE Accrual</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of eligible patients who enroll in NDURE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NDURE Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of enrolled patients who complete the baseline assessment, at least two NDURE intervention sessions, and the final follow-up assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Navigation Session Completion</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of NDURE navigation sessions completed by a participant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Navigator Caseload</measure>
    <time_frame>13 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of simultaneous cases (on-trial participants) being navigated by the NDURE navigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Navigator Time Allocation (Direct)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The time (in minutes), that the NDURE navigator spends directly interacting with the patient to identify and address barriers to timely, equitable postoperative radiation therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Navigator Time Allocation (Indirect)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The time (in minutes), that the navigator spends generating and enacting each Barrier Reduction Plan that is not directly interacting with the patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with the Interpersonal Relationship with the Navigator Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This scale is a validated, 9-item measure of the satisfaction of the interpersonal relationship with the patient navigator that has been used in prior studies of PN.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Logistical Aspects of Navigation Scale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This scale is a validated, 26-item measure of the satisfaction of the logistical aspects of PN that has been used in prior studies of PN</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Care Transition Measure-15 (CTM-15) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Care Transition Measure-15 (CTM-15) is a validated, psychometrically sound 15-item, unidimensional measure of care transitions across the healthcare system that is consistent with the concept of patient-centeredness and useful from an organization perspective for the purpose of performance measurement and quality improvement. Higher scores reflect higher levers of care integration and coordination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Interpersonal Support Evaluation List-12 (ISEL-12) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Interpersonal Support Evaluation List-12 (ISEL-12) is a validated, 12-item assessment of three domains of interpersonal support that has been used to assess support in prior PN studies. Items are rated on a 4-point Likert scale with higher scores indicating more support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived Susceptibility Questionnaire Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Susceptibility Questionnaire is modified version of a validated 3-item perceived susceptibility subscale for mammography screening to assess perceived susceptibility for delays starting PORT after HNC surgery. Items are rated on a 5-point Likert scale with higher scores indicating higher perceived susceptibility.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Illness Perception Questionnaire-Revised (IPQ-R) Consequences Subscale Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The IPQ-R consequences subscale is easily modifiable to asses disease-specific perceived severity.The IPQ-R is a validated assessment of a patient's self-representation of the health consequences of their illness. It is scored using a 5-point Likert scale with higher scores indicate higher perceived severity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Perceived Barriers Score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Barriers Questionnaire is a self-report measure of the presence/absence of pre-specified barriers to cancer care (yes/no). The questionnaire has been used extensively to assess perceived barriers in prior PN studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer of Head and Neck</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Navigation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>45 patients (15 African American, 30 white) will interact with a patient navigator three times over three months to identify and address barriers before they cause breakdowns in care delivery, employing resources, education, and care coordination from the day of surgery until post-operative radiation treatment begins.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Navigation</intervention_name>
    <description>NDURE is a theory-based, multi-level patient navigation (PN) intervention consisting of clinic-based sessions of manualized PN to reduce barriers to care, increase HNC care delivery, and improve clinical outcomes (timely, equitable PORT). NDURE will be delivered from surgical consultation to PORT initiation (~3 months). The three in-person NDURE sessions, which are expected to take 30-60 minutes each, will coincide with the presurgical consult, hospital discharge, and 1st postoperative clinic visit. During the first session, the navigator will 1) elicit barriers and facilitators to timely PORT, 2) develop the personalized barrier reduction plan (BRP), review the BRP with the patient, caregiver, and provider, and 3) implement the BRP. At the two subsequent sessions, the navigator will review and update the BRP in an iterative, dynamic fashion, identifying new barriers and systematically tracking resolution of prior barriers until the start of PORT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Navigation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        In order to be eligible to participate in this study, an individual must meet all of the
        following criteria:

          1. Age &gt; 18 years at the time of screening

          2. Histologically or pathologically confirmed invasive squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) (or
             histologic variant) of the oral cavity, oropharynx (p16 positive, negative, or
             unknown), hypopharynx, larynx, unknown primary, paranasal sinuses, or nasal cavity.

          3. American Joint Committee on Cancer (AJCC) clinical stage grouping III-IV (8th edition)
             for patients with SCC of the oral cavity, p16-negative oropharynx, hypopharynx,
             larynx, paranasal sinuses, and nasal cavity; or AJCC clinical stage grouping III-IV
             (7th edition) for patients with p16-positive SCC of the oropharynx or unknown primary.

          4. No prior exposure to radiation therapy, with or without concurrent chemotherapy, for
             treatment of HNSCC in the definitive or adjuvant therapy settings

          5. Plan for curative intent surgery at MUSC

          6. Plan for PORT (at MUSC or non-MUSC) with or without concurrent chemotherapy following
             curative intent surgery

        An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from participation
        in this study:

          1. Self-identified Hispanic ethnicity

          2. Presence of cognitive impairment that precludes participation as determined by
             oncology provider

          3. Prior radiation therapy for HNC

          4. Failure to undergo curative intent surgery at MUSC

          5. Lack of indication for PORT (with or without concurrent chemotherapy) per National
             Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) Guidelines based on final pathologic evaluation of
             adverse features and AJCC pathologic stage grouping
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evan Graboyes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ohlstein JF, Brody-Camp S, Friedman S, Levy JM, Buell JF, Friedlander P. Initial Experience of a Patient Navigation Model for Head and Neck Cancer. JAMA Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2015 Sep;141(9):804-9. doi: 10.1001/jamaoto.2015.1467.</citation>
    <PMID>26313895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cramer JD, Speedy SE, Ferris RL, Rademaker AW, Patel UA, Samant S. National evaluation of multidisciplinary quality metrics for head and neck cancer. Cancer. 2017 Nov 15;123(22):4372-4381. doi: 10.1002/cncr.30902. Epub 2017 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>28727137</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang J, Barbera L, Brouwers M, Browman G, Mackillop WJ. Does delay in starting treatment affect the outcomes of radiotherapy? A systematic review. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Feb 1;21(3):555-63. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2003 Apr 1;21(7):1424.</citation>
    <PMID>12560449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graboyes EM, Garrett-Mayer E, Ellis MA, Sharma AK, Wahlquist AE, Lentsch EJ, Nussenbaum B, Day TA. Effect of time to initiation of postoperative radiation therapy on survival in surgically managed head and neck cancer. Cancer. 2017 Dec 15;123(24):4841-4850. doi: 10.1002/cncr.30939. Epub 2017 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28841234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graboyes EM, Garrett-Mayer E, Sharma AK, Lentsch EJ, Day TA. Adherence to National Comprehensive Cancer Network guidelines for time to initiation of postoperative radiation therapy for patients with head and neck cancer. Cancer. 2017 Jul 15;123(14):2651-2660. doi: 10.1002/cncr.30651. Epub 2017 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>28241092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Divi V, Chen MM, Hara W, Shah D, Narvasa K, Segura Smith A, Kelley J, Rosenthal EL, Porter J. Reducing the Time from Surgery to Adjuvant Radiation Therapy: An Institutional Quality Improvement Project. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2018 Jul;159(1):158-165. doi: 10.1177/0194599818768254. Epub 2018 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29631478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Evan Graboyes</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Department of Otolaryngology- Head and Neck Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Navigation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 31, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/64/NCT03821064/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

