<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02397083</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-0944</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-00919</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-0944</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02397083</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Levonorgestrel-Releasing Intrauterine System With or Without Everolimus in Treating Patients With Atypical Hyperplasia or Stage IA Grade 1 Endometrial Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of the Levonorgestrel Intrauterine Device Alone or in Combination With the mTORC1 Inhibitor, Everolimus, for the Treatment of Complex Atypical Hyperplasia and Stage Ia Grade 1 Endometrial Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized phase II trial studies how well levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system
      works when given alone or with everolimus in treating patients with atypical hyperplasia (a
      pre-cancerous growth of the lining of the uterus) or stage IA grade 1 endometrial cancer. The
      levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system is designed to prevent pregnancy by releasing a
      hormone called levonorgestrel, which is a type of progesterone. Progesterone is a common type
      of hormone that is used to prevent pregnancy and may prevent or slow tumor cell growth.
      Everolimus may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed for cell
      growth. It is not yet known whether the levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system works
      better with or without everolimus in treating patients with atypical hyperplasia or stage IA
      grade 1 endometrial cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate the efficacy of the levonorgestrel intrauterine device (LIUD)
      (levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system) alone to treat complex atypical hyperplasia or
      stage Ia grade 1 endometrioid endometrial carcinoma with response rate.

      II. Estimate the efficacy of the LIUD in combination with everolimus to treat LIUD-refractory
      complex atypical hyperplasia or stage Ia grade 1 endometrioid endometrial carcinoma with
      response rate.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Document the toxicity profile of the levonorgestrel intrauterine device alone or in
      combination with everolimus using the National Institutes of Health-National Cancer Institute
      (NIH-NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version (v) 4.0.

      II. Estimate overall survival (OS) and event-free survival (EFS) of patients with complex
      atypical hyperplasia or stage Ia grade 1 endometrioid endometrial cancer treated with the
      levonorgestrel IUD alone or in combination with everolimus.

      III. Estimate the response duration associated with the levonorgestrel IUD alone or in
      combination with everolimus in patients with complex atypical hyperplasia or stage Ia grade 1
      endometrioid endometrial cancer.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVE:

      I. Determine if response to therapy can be predicted based on the molecular profile of the
      tumor, including estrogen-induced genes and relevant pathway members, or by change in gene
      expression after therapy.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo placement of the LIUD on day 1. Patients achieving stable disease at 3
      months are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms. Patients with complete response may continue
      treatment with the LIUD.

      ARM I: Patients continue treatment with the LIUD for up to 9 months in the absence of disease
      progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      ARM II: Patients continue treatment with the LIUD and receive everolimus orally (PO) once
      daily (QD) on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 9 cycles in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 6, 9, and 12 months and then
      every 6 months thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 23, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate (levonorgestrel intrauterine device [LIUD] alone)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated with a 2-sided 90% confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate (levonorgestrel intrauterine device [LIUD] alone)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated with a 2-sided 90% confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate for levonorgestrel intrauterine device (LIUD) alone or in combination with everolimus after LIUD failure (i.e., failure to achieve complete response after initial 3 months of LIUD alone)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher's exact test will be used to compare response rates by 6 months between the LIUD alone arm and the LIUD plus everolimus arm. Estimated on each arm with a 2-sided 90% confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 11 years</time_frame>
    <description>Tabulated by treatment arm, severity, and relationship to study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 11 years</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product-limit estimator. The log-rank test will be used to compare treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 11 years</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product-limit estimator. The log-rank test will be used to compare treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response duration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks after completion of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated using the Kaplan-Meier product-limit estimator. The log-rank test will be used to compare treatment arms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">270</enrollment>
  <condition>Atypical Endometrial Hyperplasia</condition>
  <condition>FIGO Grade 1 Endometrial Endometrioid Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>FIGO Grade 2 Endometrial Endometrioid Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (LIUD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients continue treatment with the LIUD for up to 9 months in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (LIUD, everolimus)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients continue treatment with the LIUD and receive everolimus PO QD on days 1-28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 9 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Everolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (LIUD, everolimus)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>42-O-(2-Hydroxy)ethyl Rapamycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Afinitor</other_name>
    <other_name>Certican</other_name>
    <other_name>RAD 001</other_name>
    <other_name>RAD001</other_name>
    <other_name>Votubia</other_name>
    <other_name>Zortress</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (LIUD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (LIUD, everolimus)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levonorgestrel-Releasing Intrauterine System</intervention_name>
    <description>Placed in the uterus</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I (LIUD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II (LIUD, everolimus)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Mirena</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients with a diagnosis of complex atypical hyperplasia OR, grade 1 endometrioid
             OR focal grade 2 adenocarcinoma in predominately grade 1 disease endometrial carcinoma
             on endometrial biopsy or dilation and curettage (D &amp; C) within three months of study
             enrollment

          -  Prior progesterone treatment is ALLOWED

          -  Ability to comply with endometrial biopsies every 3 months

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1.5 x 10^9/L

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100 x 10^9/L

          -  Hemoglobin (Hb) &gt; 9 g/dL

          -  Total serum bilirubin =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) =&lt; 2.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) =&lt; 2; factor 10A drawn if patient on
             anticoagulant Eliquis

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 x ULN

          -  Fasting serum cholesterol =&lt; 300 mg/dL OR =&lt; 7.75 mmol/L AND fasting triglycerides =&lt;
             2.5 x ULN; NOTE: in case one or both of these thresholds are exceeded, the patient can
             only be included after initiation of appropriate lipid lowering medication

          -  Signed informed consent obtained prior to any screening procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with grade 2-3 endometrioid, uterine serous, clear cell, mucinous, squamous,
             transitional cell, sarcomas, or carcinosarcoma histology

          -  Evidence of extrauterine spread of disease on imaging or during surgical evaluation

          -  Patients who have prior therapy with everolimus or any other mammalian target of
             rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor

          -  Patients currently receiving anticancer therapies (including chemotherapy, radiation
             therapy, hormonal, or antibody-based therapy); prior treatment should have a washout
             period of 28 days or 4 1/2 half-lives (7 days), whichever is shorter

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to everolimus or other rapamycin analogs (e.g.
             sirolimus, temsirolimus)

          -  Known intolerance or hypersensitivity to progesterone or its excipients

          -  Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of oral everolimus (e.g., inability to take oral
             medication or a requirement for intravenous [IV] alimentation, prior surgical
             procedures affecting absorption, malabsorption syndrome, and active peptic ulcer
             disease) are excluded; subjects with ulcerative colitis, inflammatory bowel disease,
             or a partial or complete small bowel obstruction are also excluded, as are any
             patients who cannot swallow the capsule whole

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c) &gt; 8% despite
             adequate therapy; patients with a known history of impaired fasting glucose or
             diabetes mellitus (DM) may be included, however blood glucose and antidiabetic
             treatment must be monitored closely throughout the trial and adjusted as necessary

          -  Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions such as: a)
             unstable angina pectoris, symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction
             =&lt; 6 months prior to start of everolimus, serious uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia, or
             any other clinically significant cardiac disease; b) symptomatic congestive heart
             failure of New York Heart Association class III or IV; c) active (acute or chronic) or
             uncontrolled severe infection (not responding to antibiotics), liver disease such as
             cirrhosis, decompensated liver disease, and active and chronic hepatitis (i.e.
             quantifiable hepatitis B virus-deoxyribonucleic acid [HBV-DNA] and/or positive
             hepatitis B surface antigen [HbsAg], quantifiable hepatitis C virus-ribonucleic acid
             [HCV-RNA]); d) known severely impaired lung function (spirometry and diffusing
             capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide [DLCO] 50% or less of normal and oxygen [O2]
             saturation 88% or less at rest on room air); e) active, bleeding diathesis

          -  Chronic treatment with corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents; topical or
             inhaled corticosteroids are allowed

          -  Patients who have a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity

          -  Patients who have received live attenuated vaccines within 1 week of start of
             everolimus and during the study; patient should also avoid close contact with others
             who have received live attenuated vaccines; examples of live attenuated vaccines
             include intranasal influenza, measles, mumps, rubella, oral polio, Bacillus
             Calmette-Guerin (BCG), yellow fever, varicella and TY21a typhoid vaccines

          -  Other malignancies within the past 3 years except for basal or squamous cell carcinoma
             of the skin

          -  Active (acute or chronic) or uncontrolled severe infections (not responding to
             antibiotics), including acute pelvic inflammatory disease

          -  Congenital or acquired uterine anomaly which distorts the uterine cavity

          -  Genital actinomycosis

          -  Patients with a history of non-compliance to medical regimens or who are considered
             potentially unreliable or will not be able to complete the entire study

          -  Patients who are currently part of or have participated in any clinical investigation
             with an investigational drug within 1 month prior to dosing

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Women of child-bearing potential (WOCBP), defined as women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, must use one additional highly effective methods of contraception
             in addition to the LIUD during the study and 8 weeks after; acceptable effective
             contraception methods include combo of the following: a) barrier methods of
             contraception: condom or occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps) with
             spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/ vaginal suppository; b) total abstinence or; c)
             male/female sterilization; women are considered post-menopausal and not of
             child-bearing potential if they have had 12 months of natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea
             with an appropriate clinical profile (e.g. age appropriate, history of vasomotor
             symptoms) or have had surgical bilateral oophorectomy (with or without hysterectomy)
             or tubal ligation &gt; six weeks prior to randomization

          -  Women who are on contraindicated medications to everolimus must have confirmation from
             their physician that they may change or discontinue the medication if randomized to
             the LIUD + everolimus arm
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shannon N Westin</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shannon Westin</last_name>
    <phone>713-794-4314</phone>
    <email>swestin@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Honolulu</city>
        <state>Hawaii</state>
        <zip>96813</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Keith Y. Terada</last_name>
      <phone>808-526-2477</phone>
      <email>kterada@ucera.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Keith Y. Terada</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American Health Network Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46254</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael W. Method</last_name>
      <email>mmethod@ecommunity.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael W. Method</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Summit Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley Heights</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07922</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Darlene G. Gibbon</last_name>
      <email>gibbonda@cinj.rutgers.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Darlene G. Gibbon</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cooper Hospital University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Camden</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David P. Warshal</last_name>
      <phone>855-632-2667</phone>
      <email>warshal-david@cooperhealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David P. Warshal</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OhioHealth Mansfield Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansfield</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aine E. Clements</last_name>
      <email>aine.clements@ohiohealth.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aine E. Clements</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Hermann Memorial City Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77024</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicole D. Fleming</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-3245</phone>
      <email>nfleming@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicole D. Fleming</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon Baines Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026-1967</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michaela Onstad</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-7418</phone>
      <email>maonstad@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michaela Onstad</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shannon N. Westin</last_name>
      <phone>713-794-4314</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shannon N. Westin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Woman's Hospital of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael W. Bevers</last_name>
      <email>mbevers@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael W. Bevers</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in Katy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77094</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael W. Bevers</last_name>
      <email>mbevers@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael W. Bevers</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson League City</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nassau Bay</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77058</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Behrouz Zand</last_name>
      <phone>713-563-4367</phone>
      <email>BZand@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Behrouz Zand</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christus Santa Rosa Hospital-Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Georgia A. McCann</last_name>
      <phone>210-567-3406</phone>
      <email>mccanng@uthscsa.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Georgia A. McCann</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in Sugar Land</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sugar Land</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicole D. Fleming</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-3245</phone>
      <email>nfleming@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicole D. Fleming</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson in The Woodlands</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Woodlands</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77384</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lauren P. Cobb</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-8511</phone>
      <email>lpcobb@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lauren P. Cobb</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Endometrioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levonorgestrel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

