<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03787095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACTG A5370</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>38399</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03787095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunotherapeutic Activity of an Anti-PD-1 Antibody (Cemiplimab) in Participants With HIV-1 on Suppressive cART</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Immunotherapeutic Activity of an Anti-PD-1 Antibody (Cemiplimab) in Participants With HIV-1 on Suppressive cART: A Phase I/II, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Ascending Multiple Dose Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Regeneron Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and immunotherapeutic activity of an
      anti-PD-1 antibody (cemiplimab) in participants with HIV-1 on suppressive combination
      antiretroviral therapy (cART).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety and immunotherapeutic activity of an anti-PD-1 antibody
      (cemiplimab) in participants with HIV-1 on combination antiretroviral therapy (cART) who have
      plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL and CD4+ T cell counts ≥350/mm^3.

      Participants will be enrolled into three sequential dose-rising cohorts. Participants in each
      cohort will receive infusions of either cemiplimab or placebo at study entry (Day 0) and Week
      6, for a total of two infusions. All participants will also continue their non-study provided
      ART regimen. Enrollment in the cohorts will be sequential, with the second and third cohorts
      only opening after all participants in the previous cohort have reached week 12 and an
      evaluation of safety outcomes has established that it is safe to dose escalate.

      Participants will attend study visits on Day 0 and Weeks 1, 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20,
      24, 28, 36, and 48. These visits may include a medical history, physical examination, urine
      and blood collection, and adherence assessments. Participants will be followed for 48 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of a Grade 3 or higher adverse event (AE) related to study treatment (as judged by the Clinical Management Committee [CMC], blinded to treatment arm)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Entry through Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Graded according to the Division of AIDS Table for Grading the Severity of Adult and Pediatric Adverse Events (DAIDS AE Grading Table), corrected Version 2.1, July 2017</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Grade 1 or higher immune-related adverse event (irAE) (such as, but not limited to, pneumonitis, colitis, adrenal insufficiency, or hypothyroidism), related to study treatment (as judged by the CMC, blinded to treatment arm)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Entry through Week 48</time_frame>
    <description>Graded according to the DAIDS AE Grading Table, corrected Version 2.1, July 2017</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of HIV-1 gag-specific CD8+ T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Entry through Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by intracellular staining for CD107a and interferon gamma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of HIV-1 gag-specific CD8+ T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, after first dose (average of Weeks 2-6), after the second dose (average of Weeks 8-12)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by intracellular staining for CD107a and interferon gamma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of HIV-1 gag-specific CD8+ T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Study Entry through Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by intracellular staining for interferon gamma or CD107a alone</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in polyfunctional response of HIV-1 gag-specific CD8+ T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Study Entry through Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by intracellular staining for interferon gamma, CD107a, IL-2, and tumor necrosis factor alpha</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 0.3 mg/kg of cemiplimab, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive placebo, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 1 mg/kg of cemiplimab, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive placebo, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 3 mg/kg of cemiplimab, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive placebo, administered at Day 0 and Week 6 for a total of two infusions.
Participants will also continue their current non-study provided ART regimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cemiplimab</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered as an intravenous (IV) infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Cemiplimab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>REGN2810</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Admixture of Diluent for REGN2810 and sodium chloride for injection, administered as an IV infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infection

          -  On ART for at least 24 months

          -  Receiving ART with no changes of the components of ART medications within 90 days
             prior to study entry

               -  Changes within drug class, in drug formulation or dose are allowed more than 30
                  days prior to study entry.

          -  CD4+ T cell count ≥350 cells/mm^3

          -  At least two plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt;50 copies/mL within 18 months

               -  A single detectable HIV-1 RNA but less than 1000 copies/mL is allowed if followed
                  by HIV-1 RNA below quantifiable limits.

          -  HIV-1 RNA level &lt;50 copies/mL within 90 days prior to study entry

          -  The following laboratory values within 90 days prior to entry:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1500 cells/mm^3

               -  Hemoglobin ≥13.0 g/dL for men and ≥11.0 g/dL for women

               -  Platelet count ≥150,000/mm^3

               -  Creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) within normal
                  limits

               -  Normal thyroid, adrenal and diabetes testing

          -  Negative tuberculosis (TB) test result, OR documentation of completed TB prophylaxis
             treatment

          -  HCV antibody negative result or, if HCV antibody positive, undetectable HCV RNA result

          -  Negative HBsAg result

          -  18 - 70 years of age

          -  Ability and willingness to provide informed consent.

          -  Ability and willingness to continue non-study-provided cART throughout the study.

          -  Female participants must have a negative pregnancy test. Agree not to participate in a
             conception process (e.g., active attempt to become pregnant or to impregnate, sperm
             donation, in vitro fertilization, egg donation) during the study.

          -  When participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, agree to use at
             least two reliable forms of contraception simultaneously during the study through week
             48.

          -  Participants who are not of reproductive potential (women who have been
             post-menopausal for at least 24 consecutive months or have undergone hysterectomy
             and/or bilateral oophorectomy or salpingectomy or men who have documented azoospermia
             or undergone vasectomy) are eligible without requiring the use of contraceptives.

          -  Weight ≥50 kg (110 pounds)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of malignancy within the last 5 years.

               -  Prior non-melanoma skin cancer (e.g., basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell skin
                  cancer) is not exclusionary with documentation of complete resection at least 3
                  months prior to enrollment.

          -  HIV-related opportunistic infections within the last 5 years

          -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).

          -  Prior radiation therapy.

          -  Active or previously treated active TB.

          -  Unstable asthma (e.g., sudden acute attacks occurring without an obvious trigger) or
             asthma requiring:

               -  Daily steroid or long acting beta-agonist prevention

               -  Hospitalization in the 2 years prior to entry

          -  Type I or type II diabetes mellitus.

          -  History of or active autoimmune disorders including but not limited to inflammatory
             bowel diseases, scleroderma, severe psoriasis, myocarditis, uveitis, pneumonitis,
             systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, optic neuritis, myasthenia gravis,
             adrenal insufficiency, hypothyroidism and/or hyperthyroidism, autoimmune thyroiditis,
             hypophysitis, or sarcoidosis.

          -  Immune deficiency other than that caused by HIV infection.

          -  Currently breastfeeding or pregnant.

          -  Known allergy/sensitivity or any hypersensitivity to mAb-based biologics, cemiplimab
             (anti-PD-1) or its formulation.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Receipt of investigational drug or use of investigational medical device within 6
             months prior to study entry.

          -  Use of or intent to use immunomodulators (e.g., interleukins, interferons,
             cyclosporine, systemic corticosteroids exceeding physiologic doses), HIV vaccine, or
             systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy within 60 days prior to study entry.

               -  NOTE: Participants receiving stable physiologic glucocorticoid doses, defined as
                  prednisone ≤10 mg/day or the equivalent, will not be excluded. Stable physiologic
                  glucocorticoid doses should not be discontinued for the duration of the study. In
                  addition, participants receiving topical corticosteroids will not be excluded.

          -  Any vaccination within 30 days

          -  HCV treatment within 6 months

          -  Prior immunoglobulin (IgG) therapy.

          -  History of an adverse event related to prior administration of immunoglobulin therapy.

          -  Current use or intent to use biotin ≥5 mg/day, including within dietary supplements.

          -  History of chronic congestive heart failure or other significant cardiac conditions.

          -  Any active, clinically significant medical condition that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would place the participant at increased risk.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Gay, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Chapel Hill CRS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>W. David Hardy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alabama CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35294</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Antiviral Research Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chapel Hill CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Puerto Rico</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cemiplimab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie results in the publication, after deidentification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 3 months following publication and available throughout period of funding of the AIDS Clinical Trials Group by NIH.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>With whom?
Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal for use of the data that is approved by the AIDS Clinical Trials Group.
For what types of analyses?
To achieve aims in the proposal approved by the AIDS Clinical Trials Group.
By what mechanism will data be made available?
Researchers may submit a request for access to data using the AIDS Clinical Trials Group &quot;Data Request&quot; form at: https://actgnetwork.org/about-actg/templates-and-forms. Researchers of approved proposals will need to sign an AIDS Clinical Trials Group Data Use Agreement before receiving the data.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 2, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/95/NCT03787095/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

