<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03785327</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1806799</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03785327</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Social Interaction for Adolescents With Autism During the Transition to Adulthood</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Social Interaction for Adolescents With Autism During the Transition to Adulthood</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas at Dallas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas at Dallas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study compares the efficacy of two intervention strategies for improving social outcomes
      for autistic adolescents and young adults when interacting with unfamiliar non-autistic
      peers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intellectually-capable older adolescents and young adults with autism spectrum disorder (ASD)
      often struggle to secure and maintain employment, succeed in college, or develop satisfying
      personal and professional relationships. Current psychosocial interventions for this
      population have produced limited effects on real-world functioning. These programs typically
      seek to improve social skill and understanding with the hope that these abilities will
      translate to better functioning and are often effective at increasing knowledge of social
      rules and norms,yet these improvements frequently do not translate to better social and life
      outcomes in the real world. One reason for their limited efficacy may be that the mechanisms
      involved in real-life social interaction continue to be poorly understood for this
      population. The current study is designed to specify the factors that predict more or less
      favorable social outcomes for autistic adolescents and young adults when interacting with an
      unfamiliar, non-autistic peer, and test a multifaceted intervention for improving these
      outcomes. The intervention will target both brain and behavior, not only in the individual
      with ASD but also in their typically-developing (TD) partners. For TD participants, the
      efficacy of a training program will be tested to determine if social experiences for older
      adolescents with ASD can be improved by increasing knowledge, acceptance, and understanding
      of autism among TD individuals. For the participants with ASD, this study will test the
      efficacy of an innovative, non-invasive neurostimulation session using Transcranial Direct
      Current Stimulation (tDCS) to target social brain regions involved in perspective-taking and
      social reciprocity. Social outcomes for each intervention will be compared to a &quot;no
      intervention&quot; control condition, and to each other, to provide a comprehensive examination of
      intrinsic and extrinsic factors contributing to social interaction quality for autistic
      adolescents and young adults.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>ASD participants will complete active and sham simulation sessions in a randomized, counterbalanced order approximately one week apart
TD participants will be assigned to receive or not receive a training session.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Social Interaction Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Interaction with unfamiliar partner occurs 30 minutes after completion of the active/sham stimulation; or immediately following the autism training</time_frame>
    <description>Objective social interaction quality is assessed by trained coders blind to diagnostic status of participants using the Conversation Probe (Pinkham &amp; Penn, 2006)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Social Interaction Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Interaction with unfamiliar partner occurs 30 minutes after completion of the active/sham stimulation; or immediately following the autism training; self-report measures given immediately after the interaction</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective social interaction quality is assessed using questionnaires measuring participant evaluation of the interaction and their partner.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Cognition</measure>
    <time_frame>Completed 5 minutes after subjective interaction quality measures</time_frame>
    <description>Social Cognition is assessed using a battery of social cognitive tasks assessing social perception, emotion recognition, and mentalizing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">154</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Typical Development</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active anodal tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Active anodal tDCS followed by behavioral testing Intervention: Device: active anodal tDCS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham tDCS followed by behavioral testing Intervention: Device: sham tDCS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autism Training Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training program designed to increase autism understanding followed by behavioral testing Intervention:Training program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Social interaction without intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control condition: Behavioral testing without an intervention component</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tDCS</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants either complete active and sham tDCS sessions one week apart or an autism training program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active anodal tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autism Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Autism Information Presentation developed by Dr. Grace Iarocci's Autism &amp; Developmental Disorders Lab at Simon Fraser University</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autism Training Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 18-21

          -  DSM-IV-TR or DSM-5 diagnosis of an Autism Spectrum Disorder

          -  IQ&gt;70

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence or history intellectual impairment (defined as IQ &lt;70)

          -  Presence or history of medical, cardiac, or neurological disorders that may affect
             brain function (e.g., cardiac disease, endocrine disorders, renal disease, pulmonary
             disease, history of seizures or head trauma with unconsciousness for a period of 15
             minutes or greater or CNS tumors)

          -  Presence of sensory limitation including visual (e.g., blindness, glaucoma, vision
             uncorrectable to 20/40) or hearing (e.g. hearing loss) impairments that interfere with
             assessment

          -  Not proficient in English

          -  Presence of substance abuse in the past one month

          -  Presence of substance dependence not in remission for the past six months

          -  Contraindications for tDCS (e.g., pregnancy or implanted devices such as pace maker)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas at Dallas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richardson</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75080-3021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas at Dallas</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Noah Sasson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

