<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03785730</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Unib3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03785730</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultraconservative Caries Treatment in Anterior Cavitated Caries Lesion of Primary Teeth</brief_title>
  <acronym>CEPECO2</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Ultraconservative Caries Treatment in Anterior Cavitated Caries Lesion of Primary Teeth on Survival of Teeth and Patient-reported Outcomes - Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Ibirapuera</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Ibirapuera</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this randomized clinical trial is to evaluate the efficacy of composite
      resin (CR) restorations compared to ultraconservative (UTC) treatment for proximal anterior
      teeth cavitated caries lesions, as well as the impact of these treatments on the
      cost-effectiveness of procedures, the discomfort of the patient in relation to the different
      techniques and in the perception of parents / guardians regarding the treatments received.
      Children aged 3 to 6 years will be randomly selected from the Clinical Center for Pediatric
      Dentistry at UNIB, at the Clinic of Infants and Pediatric Dentistry at Santa Cecília
      University and at Pediatric Dentistry Clinic at UNINOVAFAPI University Center. 196 teeth will
      be randomized into two experimental groups: (1) Selective removal of carious tissue and
      restoration with composite resin (RC) and (2) Ultraconservative treatment by means of cavity
      enlargement using metal sandpaper (UTC). The primary outcome will be the survival of the
      tooth that will be evaluated after 6, 12, 18 and 24 months by two trained and blinded
      examiners for the treatments performed. The duration of the treatments and the cost of the
      materials used will be considered for the estimation of the cost-effectiveness of each
      treatment. The discomfort reported by the participant will be measured after each procedure
      using the FIS scale. Parents perception will be evaluated through questionnaire. For the
      primary outcome, Kaplan-Meier survival and Cox regression with shared frailty will be used
      for comparison between groups. For all analyzes, the significance value will be adjusted to
      5%.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled, two-arms parallel-group (1:1) trial. Initially, it will be
      submitted to the Research Ethics Committee of the Ibirapuera University - UNIB. The other
      centers involved will be considered as co-participants (Santa Cecilia University - UNISANTA
      and Uninovafapi University Center - UNINOVAFAPI). Only those patients who meet the
      eligibility criteria will be included in the study after signing the Informed Consent Form by
      the parents and the child's assent to study participation.

      In order to carry out the sample calculation, the expected survival for the primary teeth
      with cavitated lesions on the proximal surface submitted to ultraconservative treatments is
      89.7% after a period of 24 months (Mijan et al., 2014). Thus, a clinically significant
      difference is expected to be 20% in the success rate between the groups. With this, adopting
      a level of significance of 0.05 and a power of 0.80, we reached the number of 136 patients.
      Since each child can contribute more than one tooth, 20% was added to that value (cluster per
      child), and 20% due to a possible sample loss. Thus, the final rounded number of 98 teeth per
      group resulted in 196 teeth in total (MedCalc version 15.8, Ostend, BE).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Outbreak of COVID-19.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tooth survival by clinical assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the survival of teeth treated with restoration of composite resin and with UTC for lesions cavitated in anterior primary teeth by clinical assessment, considering the presence of tooth in the cavity without the need for a new treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discomfort regarding the treatment options by a Face image scale (FIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Children-reported discomfort regarding the treatment options by a Face image scale (FIS). The scale present 5 different faces since &quot;very happy&quot; (scored as 1) until &quot;very sad&quot; (scored as 5) with the treatment. Higher scores mean a worse discomfort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-efficacy analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of the treatments (time of treatment) and the cost of the materials used will be considered for the estimation of the cost-efficacy of the treatments by a ratio - cost/efficacy, being efficacy considered the tooth survival.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perception of parents / guardians evaluated through questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to treatment, immediately after and 6 months later.</time_frame>
    <description>Parents perception of the treatments will be evaluated through a questionnaire - &quot;Child's and parent's questionnaire about teeth appearance&quot; - with possible answers varying from very satisfied until insatisfied. After the questionnaire is applied for the parents/guardians, the anwsers will bem transformed in scores 1 to 5, in according the original paper that validated the questionnaire. Higher scores mean a worse perception.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction of children: questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>After 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Children-reported satisfaction regarding the treatment by a questionnaire with five question which for answers will be used a Face image scale (FIS). The scale present 5 different faces since &quot;very happy&quot; (scored as 1) until &quot;very sad&quot; (scored as 5) with the treatment. Lower scores mean a better satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">196</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>UTC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Enlargement of the wells with metal sandpaper.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Restoration with composite resin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Selective caries removal and restoration with composite resin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UCT</intervention_name>
    <description>In the experimental group, the treatment will be performed after prophylaxis and relative isolation. The cavitated caries lesion will be widened with the aid of a metal sandpaper to facilitate the removal of the biofilm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>UTC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Restoration with composite resin</intervention_name>
    <description>In control group, the treatment will be performed after prophylaxis and relative isolation. The selective caries removal will be performed with appropriate dentin curettes, and then the application of the adhesive system and restoration of composite resin will be conducted.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Restoration with composite resin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children will be included that have at least one anterior tooth with carious lesion
             cavitated affecting the proximal surface.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded with special needs, using orthodontics devices and/or
             systemic diseases which may affect the oral cavity.

          -  Also, teeth with lesions affecting more than one third of the vestibular / palatine /
             lingual surfaces, with a prior history of trauma, presenting pulp exposure,
             spontaneous pain, mobility, presence of abscess or fistula next to the tooth, teeth
             with restorations, enamel formation defects or with physiological mobility
             (exfoliation) will also be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tamara Kerber Tedesco</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>04.545-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Ibirapuera</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tamara Kerber Tedesco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will be available on Mendeley database.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

