<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03786614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRD2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03786614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antidepressant Discontinuation in Treatment Resistant Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Antidepressant Discontinuation in Treatment Resistant Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Louisville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Louisville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the effects on depressive symptoms of subjects who
      discontinue serotonergic antidepressants (a certain type of antidepressant, such as Prozac,
      that works on serotonin receptors in the brain) with the effects on depressive symptoms of
      subjects who continue to take serotonergic antidepressants. During this study, subjects will
      also be presented with the opportunity to undergo genetic testing for the serotonin gene
      transporter which has a short or long form. This is being done because it has been
      demonstrated that genetic testing improves outcome while treating treatment-resistant
      depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The person performing the data collection (rater) will be blind to the randomization of the patient for the entire duration of the study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing the difference of response as measured by the Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale [MADRS] between both arms.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline and every visit [every 4 weeks] to the end of the study. [6 months]</time_frame>
    <description>The MADRS is a psychiatric scale to assess the depressive symptoms from the patient's prospective. The final score ranges from 0 to 60 with 0 indicating no depression and higher scores indicating greater depression. The final scores will be evaluated with a non-paired, two-tailed t-test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparing the difference of response as measured by the Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale [MADRS] between subjects with low expressing alleles and high expressing alleles of the serotonin gene transporter.</measure>
    <time_frame>End of study [6 months].</time_frame>
    <description>Genetic testing for the serotonin transporter gene will be done for every patient in the study. All subjects with homozygous and heterozygous low expression alleles will be combined as one group, and all high expression subjects will be the other group. One-way ANOVAs will be conducted for each genotype group, with genotype group as the independent variable (IV) and MADRS scores as the dependent variables (DV).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating changes in levels of anxiety as measured by the Hamilton Anxiety Rating Scale [HAM-A] between both arms.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline and every visit [every 4 weeks] to the end of the study. [6 months]</time_frame>
    <description>The HAM-A will be collected to assess changes in anxiety levels from the patient's prospective. It ranges from 0 to 56 with greater scores indicating more anxiety. The final scores will be evaluated with a non-paired, two-tailed t-test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluating the difference of response as measured by the Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale [C-SSRS] between both arms.</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline and every visit [every 4 weeks] to the end of the study. [6 months]</time_frame>
    <description>The C-SSRS is a psychiatric scale to assess suicidality. It ranges from 0 to 5 with 0 indicating no suicidal ideas and higher scores indicating greater suicidal ideas. The final scores will be evaluated with a non-paired, two-tailed t-test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Treatment Resistant Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Discontinuation arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will be discontinued from serotonergic antidepressants and shifting them to other categories of antidepressants, i.e., medications that work through dopamine or nor-epinephrine, or by reducing the serotonin signal rather than increasing synaptic serotonin, as might be accomplished with low dose, sub-anti-psychotic doses of some second-generation anti-psychotics.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuation arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will continue taking serotonergic antidepressants which is the standard care of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Discontinuation of serotonergic antidepressants</intervention_name>
    <description>Discontinuation of serotonergic antidepressants and possibly shift to other antidepressant categories that were proven to be effective in treating depression such as pramipexole, bupropion, quetiapine, lurasidone, brexpipazole. Additionally, subjects will have access to other treatment measures of treating treatment resistant depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Discontinuation arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuation of serotonergic medications</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuation of serotonergic medications which is the standard care of treatment. Additionally, subjects will have access to other treatment measures of treating treatment resistant depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continuation arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be a man or woman 18 to 70 years of age, inclusive.

          -  Subject must meet criteria for a major depressive disorder as confirmed by the Mini
             International Neuropsychiatric Interview [MINI].

          -  Subjects must have a current Treatment-Resistant Depression as defined below.

          -  Subjects must have been taking serotonergic antidepressants (serotonin reuptake
             inhibitor or monoamine oxidase inhibitor) for at least 2 years but not more than 4
             years, and have failed 2 previous medication trial for the current episode. Current
             Montgomery-Åsberg Depression Rating Scale [MADRS] score must be equal to or more than
             25.

          -  Subject must be medically stable.

          -  Female subjects must have a negative urine pregnancy test at screening, and agree to
             avoid pregnancy during the study.

          -  Each subject must sign an informed consent form indicating that he/she understands the
             purpose of the study and the procedures required and are willing to participate in the
             study.

          -  Subject must be able to participate in symptom measurement.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a current Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders-5 [DSM-5]
             diagnosis of bipolar disorder or has a positive screening for bipolar disorder by Mini
             International Neuropsychiatric Interview [MINI] or Mood Disorder Questionnaire [MDQ].

          -  Subject has a current DSM-5 diagnosis of schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder,
             autistic disorder, or intellectual disability.

          -  Subject has a substance use disorder (except for nicotine or cannabis) within 3 months
             prior to screening or has a positive drug screen test for any recreational drugs at
             the time of screening with the exception of Cannabis.

          -  Subject has evidence of any clinically significant, unstable medical problems that may
             create a safety risk for a subject, interfere with study participation, or make
             results difficult to interpret.

          -  Subject is at imminent risk of suicide according to the investigator's clinical
             judgment and/or a Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) 3 or more at any
             time in the study.

          -  Subject is a woman who is pregnant, breast-feeding or planning to become pregnant
             while enrolled in the study.

          -  Subject has any condition (according to the investigator) for which participation will
             not be the best interest for the subject or it can prevent, limit or confound the
             protocol-specified assessments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rifaat S. El-Mallakh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Louisville, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sharon Nuss</last_name>
    <phone>502-588-0678</phone>
    <email>sharon.nuss@louisville.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sharon Nuss</last_name>
      <phone>502-588-0678</phone>
      <email>sharon.nuss@louisville.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rif S. El-Mallakh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ziad A. Ali, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Louisville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rifaat S. El-Mallakh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>treatment resistant depression</keyword>
  <keyword>serotonergic antidepressants</keyword>
  <keyword>short form of serotonin transporter</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Treatment-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

