<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03788941</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XH-18-015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03788941</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Left Atrial Appendage Closure in Combination With Catheter Ablation</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Efficacy and Safety of Left Atrial Appendage Closure in Combination With Catheter Ablation in Patients With Atrial Fibrillation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective cohort study aimed at investigating the efficacy and safety of
      left atrial appendage closure in combination with catheter ablation in patients with atrial
      fibrillation.

      Patients diagnosed with paroxysmal or persistent atrial fibrillation with an age between 18
      and 80 years will be enrolled in this study. After enrollment, patients will be divided
      nonrandomly into two cohorts. In the first cohort, patients will only receive atrial
      fibrillation ablation. In the other cohort, patients will receive both standard ablation
      procedure as well as left atrial appendage closure(&quot;one-stop&quot; treatment). For each cohort,
      180 patients will be included, with an estimated total number of 360 participants in this
      clinical study. After the procedure, the patients will be followed with a duration of 12
      months. During the follow-up, events of atrial arrhythmias, events of stroke/TIA and
      systematic embolism, bleeding, hospitalization due to heart failure et al. will be identified
      and recorded. Patients will be followed-up in the 3rd, 9th, 12th months after the ablation
      procedure or&quot;one-stop&quot; therapy. Items including 12-leads ECG, 24h Holter ECG, transesophageal
      echocardiography and transthoracic echocardiography will be performed accordingly. Head
      computed tomography or MRI will also be conducted if necessary. The investigators will only
      harvest whole blood to determine the biomarkers including NT-proBNP and inflammatory
      cytokines. Statistics analysis will be performed to compare the differences between the two
      cohorts in the events of primary and secondary endpoints. The investigators hypothesize that
      &quot;one-stop&quot; treatment will be superior to catheter ablation alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective and observational clinical trial investigating the efficacy and
      safety of catheter ablation in combination with left atrial appendage closure in treating
      patients with atrial fibrillation. The investigators and sponsors will work together to
      develop research protocols, case report forms, research medical records, and informed consent
      in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Research related materials will be reported
      to the Medical Ethics Committee for review and approval. All included patients will sign the
      informed consent form and followed-up regularly for clinical outcomes and adverse events.

      This study will be conducted in accordance with the following procedures:

        1. Screen out 360 patients in accordance with the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The
           screening period begins with the subject signing the informed consent form and until the
           subject begins receiving treatment. Usually, the subject's written informed consent must
           be obtained prior to any trial-related procedures. If the subject has received physical
           examinations and laboratory tests within 2 weeks prior to screening after admission, the
           participants may also sign informed consent and use the results as screening data. After
           obtaining informed consent, the subject's basic information is recorded in the &quot;subject
           screening form.&quot; The following screening assessments should be made: demographic data,
           medical history, physical examination, vital signs data, the height and body weight,
           laboratory parameters, ECG examination, assessment for medication and evaluation for
           inclusion/exclusion criteria.

        2. After enrollment, participants will be nonrandomly divided into two cohorts according to
           patients' medical conditions and willingness to the therapeutic approaches, receiving
           radiofrequency ablation and the radiofrequency ablation in combination with left atrial
           appendage closure respectively. Participants will be assessed and observed carefully
           during and after the operation.

        3. The participants will be followed-up in the third, ninth and twelfth months after the
           treatments. The main follow-up includes the review of ECG, 24h Holter, echocardiography,
           transesophageal echocardiography, coronary CT et al., and brain CT or MRI if necessary.
           participants' medication and symptoms will also be observed and recorded. The incidence
           of stroke, systemic embolism, and cardiovascular death; the rate of patients maintaining
           sinus rhythm, hospitalization due to heart failure, and perioperative complications such
           as pericardial tamponade, wound hematoma and long-term surgery-related complications
           will be recorded. Adverse events during the trial will also be assessed and recorded.

        4. Collect research data and perform the statistical analysis. For Statistical analysis,
           the sample size calculation is based on the overall incidence of stroke, systemic
           embolism, and cardiovascular death events. The study included multiple endpoint tests
           that would use a 5% significance level with a test efficacy of 90%. Assume that 10% of
           patients have withdrawn from the middle and 10% have lost follow-up. According to the
           literature and most experts, the total proportion of stroke, systemic embolism, and
           cardiovascular death in patients with atrial fibrillation is 6.3/100 person-years. The
           investigators estimate that with the use of radiofrequency ablation in combination with
           left atrial appendage closure, the proportion of events is 2.0/100 person-years.
           According to the sample size estimation formula, the number of trials should be 360
           patients (180 in each group).

      The overall timing of the trial: patients' enrollment and treatment will be completed from
      January 2019 to December 2020. The last participants will be followed-up for 1 year after
      completion of the treatment. It is expected that the trial will be completed in a total of 36
      months by December 2021.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of stroke/TIA events as assessed by CT scans</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after the procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of stroke/TIA events in the participants will be reported. Participants with clinical manifestations of stroke/TIA will undergo neurological examination and CT scans for diagnosis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of systemic embolism events as assessed by CT scans</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after the procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of systemic embolism events in the participants will be reported. Systemic embolism usually refers to pulmonary artery embolism and embolism in the arteries of other organs like kidney, spleen and mesentery et al.. CT scans are effective in diagnosing an artery embolism.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of maintenance of sinus rhythm as assessed by electrocardiogram</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after the procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>This refers to the percentage of patients who maintain sinus rhythm after catheter ablation or catheter ablation in combination with left atrial appendage closure. Electrocardiogram can be used to diagnose sinus rhythm or arrhythmias.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with early-term complications</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after the procedure.</time_frame>
    <description>These are usually refer to perioperative complications such as cardiac tamponade, lesion hematoma and pseudoaneurysm et al. which are related to the manipulation of operator. Diagnostic ultrasound imaging can efficiently identify these complications.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LAAC plus Catheter ablation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will receive both left atrial appendage closure and catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation for treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Catheter ablation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will only receive catheter ablation of atrial fibrillation for treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>left atrial appendage closure and catheter ablation</intervention_name>
    <description>Left atrial appendage closure (LAAC) is a treatment strategy to reduce the risk of left atrial appendage blood clots from entering the bloodstream and causing a stroke in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation (AF).
Catheter ablation is a procedure used to remove or terminate a faulty electrical pathway or pathological sites from sections of the hearts of those who are prone to developing cardiac arrhythmias such as atrial fibrillation, atrial flutter, supraventricular tachycardias (SVT) and Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome (WPW syndrome). The ablation procedure can be classified by energy source: radiofrequency ablation and cryoablation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LAAC plus Catheter ablation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>left atrial appendage occlusion; radiofrequency ablation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will only harvest whole blood to determine the biomarkers of heart failure
      and inflammation in the plasma. The investigators will not retain any tissue or other
      specimens or extract DNA from tissues or plasma.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. History of paroxysmal/sustained atrial fibrillation (evidence includes any of the
             following: Holter or 12-lead ECG recorder to atrial fibrillation);

          2. One or more drug treatments are ineffective or patients unwilling to be treated with
             long-term drugs;

          3. Unable to tolerate drug treatment or with contraindications

          4. CHA2DS2-VASc score ≥ 2 and/or HAS-BLED score ≥ 3

          5. Provide informed consent to participate in the study, follow-up trials and assessment
             procedures;

          6. with an age between 18-80 years
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. History of paroxysmal/sustained atrial fibrillation (evidence includes any of the
             following: Holter or 12-lead ECG recorder to atrial fibrillation);

          2. One or more drug treatments are ineffective or patients unwilling to be treated with
             long-term drugs;

          3. Unable to tolerate drug treatment or with contraindications

          4. CHA2DS2-VASc score ≥ 2 and/or HAS-BLED score ≥ 3

          5. Provide informed consent to participate in the study, follow-up trials and assessment
             procedures;

          6. with an age between 18-80 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. There are acute lesions, such as acute phase after myocardial infarction (within 3
             months), acute heart attack or 3 months after new cerebral infarction;

          2. On the list of a heart transplant;

          3. Life expectancy is less than 1 year;

          4. There are other bleeding diseases that cannot be treated with anticoagulation;

          5. With left atrial thrombus;

          6. Patients with uncontrolled cancer ;

          7. Obvious liver and kidney dysfunction (and/or ALT, AST is more than 1 times the upper
             limit of normal, CCr &lt;50%);

          8. previous radiofrequency ablation of atrial fibrillation or cardiac surgery;

          9. Women who are pregnant, breastfeeding or of childbearing age who do not adopt reliable
             methods of contraception.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yi-Gang Li, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiaotong University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhi-Quan Wang, Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>86 021 25077275</phone>
    <email>wangzhiquan@xinhuamed.com.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Björck S, Palaszewski B, Friberg L, Bergfeldt L. Atrial fibrillation, stroke risk, and warfarin therapy revisited: a population-based study. Stroke. 2013 Nov;44(11):3103-8. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.002329. Epub 2013 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23982711</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Haim M, Hoshen M, Reges O, Rabi Y, Balicer R, Leibowitz M. Prospective national study of the prevalence, incidence, management and outcome of a large contemporary cohort of patients with incident non-valvular atrial fibrillation. J Am Heart Assoc. 2015 Jan 21;4(1):e001486. doi: 10.1161/JAHA.114.001486.</citation>
    <PMID>25609415</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Benjamin EJ, Wolf PA, D'Agostino RB, Silbershatz H, Kannel WB, Levy D. Impact of atrial fibrillation on the risk of death: the Framingham Heart Study. Circulation. 1998 Sep 8;98(10):946-52.</citation>
    <PMID>9737513</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stewart S, Hart CL, Hole DJ, McMurray JJ. A population-based study of the long-term risks associated with atrial fibrillation: 20-year follow-up of the Renfrew/Paisley study. Am J Med. 2002 Oct 1;113(5):359-64.</citation>
    <PMID>12401529</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Andersson T, Magnuson A, Bryngelsson IL, Frøbert O, Henriksson KM, Edvardsson N, Poçi D. All-cause mortality in 272,186 patients hospitalized with incident atrial fibrillation 1995-2008: a Swedish nationwide long-term case-control study. Eur Heart J. 2013 Apr;34(14):1061-7. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs469. Epub 2013 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23321349</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Di Biase L, Mohanty P, Mohanty S, Santangeli P, Trivedi C, Lakkireddy D, Reddy M, Jais P, Themistoclakis S, Dello Russo A, Casella M, Pelargonio G, Narducci ML, Schweikert R, Neuzil P, Sanchez J, Horton R, Beheiry S, Hongo R, Hao S, Rossillo A, Forleo G, Tondo C, Burkhardt JD, Haissaguerre M, Natale A. Ablation Versus Amiodarone for Treatment of Persistent Atrial Fibrillation in Patients With Congestive Heart Failure and an Implanted Device: Results From the AATAC Multicenter Randomized Trial. Circulation. 2016 Apr 26;133(17):1637-44. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.115.019406. Epub 2016 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>27029350</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hu H, Cui K, Jiang J, Fu H, Zeng R. Safety and efficacy analysis of one-stop intervention for treating nonvalvular atrial fibrillation. Pacing Clin Electrophysiol. 2018 Jan;41(1):28-34. doi: 10.1111/pace.13250. Epub 2017 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>29194654</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Phillips KP, Pokushalov E, Romanov A, Artemenko S, Folkeringa RJ, Szili-Torok T, Senatore G, Stein KM, Razali O, Gordon N, Boersma LVA. Combining Watchman left atrial appendage closure and catheter ablation for atrial fibrillation: multicentre registry results of feasibility and safety during implant and 30 days follow-up. Europace. 2018 Jun 1;20(6):949-955. doi: 10.1093/europace/eux183.</citation>
    <PMID>29106523</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lemola K, Sneider M, Desjardins B, Case I, Chugh A, Hall B, Cheung P, Good E, Han J, Tamirisa K, Bogun F, Pelosi F Jr, Kazerooni E, Morady F, Oral H. Effects of left atrial ablation of atrial fibrillation on size of the left atrium and pulmonary veins. Heart Rhythm. 2004 Nov;1(5):576-81.</citation>
    <PMID>15851222</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Perea RJ, Tamborero D, Mont L, De Caralt TM, Ortiz JT, Berruezo A, Matiello M, Sitges M, Vidal B, Sanchez M, Brugada J. Left atrial contractility is preserved after successful circumferential pulmonary vein ablation in patients with atrial fibrillation. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol. 2008 Apr;19(4):374-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1540-8167.2007.01086.x. Epub 2008 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18266672</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Luani B, Groscheck T, Genz C, Tanev I, Rauwolf T, Herold J, Medunjanin S, Schmeisser A, Braun-Dullaeus RC. Left atrial enlargement and clinical considerations in patients with or without a residual interatrial shunt after closure of the left atrial appendage with the WATCHMAN™-device. BMC Cardiovasc Disord. 2017 Dec 12;17(1):294. doi: 10.1186/s12872-017-0728-6.</citation>
    <PMID>29233088</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Holmes DR Jr, Kar S, Price MJ, Whisenant B, Sievert H, Doshi SK, Huber K, Reddy VY. Prospective randomized evaluation of the Watchman Left Atrial Appendage Closure device in patients with atrial fibrillation versus long-term warfarin therapy: the PREVAIL trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Jul 8;64(1):1-12. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2014.04.029. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Sep 16;64(11):1186.</citation>
    <PMID>24998121</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 28, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

