<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03785652</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LY03005-CHN-204</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03785652</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose-Finding Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of LY03005 Extended-release Tablets in the Treatment of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multicenter,Randomized,Double-blind,Placebo,Parallel-controlled,Dose-Finding Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of LY03005 Extended-release Tablets in the Treatment of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Luye Pharma Group Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shandong Luye Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Luye Pharma Group Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo, parallel-controlled,
      dose-finding Phase II clinical trial to find the optimal dose of LY03005 Extended-release
      Tablets for the treatment of MDD and to evaluate the preliminary efficacy and safety,
      providing a basis for the design of phase III clinical trials and the determination of dosing
      regimens.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study consisted of two periods: a screening and washout period of 2 weeks (recommended 8
      days) and a double-blind treatment period (6 weeks). The first period is the screening and
      washing period, the longest is 14 days and the shortest is 8 days (recommended 8 days), in
      which the enrolled MDD subjects will start a one-week placebo wash period and receive
      prescribed a placebo, 2 pills once a day for 7 consecutive days. The second period was a
      double-blind treatment period of 6 weeks. After the placebo washout period, 260 enrolled
      subjects were randomized into one of 5 study groups in the 1:1:1:1:1 ratio, 4 LY03005
      Extended-release Tablets treatment groups with different dose or 1 placebo group. Subjects
      were given investigatory drug or placebo according to the protocol, 4 pills once a day and
      followed up at the end of 1, 2, 4 and 6 weeks.

      Effectiveness of the investigational drug was evaluated using 17 Hamilton Depression Scale
      (HAM-D17), Montgomery-Asberg Depression Scale (MADRS), Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAMA),
      Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI) and Visual Analog Scale—Pain intensity (VAS-PI)
      scores. Safety of the treatment was evaluated by adverse events, vital signs, laboratory
      measurements (blood routine, urine routine, blood biochemistry and serology), 12-lead ECG,
      physical examination, the Arizona Sexual Experience Scale (ASEX) and the Columbia-Suicide
      Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 9, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline in the total score of 17 items of Hamilton Depression Scale (HAM-D17) at the end of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Montgomery- Åsberg Depression Rating Scale(MADRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes from baseline in the 10-items Montgomery- Åsberg Depression Rating Scale(MADRS) total scores at the end of treatment;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression Scale - improvement (CGI-I)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the Clinical Global Impression Scale - improvement (CGI-I) scores at the end of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 extended-release tablets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LY03005 extended-release tablets at 4 doses 40 mg, 80mg, 120mg or 160mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tablet</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY03005 extended-release tablets 40 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>LY03005 extended-release tablets 40 mg group :40mg/day，orally once a day, at a regular morning time on an empty stomach or after breakfas</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 extended-release tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY03005 extended-release tablets 80 mg group</intervention_name>
    <description>LY03005 extended-release tablets 80 mg group :
80mg/day，orally once a day, at a regular morning time on an empty stomach or after breakfast</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 extended-release tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY03005 extended-release tablets 120 mg group</intervention_name>
    <description>LY03005 extended-release tablets 120 mg group :
120mg/day，orally once a day, at a regular morning time on an empty stomach or after breakfast</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 extended-release tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LY03005 extended-release tablets 160 mg group</intervention_name>
    <description>LY03005 extended-release tablets 160 mg group :
160mg/day，orally once a day, at a regular morning time on an empty stomach or after breakfast</description>
    <arm_group_label>LY03005 extended-release tablets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo group</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo group :
Placebo ，orally once a day, at a regular morning time on an empty stomach or after breakfast</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female aged 18 to 65 years subjects from outpatient or inpatient;

          2. Subjects who meet the diagnostic criteria for MDD in DSM-IV-TR (Diagnostic and
             Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition) with either single or recurrent
             episodes (296.2/296.3) without psychotic characteristics;

          3. Total scores of 17-item Hamilton Depression Scale (HAM-D17) ≥ 20 points at screening
             and baseline visits；

          4. First item (depressive mood) score of HAM-D17 scale ≥ 2 points at screening and
             baseline visits;

          5. Clinical global impression scale-disease severity (CGI-S) score ≥ 4 points at
             screening and baseline visits;

          6. At screening and baseline, women of childbearing age (e.g., women who have not
             undergone surgical sterilization or less than one year after menopause) have a urine
             negative pregnancy test result. Male and female subjects of childbearing age agree to
             take effective contraceptive measures during the entire study period and at least 28
             days after the last dose of investigatory drug;

          7. Subjects voluntarily participate in the trial by signing the informed consent form and
             are able to follow the schedule in the protocol for visits, treatment, laboratory
             tests and other research procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Allergic or known to be allergic to venlafaxine and desvenlafaxine;

          2. MDD subjects who were not responsive to the previous venlafaxine treatment with
             sufficient amount and duration or TRD, to at least two different mechanisms of action
             antidepressants with adequate amount and duration in the past;

          3. Total scores of HAM-D17 scale at baseline was decreased ≥25% compared with the one at
             screening;

          4. There is a clear suicide attempt or behavior and score of the 3rd item (suicidal
             thought) in HAM-D17 total scale ≥ 3 points;

          5. Gestational and lactating women or the subjects of childbearing age who do not take
             effective contraception or who do not agree to continue using contraception within 28
             days of the last dose;

          6. Suppressed subjects who also meet other diagnoses on the DSM-IV-TR axis I or received
             the treatment for such diagnoses (including current or previous diagnosis of anorexia
             nervosa or bulimia nervosa), or was diagnosed as dysthymia in the past 2 years;

          7. MDD secondary to other mental illnesses or physical illnesses;

          8. Those with a history of seizures (except for convulsions caused by febrile seizures in
             children);

          9. Those receiving electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) within 3 months prior to screening or
             according to the investigator's judgment that ECT is currently required; Those who
             have received systematic psychotherapy (interpersonal relationship therapy, dynamic
             therapy, cognitive behavioral therapy) within 3 months prior to screening；Those who
             have received transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) within 3 months prior to
             screening, or have received light therapy within 2 weeks prior to screening;

         10. Subjects who have regularly taken anti-depressants within 2 weeks prior to screening,
             and have stopped the anti-depressants less than 2 weeks or psychotropic drugs for less
             than 7 half-lives prior to study randomization (monoamine oxidase inhibitor for at
             least 2 weeks, fluoxetine for at least 1 month);

         11. Subjects who have seriously unstable cardiovascular, liver, kidneys, blood, endocrine
             and other physical diseases or a medical history;

         12. Hypertensive patients with poor blood pressure control (SBP≥140 mmHg or DBP≥90 mmHg at
             screening and baseline);

         13. There is a history of gastrointestinal disease known to interfere with drug absorption
             or excretion or a history of surgery known to interfere with drug absorption or
             excretion;

         14. A history of increased intra-ocular pressure or narrow-angle glaucoma;

         15. Clinically significant abnormalities based in investigators judgment during screening
             (for example, such as alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST) is 1.5 times higher than upper limit of normal range; creatinine (Cr) is higher
             than the upper limit of normal ranges and clinical significant abnormal thyroid
             function);

         16. Electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities are clinically significant at screening and the
             investigators believe that it is inappropriate for the subjects to be enrolled, such
             as QTc interval ≥450 ms for male and QTc interval ≥460 ms for female;

         17. Those who have participated in other clinical trials within 3 months prior to
             screening;

         18. Those with serious acute or chronic diseases, mental illnesses or clinically
             significant abnormalities in laboratory tests, of which investigators believe that the
             subjects are not suitable for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Approval Letter of Ethics Committee of The Sixth Hospital of Peking University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haidian District,</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100191</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

