<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03832400</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MET-2-201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03832400</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Microbial Ecosystem Therapeutic-2 (MET-2) in Patients With Ulcerative Colitis (UC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b, Placebo-controlled, Study of the Safety and Efficacy of MET-2 in Patients With Ulcerative Colitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NuBiyota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NuBiyota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To define the parameters for dose-dependent engraftment of MET-2 commensal bacteria for the
      treatment of mild to moderate ulcerative colitis
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will deliver MET-2 at two different doses via an oral capsule in patients with
      active mucosal inflammation and observe its safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetics (PK),
      pharmacodynamics (PD) and clinical efficacy as compared to placebo. The goal is to define the
      parameters for dose-dependent engraftment of MET-2 commensal bacteria for the treatment of
      mild to moderate ulcerative colitis not fully responsive to conventional therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a Phase 1b, placebo-controlled, multiple dose pilot study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The assessor will be blinded as to which dosing arm the subjects are assigned.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut Microbiome restoration</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs. day 42</time_frame>
    <description>Microbiologic assessment of fecal deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) samples will be obtained before, during and after treatment to quantify the change in microbial alpha diversity using statistical methods such as Shannon Diversity Index and Microbiome Health Index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of mucosal healing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs. Day 42</time_frame>
    <description>Mucosal biopsies will be taken and assessed. Assessment will be made using the Mayo Score for Ulcerative Colitis. There are four domains in this scale: Stool frequency, Rectal bleeding, Findings on endoscopy, Physician's global assessment. Each domain has a scoring range of 0 - 3, where 0 represents best possible outcome and 3 represents worst possible outcome. Efficacy of treatment will be defined as a 'Findings on endoscopy' score of less than or equal to one.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs. Day 42</time_frame>
    <description>This is a self-administered questionnaire. There are 32 quality of life questions related to bowel function. Each question is rated on a numerical scale. The number of possible ratings varies between questions but is most frequently from 1 to 7.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MET-2 20 g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be given a once-daily loading dose of 5 grams (g) of MET-2 in the form of 10 MET-2 capsules orally for the first 4 days. For the following 10 days, patients will take 1.5 g MET-2 in the form of three MET-2 capsules taken once-daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MET-2 40 g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be given a once-daily loading dose of 10 g of MET-2 in the form of 20 MET-2 capsules orally for the first 4 days. For the following 10 days, subjects will take 1.5 g MET-2 in the form of three MET-2 capsules taken once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo oral capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects receive 10 placebo capsules that are identical in appearance to the MET-2 capsules</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MET-2</intervention_name>
    <description>MET-2 is a defined consortium of human commensal bacteria derived from a healthy donor, which has the full metabolic functional capacity of fecal microbiota.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MET-2 20 g</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MET-2 40 g</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo oral capsule which is identical to the MET-2 capsules.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo oral capsule</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Mild to Moderate UC.

          2. ≥ 18 years old.

          3. Able to provide informed consent, or have a caregiver able to provide consent.

          4. Subjects must have a documented diagnosis (radiologic or endoscopic with histology) of
             UC for &gt;3 months before screening. The following must be available in each subject's
             source documentation:

               -  A biopsy report to confirm the histological diagnosis

               -  A report documenting disease duration and medication history prior to study
                  colonoscopy

          5. Subjects receiving any treatment(s) forUC are eligible provided they are anticipated
             to be on a stable dose for the duration of the study period and have been on therapy
             prior to the randomization visit for the following amount of time:

             Prednisone - 4 weeks; Budesonide - 4 weeks; 5-aminosalicylic acid (5-ASA) containing
             products - 4 weeks; Thiopurine analogs (azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine) - 12 weeks;
             Biologic therapy (infliximab, adalimumab, vedolizumab) - 12 weeks; Tofacitinib - 8
             weeks.

             No change in dose is permitted for the following time period prior to the
             randomization visit:

             Prednisone - 2 weeks; Budesonide - 4 weeks; 5-ASA containing products - 4 weeks;
             Thiopurine analogs (azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine) - 6 weeks; Biologic therapy
             (infliximab, adalimumab, vedolizumab) - 6 weeks; Tofacitinib - 4 weeks.

          6. Subjects are males or nonpregnant, nonlactating females who, if sexually active, agree
             to comply with the contraceptive requirements of the protocol, or females of
             nonchildbearing potential. Males and females of reproductive potential who are
             sexually active must agree to use acceptable contraception for the duration of the
             study.

          7. Willing to participate in follow up as part of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Ulcerative colitis with disease limited to only the distal rectum (&lt;5cm from dentate
             line).

          2. Subjects with indeterminate colitis, microscopic colitis, ischemic colitis, infectious
             colitis, or clinical/histologic findings suggestive of Crohn's disease will be
             excluded.

          3. Subjects with colonic dysplasia or neoplasia. (Subjects with prior history of
             adenomatous polyps will be eligible if the polyps have been completely removed).

          4. Subjects with toxic megacolon or hospitalized for ulcerative colitis.

          5. Subjects with colonic stricture, past medical history of colonic resection, a history
             of bowel surgery within 6 months before screening, or who are likely to require
             surgery for UC during the treatment period.

          6. Use of antibiotics within 6 weeks of randomization visit.

          7. Allergy to vancomycin.

          8. Elective surgery that will require preoperative antibiotics planned within 3 months of
             enrolment.

          9. Pregnant or planning to get pregnant in the next 6 months.

         10. Any condition for which, in the opinion of the investigator, the subject should be
             excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Allan H Steinhart, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MOUNT SINAI HOSPITAL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Allan H Steinhart, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(416) 586-5121</phone>
    <email>Hillary.Steinhart@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mark Silverberg, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(416) 586-4800</phone>
    <phone_ext>8236</phone_ext>
    <email>mark.silvererg@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Allan H Steinhart, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 586-5121</phone>
      <email>Hillary.Steinhart@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mark Silverberg, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>(416) 586-4800</phone>
      <phone_ext>8236</phone_ext>
      <email>mark.silverberg@sinaihealthsystem.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

