<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03830476</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Navigator ACT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03830476</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ACT -Groups for Parents to Children With Disabilities</brief_title>
  <acronym>NavigatorACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy Group, Navigator ACT for Parents to Children With Disabilities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stockholm County Council, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of the pragmatic multicenter RCT is to investigate acceptance and commitment
      therapy groups in treatment of distress in parents to children with disabilities.in a
      clinical disability services context. Participants in the study are parents reporting
      symptoms of depression, anxiety or parenting stress due to parenting a child with disability.
      The participants have a child/children (0-17 years) currently enrolled in the disability
      services in Sweden.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Navigator ACT group treatment consists of 5 sessions (each 3.5 hours), and is developed to
      address distress in parents raising a child with an Autism Spectrum Disorder and/or other
      disabilities.The aims of the study is to examine the feasibility, participant satisfaction
      and efficacy of the manual-based Navigator ACT group treatment in (a) improving
      psychological/behavioral flexibility (b) increasing mindfulness (c) reducing symptoms of
      depression and anxiety (d) reducing parenting stress (e) reducing behavioral problems of
      children with disability. This pragmatic multicenter RCT will be conducted mainly in
      Stockholm County Council disability services but even in other regions in Sweden. Parents
      participating in the study have their children (0-17 years) currently enrolled in the
      disability services (experiment group n=42, control group n=42, totaling at least 84 parents,
      with the power calculation for medium large effect of 90% ES=0.50). To balance for attrition
      approximately 100 parents will be included in the study.

      The participants will be block randomized in several blocks. The experiment group will be
      receiving Navigator ACT treatment directly after the randomizing procedure, the control group
      approximately six months after. The parents in the control group fill the efficacy-related
      self-rating forms at the same measuring points as the parents in the experiment group as well
      during their own group process.

      The feasibility of Navigator ACT in the disability services context is measured by
      attendance, that is: parents participating in at least 4 out of 5 sessions are considered as
      completers. The parent satisfaction is measured by session- and course evaluations. Five
      self-rating questionnaire are used to measure efficacy: The Mindfulness Awareness Attention
      Scale (MAAS), Parental Acceptance and Action Questionnaire (PAAQ) Parental Stress Scale (PSS)
      Hospital Anxiety and depression scale (HADS), The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire
      (SDQ). Self-rating questionnaires are administered to parents at the baseline (0-2 weeks
      before the treatment start, T1), at the end of the treatment (0-2 weeks after, T2) and at the
      follow-up (3-4 months after the end of the treatment, T3). The data will be analyzed from
      baseline T1 to T2 (post treatment) as well as from T1 (baseline) to T3 (follow-up) with
      separate series of repeated measures ANOVA between-group.

      The Regional Ethics Committee of Stockholm (2016/526-21-1,2016/115-31/4, 2017/573-31/5 ) has
      approved the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>RCT</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>Masking at baseline of both participant and care-provider.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1. Change (increase) in parental psychological flexibility</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: Change in psychological flexibility measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three-four month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>Parental Acceptance and Action Questionnaire (PAAQ), a 15-item scale that targets psychological flexibility in the parenting context, i.e. measures to which extent parents' accept inner and outer experiences as they are and are willing to take action in parenting situations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2. Change (increase) in mindfulness skills</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: Change in psychological flexibility measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three-four month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>The Mindfulness Awareness Attention Scale (MAAS), a 15-item scale (scored 1-6) assessing dispositional mindfulness in regards to cognitive, emotional, physical, interpersonal and general domains.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3. Change (decrease) in depression and anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: Change in psychological flexibility measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three-four month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). Has 14 items scored 0 (&quot;Often&quot;) - 3 (&quot;Seldom&quot;), subsequently summarized for an overall score; high scores indicate higher levels of depression or anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>4. Change (decrease) in parental stress.</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: Change in psychological flexibility measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three-four month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>The Parental Stress Scale (PSS) is a18-item tool for measurement of parenting stress, scored 1-5 on a 5-point Likert scale. The initial factor has suggested four-factor structure for the PSS consisting of parental 1) rewards, 2) stressors, 3) lack of control and 4) satisfaction in parenting. High scores indicate higher levels of stress in parenting context.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5. Change (decrease) in child's difficulties and the impact of these difficulties on the child's family.</measure>
    <time_frame>[Time Frame: Change in psychological flexibility measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three-four month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>The Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (P4-17 SDQ), a caregiver administered, 25-item extended version of SDQ used for behavior screening of children and adolescents in ages 4-17 years. The SDQ P4-17 covers common areas of emotional and behavioral difficulties and strengths as well as includes a caregiver reported impact- and burden assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Credibility Scale (TCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Measured at baseline, immediately after the intervention and at three month follow-up]</time_frame>
    <description>As a measure of feasibility, TCS is used to measure the expectation of improvement and treatment credibility. The TCS is a visual analogue scale rated from &quot;Low credibility&quot;/ &quot;Not at all&quot; (0) to &quot;High credibility&quot;/&quot;Very much&quot; (10) and the score calculated is a mean of all items. The TCS was administered after providing thorough information and presentation of the treatment content at baseline and after completion of the treatment. The item wording after adjustment to the current study were: (1) How logical does Navigator ACT treatment seem to you? (2) How confident are you that this treatment will reduce your distress? (3) Would you recommend Navigator ACT to a friend experiencing the same type of distress? (4) How successful do you feel this type of intervention is in improving your psychological health? 5) At this very moment, to what degree the intervention has improved your psychological health?</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Parenting</condition>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Disability, Developmental</condition>
  <condition>Behavior, Child</condition>
  <condition>Acceptance Processes</condition>
  <condition>Parent-Child Relations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acceptance- and Commitment therapy group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Experiment group that receives the treatment direct after the baseline measurement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comparison group that receives treatment as usual and the Navigator ACT intervention appr 6 months later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Acceptance- and Commitment therapy group for parents to children with disabilities</intervention_name>
    <description>ACT groups adjusted for parents to children with (any kind of) disabilities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acceptance- and Commitment therapy group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Navigator ACT group treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual.</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment as usual within outpatient disability services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a parent to a child 2-17 years with disability

          -  mild to severe symptoms of parental stress, depression or anxiety

          -  a possibility to participate in all group sessions

          -  an ability to function in a group

          -  a knowledge of the Swedish language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  deep depression with suicidality

          -  psychosis or manic episodes

          -  severe post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD)

          -  homelessness or other extreme life situation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Parent report their own and their child's gender during the screening interview.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tatja Hirvikoski, Associate professor</last_name>
    <phone>+46708327637</phone>
    <email>tatja.hirvikoski@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tiina Holmberg Bergman, M.Sc.</last_name>
    <phone>+46705755788</phone>
    <email>tiina.holmberg.bergman@ki.se</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>17177</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tiina Holmberg Bergman</last_name>
      <phone>705755788</phone>
      <email>tiina.holmberg.bergman@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tatja Hirvikoski, Docent</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tatja Hirvikoski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acceptance- and Commitment Therapy, Parenting stress, depression, anxiety, parenting, children with disabilities</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Developmental Disabilities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

