<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03830333</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7625A-015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MK-7625A-015</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03830333</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ceftolozane/Tazobactam (MK-7625A) Plus Metronidazole Versus Meropenem for Participants With Complicated Intra-abdominal Infection (MK-7625A-015)</brief_title>
  <acronym>7625ACNPhase3</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Double-blind, Randomized, Active-controlled Clinical Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Ceftolozane/Tazobactam (MK-7625A) Plus Metronidazole Versus Meropenem in Chinese Participants With Complicated Intra-abdominal Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to evaluate the efficacy of ceftolozane/tazobactam (MK-7625A) plus
      metronizazole versus meropenem in adults diagnosed with complicated intra-abdominal infection
      (cIAI). The primary hypothesis is ceftolozane/tazobactam plus metronizazole is non-inferior
      to meropenem, as measured by the clinical response rate at the Test-of Cure (TOC) visit in
      the Clinically Evaluable (CE) population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 13, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 13, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable clinical response at the TOC visit (CE population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a clinical response of cure at the test of cure (TOC) visit in the clinically evaluable (CE) population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable clinical response at the EOT visit (ITT population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4 up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a clinical response of cure at the end of therapy (EOT) visit in the intent to treat (ITT) population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable clinical response at the TOC visit (ITT population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a clinical response of cure at the TOC visit in the ITT population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable clinical response at the EOT visit (CE population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 4 up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with a clinical response of cure at the EOT visit in the CE population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Favorable microbiological response at the TOC visit (EME population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants achieving a favorable microbiological response at the TOC visit in the expanded microbiologically evaluable (EME) population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathogens achieving a favorable microbiological response at the TOC visit (EME population)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of baseline intra-abdominal pathogens achieving a favorable microbiological response at the TOC visit in the EME population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants with an adverse event (AE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Discontinuations of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 14</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants who discontinued treatment due to an AE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">268</enrollment>
  <condition>Complicated Intra-abdominal Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftolozane/Tazobactam + Metronidazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ceftolozane 1000 mg / Tazobactam 500 mg; plus Metronidazole 500 mg by intravenous (IV) infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days. Participants with creatinine clearance (CrCL) of 30 to ≤ 50 mL/min will receive Ceftolozane 500 mg / Tazobactam 250 mg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meropenem + Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Meropenem 1000 mg; plus saline by IV infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days. Participants with CrCL of 30 to ≤ 50 mL/min will receive meropenem by IV infusion every 12 hours.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceftolozane/Tazobactam</intervention_name>
    <description>Ceftolozane 1000 mg / Tazobactam 500 mg by IV infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days. Participants with CrCL of 30 to ≤ 50 mL/min will receive Ceftolozane 500 mg / Tazobactam 250 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftolozane/Tazobactam + Metronidazole</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MK-7625A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metronidazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Metronidazole 500 mg by IV infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftolozane/Tazobactam + Metronidazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meropenem</intervention_name>
    <description>Meropenem 1000 mg by IV infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days. Participants with CrCL of 30 to ≤ 50 mL/min will receive IV infusion every 12 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meropenem + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline by IV infusion every 8 hours for 4 to 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meropenem + Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must have one of the following diagnoses in which there is evidence of bacterial
             intraperitoneal infection: Cholecystitis (including gangrenous cholecystitis) with
             rupture, perforation, or progression of the infection beyond the gallbladder wall;
             Acute gastric or small intestine including duodenal perforation, only if operated on &gt;
             24 hours after perforation occurs; Traumatic perforation of the intestine (including
             colon), only if operated on &gt; 12 hours after perforation occurs; Appendiceal
             perforation or peri-appendiceal abscess; Diverticular disease with perforation or
             abscess; Peritonitis due to other perforated viscus or following a prior operative
             procedure; Intra-abdominal abscess (including liver or spleen).

          -  Evidence of systemic infection

          -  Requires surgical intervention (e.g., laparotomy, laparoscopic surgery, or
             percutaneous draining of an abscess) within 24 hours of (before or after) the first
             dose of study drug

          -  If participant is to be enrolled preoperatively, the participant should have
             radiographic evidence of gastric or bowel perforation or intra-abdominal abscess or
             other radiographic evidence for cIAI

          -  Participants who failed prior antibacterial treatment for the current cIAI can be
             enrolled but must: (a) have a positive culture (from an intra-abdominal site or blood
             sample) and (b) require surgical intervention.

          -  Is a Chinese participant, defined as a person of Chinese descent. A potential
             participant who is of ex-China descent (e.g. Western European) descent living in China
             will be excluded

          -  Male agrees to use contraception during the treatment period, and for at least 30 days
             after the last dose of study medication, and refrain from donating sperm during this
             period

          -  Female is not pregnant; is not a woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP); and if WOCBP
             agrees to follow the contraceptive guidance during the treatment period, and for at
             least 30 days after the last dose of study medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has any of the following diagnoses:simple appendicitis; abdominal wall abscess; small
             bowel obstruction or ischemic bowel disease without perforation; spontaneous (primary)
             bacterial peritonitis associated with cirrhosis and chronic ascites; or pelvic
             infections

          -  Has any of the following diseases: acute suppurative cholangitis; infected necrotizing
             pancreatitis; pancreatic abscess

          -  Has complicated intra-abdominal infection managed by staged abdominal repair (STAR),
             open abdomen technique (i.e. fascia not closed) including temporary closure of the
             abdomen, or any situation where infection source control was not likely to be achieved

          -  Has abscess that is confirmed on imaging test but has not been or cannot be managed by
             surgical intervention including drainage

          -  Is expected to be cured by only surgical intervention (e.g., drainage) without use of
             systemic antibiotic therapy

          -  Has the following underlying conditions or the following serious conditions:
             considered unlikely to survive during the study period (predicted life expectancy is &lt;
             4 weeks after randomization); organic brain or spinal cord disease; any
             rapidly-progressing disease or immediately life-threatening illness (including
             respiratory failure and septic shock); an immunocompromising condition

          -  Has a history of any hypersensitivity or allergic reaction to any betalactam,
             antibacterials, including cephalosporins, carbapenems, penicillins, or tazobactam, or
             metronidazole, or nitroimidazole derivatives; or if a skin test is required by local
             clinical regulations, has a positive skin test result if no prior history of allergic
             reaction to betalactam antibacterial

          -  A WOCBP who has a positive serum pregnancy test within 24 hours before the first dose
             of study intervention

          -  Used systemic antibiotic therapy with known coverage of pathogens that cause IAI for
             more than 24 hours during the previous 72 hours prior to the first dose of study drug,
             unless there is a documented treatment failure with such therapy

          -  For participants that are enrolled postoperatively, more than 1 dose of an active
             non-study antibacterial regimen administered postoperatively. For participants
             enrolled preoperatively, no postoperative non-study antibacterial therapy is allowed

          -  Participants who need additional non-study systemic antibacterial therapy with
             gram-negative activity in addition to study drug therapy; drugs with only
             gram-positive activity (eg, IV vancomycin, teicoplanin, linezolid and daptomycin) are
             allowed

          -  Anticipates treatment with traditional chinese medicine or herbal medicine during
             study period

          -  Has received disulfiram, valproic acid or divalproex sodium within 14 days before the
             proposed first day of study drug or who are currently receiving probenecid

          -  Is currently participating in, or has participated in, any other clinical study
             involving the administration of investigational or experimental medication (not
             licensed by regulatory agencies) at the time of the presentation or during the
             previous 90 days prior to screening or is anticipated to participate in such a
             clinical study during the course of this study

          -  Has participated in a ceftolozane/tazobactam clinical study at any time in the past

          -  Has severe impairment of renal function (CrCL &lt;30 mL/min) or requirement for
             peritoneal dialysis, hemodialysis or hemofiltration, or oliguria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Toll Free Number</last_name>
    <phone>1-888-577-8839</phone>
    <email>Trialsites@merck.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Anhui Provincial Hospital ( Site 0033)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hefei</city>
        <state>Anhui</state>
        <zip>230001</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613855168588</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Navy General Hospital ( Site 0009)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100048</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8618600310222</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University Third Hospital ( Site 0002)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100191</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613701080921</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University ( Site 0026)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510120</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613903070123</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Southern Medical University Nanfang Hospital ( Site 0055)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510515</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613802771450</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hainan General Hospital ( Site 0042)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Haikou</city>
        <state>Hainan</state>
        <zip>570311</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8618889765723</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baotou Central Hospital ( Site 0013)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baotou</city>
        <state>Inner Mongolia</state>
        <zip>014040</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8604726955473</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First People's Hospital of Changzhou ( Site 0054)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>213000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8651968870835</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wuxi No.2 People's Hospital ( Site 0050)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuxi</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>214002</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8651068563496</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wuxi People's Hospital ( Site 0020)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wuxi</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>214023</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>862163240090</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Subei People's Hospital ( Site 0046)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yangzhou</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>200080</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>8651487373012</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Affiliated Hospital of Jiangsu University ( Site 0049)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zhenjiang</city>
        <state>Jiangsu</state>
        <zip>212000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8651185082272</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University ( Site 0029)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <state>Jiangxi</state>
        <zip>330006</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8679188692748</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Nanchang University ( Site 0053)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nanchang</city>
        <state>Jiangxi</state>
        <zip>330006</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613907008850</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Second Hospital of Jilin University ( Site 0048)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Changchun</city>
        <state>Jilin</state>
        <zip>130022</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+86043181136313</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liaocheng People s hospital ( Site 0014)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liaocheng</city>
        <state>Shandong</state>
        <zip>252000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613346256926</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhongshan Hospital of Fudan University ( Site 0001)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200032</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+862160267662</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai General Hospital ( Site 0016)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200080</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+862163240090</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Central Hospital of Minhang District ( Site 0052)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>201100</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8651185082272</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tianjin People's Hospital ( Site 0040)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tianjin</city>
        <state>Tianjin</state>
        <zip>300121</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8602227557550</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Xinjiang Medical University ( Site 0034)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Urumqi</city>
        <state>Xinjiang</state>
        <zip>830054</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8613699995676</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Hospital of Kunming ( Site 0041)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kunming</city>
        <state>Yunnan</state>
        <zip>650200</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8615877991051</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taizhou Hospital of Zhejiang Province ( Site 0035)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taizhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>317000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+86057685199810</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The 2nd Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University ( Site 0051)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wenzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>325000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>+8657788002738</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Wenzhou Medical University ( Site 0015)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wenzhou</city>
        <state>Zhejiang</state>
        <zip>325000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
      <phone>13857771611</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intraabdominal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metronidazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Meropenem</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tazobactam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ceftolozane</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ceftolozane, tazobactam drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>http://engagezone.msd.com/doc/ProcedureAccessClinicalTrialData.pdf</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>http://engagezone.msd.com/ds_documentation.php</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

