<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03835728</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU-2018-0185</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03835728</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Ocrelizumab in Autoimmune Encephalitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploratory Study of Efficacy of Ocrelizumab in Autoimmune Encephalitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study is a randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled study of the efficacy of
      ocrelizumab in autoimmune encephalitis. Subjects with new diagnosis of autoimmune
      encephalitis will be invited to enroll in this study. Subjects will be randomized to receive
      ocrelizumab (an anti-CD20 therapy) or matched placebo, and will undergo three infusions over
      a six month period. Subjects will complete clinical visits over the study period, during
      which safety monitoring and neuropsychological assessments will be performed to assess for
      signs of clinical worsening from encephalitis. The primary outcome of this study is the
      proportion of patients who fail to complete the twelve month period without clinical
      worsening, as defined by the protocol. Subjects who experience early clinical worsening
      during the study may be offered open-label treatment with ocrelizumab at the discretion of
      the investigators.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 22, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 22, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>failure rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome of the treatment trial will be the proportion of patients who fail to complete the 12 month study without clinical worsening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment failure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome will be time to treatment failure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in TFLS (Texas Functional Living Scale) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>6-12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome: TFLS (Texas Functional Living Scale) scores at 6 and 12 months compared to baseline. - A performance-based measure of functional competence designed to assess instrumental activities of daily living (e.g., managing money) that are thought to be more susceptible to cognitive change than basic activities of daily living (e.g., dressing).
Content and Structure: The TFLS is comprised of 24 items divided into four subscales assessing abilities related to Time, Money and Calculation, Communication, and Memory. Many items provide a range of possible points allowing the instrument to account for the varying levels of functioning that may be observed in clinical populations.
Total raw score ranges between 0 and 50 with standardized T-score values between 20 and 66. The higher the score, the better the performance.
Subscale ranges:
Time: 0-9 Money and Calculation: 0-8 Communication: 0-28 Memory: 0-5</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Autoimmune Encephalitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ocrelizumab will be administered 3 times over a 1 year study period. Subjects will receive a dose of 300 mg at week 0 (baseline) and again at week 2. The final dose of 600 mg will be administered at week 24.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline will be used as the matching placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ocrelizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized in a 1:1 fashion to receive infusion of Ocrelizumab (2 doses at 300 mg and 1 dose at 600 mg) or matched placebo. The 2 300 mg doses will be administered at day 2 and day 14. The 600 mg dose will be administered during the 6 month visit. The drug will be administered via infusion three times throughout the trial period: after the initial screening, at two weeks from initial infusion, and at 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>This will be the matching placebo used in the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Placebo Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 or greater

          2. Able to obtain informed consent from patient or appropriate designee

          3. Possible autoimmune encephalitis as defined by Table 1:

               1. Reasonable exclusion of alternative causes

               2. Subacute onset (&lt; 3 months) of memory deficits, altered consciousness, and/or
                  psychiatric symptoms

               3. One or more of the following:

                    -  CSF (cerebrospinal fluid) pleocytosis (&gt;5 cells/µl corrected, if necessary,
                       for traumatic lumbar puncture)

                    -  EEG (electroencephalogram) with epileptiform or focal slow wave
                       abnormalities involving temporal lobes

                    -  Brain abnormalities on T2/FLAIR MRI restricted to the mesial temporal
                       (limbic) lobes

                    -  Associated dyskinesias (faciobrachial dystonic movements or orofacial
                       dyskinesias)

          4. Completed initial treatment with iv steroids (at least 3000mg solumedrol) and plasma
             exchange (at least 3 exchanges) within the past 8 weeks

          5. Presence of one (or more) of the following autoantibodies in serum or CSF

               -  NMDA receptor

               -  LGI1

               -  CASPR2

               -  DPPX

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior immunosuppression treatment in past year (other than steroids, intravenous
             immunoglobulin and plasma exchange)

          2. Active malignancy requiring chemotherapy

          3. Pregnancy

          4. Evidence of active hepatitis or tuberculosis infection

          5. Medical condition that (in investigators opinion) precludes the use of ocrelizumab
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Vernino, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Hopkins</last_name>
    <phone>2146489275</phone>
    <email>steve.hopkins@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kyle Blackburn, MD</last_name>
    <phone>2146489275</phone>
    <email>kyle.blackburn@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Hopkins</last_name>
      <phone>214-648-9275</phone>
      <email>steve.hopkins@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kyle Blackburn, MD</last_name>
      <phone>2146489275</phone>
      <email>kyle.blackburn@utsouthwestern.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Vernino, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graus F, Titulaer MJ, Balu R, Benseler S, Bien CG, Cellucci T, Cortese I, Dale RC, Gelfand JM, Geschwind M, Glaser CA, Honnorat J, Höftberger R, Iizuka T, Irani SR, Lancaster E, Leypoldt F, Prüss H, Rae-Grant A, Reindl M, Rosenfeld MR, Rostásy K, Saiz A, Venkatesan A, Vincent A, Wandinger KP, Waters P, Dalmau J. A clinical approach to diagnosis of autoimmune encephalitis. Lancet Neurol. 2016 Apr;15(4):391-404. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(15)00401-9. Epub 2016 Feb 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26906964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Titulaer MJ, McCracken L, Gabilondo I, Armangué T, Glaser C, Iizuka T, Honig LS, Benseler SM, Kawachi I, Martinez-Hernandez E, Aguilar E, Gresa-Arribas N, Ryan-Florance N, Torrents A, Saiz A, Rosenfeld MR, Balice-Gordon R, Graus F, Dalmau J. Treatment and prognostic factors for long-term outcome in patients with anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis: an observational cohort study. Lancet Neurol. 2013 Feb;12(2):157-65. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(12)70310-1. Epub 2013 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23290630</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dubey D, Sawhney A, Greenberg B, Lowden A, Warnack W, Khemani P, Stuve O, Vernino S. The spectrum of autoimmune encephalopathies. J Neuroimmunol. 2015 Oct 15;287:93-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jneuroim.2015.08.014. Epub 2015 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26439968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hashimoto Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ocrelizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

