<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03836209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PrE0905</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03836209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Trial of Gilteritinib vs Midostaurin in FLT3 Mutated Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Trial of Gilteritinib vs Midostaurin in FLT3 Mutated Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PrECOG, LLC.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PrECOG, LLC.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Eligible untreated patients with FLT3 acute myeloid leukemia (AML) between the ages of 18 and
      65 will be randomized to receive gilteritinib or midostaurin during induction and
      consolidation. Patients will also receive standard chemotherapy of daunorubicin and
      cytarabine during induction and high-dose cytarabine during consolidation.

      Gilteritinib, is an oral drug that works by stopping the leukemia cells from making the FLT3
      protein. This may help stop the leukemia cells from growing faster and thus may help make
      chemotherapy more effective. Gilteritinib has been approved by the Food and Drug
      Administration (FDA) for patients who have relapsed or refractory AML with a FLT3 mutation
      but is not approved by the FDA for newly diagnosed FLT3 AML, and its use in this setting is
      considered investigational.

      Midostaurin is an oral drug that works by blocking several proteins on cancer cells,
      including FLT3 that can help leukemia cells grow. Blocking this pathway can cause death to
      the leukemic cells. Midostaurin is approved by the FDA for the treatment of FLT3 AML.

      The purpose of this study is to compare the effectiveness of gilteritinib to midostaurin in
      patients receiving standard combination chemotherapy for FLT3 AML.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately one third of patients with AML have a particular change in their leukemia cells
      (called a mutation) in a gene called FLT3. The presence of a FLT3 mutation can be used to
      direct treatment options.

      This is an open-label phase II study. Patients will receive standard chemotherapy of
      daunorubicin and cytarabine during Induction and high-dose cytarabine during Consolidation.
      Patients will be randomized to gilteritinib or midostaurin. After approximately 90 patient's
      complete treatment, a review of the effectiveness of gliteritinib compared to midostaurin
      will be done. If gilteritinib is not as effective as midostaurin, the study may be stopped.

      Bone marrow aspirate and biopsy will be done on Day 21 after start of Induction and after
      Induction to assess response. Patients with a complete response may proceed to consolidation
      chemotherapy. Another bone marrow aspirate and biopsy will be done after consolidation is
      complete.

      Mandatory prescreening bone marrow and/or blood samples are required for FLT3 testing. Any
      left-over samples will be requested for future research (optional).

      Mandatory bone marrow samples for research are required after Induction and Consolidation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 6, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Open-Label, Randomized trial of Daunorubicin/Cytarabine and High Dose Cytarabine + Gilteritinib vs Midostaurin for Induction and Consolidation. FLT3 mutated patients will be stratified based on TKD vs ITD. Patients who are FLT3 ITD will be further stratified by Signal Ratio (high vs. low of FLT3 Wild Type) and Nucleophosmin 1-Mutated (NPM1) [positive vs negative].</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FLT3 Mutation Negative Composite Complete Response (CRc) [includes Complete Response (CR) or CR with incomplete hematologic recovery (CRi)] at end of Induction</measure>
    <time_frame>40 months</time_frame>
    <description>CRc evaluated by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) after Induction</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FLT3 mutation negative Complete Response (CR) rate at end of Induction</measure>
    <time_frame>40 months</time_frame>
    <description>CR evaluated by FLT3 testing after Induction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Minimal Residual Disease (MRD)- CRc rate at end of Induction</measure>
    <time_frame>40 months</time_frame>
    <description>MRD- CRc evaluated by flow cytometry after Induction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CRc (CR or CRi) rate at end of Induction</measure>
    <time_frame>40 months</time_frame>
    <description>CRc assessed in accordance with 2017 European LeukemiaNet (ELN)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event Free Survival (EFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>68 months</time_frame>
    <description>EFS assessed in accordance with 2017 ELN</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>68 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS assessed in accordance with 2017 ELN</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants treatment-related adverse events on Arm A (gilteritinib) as assessed by CTCAE v5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>68 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory values and/or adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants treatment-related adverse events on Arm B (midostaurin) as assessed by CTCAE v5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>68 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory values and/or adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">179</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: Daunorubicin, cytarabine and gilteritinib. Depending on response, second cycle of Induction may be given.
Consolidation: High-dose cytarabine for up to 4 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction: Daunorubicin, cytarabine and midostaurin. Depending on response, second cycle of Induction may be given.
Consolidation: High-dose cytarabine for up to 4 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gilteritinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction: 120 mg orally daily x 14 days starting on day 8
Consolidation: 120 mg orally daily x 14 days starting on day 8 of each cycle (up to 4 cycles)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ASP2215</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midostaurin</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction: 50 mg orally twice daily x 14 days beginning on day 8
Consolidation: 50 mg orally twice daily x 14 days beginning on day 8 of each cycle (up to 4 cycles)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RYDAPT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Daunorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>First Induction: Daunorubicin 90 mg/m²/day IV Days 1,2,3
Second Induction, if needed: Daunorubicin 45 mg/m²/day IV Days 1,2,3</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Daunorubicin hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Daunomycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Rubidomycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Cerubidine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction: Cytarabine 100 mg/m²/day continuous infusion x 7 days starting Day 1
Second Induction, if needed: Cytarabine 100 mg/m²/day continuous infusion x 7 days starting Day 1
Consolidation: Cytarabine 3 g/m² (1.5 g/m² for age ≥ 55) every 12 hours IV Days 1,3,5 for 6 doses for up to 4 cycles</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cytosar-U</other_name>
    <other_name>Ara-C</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinosyl</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine Arabinoside</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Preregistration Criteria:

          -  Any patient undergoing bone marrow biopsy with suspicion of or known diagnosis of
             acute myeloid leukemia (AML) will be asked to sign a Prescreening Consent to allow for
             centralized testing of bone marrow/peripheral blood samples.

        Eligibility Criteria:

          -  Patient must have previously untreated FLT3 mutated Non M3 AML (FLT3-TKD or FLT3-ITD
             allowed).

          -  Patient must have had no prior systemic therapy for AML, except as noted below:

               -  Hydroxyurea and emergent leukapheresis or preemptive treatment with retinoic acid
                  prior to exclusion of Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia (APL) allowed.

               -  Prior therapy for myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) or myeloproliferative neoplasms
                  (MPN) (e.g., thalidomide or lenalidomide, interferon, jakafi, cytokines,
                  5-azacytidine or decitabine, histone deacetylase inhibitors).

          -  Patient may not have hypomethylating agent within 21 days.

          -  Patient may not have M3 AML.

          -  Patient may not have AML with known Core Binding Factor -t(8;21), inv(16), t(16;16).

          -  Patient may not have known active Central Nervous System (CNS) leukemia.

          -  Patient must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of
             0-3.

          -  Patient must be age ≥ 18 years to ≤ 65 years.

          -  Patient must be able to understand and willing to sign Institutional Review Board
             (IRB)-approved informed consent.

          -  Patient must be willing to provide mandatory bone marrow and blood samples for
             research.

          -  Patient must have adequate organ function as measured by the following criteria,
             obtained ≤ 48 hours prior to randomization except ECG and left ventricular ejection
             fraction (LVEF) which can be done ≤ 2 weeks prior to randomization:

               -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN), or if serum
                  creatinine outside normal range, then glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt;40 mL/min
                  as measured by Cockcroft-Gault formula.

               -  Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) and Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3x ULN,
                  unless secondary to leukemia.

               -  Serum total or direct bilirubin &lt;2 mg/dL, unless due to Gilbert's, hemolysis or
                  leukemic infiltration.

               -  Fridericia-Corrected QT Interval (QTcF) interval ≤ 500 msec (using Friderica's
                  correction).

               -  Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction &gt;45%.

          -  The patient may not be known to have hypokalemia and/or hypomagnesemia that does not
             respond to supplementation.

          -  A female patient is eligible to participate if she is not pregnant and at least one of
             the following conditions apply:

               -  Not a woman of childbearing potential (WOCBP) OR

               -  WOCBP who agrees to follow the contraceptive guidance throughout the treatment
                  period and for at least 180 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  Female patient must agree not to breastfeed or donate ova starting at screening and
             throughout the study period, and for at least 180 days after the final study drug
             administration.

          -  A male patient must agree not to donate sperm starting at screening and throughout the
             study period, and for at least 120 days after the final study drug administration.

          -  A male patient with female partner(s) of child-bearing potential must agree to use
             contraception during the treatment period, and for at least 120 days after the final
             study drug administration.

          -  Male patient with a pregnant or breastfeeding partner(s) must agree to remain
             abstinent or use a condom for the duration of the pregnancy or time partner is
             breastfeeding throughout the treatment period, and for at least 120 days after the
             final study drug administration.

          -  Patient may not have another malignancy that could interfere with the evaluation of
             safety or efficacy of this combination.

          -  Patient may not have a history of Long QT Syndrome.

          -  Patient may not have evidence of uncontrolled angina, severe uncontrolled ventricular
             arrhythmias, electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia, or congestive heart
             failure (CHF) New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class 3 or 4. Patient may also not
             have a history of CHF NYHA Class 3 or 4 in the past, unless a prescreening
             echocardiogram (ECHO) or multigated acquisition scan (MUGA) performed within 2 weeks
             prior to study entry with results of left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;45%.

          -  Patient may not have had major surgery or radiation therapy within 4 weeks of
             registration.

          -  Patient may not require treatment with concomitant drugs that are strong inducers of
             CYP3A with the exception of drugs considered essential for the care of the patient.

          -  Patient with a known allergy to any of the study medications, their analogues, or
             excipients in the various formulations of any agent are not eligible.

          -  Patient with known gastrointestinal (GI) disease or prior GI procedure that could
             interfere with the oral absorption or tolerance of gilteritinib or midostaurin
             including difficulty swallowing are not eligible.

          -  Patient with any serious medical or psychiatric illness that could, in the
             investigator's opinion, potentially interfere with the completion of the treatment
             according to the protocol are not eligible.

          -  Patient may not participate in any other therapeutic clinical trials, including those
             with other investigational agents not included in this trial during treatment on this
             study without prior approval from PrECOG.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Selena Luger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lauren Reilly, BS</last_name>
    <phone>267-239-7265</phone>
    <email>PrE0905@precogllc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HonorHealth Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85258</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nyssa Hoffman</last_name>
      <phone>480-323-1272</phone>
      <email>nhoffman@HonorHealth.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jeffrey Schriber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bruck Habtemariam</last_name>
      <phone>310-794-7538</phone>
      <email>bhabtemariam@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Schiller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UC Irvine Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>An To</last_name>
      <phone>714-509-2369</phone>
      <email>aqto@uci.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Deepa Jeyakumar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic- Jacksonville, FL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Simpson</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
      <email>simpson.sarah@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James M. Foran, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Augusta University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandy Wall</last_name>
      <phone>706-721-4430</phone>
      <email>swall@augusta.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Trisha Loveday</last_name>
      <phone>706-721-5095</phone>
      <email>ploveday@augusta.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Vamsi Kota, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samantha Warner</last_name>
      <phone>312-695-1202</phone>
      <email>samantha.warner@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jessica Altman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky Markey Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corisa Logan</last_name>
      <phone>859-323-5785</phone>
      <email>corisa.logan@uky.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerhard Hildebrandt, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colin Huck</last_name>
      <phone>410-614-3725</phone>
      <email>chuck1@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Levis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Mercy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Velfling</last_name>
      <phone>734-712-4950</phone>
      <email>christina.velfling@stjoeshealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher M. Reynolds, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic- Rochester, MN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samantha Wallerich</last_name>
      <phone>507-293-3826</phone>
      <email>wallerich.samantha@mayo.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mithun Shah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nebraska Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hillary Stevenson</last_name>
      <phone>402-836-9305</phone>
      <email>hillary.stevenson@unmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Krishna Gundabolu, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Atlantic Health Systems/Morristown Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morristown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07962</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maureen Nowakowski</last_name>
      <phone>973-971-5569</phone>
      <email>maureen.nowakowski@atlantichealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Farber, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Madhulika Shukla</last_name>
      <phone>646-608-2783</phone>
      <email>shuklam@mskcc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ellin Berman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Rollinson</last_name>
      <phone>585-275-9485</phone>
      <email>sarah_rollinson@URMC.Rochester.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristen O'Dwyer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kimberlee Eakins</last_name>
      <phone>216-286-9210</phone>
      <email>kimberlee.eakins@uhhospitals.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brenda Cooper, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oklahoma Stephenson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oklahoma City</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Silas Day</last_name>
      <phone>405-271-8001</phone>
      <phone_ext>48748</phone_ext>
      <email>silas-day@ouhsc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>George Selby, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geisinger Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Danville</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17822</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Julie Gombert</last_name>
      <phone>570-214-9603</phone>
      <email>jagombert@geisinger.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Vadakara, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Lee</last_name>
      <phone>215-615-5081</phone>
      <email>eric.lee2@pennmedicine.upenn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander Perl, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Lopez</last_name>
      <phone>215-955-1073</phone>
      <email>kelly.lopez@jefferson.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neil Palmisiano, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy O'Connell</last_name>
      <phone>412-623-3083</phone>
      <email>oconnellka2@upmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Boyiadzis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Channing Dudley</last_name>
      <phone>615-875-8757</phone>
      <email>channing.v.dudley@vumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen A. Strickland, Jr., MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Vermont Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Gamelin</last_name>
      <phone>802-656-9427</phone>
      <email>melissa.gamelin@med.uvm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicodia Williams</last_name>
      <phone>802-656-2180</phone>
      <email>nicodia.williams@med.uvm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elvira Umyarova, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MultiCare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Horton</last_name>
      <phone>509-724-4463</phone>
      <email>jkhorton@multicare.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brett Gourley, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kelly Ross, MD</last_name>
      <phone>304-293-4229</phone>
      <phone_ext>2</phone_ext>
      <email>kelly.ross@hsc.wvu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lindsay Carter</last_name>
      <phone>304-293-0220</phone>
      <email>lindsay.carter@hsc.wvu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kelly Ross, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UW Cancer Center at ProHealth Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waukesha</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53188</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chanda Miller</last_name>
      <phone>262-928-5539</phone>
      <email>chanda.miller@phci.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Timothy Wassenaar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gilteritinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Midostaurin</keyword>
  <keyword>Daunorubicin</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytarabine</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3 Mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3 Internal Tandem Duplication (ITD)</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3 ITD</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3 Tyrosine Kinase Domain (TKD)</keyword>
  <keyword>FLT3 TKD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Daunorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midostaurin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data is proprietary.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

