<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03816709</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HE19132</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03816709</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intramuscular Heating Rates of a Chattanooga Intelect XT Therapeutic Ultrasound</brief_title>
  <official_title>Intramuscular Heating Rates of a Chattanooga Intelect XT Therapeutic Ultrasound With 3 MHz, 1.0 W/cm2 at Three Depths up to 2.5 cm</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>North Dakota State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>North Dakota State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the rate of tissue temperature increase in the
      triceps surae during an ultrasound treatment using the Chattanooga Intelect Legend XT. The
      following parameters will be used: 3 MHz frequency, 1.0 W/cm2 intensity, 15 minute treatment
      time. Thermocouples will be inserted at 1.0, 1.75, and 2.5 cm depths to determine the heating
      rates. Most modality textbook recommendations for therapeutic ultrasound are based on studies
      performed with the Omnisound ultrasound machine. Previous research has shown variations in
      power output across manufacturers, producing differences in tissue temperature increases. No
      information has been published regarding the heating rates of the Chattanooga Intelect Legend
      XT machine for ultrasound treatments. By determining the heating rates for this machine,
      clinicians will be better able to utilize the Chattanooga Intelect Legend XT to help reach
      therapeutic goals.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Individual subjects will report to the research lab. They will be instructed to wear
      appropriate shorts or pants that can be rolled up to expose the gastrocnemius (calf) muscle.
      The subject will lay prone on the treatment table with the foot and lower leg off of the
      treatment table in a relaxed, comfortable position. The following procedures will be
      completed using universal precautions:

        1. The investigator will prep the treatment area by having the subject flex the calf to
           determine the proper location for the ultrasound treatment in the middle of the medial
           gastrocnemius muscle belly at its largest girth.

             1. A carpenter's square with markings along the vertical arm at the three experimental
                depths (1.0, 1.75, 2.5 cm) will be used.

             2. The horizontal arm of the carpenter's square will be covered in tape. The
                carpenter's square is then placed just proximal to the treatment mark while the
                level on the horizontal arm is used to maintain a level measure.

             3. Marks will be made on the muscle belly parallel to the marks on the vertical axis
                at 1.0, 1.75 and 2.5 cm depths.

             4. A mark is also made on the horizontal arm tape in line with the treatment mark on
                the medial gastrocnemius.

        2. The Terason uSmart 3300 diagnostic ultrasound unit will be used to measure the adipose
           thickness over the treatment area and look for abnormalities in the treatment and
           thermocouple insertion areas. Aquasonic® 100 ultrasound gel will be placed on the 15L4
           transducer. The transducer with gel will be placed over the mark of the treatment area.
           Once the transducer is in place, the screen will be frozen and the skin and adipose
           thickness will be measured using the caliper tool.

        3. The thermocouples will be removed from the MetriCide after sterilizing for a minimum of
           12 hours prior to insertion.

             1. The distal aspect of the thermocouple will be wiped dry with sterile gauze.

             2. A mark with a sharpie will be made on each thermocouple just past the length marked
                on the horizontal arm of the carpenter's square. This allows the tip of each
                thermocouple to be directly below the treatment site. A second mark will be made at
                5 cm to make sure the thermocouple does not go too deep into the tissue.

             3. The distal end of the thermocouple will be wiped clean again using a 70% isopropyl
                alcohol wipe up to the marks and then the thermocouple will be wrapped in sterile
                gauze until it is inserted.

        4. The insertion areas will be shaved to remove any body hair (if necessary) and cleaned
           using Betadine.

           a. Once the Betadine dries, 70% isopropyl alcohol will be wiped over the insertion area
           and given time to dry.

        5. The subject will be instructed to take two deep breaths, while the researcher lightly
           grasps the gastrocnemius to confirm muscle relaxation.

             1. During the second exhalation, the 1.16 in needle catheter will be placed into the
                subject's calf at the 1.0 cm depth insertion mark using the level to guide the
                needle in. The needle will be removed leaving the catheter in the tissue.

             2. The thermocouple will be threaded through the catheter to the appropriate depth
                marked on the thermocouple and the catheter will be removed.

             3. The thermocouple will be secured using medical tape to keep it from moving.

             4. This procedure will be performed 3 times, with one thermocouple placed at each
                respective depth: 1.0 cm, 1.75 cm, and 2.5 cm.

        6. Each thermocouple will be attached to the Iso Thermex electronic thermometer (Columbus
           Instruments, Columbus, OH), which will measure and record intramuscular temperatures
           from the tips of the thermocouples.

        7. An ultrasound treatment template will be applied at the treatment site and secured with
           tape to maintain consistent treatment size.

           a. This template will be twice the size of the transducer's Effective Radiating Area
           (ERA).

        8. A metronome will be utilized to consistently move the transducer at a rate of 4 cm/s .

        9. The ultrasound treatment will begin once the intramuscular temperature has remained the
           same for a minute.

       10. Each subject will receive one ultrasound treatment at the following parameters: 3 MHz
           frequency, 1.0 W/cm2 intensity, and 100% duty cycle using the Chattanooga Intelect®
           Legend XT.

           a. Termination of treatment will result when any of the following occur: i. A 15-minute
           treatment time is obtained. ii. A 4°C temperature increase occurs at all three depths as
           this has been shown as the necessary temperature change to increase tissue
           extensibility.

           iii. A 45°C temperature is reached at any depth, due to concern of tissue damage at high
           temperatures.

           iv. The subject experiences any pain or discomfort during the treatment.

       11. Following the treatment, the ultrasound gel will be wiped from the leg, the template and
           thermocouples will be removed, and the insertion sites will be cleaned with 70%
           isopropyl alcohol wipes and covered with a band aid.

       12. The subject will then be instructed on the possibility of minor soreness for the next
           day or two and instructed on an icing schedule to decrease discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 11, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heating rate at 1 cm depth</measure>
    <time_frame>The tissue temperatures was recorded every 5 seconds and analyzed at the following 4 times: baseline, 5 minutes, 10 minutes, and 15 minutes/end time.</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of tissue temperature increase in degrees Celsius over the 15 minute treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heating rate at 1.75 cm depth</measure>
    <time_frame>The tissue temperatures was recorded every 5 seconds and analyzed at the following 4 times: baseline, 5 minutes, 10 minutes, and 15 minutes/end time.</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of tissue temperature increase in degrees Celsius over the 15 minute treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heating rate at 2.5 cm depth</measure>
    <time_frame>The tissue temperatures was recorded every 5 seconds and analyzed at the following 4 times: baseline, 5 minutes, 10 minutes, and 15 minutes/end time.</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of tissue temperature increase in degrees Celsius over the 15 minute treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Ultrasound Therapy; Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic ultrasound treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects received a therapeutic ultrasound treatment with the Chattanooga Intelect Legend XT machine with the following parameters: 3 MHz, 1.0 W/cm2, 15 minute treatment time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Therapeutic Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>A therapeutic ultrasound treatment was applied to the left medial gastrocnemius muscle with the following parameters: 3 MHz, 1.0 W/cm2 for 15 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Therapeutic ultrasound treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ultrasound therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  males and females between the ages of 18 - 35 years old

          -  able to speak English

          -  have less than 1 cm of adipose over the left medial gastrocnemius muscle.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  any current lower extremity injury

          -  any lower extremity injuries within the last 6 months

          -  open wounds

          -  skin infections

          -  impaired circulation

          -  peripheral vascular disease

          -  deep vein thrombosis

          -  advanced arthritis

          -  poor thermal regulation

          -  anesthetic areas

          -  neoplasms/tumors

          -  thrombophlebitis

          -  closed infections

          -  any allergies or sensitivities to betadine

          -  any abnormalities observed in the medial gastrocnemius muscle determined by diagnostic
             ultrasound

          -  1.0 cm or greater adipose over the left medial gastrocnemius muscle.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kristy Shirley</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NDSU IRB</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Dakota State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fargo</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58108-6050</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gange KN, Kjellerson MC, Berdan CJ. The Dynatron Solaris® Ultrasound Machine: Slower Heating Than Textbook Recommendations at 3 MHz, 1.0 W/cm(2). J Sport Rehabil. 2018 Jan 1;27(1):22-29. doi: 10.1123/jsr.2016-0173. Epub 2018 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27992304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Merrick MA, Bernard KD, Devor ST, Williams MJ. Identical 3-MHz ultrasound treatments with different devices produce different intramuscular temperatures. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2003 Jul;33(7):379-85.</citation>
    <PMID>12918863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Draper DO, Castel JC, Castel D. Rate of temperature increase in human muscle during 1 MHz and 3 MHz continuous ultrasound. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 1995 Oct;22(4):142-50.</citation>
    <PMID>8535471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>North Dakota State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kara Gange</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>heating rates</keyword>
  <keyword>therapeutic ultrasound</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Once the data has been analyzed to determine the heating rates, a manuscript including the heating rates will be submitted for publication.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 5, 2020</submitted>
    <returned>March 17, 2020</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

