<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03818763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO00033763</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03818763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gene Therapy Trial for Platelet Derived Factor VIII Production in Hemophilia A</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study Evaluating Safety and Feasibility of Hematopoietic Stem Cell Gene Transfer That Targets Factor VIII Delivery From Platelets for Patients With Hemophilia A</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Parameswaran Hari</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase I study. This research study is being conducted to find new ways to treat
      severe hemophilia A. This study is a gene therapy study. Gene therapy is an experimental way
      to introduce, into a person's cells, specific genetic material. A gene can be
      delivered/introduced into a cell using a carrier known as a &quot;vector.&quot; In this study, a virus
      (lentivirus), the &quot;vector&quot;, is used to introduce or deliver a gene that creates and stores a
      protein Factor VIII (FVIII) in your platelets. These platelets are made from stem cells
      (mother cells for your bone marrow) that are removed from your blood by a procedure called
      apheresis. This research study will take some of the patient's own stem cells, from the
      apheresis procedure, and genetically modify them using the vector in order to make them
      produce FVIII in platelets that arise from the stem cells. They will then give the
      genetically modified stem cells back to the patient so that they can possibly create
      platelets that produce and store Factor VIII on their own.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label, nonrandomized, single center, phase I cohort study, involving reduced
      intensity conditioning, followed by a single infusion of autologous CD34+PBSC, transduced
      with a lentiviral vector (-889ITGA2B-BDDFVIII-WPTS (MUT6)(VSVg)) also known as
      (Pleightlet(MUT6)) encoding the B domain deleted from of human coagulation factor VIII
      (BDDFVIII) in up to five hemophilia A patients with inhibitors to FVIII.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 29, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2033</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Open-label, nonrandomized, single-center phase I cohort study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of enrolled participants with adequate gene transduced hematopoietic stem cells for FVIII gene therapy infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by availability of ≥4x106 transduced clinical grade CD34+PBSC per kg meeting release criteria for infusion; undetectable microbiological contamination and cell viability ≥70%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicity from gene therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 3 months of gene therapy infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Number of events meeting CTCAE criteria grade 3 or 4 toxicity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemophilia A</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous CD34+PBSC transduced with a lentiviral vector</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive a patient specific (autologous) cytokine mobilized CD34+Peripheral Blood Stem Cells (PBSC) transduced ex vivo with a lentiviral vector containing cDNA encoding the human B-domain deleted FVIII protein.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auto CD34+PBSC, transduced with a lentiviral vector encoding the B domain deleted from of human coagulation factor VIII</intervention_name>
    <description>Reduced intensity conditioning with melphalan and fludarabine, followed by a single infusion of autologous CD34+PBSC, transduced with a lentiviral vector (-889ITGA2B-BDDFVIII-WPTS(MUT6)(VSVg)) also known as (Pleightlet(MUT6)) encoding the B domain deleted from of human coagulation factor VIII (BDDFVIII) in up to five hemophilia A patients with inhibitors to FVIII
The infusion volume of transduced cells will not exceed 20 ml/kg body weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous CD34+PBSC transduced with a lentiviral vector</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Study population will include: adult males ≥18 years of age with a diagnosis of severe
             hemophilia A and currently active high titer FVIII inhibitors (&gt;5 BU). Females will be
             excluded because hemophilia A is an X-linked disorder that is extremely rare in
             females.

               1. Confirmed diagnosis of severe hemophilia A by undetectable plasma factor VIII:C
                  by a one-stage PTT-based assay and coatest chromogenic factor VIII assay. Only
                  subjects with the presence of a high titer factor VIII inhibitor (&gt;5 BU) will be
                  included for enrollment.

               2. Subject may be prescribed prophylactic therapy with factor VIII bypassing agents
                  or factor VIII mimetics prior to referral for inclusion in the study.

               3. Subjects who are treated on demand using factor VIII bypassing agents must have a
                  history of four or more bleeding episodes requiring treatment in the six-month
                  period prior to referral for inclusion in the study.

               4. Adequate bone marrow reserve as demonstrated by ANC &gt;1.5/cu.mm; Hemoglobin
                  &gt;9g/dL; Platelets &gt;100,000/microliter.

               5. Adequate renal function, defined as creatinine clearance&gt;60 ml/min
                  (Cockroft-Gault formula)

               6. Adequate liver function, defined as defined as total bilirubin ≤1.5 times the
                  upper limit of normal (ULN) (excluding Gilbert's syndrome), both AST and ALT ≤3
                  times ULN at the time of screening, and no clinical signs or known
                  laboratory/radiographic evidence consistent with cirrhosis.

               7. Subject must sign an informed consent after explanation of the study and having
                  questions answered.

               8. Subject must be willing and able to document type of bleeding episodes and
                  treatment in a paper or electronic diary during the study.

               9. Subject must be willing to return for regular follow-up visits during the 15-year
                  study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A potential subject who meets any of the following exclusion criteria is ineligible to
             participate in the study.

               1. Therapy with factor VIII with the intent of immune tolerance induction within 30
                  days prior to inclusion within the study.

               2. Enrollment in another interventional clinical trial within 60 days prior to study
                  inclusion.

               3. Medical contraindication to PBSC cytokine mobilization, use of GCSF, PBSC
                  apheresis procedure or conditioning regimen.

               4. Medically significant organ dysfunction that would prevent compliance with
                  conditioning or would severely limit the probability of survival based on
                  clinical status.

               5. Those with a known co-existing clinically significant thrombophilic disorder, or
                  as determined by the presence of any of the below identified on screening
                  laboratory assessments:

                    -  FV Leiden

                    -  Protein S deficiency

                    -  Protein C deficiency

                    -  Prothrombin mutation (G20210A)

                    -  D-dimer &gt;3 x the upper limit of normal (ULN) at Screening All known patients
                       with the above and any patient with a personal or significant family history
                       of thrombotic events (DVT, PE, arterial clots) as deemed by the principal
                       investigator will be screened for the above disorders.

               6. Active invasive malignancy (Non-melanoma skin cancers and carcinoma in situ are
                  not excluded).

               7. Known bone marrow disorders or abnormal bone marrow cytogenetics.

               8. Fertile males who are unwilling to use contraceptive techniques during and for
                  the twelve months following treatment.

               9. Life expectancy severely limited by disease(s) other than hemophilia A.

              10. Patients with HIV, hepatitis B, hepatitis C (with an AST/ALT &gt; 3 times the upper
                  limit of normal).

              11. Other active infectious disease that is a contraindicat ion for immunosuppressive
                  therapy.

              12. Patients who have elective surgery scheduled during the study period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Parmeswaran Hari, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Froedtert Hosptial and Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Parameswaran Hari, MD</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-4600</phone>
    <email>phari@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Debra Pastorek, RN</last_name>
    <phone>414-805-6800</phone>
    <email>dpastore@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert Hospital and the Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Parameswaran Hari, MD</last_name>
      <phone>414-805-4600</phone>
      <email>phari@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Temi Oloyede</last_name>
      <phone>414-805-4869</phone>
      <email>toloyede@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 28, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Parameswaran Hari</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of the Division of Hematology and Oncology, Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gene Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemophilia A</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Factor VIII</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

