<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03040414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UC4DK108611</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UC4DK108611</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03040414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fuzzy Logic Automated Insulin Regulation</brief_title>
  <acronym>FLAIR</acronym>
  <official_title>Home Use of MD-Logic Automated Insulin Delivery System: Safety and Efficacy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>HealthPartners Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medtronic</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jaeb Center for Health Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Schneider Children's Medical Center, Israel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Joslin Diabetes Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Diabetes Center at Park Nicollet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kinderkrankenhaus auf der Bult</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>HealthPartners Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adolescents and young adults with type 1 diabetes often have a difficult time achieving good
      glucose control, which is so important in reducing the risk for diabetes complications.
      Despite the use of multiple daily injections or insulin pumps and glucose sensors, there is
      still a need for many individuals to further improve glucose levels without causing low blood
      glucose levels (hypoglycemia) or adding to the daily burden of living with diabetes. Today an
      insulin pump can receive glucose readings from a continuous glucose monitor and adjust the
      insulin delivery in an attempt to keep glucose levels in a more optimal range. These systems
      are called hybrid closed loop (HCL). This means that much of the insulin delivery is
      automated, yet the patient still interacts regularly with the system, particularly to help
      determine the insulin dose to deliver to cover a meal. Results of early studies using HCL
      systems in adolescents and adults with type 1 diabetes are encouraging.

      The objective of this study is to compare the efficacy and safety of the automated insulin
      delivery (AID) system with proportional integral-derivative (PID) algorithm (Minimed 670G 3.0
      HCL) to an AID system with combined PID and Fuzzy Logic Algorithm (Minimed 670G 4.0 Advanced
      Hybrid Closed-Loop (AHCL)). The trial will test the hypothesis that the Minimed AHCL can
      reduce daytime hyperglycemia, currently the biggest challenge for AID systems, without
      increasing hypoglycemia.

      Up to 124 adolescents and young adults (ages 14-&lt;30) will be recruited to test each system
      for three months in a randomized crossover trial. Investigators will compare how effective
      each hybrid closed loop system is at preventing high blood glucose readings during the day.
      The investigators will also evaluate the safety of each system and how participants adjust to
      the daily use of the technology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose of the study: A randomized crossover trial involving up to four clinical sites in the
      United States and three sites outside the US (Germany, Israel and Slovenia) will compare the
      efficacy and safety of an AID system with a PID algorithm versus an AID system with a PID
      algorithm enhanced with a fuzzy logic algorithm.

      Study Objectives:

        1. EFFICACY: The co-primary outcomes are difference in continuous glucose monitoring
           (CGM)-measured metrics between periods:

             -  Superiority for percent of time &gt;180 mg/dL (10.0 mmol/L) from 6 AM to 11:59 PM; and

             -  Non-inferiority of percent of time &lt;54 mg/dL (3.0 mmol/L) during the entire 24-hour
                period.

        2. KEY SAFETY OUTCOMES:

             -  Percentage of sensor glucose readings &lt;54 mg/dL (overall is a co-primary outcomes)
                and &lt;70 mg/dL (3.0 and 3.9 mmol/L, respectively)

             -  Diabetic Ketoacidosis (DKA) events

             -  Severe hypoglycemia events

           Study design: Randomized crossover trial with two 12-week crossover periods in automode,
           preceded by a run-in phase.

           Population: A maximum of 124 individuals may be enrolled and start the run-in phase.
           Approximately 112 are expected to enter the crossover trial, with a goal of at least 100
           people completing the trial.

           Maximum duration of a study for a subject: Approximately 28-36 weeks.

           Recruitment: Subjects will be recruited through the clinical sites.

           Consent: Written consent/assent will be obtained for all subjects and/or guardians, in
           accordance with human subjects and regulatory requirements.

           Screening Assessments:

             -  Informed consent will be signed and eligibility will be assessed

             -  Medical history and physical examination

             -  HbA1c measurement

             -  Urine pregnancy test (if applicable)

             -  Surveys investigating participants' quality of life, psychosocial and cognitive
                functioning, and response to their current treatment will be distributed.

           Study Training:

           Run-In Period: (2-8 weeks)

           * Eligible participants will use the study 670G 3.0 HCL pump during the run-in.
           Participants who were pump users at screening may skip the Pump Run-In period (but must
           participate in the Pump+CGM Run-In period) per investigator discretion. 670G auto mode
           users may use the 670G pump in auto mode.

           Screening and start of run-in training visits may occur on the same day or separate
           days, but no more than 14 days apart.

           Standardized pump training will be provided to study participants and their diabetes
           care partners (for participants &lt;18 years old). The study team will assist the
           participant in study pump infusion site initiation and will start the participant on the
           study pump. For current pump users, the study pump will be programmed with the
           participants usual basal rates and pump parameters. The participants personal pump will
           be removed. Participants may continue to use their personal CGM if applicable.

           The pump will be used for at least two weeks during the Pump Run-In, with the option of
           repeating Pump Run-In for an additional two weeks per investigator discretion. Contact
           will be made each week with additional contacts as needed. Prior to each contact,
           participants will be asked to upload device data for study staff to review.

           After completion of Pump Run-In, participants will proceed to use the study CGM along
           with the study 670G HCL pump during the Pump+CGM Run-In period.

           * Pump+CGM Run-In (670G 3.0 HCL + Guardian Sensor (3)) All participants must complete a
           two-week run-in period with the use of the study pump and CGM before being randomized
           into the crossover trial. During Pump+CGM Run-In, the predictive low glucose suspend
           feature will be turned on and auto mode will be off (i.e. manual mode). Participants who
           were 670G auto mode users at screening may use the pump in auto mode.

           Standardized device training will be provided to study participants and their diabetes
           care partners (for participants &lt;18 years old). Personal pumps and CGMs will be removed
           during the Pump+CGM Run-In period as applicable.

           Contact will be made each week with additional contacts as needed. Prior to each
           contact, participants will be asked to upload device data for study staff to review.

           Run-In Assessment Successful completion of Pump Run-In is per investigator discretion.
           Pump Run-In may be repeated once.

           Successful completion of the Pump+CGM Run-In requires CGM data to be collected on at
           least 80% of the possible time in the prior 14 days of use. An average of at least three
           blood glucose meter (BGM) tests per day also will be required. If these are not
           achieved, the Pump+CGM Run-In period may be repeated once.

           Randomization into the Crossover Trial

           Eligible participants who successfully complete the Pump+CGM Run-In will be randomly
           assigned to begin with one Automated Insulin Delivery (AID) system during Period 1 and
           then crossover to the other AID system during Period 2. The two study AID systems
           (treatments) are:

             -  670G 3.0 Hybrid Closed-Loop (HCL) (PID) insulin pump + Guardian Sensor (3) CGM

             -  670G 4.0 Advanced Hybrid Closed-Loop (AHCL) (PID + Fuzzy Logic) insulin pump +
                Guardian Sensor (3) CGM

           Home Use of AID System during the Crossover Trial Period 1 (~13 weeks) Participants and
           their diabetes care partners (for participants &lt;18 years old) will be trained by
           qualified personnel on the use of the assigned pump and on auto mode feature use
           including meal announcement, meal bolusing, and exercise.

           Training will also be provided in performing specific tasks including the following:

             -  Confirming pump parameters

             -  When not to use or rely on auto mode particularly during significant illness or
                acetaminophen use

             -  CGM calibration instructions

             -  Meal bolus procedures

             -  What to do when exercising while using the system

             -  How to react to safety/alert notifications

             -  How to perform fingerstick blood glucose measurements in accordance with the
                labeling of the study CGM device

             -  When and how to contact study staff to ask questions during the study

           Study staff will discuss the visit and contact schedule with the participant and will
           make arrangements for follow-up appointments. Participants will be asked to upload data
           before each contact and at least every two weeks.

           After auto mode training has been completed, participants will proceed with home use of
           the AID system (meaning free-living use at work, home, etc.) during Period 1 with either
           the 670G 3.0 HCL or 670G 4.0 AHCL pump. The predictive low glucose suspend feature will
           be on.

           The system will initially be used with auto mode deactivated (except for 670G auto mode
           users at screening who may activate auto mode if using the 670G 3.0 HCL pump) until
           participants are contacted 6-10 days into Period 1 with instructions to activate auto
           mode. Participants will be instructed to obtain an overnight fingerstick blood glucose
           measurement (between 2-3AM) for 2-3 nights following auto mode initiation and if
           fingerstick blood glucose is &lt;70 mg/dL to treat with carbohydrate. Participants will
           then continue using the AID system for 12 weeks after auto mode is initialized.

           Participants will be expected to use auto mode at all times at home with some exceptions
           (e.g. times of illness, acetaminophen use).

           Participants on the 670G 4.0 AHCL will begin with an auto mode target glucose set point
           of 120 mg/dL (6.7 mmol/L) that may be lowered to 100 mg/dL (5.6 mmol/L) if participant
           meets the safety criteria per protocol and investigator discretion.

           HbA1c, C-peptide, and glucose levels will be collected for central lab analysis at the
           beginning of Study Period 1. Human Factors and Diabetes Technology Attitude Surveys will
           be administered at the end of Study Period 1.

           Period 2 (~13 weeks) At the beginning of Period 2, a urine pregnancy test will be
           completed as applicable. Eligible participants will then use the other AID system during
           Period 2. The procedures in Period 1 will be repeated in Period 2.

           At the end of the 12-weeks of AID use in auto mode at home, the participant will
           complete a final study visit. That visit may be completed in-person in clinic or in an
           alternate location such as the participant's home. The study visit may occur remotely
           via phone or videoconferencing. Certain procedures, such as the measurement of height,
           weight, vitals, and collection of the central HbA1c sample, may be missed if the visit
           is not completed in-person. Participants requiring a remote final visit will be
           transitioned off of the study device during the remote contact and an arrangement will
           be made between site staff and the participant to return all required study devices
           either in-person or via mail.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized crossover trial with two 12-week crossover periods in auto mode preceded by a run-in phase.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Superiority for percent of time &gt;180 mg/dL (10.0 mmol/L) from 6 AM to 11:59 PM</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose levels based on sensor glucose data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-inferiority for percent of time &lt;54 mg/dL (3.0 mmol/L) during the entire 24-hour period.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose levels based on sensor glucose data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy: CGM derived indices</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>CGM derived indices over the first 84 days of each treatment period for 24 hours (excluding time before auto mode is turned on) daytime (6 AM-11:59 PM), nighttime (12 AM - 5:59 AM), and for each post-meal period, measured for up to three hours after a meal (or until another carbohydrate is entered).Glucose levels based on sensor glucose data for Mean glucose; coefficient of variation; percentage of sensor glucose readings in the range of 70 to 180 mg/dL (3.9-10.0 mmol/L) and 70 to 140 mg/dL (3.9 to 7.8 mmol/L); percentage of sensor glucose readings &gt;180 mg/dL (daytime is a co-primary outcome) and &gt;250 mg/dL (10.0 and 13.9 mmol/L, respectively); and peak glucose and change in glucose from the start of the meal to the peak (only calculated for post-meal periods)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy: Amount of total, basal and bolus daily insulin over the first 84 days of each treatment period</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>Amount of total, basal, and bolus daily insulin over the first 84 days of each treatment period (excluding time before auto mode is turned on) for 24 hours, daytime (6 AM-11:59 PM), nightime (12 AM and 5:59 AM), and for each post-meal period, from the time the carbohydrate is entered for up to three hours or until another carbohydrate is entered. Glucose levels based on sensor glucose data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy: HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Screening visit, at initiation (Day 0); randomization (Week 2 through 8, depending); end of crossover period 1 (Week 14 through 20, depending); and end of crossover period 2 (Week 26-32, depending)</time_frame>
    <description>Lab measured</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy: BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Screening visit, at initiation (Day 0); randomization (Week 2 through 8, depending); end of crossover period 1 (Week 14 through 20, depending); and end of crossover period 2 (Week 26-32, depending)</time_frame>
    <description>Height and weight</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Key Safety Outcome 1) Percentage of sensor glucose readings &lt;54 mg/dL and &lt;70 mg/dL (3.0 and 3.9 mmol/L, respectively)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>Glucose levels based on sensor glucose data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Key Safety Outcome 2) DKA events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>As determined by ketone levels</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Key Safety Outcome 3) Severe hypoglycemia events</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>As defined by the Diabetes Control and Complications Trial (DCCT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of total basal and bolus insulin at daytime, nighttime and post-meal, analyzing both total units and units/kg</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks for each arm of the crossover</time_frame>
    <description>Based on sensor glucose data</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Human Factors and Diabetes Technology Attitude and Human Factors questionnaires</measure>
    <time_frame>Time Frame: Screening visit, at initiation (Day 0); end of crossover period 1 (Week 14 through 20, depending); and end of crossover period 2 (Week 26-32, depending)</time_frame>
    <description>Surveys completed by participants</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PID Algorithm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive insulin delivered by the Medtronic Minimed 670G 3.0 HCL system using a PID algorithm..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PID + Fuzzy Logic Algorithm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive insulin delivered by the Medtronic advanced hybrid closed loop system (Minimed 670G 4.0 AHCL) with Guardian Sensor (3) continuous glucose monitoring sensor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MedtronicMinimed 670G 3.0 hybrid closed loop system</intervention_name>
    <description>The components of the intervention are the insulin pump with insulin delivery algorithm (PID).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PID Algorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medtronic Minimed 670G 4.0 AHCL with Guardian Sensor (3) continuous glucose monitoring sensor.</intervention_name>
    <description>The components of the intervention are the insulin pump with insulin delivery algorithm (PID + Fuzzy Logic) and Guardian Sensor (3).</description>
    <arm_group_label>PID + Fuzzy Logic Algorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Type 1 diabetes mellitus (as diagnosed clinically) for at least one year

          2. Age 14-&lt;30 years at enrollment

          3. For females, not currently known to be pregnant, be breast-feeding or planning to
             become pregnant within the study duration.

          4. Using an insulin pump or multiple daily injections of insulin

               1. Participant must be able to obtain U-100 rapid acting insulin analogues, Aspart
                  or Lispro, for use during the study (since these are the only insulins approved
                  for the study pump and the study is not supplying insulin)

               2. MDI users must be on a basal/bolus regimen

               3. Participants must have a minimum total daily dose (TDD) of at least eight units

          5. HbA1c from an approved HbA1c point of care analyzer with a value 7.0%-11.0%

          6. Willingness or ability to do carbohydrate counting

          7. In the investigator's judgment, able to understand and likely to be adherent to the
             protocol

          8. For subjects &lt;18 years old, living with one or more diabetes care partners (eg.g.
             parent/legal guardian), of whom at least one is committed to participating in study
             training for emergency procedures for severe hypoglycemia and able to contact the
             participant in case of an emergency.

          9. Have adequate internet access and a computer system that meets requirements for
             uploading data.

         10. For participants currently using CGM or insulin pump, willingness to discontinue
             personal CGM and pump when using the study CGM and pumps (note: including implantable
             CGMs).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Individuals meeting any of the following exclusion criteria at screening will be excluded
        from study participation:

          1. Concomitant disease that influences metabolic control or HbA1c interpretation (e.g.
             anemia, significantly impaired hepatic function, confirmed gastroparesis, renal
             failure, history of adrenal insufficiency, sickle cell disease, haemoglobinopathy, or
             has received red blood cell transfusion or erythropoietin within three months prior to
             time of screening) or other medical condition which, in the Investigator's opinion,
             may compromise patient safety, affect outcome assessments, or affect the participant's
             ability to follow the protocol

          2. Oral or parenteral glucocorticoids taken within 1 month prior to enrollment, or plans
             to take oral or parenteral glucocorticoids within the planned study duration.
             Exceptions: Short term oral or parenteral glucocorticoids up to seven days

          3. Use of antidiabetic agents other than insulin

          4. Use of other medications, which in the judgment of the investigator would be a
             contraindication to participation in the study

          5. One or more episodes of severe hypoglycemia (hypoglycemia requiring treatment by
             another person) within the previous six months

          6. Known allergy to medical grade adhesives

          7. Participation in another study of a medical device or drug that could affect glucose
             measurements or glucose management or receipt of any investigational medical product
             within 1 month prior to enrollment

          8. Current eating disorder such as anorexia or bulimia

          9. Currently abusing illicit drugs, marijuana, prescription drugs, or alcohol

         10. Visual impairment or hearing loss, which may compromise the participant's ability to
             perform all study procedures safely, as determined by the investigator

         11. One or more episodes of diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA) requiring hospitalization within
             six months prior to screening

         12. Working night shifts

         13. Untreated celiac disease, hyperthyroidism, or hypothyroidism

         14. Clinically significant nephropathy (eGFR &lt;45 mL/min) or on dialysis. Creatinine to
             determine eGFR must have been obtained as part of usual care within 12 months prior to
             enrollment (if not available, at time of enrollment, screening can proceed but it must
             be available prior to randomization)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Bergenstal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>International Diabetes Center, HealthPartners Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Moshe Phillip, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Schneider Children's Medical Center, Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joslin Diabetes Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Diabetes Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis Park</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55416</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kinderkrankenhaus Auf Der Bult</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hannover</city>
        <zip>30173</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Schneider Children's Medical Center of Israel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Petah Tikva</city>
        <zip>4920235</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ljubljana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergenstal RM, Tamborlane WV, Ahmann A, Buse JB, Dailey G, Davis SN, Joyce C, Peoples T, Perkins BA, Welsh JB, Willi SM, Wood MA; STAR 3 Study Group. Effectiveness of sensor-augmented insulin-pump therapy in type 1 diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2010 Jul 22;363(4):311-20. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1002853. Epub 2010 Jun 29. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2010 Sep 9;363(11):1092.</citation>
    <PMID>20587585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillip M, Battelino T, Atlas E, Kordonouri O, Bratina N, Miller S, Biester T, Stefanija MA, Muller I, Nimri R, Danne T. Nocturnal glucose control with an artificial pancreas at a diabetes camp. N Engl J Med. 2013 Feb 28;368(9):824-33. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1206881.</citation>
    <PMID>23445093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergenstal RM, Klonoff DC, Garg SK, Bode BW, Meredith M, Slover RH, Ahmann AJ, Welsh JB, Lee SW, Kaufman FR; ASPIRE In-Home Study Group. Threshold-based insulin-pump interruption for reduction of hypoglycemia. N Engl J Med. 2013 Jul 18;369(3):224-32. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1303576. Epub 2013 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23789889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nimri R, Muller I, Atlas E, Miller S, Fogel A, Bratina N, Kordonouri O, Battelino T, Danne T, Phillip M. MD-Logic overnight control for 6 weeks of home use in patients with type 1 diabetes: randomized crossover trial. Diabetes Care. 2014 Nov;37(11):3025-32. doi: 10.2337/dc14-0835. Epub 2014 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25078901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nimri R, Phillip M. Artificial pancreas: fuzzy logic and control of glycemia. Curr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes. 2014 Aug;21(4):251-6. doi: 10.1097/MED.0000000000000073. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24937038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nimri R, Muller I, Atlas E, Miller S, Kordonouri O, Bratina N, Tsioli C, Stefanija MA, Danne T, Battelino T, Phillip M. Night glucose control with MD-Logic artificial pancreas in home setting: a single blind, randomized crossover trial-interim analysis. Pediatr Diabetes. 2014 Mar;15(2):91-9. doi: 10.1111/pedi.12071. Epub 2013 Aug 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23944875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bergenstal RM, Garg S, Weinzimer SA, Buckingham BA, Bode BW, Tamborlane WV, Kaufman FR. Safety of a Hybrid Closed-Loop Insulin Delivery System in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes. JAMA. 2016 Oct 4;316(13):1407-1408. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.11708.</citation>
    <PMID>27629148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nimri R, Bratina N, Kordonouri O, Avbelj Stefanija M, Fath M, Biester T, Muller I, Atlas E, Miller S, Fogel A, Phillip M, Danne T, Battelino T. MD-Logic overnight type 1 diabetes control in home settings: A multicentre, multinational, single blind randomized trial. Diabetes Obes Metab. 2017 Apr;19(4):553-561. doi: 10.1111/dom.12852. Epub 2017 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27981804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 31, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hybrid closed loop</keyword>
  <keyword>Closed loop</keyword>
  <keyword>Artificial pancreas</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 17, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/14/NCT03040414/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

