<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04312126</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200060</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>20-N-0060</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04312126</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Beneficial Effects of Naps on Motor Learning</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mechanisms Underlying the Beneficial Effects of Naps on Motor Learning</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Memory consolidation is the process by which memories become stable, long-term
      representations in the brain. Consolidation of a motor skill is dependent upon sleep. Some
      research shows that daytime naps improve people s motor performance and memory retention.
      Researchers want to find out how daytime naps may contribute to learning and support
      consolidation of motor skill memories.

      Objective:

      To learn the role of memory replay during wakeful rest and sleep (naps) in retaining a newly
      learned skill.

      Eligibility:

      English-speaking adults ages 18 and older with chronic stroke, or healthy, right-handed,
      English-speaking adults ages 18-35 and 50-80

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

        -  medical history

        -  neurological history

        -  medicine review

        -  medical exam

        -  neurological exam.

      Participants will have a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of the brain. For this, they
      will lie down in a scanner. The scanner makes loud noises, so they will wear earplugs. They
      will fill out an MRI screening form before each MRI.

      Participants will also have magnetoencephalography (MEG). MEG maps brain activity. It does
      this by recording the magnetic fields produced by naturally occurring electrical currents in
      the brain. For MEG, participants will lie down in the MEG room. Their eye movements may be
      recorded by a video camera.

      Participants will have behavior testing. They will practice typing random keys. Then they
      will repeatedly type a custom sequence that they see on a computer screen. Then they will
      take a 2-hour nap. Then they will type the same sequence again.

      Participants will have no more than 4 visits at the NIH over 3 months. Visits will last 2-4
      hours each.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Description: We will investigate sleep neural replay to motor skill consolidation in
      three groups: (a) young healthy subjects, (b) older healthy subjects and (c) patients with
      chronic stroke.

      Objective: The primary aim is to determine the relative contribution of neural replay during
      wakeful rest and sleep to consolidation of a newly learned skill in young and older healthy
      volunteers, and in chronic stroke patients with magnetoencephalography (MEG). The secondary
      aim is to evaluate differences in replay rates between these subject cohorts. We will also
      explore differences in replay rates, spatiotemporal dynamics of neural replay and sleep
      spindles to generate additional hypotheses and preliminary data for future studies.

      Endpoints: The primary endpoint measure is motor skill consolidation (i.e., offline change in
      correct sequence typing speed following a nap). The secondary endpoint measure is neural
      replay rate. Exploratory endpoints measures are spatial (i.e. - parcellated source space) and
      time-frequency maps of neural replay during wakeful rest and sleep, and changes in
      button-press finger movement kinematics during learning.

      Study Population:

      Arm 1: 46 healthy young (18-35) volunteers.

      Arm 2: 46 healthy older (50-80) volunteers.

      Arm 3: 46 chronic (&gt;6 months post-stroke) stroke patients.

      Phase: N/A

      Descriotion of Site/Facilities: This protocol utilizes the NIH Clinical Center Outpatient
      Clinic, and NMRF and MEG core facilities.

      Intervention: N/A

      Study Duration: 48 months

      Participant Duration: Up to 4 visits lasting approximately 2-4 hours each.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The degree to which motor skill consolidation is predicted by replay rates during wakeful rest and sleep, and spindle rates during sleep.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint measure is the degree to which motor skill consolidation (i.e., offline change in correct sequence typing speed) is predicted by replay rates during wakeful rest and sleep, and spindle rates during sleep (i.e. multiple regression model with 3 predictors). Exploratory endpoints measures are spatial (i.e. - parcellated source space) and time-frequency maps of neural replay during wakeful rest and sleep.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatial and time-frequency maps of neural replay during wakeful rest and sleep.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint measure is the degree to which motor skill consolidation (i.e., offline change in correct sequence typing speed) is predicted by replay rates during wakeful rest and sleep, and spindle rates during sleep (i.e. multiple regression model with 3 predictors). Exploratory endpoints measures are spatial (i.e. - parcellated source space) and time-frequency maps of neural replay during wakeful rest and sleep.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">138</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>46 healthy young (18-35) volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>46 healthy older (50-80) volunteers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <description>46 chronic (&gt;6 months post-stroke) stroke patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy adults 18-35 or 50-80; Stroke patients 18 and older
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  HEALTHY VOLUNTEERS:

        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18-35 (Arm 1) or 50-80 (Arm 2)

          -  English speaking

          -  Clear right-hand dominance (&gt;74 on Edinburgh Handedness Inventory)

          -  Normal neurological examination as determined by the screening clinician

          -  Severe or progressive neurological, psychological or medical condition as determined
             by the screening clinician.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  HCPS-section affiliated NIH staff

          -  Current pregnancy

          -  Contraindications for MRI or MEG.

          -  Use of sleep medications within 24 hours of Experimental Session participation

        STROKE PATIENTS:

        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Willing and able to provide consent

          -  Experienced a stroke 6 months ago or more that affected at least one of the upper
             extremities at time of stroke diagnosis

          -  Ability to perform the study task as assessed during physical examination

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  HCPS-affiliated NIH staff.

          -  Current pregnancy

          -  History of large stroke in brainstem or cerebellum

          -  Severe or progressive neurological disorder other than stroke (e.g., Parkinson s
             disease or multiple sclerosis)

          -  Uncontrolled heart, lung, kidney, gastrointestinal, metabolic, psychiatric, sleep, or
             endocrine disorders

          -  Contraindications for MRI or MEG.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leonardo G Cohen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margaret K Hayward, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-1335</phone>
    <email>HCPS.research@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2020-N-0060.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 9, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Motor Skill</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Naps</keyword>
  <keyword>Neural Replay</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

