<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04318756</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2458 CWS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04318756</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Italian Version of Cancer Worry Scale</brief_title>
  <acronym>CWS_Ita</acronym>
  <official_title>The Italian Version of the Cancer Worry Scale . A Pancreatic Context Adaptation and Reliability Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Integrata Verona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Integrata Verona</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An Italian language version of the Cancer Worry Scale is not available yet.

      The aim of this study is to develop and validate the Italian version of Cancer Worry Scale
      through subjects at high risk of pancreatic cancer for familiarity/genetic predisposition, or
      suffering from premalignant cystic lesions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Fear of Cancer remains a significant problem for subjects enrolled surveillance programs.
      This emotional condition can influence the patients' wellbeing and their adherence to
      treatments. No results coming from the application of Cancer Worry Scale on high-risk of
      Pancreatic cancer individuals have been provided yet.

      The fear is an emotional reaction that can be the result of interpretation and cognitions of
      perceived internal cues and/or external cues. To objectify this emotion, a cancer worry
      scale, has been developed to investigate the fear in female breast cancer survivors. The
      proposed scale assesses the psychological distress caused by fear of cancer.

      The detection of high level of fear can prevent problematic behaviours, including anxious
      preoccupation, avoidance, and excessive checking, and moreover it can help patients to reduce
      difficulties in performing the individual's daily and social activities. The scale could use
      to evaluate the psychological burden produced by the enrolment in a surveillance program due
      to a certain predisposition to Pancreatic cancer. One step forward will be to manage those
      individuals with high-level of Fear of cancer, providing them a proper psychological support.

      At the General and Pancreatic Surgery Unit of the Pancreas Institute, some experimental
      self-made psychological support programs that investigate different psychologic distress
      through validated instruments, like anxiety, depression, perceived stress and global
      assessment or quality of life have been built up. It must be noted that the scale is not
      available specifically for Pancreatic cancer (originally it was created for breast cancer) ,
      and for the Italian language, thus it has never been applied in an italian
      surveillance/follow-up program dealing with Pancreatic cancer. Nowadays, there is only a
      well-structured paper assessing psychological factors associated with cancer worries in high
      risk participants in a pancreatic cancer surveillance program. Differently than what has been
      already reported by Konings et al, the cohorts of patients that will be considered are
      heterogeneous, reflecting more accurately the real-life scenario of the subjects to whom the
      scale is administered to. In addition, this may help to identify those individuals that may
      benefit from a psychological support, in order to prevent a withdrawal from the surveillance
      program.

      However, a cut-off has not been provided yet. With next step study we'll aim at determining a
      cut-off for the detection clinically relevant worry for cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Syntactic and semantic equivalence of Cancer worry scale' items between English and Italian language and vice versa</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>the Syntactic and semantic equivalence of scale between two languages will be verified through the evaluation of differential item functioning analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Face Validity of cancer worry scale on Italian subjects</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Face Validity will be measured through the evaluation of Clarity/ comprehensibility of each item of cancer worry scale (format and meaning)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory comparison between Patients Health Questionnaire and Irritability Depression Anxiety Scale and cancer worry scale</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>the comparison will be done considering the total score of scales</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer Fear</condition>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Italian patients suffering from mucinous neoplasms</arm_group_label>
    <description>Italian patients suffering from mucinous neoplasms will follow a brief interview made by a psychologist. The interview of pilot group will be record to allow us to investigate and track detail that will highlight the comprehension of cancer worry scale and participants' suggestion. Moreover during the session will be ask to patients to fill inn Irritability-Depression-Anxiety Scale and Patient Health Questionnaire-9 to evaluate other psycho-emotional information about fear of cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Italian patients with familiarity/genetic predisposition</arm_group_label>
    <description>Italian patients with familiarity/genetic predisposition will follow a brief interview made by a psychologist. The interview of pilot group will be record to allow us to investigate and track detail that will highlight the comprehension of cancer worry scale and participants' suggestion. Moreover during the session will be ask to patients to fill inn Irritability-Depression-Anxiety Scale and Patient Health Questionnaire-9 to evaluate other psycho-emotional information about fear of cancer</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Translation and cultural adaptation go the cancer worry scale</intervention_name>
    <description>To develop and validate the Italian version of Cancer worry scale using high risk subjects for familiarity/genetic predisposition and patients with premalignant lesions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Italian patients suffering from mucinous neoplasms</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Italian patients with familiarity/genetic predisposition</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1) Preliminary pilot testing conducted on a pilot group on patients under surveillance for pancreatic cancer</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subject will be recruited from the current outpatients' clinic activity of the General and
        Pancreatic Surgery Unit, Pancreas Institute, Verona University Hospital. Subjects must be
        able to read and write in Italian. After obtained informed consent we will ask them to
        participate to preliminary pilot phase.

        The interview of the pilot group will be audio recorded to allow to investigate and track
        detail that will highlight the comprehension of scale and participants' suggestion.

        Patients affected by cynic neoplasm (group A) and high risk subjects for
        familiarity/genetic predisposition (group B) are currently enrolled at General and
        Pancreatic Surgery Unit of the Pancreas Institute of the University of Verona.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subject will be recruited from the current outpatients' clinic activity of the General and
        Pancreatic Surgery Unit, Pancreas Institute, Verona University Hospital. Subjects must be
        able to read and write in Italian. After obtained informed consent we will ask them to
        participate to preliminary pilot phase.

        The interview of the pilot group will be audio recorded to allow to investigate and track
        detail that will highlight the comprehension of scale and participants' suggestion.

        Patients affected by cynic neoplasm (group A) and high risk subjects for
        familiarity/genetic predisposition (group B) are currently enrolled at General and
        Pancreatic Surgery Unit of the Pancreas Institute of the University of Verona.

        Group A Patients with premalignant lesions (such as intraductal papillary mucinous
        neoplasms) that are followed-up at our Institution, to detect any clinic-radiological
        progression. Subjects older than 18 will be enrolled.

        Group B

        The enrolment criteria were the following :

          -  Having at least 45 years of age or 10 years younger than the age of the youngest
             relative with pancreatic cancer (only for subject with familiar history of pancreatic
             cancer)

          -  Having at least 40 years of age or 5 years younger than the age of the youngest
             relative with pancreatic cancer (only for subject with familial pancreatitis and
             subject affected by Lynch syndrome with at least one relative first- or second-degree
             affected by pancreatic cancer and subject having a known genetic mutation with at
             least a first-degree relative or a second-degree relative affected by pancreatic
             cancer

          -  Having at least 30 years of age for subject with Familial Multiple Melanoma Syndrome

          -  Having at least 30 years of age for patients affected by Peutz-Jeghers syndrome.

        The interview of pilot group will be record to allow us to investigate and track detail
        that will highlight the comprehension of cancer worry scale and participants' suggestion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients who not meet eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Salvotore Paiella, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0458126669</phone>
    <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
    <email>salvatore.paiella@univr.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cancer worry scale</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer fear</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreatic cancer risk</keyword>
  <keyword>pancreatic cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

