<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04310761</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>XX/2020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04310761</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Retrospective Comparison of Pregnancy Outcome of Infertile Patients After Fresh and Warmed Single Blastocyst Transfer From 2014 to 2018.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Retrospective Comparison of Pregnancy Outcome of Infertile Patients After Fresh and Warmed Single Blastocyst Transfer From 2014 to 2018.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators retrospectively analysed the maternal and neonatal outcomes following a
      single fresh blastocyst transfer and a single warmed blastocyst transfer from procedures
      performed between 2014 and 2018 in a tertiary level university based fertility clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies that analysed pregnancy outcomes in women who underwent frozen single
      blastocyst transfer have shown an increase rate of large for gestational age and very large
      for gestational age (Zhang et al., 2019),increased maternal risks of placenta accreta and
      pregnancy-induced hypertension (Ishihara et al.,2014),and lower risks of placenta previa,
      placental abruption, very pre-term birth, small for gestational age, and perinatal mortality
      (Sha, Yin, Cheng,&amp; Massey, 2018) than fresh blastocyst transfer.

      The main outcome of this study is to analyse the rate of live births with the relative
      gestational period and neonatal weight and still death and neonatal death per each single
      blastocyst transfer, both fresh and warmed. Secondary outcomes include the incidence of
      obstetric pathologies, gestational diabetes and pre-eclampsia, and defects of placentation.

      The study database included all pregnancies occurred after both a single fresh and warmed
      blastocyst transfer between the five-year period from 2014 to 2018 at Humanitas Fertility
      Centre. The inclusion criteria were all patients, without any age limitations, which
      underwent either FIVET or ICSI and only transferred a single blastocyst. With regards to
      exclusion criteria, the following were considered: ovodonation, suspended cycles and embryos
      which were subjected to pre-implantation genetic testing.The investigator performed a
      comparison of maternal and neonatal outcomes in these pregnancies which occurred in the same
      period of time and in the same age-group of women.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of live births</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of live births with the relative gestational period and neonatal weight and still death and neonatal death per each single blastocyst transfer, both fresh and warmed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of obstetric pathologies</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of obstetric pathologies, gestational diabetes and pre-eclampsia, and defects of placentation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4613</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Maternal and Neonatal Outcomes; Assisted Reproductive Technology</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy population after one single blastocyst transfer</arm_group_label>
    <description>The data have been collected from the Humanitas Fertility Center' Department database (ART.it) from a period between 2014 and 2018.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>one single blastocyst transfer, both fresh and warmed</intervention_name>
    <description>Ultrasound guided transvaginal embryo transfer.</description>
    <arm_group_label>pregnancy population after one single blastocyst transfer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All infertile patients which performed a single fresh and a single frozen embryo transfer
        from 2014 to 2018.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infertile women, without any age limitations, which underwent either FIVET or ICSI and
             only transferred a single blastocyst (warmed or fresh).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Ovodonation, suspended cycles, and embryos subjected to pre-implantation genetic
             testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang J, Wang Y, Liu H, Mao X, Chen Q, Fan Y, Xiao Y, Kuang Y. Effect of in vitro culture period on birth weight after vitrified-warmed transfer cycles: analysis of 4,201 singleton newborns. Fertil Steril. 2019 Jan;111(1):97-104. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2018.10.006. Epub 2018 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>30458993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ishihara O, Araki R, Kuwahara A, Itakura A, Saito H, Adamson GD. Impact of frozen-thawed single-blastocyst transfer on maternal and neonatal outcome: an analysis of 277,042 single-embryo transfer cycles from 2008 to 2010 in Japan. Fertil Steril. 2014 Jan;101(1):128-33. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2013.09.025. Epub 2013 Oct 23. Erratum in: Fertil Steril. 2014 Apr;101(4):1200.</citation>
    <PMID>24268706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sha T, Yin X, Cheng W, Massey IY. Pregnancy-related complications and perinatal outcomes resulting from transfer of cryopreserved versus fresh embryos in vitro fertilization: a meta-analysis. Fertil Steril. 2018 Feb;109(2):330-342.e9. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2017.10.019. Epub 2018 Jan 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29331236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

