<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04317716</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-00457</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04317716</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Self-management Program to Prevent Falls in People With Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Self-management Program to Prevent Falls in Ambulatory and Non-ambulatory Community Dwelling People With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Forte</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project's overall aim is to develop, deliver, and evaluate an innovative fall prevention
      program for ambulatory and non-ambulatory people with multiple sclerosis. The program will
      use a comprehensive intervention approach to address a variety of fall risk factors, and
      utilise self-management strategies. Specific aims are to 1) develop a fall prevention
      program, that addresses diverse fall risk factors and utilises self-management strategies,
      for ambulatory and non-ambulatory people with multiple sclerosis using a co-design process.

      2) To determine if the fall prevention program is effective in reducing falls in ambulatory
      and non-ambulatory people with multiple sclerosis.

      3) To identify change processes that can explain the potential effects of the fall prevention
      program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In line with the recommendations for complex interventions, the fall prevention program will
      be developed and evaluated using quantitative and qualitative methods, and evaluation of both
      process (including feasibility) and outcome will occur. The program will be developed in a
      co-design process with people with multiple sclerosis and health professionals and evaluated
      via a randomised controlled trial. The Swedish MS-registry will be used to identify potential
      participants. MS specific representatives from the patient organisation Neuro Sweden will be
      involved in program design and implementation. The intervention group will receive the fall
      prevention program and the control group will receive group-based brief advice about fall
      risk factors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be stratified for ambulation level (ambulatory/non-ambulatory) and a 1:1 allocation ratio of blocks of 10 will be used.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The facilitators of the fall prevention program will not be involved in the usual care of the participants. The intervention will take place at locations intended for patient education (i.e., separate from the regular clinical care) situated at the Academic Specialist Center of Neurology. Control-group participants will receive one two-hour session of group-based brief advice about fall risk factors at locations situated at the Medical Unit Occupational Therapy &amp; Physiotherapy, Karolinska University Hospital. Baseline and follow-up assessments will be performed by blinded evaluators.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months (from baseline to 12 months after end of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Falls will be monitored via an online short message service (SMS). A SMS will be sent once a week (to avoid recall bias) asking &quot;Have you fallen within the last week?&quot; Participants answering &quot;yes&quot; will be contacted with questions regarding the circumstances of the fall.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of fear of falling developed by Clemson et al 2015</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire with one question &quot;Are you afraid of falling?&quot; and six response options: Not at all afraid, Somewhat afraid, Fairly afraid, Very afraid, Don't know, Refused
Not at all afraid Somewhat afraid Fairly afraid Very afraid Don't know Refused ARE YOU AFRAID OF FALLING?
Not at all afraid Somewhat afraid Fairly afraid Very afraid Don't know Refused ARE YOU AFRAID OF FALLING?
Not at all afraid Somewhat afraid Fairly afraid Very afraid Don't know Refused ARE YOU AFRAID OF FALLING?
Not at all afraid Somewhat afraid Fairly afraid Very afraid Don't know Refused ARE YOU AFRAID OF FALLING?
Not at all afraid Somewhat afraid Fairly afraid Very afraid Don't know Refused</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Falls Efficacy Scale -International</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire that consists of 16 questions regarding 'how concerned' the person is when performing daily activities. Each question is answered with a four-graded scale (1-4); not at all concerned, somewhat concerned, fairly concerned and very concerned. A total score is calculated and ranges from 16 to 64</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fall Prevention Strategy Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The scale includes 14 fall prevention strategies. Participants report whether they currently use or have used the strategies to manage falls risk. If they are using it, they rate strategy effectiveness on a scale of 0-10. If they are not using it, they identify why (e.g., forgot, didn't think it would work, don't know how). This instrument produces three outcome indicators: (a) number of strategies used (pre and post intervention), (b) percent change in use for each individual strategy, and (c) the average effectiveness (self-rated)for the strategies used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multiple Sclerosis Impact Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>29-item self-report measure with 20 items associated with a physical scale and 9 items with a psychological scale. Items ask about the impact of multiple sclerosis on day-to-day life in the past two weeks. All items have 5 response options: 1 &quot;not at all&quot; to 5&quot;extremely&quot;. Each of the two scales are scored by summing the responses across items, then converting to a 0-100 scale where 100 indicates greater impact of disease on daily function (worse health)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EuroQol 5D-5L</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>EuroQol 5D, consists of the EQ-5D Index and the EQ Visual Analog Scale. The EuroQol 5D comprises 5 pre-defined dimensions: Mobility, Self-care, Usual activities, Pain/discomfort and Anxiety/depression. The respondent rates each dimension on a three level scale as having no problem, a moderate problem or a severe problem. The answers are then converted to an index value (the EQ Index) ranging from 0 (death) to 1 (full health). The EQ VAS records the respondent's self-rated health on a 20-centimeter vertical visual analog scale with end-points ranging from 0 to 100. The single global question in the EQ VAS asks the individual to label his/her health as &quot;the worst health you can imagine&quot; (0) to &quot;the best health you can imagine&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on Participation and Autonomy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Directly after the intervention and at 12 months after the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Measures two different aspects of participation: perceived participation and the experience of problems for each aspect of participation. The perceived participation scale consists of 31 items which are assessed using a 5 point rating scale (1=very good and 5=very poor) and the problem scale contains 8 items which are assessed using a 3 point rating scale (0=no problem and 2=severe problem). A participation score (range: 30-155) and a problem score (0-16) are produced by summing items in each scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">214</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fall prevention program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Advice about fall risk factors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fall prevention program</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists of the fall prevention program for ambulatory and non-ambulatory people with multiple sclerosis. The program will be group-based with 6-8 participants, led by a facilitator (researcher), and performed in approximately six two-hour sessions, the first five over five consecutive weeks and the last final session held one month after the fifth session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>brief advice about fall risk factors</intervention_name>
    <description>Control-group participants will receive one two-hour session of group-based brief advice about fall risk factors at locations situated at the Medical Unit Occupational Therapy &amp; Physiotherapy, Karolinska University Hospital. They will be advised to live their normal lives and receive usual care at the discretion of their physician since no treatment can be considered the gold standard.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Community-dwelling adults aged ≥ 18 years

          -  Diagnosed with multiple sclerosis

          -  Able to understand and communicate in Swedish.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other conditions or diagnoses judged to potentially interfere with the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charlotte Ytterberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>associate professor (docent)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

