<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04319068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SSIS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04319068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sodium Storage in Singaporeans</brief_title>
  <acronym>SSIS</acronym>
  <official_title>Sodium Storage in Singaporeans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jens Titze</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart Centre Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overarching hypothesis of this study is that the kidney and the skin form an integrative
      network for water conservation, where Na+ storage is utilized to prevent body water loss,
      even at the expense of increased cardiovascular risk. The aim of this project is to
      characterise skin and muscle Na+ storage in a cohort designed to prospectively measure
      cardiovascular outcomes in Singaporeans, in order to determine whether humans with increased
      tissue Na+ storage have increased cardiovascular risk. To gain a better understanding of the
      mechanisms behind Na+ storage, the investigators will also test the hypothesis that
      participants with mutations of the skin protein filaggrin, who have increased water loss
      through the skin, will have increased skin Na+ storage and higher blood pressure levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cardiovascular disease (CVD) occurs with increasing age and is the leading cause of death
      worldwide. A causal relationship between salt and CVD, although well established in animal
      models, has been difficult to prove in human populations. First, because humans do not live
      under the strict experimental conditions necessary to quantify sodium intake, and second,
      because tissue sodium stores cannot be detected with the available clinical methods, making
      reliable measurements of total body sodium extremely challenging.

      The investigators have previously implemented 23NaMRI technology to detect and quantify
      tissue Na+ stores in humans. Previous studies have sown that humans store large amounts of
      Na+ in their skin and muscle as they age and that skin Na+ storage is linked with
      hypertension, while muscle Na+ storage is coupled with insulin resistance and diabetes. More
      recent studies show that the adverse effect of Na+ on human health goes far beyond the
      well-established salt-blood pressure relationship. The investigators have found that urea
      and/or Na+ storage in barriers such as kidney or skin is a key principle of water
      conservation.

      This study aims to test the hypothesis that water conservation in the skin is essential for
      systemic fluid and blood pressure homeostasis, and that skin Na+ storage is utilized to
      prevent water loss, even at the expense of increased cardiovascular risk.

      This is a cross-sectional study design with one study visit and a recruitment period of 3
      years. 600 participants will be recruited from the Biobank cohort and tissue Na+ will be
      measured using 23NaMRI. The study will test whether increased Na+ storage in the skin is
      coupled with transepidermal water loss at the expense of high blood pressure levels, and
      examine the association between tissue sodium storage and specific cardiovascular markers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin and muscle Na+ content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in skin and muscle Na+ content (measured with 23NaMRI) between healthy participants and hypertensive patients, overall and according to age, gender and race/ethnicity</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between skin water loss and skin Na+ content</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To show that participants with high transepidermal water loss (measured with Tewameter TM300) have higher skin sodium content (measured with 23NaMRI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin water loss in hypertensive participants</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>To show that hypertensive participants have higher transepidermal water loss (measured with Tewameter TM300) and higher skin Na+ content than healthy participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eligible participants from the Biobank cohort at the National Heart Centre, Singapore, will be screened will be recruited for the study over a period of 3 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypertensive</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eligible participants from the Biobank cohort at the National Heart Centre, Singapore, will be screened will be recruited for the study over a period of 3 years</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Urine and Serum samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible participants from the Biobank cohort at the National Heart Centre, Singapore, will
        be screened and estimated 600 subjects (healthy controls and hypertensive patients) will be
        recruited for the study over a period of 3 years. No ethnic group or gender is targeted for
        or excluded from this reasearch.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Participants from the Biobank (Molecular and Imaging Studies of Cardiovascular Health
             and Disease) cohort in Singapore, who agreed to be contacted for further studies

          2. Male and female patients older than 21 years

          3. Willingness to participate and ability to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with exclusion criteria for the MRI, such as:

               1. implanted devices (surgical clips, heart pacemakers or defibrillators, cochlear
                  implants)

               2. iron-based tattoos

               3. any other pieces of metal or devices that are not MR-Safe anywhere in the body

               4. patients who exhibit noticeable anxiety and/or claustrophobia into the MRI
                  scanner

          2. Pregnant women

          3. Diagnosis of heart failure NYHA classes III and IV

          4. Impaired renal function with eGFR&lt;45 ml/min or proteinuria &gt; 0.5 g/24h

          5. Liver disease with cirrhosis (Child-Pugh class C) or hypoalbuminemia

          6. Peripheral oedema as assessed by the investigator

          7. Active cancer

          8. Patients who have received an organ or bone marrow transplant

          9. Patients who have had major surgery in the past 3 months

         10. Patients who have severe comorbid conditions likely to compromise survival or study
             participation

         11. Unwillingness or other inability to cooperate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adriana Marton, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6516 7666</phone>
    <email>adriana.marton@duke-nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>TzyTiing Lim, BSC</last_name>
    <email>tzytiing.lim@duke-nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart Centre Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169609</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katherina Oh</last_name>
      <email>katherina.oh@nhcs.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Calvin Chin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke-NUS Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169857</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kopp C, Linz P, Dahlmann A, Hammon M, Jantsch J, Müller DN, Schmieder RE, Cavallaro A, Eckardt KU, Uder M, Luft FC, Titze J. 23Na magnetic resonance imaging-determined tissue sodium in healthy subjects and hypertensive patients. Hypertension. 2013 Mar;61(3):635-40. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.111.00566. Epub 2013 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23339169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Titze J. Sodium balance is not just a renal affair. Curr Opin Nephrol Hypertens. 2014 Mar;23(2):101-5. doi: 10.1097/01.mnh.0000441151.55320.c3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24401786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider MP, Raff U, Kopp C, Scheppach JB, Toncar S, Wanner C, Schlieper G, Saritas T, Floege J, Schmid M, Birukov A, Dahlmann A, Linz P, Janka R, Uder M, Schmieder RE, Titze JM, Eckardt KU. Skin Sodium Concentration Correlates with Left Ventricular Hypertrophy in CKD. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2017 Jun;28(6):1867-1876. doi: 10.1681/ASN.2016060662. Epub 2017 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28154199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Titze J. Estimating salt intake in humans: not so easy! Am J Clin Nutr. 2017 Jun;105(6):1253-1254. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.117.158147. Epub 2017 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28515066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rakova N, Kitada K, Lerchl K, Dahlmann A, Birukov A, Daub S, Kopp C, Pedchenko T, Zhang Y, Beck L, Johannes B, Marton A, Müller DN, Rauh M, Luft FC, Titze J. Increased salt consumption induces body water conservation and decreases fluid intake. J Clin Invest. 2017 May 1;127(5):1932-1943. doi: 10.1172/JCI88530. Epub 2017 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28414302</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Duke-NUS Graduate Medical School</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jens Titze</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

