<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04318548</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>205419</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-003722-16</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04318548</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess the Immunogenicity and Safety of GSK's Meningococcal Group B Vaccine When Administered Concomitantly With GSK's Meningococcal MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine in Healthy Subjects of 16-18 Years of Age</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIIB, Randomized, Observer-blind, Multicenter Study to Assess the Safety and Immunogenicity of GSK's Meningococcal Group B Vaccine When Administered Concomitantly With GSK's Meningococcal MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine to Healthy Subjects of 16-18 Years of Age</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the immunogenicity, safety and tolerability of
      rMenB+OMV NZ and MenACWY vaccines when concomitantly administered to healthy subjects 16-18
      years of age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      As per the recommendation from Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (CBER) the study
      has been amended to include a new &quot;agar-overlay&quot; serum bactericidal assay using human serum
      complement (hSBA). Additional changes include validation of the MenB manual to measure
      immunogenicity of the meningococcal group B vaccine, a modification in the definition of
      4-fold increase in post-vaccination hSBA titer definition when the pre-vaccination titer is
      below the limit of detection, and a modification in the population set to be used for safety
      analysis wherein the exposed set is to be used for all safety analyses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 4, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 4, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 4, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Observer-blinded study. Recipients &amp; study evaluators will be unaware of vaccine administered.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with solicited local adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 7 days (including day of vaccination) after each vaccination (Administered on day 1, day 61 and day 91)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation subject, temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not considered related to the medicinal product. Solicited local adverse events assessed are injection site pain, erythema, swelling, induration. Any erythema, swelling and swelling is defined as a symptom with a surface diameter equal or greater than 25 millimeter.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with solicited systemic adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 7 days (including day of vaccination)after each vaccination (Administered on day 1, day 61 and day 91)</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited systemic adverse events assessed are (i.e., fever [temperature ≥ 38.0°C/100.4°F], nausea, fatigue, myalgia, arthralgia, headache).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with any unsolicited adverse events, Serious Adverse Events (SAEs), AEs leading to withdrawal and medically attended AEs .</measure>
    <time_frame>During the 30 days (including day of vaccination)after each vaccination (Administered at Day 1, Day 61 and Day 91)</time_frame>
    <description>Unsolicited adverse events are defined as any AE reported in addition to those solicited during the clinical study. Also, any 'solicited' symptom with onset outside the specified period of follow-up for solicited symptoms are reported as an unsolicited adverse event. SAEs are any untoward medical occurrence that result in death, are life-threatening, require hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, result in disability/incapacity and is a congenital anomaly/birth defect in the offspring of a study subject. Medically attended AEs are symptoms or illnesses requiring hospitalization, or emergency room visit, or visit to/by a health care provider.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with any SAEs, AEs leading to withdrawal and medically attended AEs.</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period (Day 1 to Day 451).</time_frame>
    <description>Serious adverse events, AEs leading to withdrawal and medically attended AEs throughout the study period are assessed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with adverse events of special interest (AESI).</measure>
    <time_frame>Throughout the study period (Day 1- Day 451).</time_frame>
    <description>AESIs are predefined (serious or non-serious) adverse events of scientific and medical concern specific to the product or program, for which ongoing monitoring and rapid communication by the investigator to the sponsor can be appropriate, because such an event might warrant further investigation in order to characterize and understand it.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Human Serum Bactericidal Assay Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup B strains after the second vaccination with rMenB+OMV NZ</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the second vaccination with rMenB+OMV NZ in MenB+MenACWY and MenB groups (i.e. at Day 91).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune responses to rMenB+OMV NZ given with or without MenACWY, as measured by serum bactericidal assay using human complement (hSBA), are expressed as Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) against N. meningitidis serogroup B indicator strains (M14459, 96217, NZ98/254 and M07-0241084).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA GMTs against each of the N. meningitidis serogroups A, C, W and Y after vaccination with MenACWY</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the vaccination with MenACWY in MenACWY and MenB+MenACWY groups (i.e. at Day 31).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune responses to MenACWY given with or without rMenB+OMV NZ, as measured by serum bactericidal assay using human complement (hSBA) are expressed as Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) against each of the 4 serogroups A, C, W and Y</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA Geometric Mean Concentrations (GMCs) measured by ELISA against each of the N. meningitidis serogroups after MenACWY vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the vaccination of MenACWY in MenACWY and MenB+MenACWY groups (i.e. at Day 31).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to MenACWY given with or without rMenB+OMV NZ, as measured by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA) GMCs against each of the serogroups A, C, W and Y.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hSBA GMTs against each of the serogroup B strains in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after first rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after first vaccination with rMenB+OMV NZ (i.e. at Day 31).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ given with or without MenACWY, as measured by bactericidal activity against N. meningitidis serogroup B indicator strains (M14459, 96217, NZ98/254 and M07-0241084) and expressed in GMTs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean ratios (GMRs) against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup B strains in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the first rMenB+OMV NZ dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after first rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination (i.e.at Day 31) compared to the baseline (Day 1).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ given with or without MenACWY as measured by bactericidal activity against N. meningitidis serogroup B indicator strains (M14459, 96217, NZ98/254 and M07-0241084) in terms of GMRs at one month after the first rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination compared to the baseline at Day 1/Month 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean ratios (GMRs) against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup B strains in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the second rMenB+OMV NZ dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the second rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination (i.e. at Day 91) compared to the baseline (Day 1)</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ given with or without MenACWY, as measured by bactericidal activity against N. meningitidis serogroup B indicator strains (M14459, 96217, NZ98/254 and M07-0241084) in terms of GMRs at one month after the second rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination compared to the baseline at Day 1/Month 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for each of the serogroup B test strains in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the first rMenB+OMV NZ dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>At one month after the first rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination (i.e. Day 31).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ vaccine is evaluated by measuring bactericidal activity in terms of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ LLOQ against N. meningitidis serogroup B test strains</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for each of the serogroup B test strains in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the second rMenB+OMV NZ dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the second rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination (i.e. at Day 91).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ vaccine is evaluated by measuring bactericidal activity in terms of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ LLOQ against N. meningitidis serogroup B test strains.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with 4-fold increase in hSBA titers relative to baseline in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the first rMenB+OMV NZ dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the first rMenB+OMV NZ vaccination (i.e at Day 31) relative to baseline (i.e. Day 1).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ vaccine is evaluated by measuring bactericidal activity against each of N. meningitidis serogroup B test strains in terms of the Four-fold increase defined as: - For a pre-vaccination titer &lt; limit of detection (LOD), a post-vaccination titer of ≥ 4-fold the LOD or ≥ LLOQ, whichever is greater, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥LOD but &lt;LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the LLOQ, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥ LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the pre-vaccination titer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with 4-fold increase in hSBA titers relative to baseline in both MenB+MenACWY and MenB Groups after the second rMenB+OMV NZ dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after the second rMenB+OMV vaccination (i.e at Day 91) relative to baseline (i.e. Day 1).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to rMenB+OMV NZ vaccine is evaluated by measuring bactericidal activity against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup B test strains in terms of the Four-fold increase defined as: - For a pre-vaccination titer &lt; limit of detection (LOD), a post-vaccination titer of ≥ 4-fold the LOD or ≥ LLOQ, whichever is greater, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥LOD but &lt;LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the LLOQ, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥ LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the pre-vaccination titer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for each of the serogroup A, C, W and Y in both MenB+MenACWY and MenACWY Groups after MenACWY vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>At one month after the MenACWY vaccination (i.e. Day 31).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to MenACWY vaccines is expressed in terms of percentage of subjects with hSBA titers ≥ lower limit of quantitation (LLOQ) for each of the serogroup A, C, W and Y</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric mean ratios (GMRs) against each of the N. meningitidis serogroup A, C, W and Y in both MenB+MenACWY and MenACWY Groups after MenACWY vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after MenACWY vaccination (i.e.at Day 31) compared to the baseline (Day 1).</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response to MenACWY given with or without rMenB+OMV NZ as measured by bactericidal activity against the four serogroups A, C, W and Y in terms of GMRs at one month after MenACWY vaccination compared to the baseline at Day 1/Month 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with 4-fold increase in hSBA titers relative to baseline in both MenB+MenACWY and MenACWY Groups after MenACWY vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 month after MenACWY vaccination (i.e at Day 31) relative to baseline (i.e. Day 1).</time_frame>
    <description>The immune response to MenACWY vaccine is evaluated by measuring for the four serogroups A, C, W and Y, the Four-fold increase defined as: - For a pre-vaccination titer &lt; limit of detection (LOD), a post-vaccination titer of ≥ 4-fold the LOD or ≥ LLOQ, whichever is greater, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥LOD but &lt;LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the LLOQ, - For a pre-vaccination titer ≥ LLOQ, a post vaccination titer of at least 4-fold the pre-vaccination titer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">945</enrollment>
  <condition>Infections, Meningococcal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MenB+MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 1 dose rMenB+OMV NZ given concomitantly with MenACWY at Day 1, 1 dose of rMenB+OMV NZ at Day 61 and 1 dose of placebo at Day 91.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MenB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 1 dose of rMenB+OMV NZ and placebo concomitantly at Day 1, 1 dose of rMenB+OMV NZ at Day 61 and 1 dose of MenACWY at Day 91.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 1 dose of MenACWY and placebo concomitantly at Day 1, 1 dose of rMenB+OMV NZ each at Day 61 and at Day 91.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meningococcal Group B Vaccine (GSK3536829A) (rMenB+OMV NZ)</intervention_name>
    <description>rMenB+OMV will be administered intramuscularly as 1 dose each at day 1 and 61 to subjects in MenB+MenACWY group and MenB group and as 1 dose at day 91 to subjects in MenACWY group, to the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB+MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bexsero</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meningococcal MenACWY Conjugate Vaccine (GSK3536820A) (MenA lyo + MenCWY liquid)</intervention_name>
    <description>MenACWY will be administered intramuscularly as 1 dose at day 1 to subjects in MenB+MenACWY group, 1 dose at day 91 for MenB group and as 1 dose at day 1 to subjects in MenACWY group, to the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB+MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Menveo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will be administered intramuscularly as 1 dose at day 91 to subjects in MenB+MenACWY group, 1 dose at day 1 to subjects in MenB group and MenACWY group, to the deltoid region of the non-dominant arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MenB+MenACWY Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NaCl, saline solution</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will comply with the
             requirements of the protocol or/and subjects' parent(s)/Legally Acceptable
             Representative(s) [LAR(s)] who, in the opinion of the investigator, can and will
             comply, with the requirements of the protocol.

          -  Previous vaccination with 1 dose of quadrivalent meningococcal conjugate vaccine
             (MenACWY, Menveo or Menactra) at least 4 years prior to informed consent and assent as
             applicable.

          -  Written or /witnessed/thumb printed informed consent obtained from the
             subject/parent(s)/LAR(s) of the subject prior to performance of any study specific
             procedure.

          -  Written informed assent obtained from the subject (if applicable) along with informed
             consent from the subject's parent(s)/LAR(s) prior to performing any study specific
             procedure.

          -  A male or female between, and including, 16 and 18 years of age at the time of the
             first vaccination.

          -  Healthy subjects as established by medical history and clinical examination before
             entering into the study.

          -  Female subjects of non-childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study.
             Non-childbearing potential is defined as pre-menarche, current bilateral tubal
             ligation or occlusion, hysterectomy, bilateral ovariectomy or post-menopause.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential may be enrolled in the study, if the
             subject:

               -  has practiced adequate contraception for 30 days prior to vaccination, and

               -  has a negative pregnancy test on the day of vaccination, and

               -  has agreed to continue adequate contraception during the entire treatment period
                  and for 2 months after completion of the vaccination series.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Medical conditions

          -  Progressive, unstable or uncontrolled clinical conditions.

          -  Clinical conditions representing a contraindication to intramuscular vaccination and
             blood draws.

          -  Abnormal function of the immune system resulting from:

               -  Clinical conditions.

               -  Systemic administration of corticosteroids (PO/IV/IM) for more than 14
                  consecutive days within 90 days prior to study vaccination. This will mean
                  prednisone ≥ 20 mg/day (for adult subjects) or ≥ 0.5 mg/kg/day or 20 mg/day
                  whichever is the maximum dose for paediatric subjects, or equivalent. Inhaled and
                  topical steroids are allowed.

               -  Administration of antineoplastic or immunomodulating agents or radiotherapy
                  within 90 days prior to informed consent.

          -  Are obese at screening (obesity is defined as a BMI of ≥ 95th percentile for age and
             gender).

          -  Any other clinical condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, might pose
             additional risk to the subject due to participation in the study.

          -  History of any reaction or hypersensitivity likely to be exacerbated by any component
             of the vaccines.

          -  History of any reaction or hypersensitivity likely to be exacerbated by any medicinal
             products or medical equipment whose use is foreseen in this study.

          -  Current or previous, confirmed or suspected disease caused by N. meningitidis.

          -  Known contact to an individual with any laboratory-confirmed N. meningitidis infection
             within 60 days, prior to enrolment.

          -  History of neuroinflammatory or autoimmune condition.

          -  Recurrent history or un-controlled neurological disorders or seizures.

        Prior/Concomitant therapy

          -  Use of any investigational or non-registered product other than the study vaccine(s)
             during the period starting 30 days before the informed consent or planned use during
             the study period.

          -  Administration of immunoglobulins and/or any blood products or plasma derivatives
             during the period starting 180 days before the informed consent or planned
             administration during the study period.

          -  Previous vaccination with any group B meningococcal vaccine at any time prior to
             informed consent and assent as applicable.

          -  Previous vaccination with 2 doses of quadrivalent meningococcal conjugate vaccine
             (MenACWY, Menveo or Menactra).

        Prior/Concurrent clinical study experience

        • Subject concurrently participating in another clinical study, at any time during the
        study period, in which the subject has been or will be exposed to an investigational or a
        non-investigational vaccine/product, will not be enrolled.

        Other exclusions

          -  Child in care.

          -  Pregnant or lactating female.

          -  Female planning to become pregnant or planning to discontinue contraceptive
             precautions.

          -  Any study personnel or immediate dependants, family, or household member.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 20 89904466</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Meningitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Invasive meningococcal disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Bexsero</keyword>
  <keyword>Menveo</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Meningococcal Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD for this study will be made available via the Clinical Study Data Request site.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>IPD will be made available within 6 months of publishing the results of the primary endpoints of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access is provided after a research proposal is submitted and has received approval from the Independent Review Panel and after a Data Sharing Agreement is in place. Access is provided for an initial period of 12 months but an extension can be granted, when justified, for up to another 12 months.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

