<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04317352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UE-CHU 003-2020</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04317352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multivisceral Resection in Distal Pancreatectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ERPANDIS-MRV</acronym>
  <official_title>Distal Pancreatectomy With Multivisceral Resection: A Multicentric Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de Extremadura</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de Extremadura</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the study is to evaluate the characteristics of the patients and the results
      of morbidity and mortality after distal pancreatectomy isolated or accompanied by
      multivisceral resection including cholecystectomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Multicenter study that includes patients operated on for distal pancreatectomy between
      January 2009 to December 2019 for primary pancreatic tumors. Both open or laparoscopic
      approaches are considered in the study. The objective is to evaluate the characteristics of
      the patients and the results of morbidity and mortality after distal pancreatectomy isolated
      or accompanied by multivisceral resection including cholecystectomy. For this, demographic
      data, variables related to the tumor, surgical intervention and postoperative evolution were
      collected.

      Definitions:

      Diagnosis was based mainly on computed tomography (CT scan), Magnetic Resonance (MRI) and
      endoscopic ultrasonography (USE) plus biopsy. Surgical technique includes open and
      laparoscopic approach with or without spleen preservation. Complications were assessed at 90
      days using the Clavien - Dindo classification, and those defined as Clavien - Dindo grade
      IIIA or higher were considered major. For the recording of complications, the medical and
      nursing notes of the electronic or histories of each patient were consulted. For the specific
      complications of pancreatic surgery, the definitions of the International Study Group on
      Pancreatic Surgery (ISGPS) of delayed gastric emptying (21), post-pancreatic hemorrhage (22)
      and pancreatic fistula were used. The resection margins of the surgical specimen were
      categorized according to the definitions of the Royal College of Pathologists: R0 (margin to
      the tumor ≥ 1mm), R1 (margin to the tumor &lt;1mm) and R2 (macroscopically positive margin)
      (24). Tumors were staged according to the TNM classification 8 º Ed. (TNM). Follow up scheme
      was: 6-month outpatient clinic visit during first five years including tumoral markers and
      CT/MRI. After five years only once a year visit policy was applied.

      Variables The following variables were studied: Epidemiological: age, sex, past medical
      history, medication, Charlson Index and American Society of Anesthesiology (ASA)
      classification; Clinical: symptoms due to mucinous neoplasm (MCN); Serological tests:
      leukocytes, amylase; hemoglobin (gr/dl), bilirubin, creatinin, prothrombin time,
      carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA) and carbohydrate antigen (CA) 19-9; Radiological/diagnostic:
      diagnostic tests performed (CT/MRI/EUS), number, size and location of MCN, vascular
      infiltration (arterial and venous) and preoperative biopsy; Surgical: type of approach
      (open/laparoscopy/conversion), spleen preservation, associated procedures (organs resected),
      type of closure of pancreatic remnant, intraoperative bleeding (ml); postoperative course:
      morbidity and mortality (according to the Clavien-Dindo (CD) classification) (13), pancreatic
      fistula, postoperative hemorrhage and delayed gastric empting, if present, was classified
      according to the International Group Study Pancreatic Surgery (IGSPS) classification (14,15),
      hospital stay and readmissions. The histological data retrieved were TNM: tumor size and
      lymph nodes harvested and R status. Postoperative follow-up (months) including endocrine and
      exocrine insufficiency rate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Any complication in the postoperative period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>If the patient dies in the postoperative period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">435</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Surgical Procedure, Unspecified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multivisceral resection (MRV)</arm_group_label>
    <description>MVR: Multivisceral resection was considered when the exeresis of an organ other than the pancreatic body-tail and / or spleen was performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MVR</intervention_name>
    <description>Multivisceral resection was considered when the exeresis of an organ other than the pancreatic body-tail and / or spleen was performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multivisceral resection (MRV)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing distal pancreatectomy for primary pancreatic tumor at participating
        centers during the period from January 2009 to December 2018
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any distal pancreatectomy (DP) with multivisceral resection (MVR) defining MVR as any
             organ different from distal pancreas or spleen

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Distal Pancreatectomy with celiac trunk resection (Appleby procedure) or portal vein
             resection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José Manuel Ramia, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidad de Extremadura- Facultad de Medicina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badajoz</city>
        <zip>06080</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malinka T, Klein F, Andreou A, Pratschke J, Bahra M. Distal Pancreatectomy Combined with Multivisceral Resection Is Associated with Postoperative Complication Rates and Survival Comparable to Those After Standard Procedures. J Gastrointest Surg. 2018 Sep;22(9):1549-1556. doi: 10.1007/s11605-018-3804-z. Epub 2018 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>29748738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burdelski CM, Reeh M, Bogoevski D, Gebauer F, Tachezy M, Vashist YK, Cataldegirmen G, Yekebas E, Izbicki JR, Bockhorn M. Multivisceral resections in pancreatic cancer: identification of risk factors. World J Surg. 2011 Dec;35(12):2756-63. doi: 10.1007/s00268-011-1263-8.</citation>
    <PMID>21938586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panzeri F, Marchegiani G, Malleo G, Malpaga A, Maggino L, Marchese T, Salvia R, Bassi C, Butturini G. Distal pancreatectomy associated with multivisceral resection: results from a single centre experience. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2017 May;402(3):457-464. doi: 10.1007/s00423-016-1514-0. Epub 2016 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27787606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irani JL, Ashley SW, Brooks DC, Osteen RT, Raut CP, Russell S, Swanson RS, Whang EE, Zinner MJ, Clancy TE. Distal pancreatectomy is not associated with increased perioperative morbidity when performed as part of a multivisceral resection. J Gastrointest Surg. 2008 Dec;12(12):2177-82. doi: 10.1007/s11605-008-0605-9. Epub 2008 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18677539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Song KB, Kwon J, Kim YW, Hwang DW, Lee JH, Hong S, Lee JW, Hwang K, Yoo D, Kim SC. Prognostic value of adjacent organ resection in patients with left-sided pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma following distal pancreatectomy. J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci. 2019 Jun;26(6):227-234. doi: 10.1002/jhbp.627. Epub 2019 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>30980486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nikfarjam M, Sehmbey M, Kimchi ET, Gusani NJ, Shereef S, Avella DM, Staveley-O'Carroll KF. Additional organ resection combined with pancreaticoduodenectomy does not increase postoperative morbidity and mortality. J Gastrointest Surg. 2009 May;13(5):915-21. doi: 10.1007/s11605-009-0801-2. Epub 2009 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19198960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 19, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de Extremadura</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gerardo Blanco-Fernández</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Complications</keyword>
  <keyword>distal pancreatectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Multivisceral</keyword>
  <keyword>resection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study data will be available upon request to the principal investigator via e-mail.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

