<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04316793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-3133</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04316793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Dry Needling When Applied to the Infraspinatus Muscle in People With Chronic Shoulder Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurophysiological, Biomechanical and Clinical Effects of Dry Needling Versus Sham Needling When Applied to the Infraspinatus Muscle in People With Chronic Shoulder Pain: a Randomized Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Sherbrooke</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ordre Professionnel de la Physiothérapie du Québec (OPPQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre de recherche du Centre hospitalier universitaire de Sherbrooke</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Sherbrooke</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Up to 77% of patients with chronic shoulder pain have a trigger point (TrP) in the
      infraspinatus muscle. These TrPs can lead to pain, limitation of activities and reduced
      quality of life. Dry needling (DN) is gaining popularity as a treatment for TrPs in
      physiotherapy. However, its clinical effects remain poorly understood mechanistically and its
      neurophysiological effects little studied.

      The primary objective of this study is to determine the feasibility of a larger scale study.

      The secondary objective of this study is to to explore the immediate neurophysiological,
      biomechanical and clinical effects of DN and sham needling when applied to TrP of the
      infraspinatus muscle in people with chronic non-traumatic shoulder pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methodology

      In this randomized, double-blind, parallel-group trial, twenty adults with chronic
      non-traumatic shoulder pain and with a infraspinatus TrP will be recruited according to
      established criteria. Participants will be randomized into two groups: one group (n = 10)
      receiving a DN in the infraspinatus TrP and another group (n = 10) receiving a sham needling.

      Recruitment strategies

      Recruitment will be done through posters that will be posted on bulletin boards of the
      Faculty of Medicine and Health Sciences of the University of Sherbrooke and in physiotherapy
      clinics in the region. The persons interested will be invited to contact the research
      assistant in charge of the study to verify their eligibility to participate.

      Data collection procedure

      The experimental procedure will take place in a laboratory located at the Research Center on
      Aging in Sherbrooke, Quebec, Canada. Upon arrival, individuals will be greeted by a research
      assistant. Verification of the presence of TrP in the infraspinatus to confirm eligibility to
      participate will be carried out by a physiotherapist with more than 20 years of experience in
      the identification of TrPs and with the application of DN, according to the following
      procedure: Participants will be asked to lie in a decubitus lateral position on a treatment
      table and on the asymptomatic side. The upper arm will be supported on a box placed in front
      of them, so that the muscles can be relaxed, but the arm will be positioned in a and have a
      slight horizontal adduction to slightly stretch the fibers of the infraspinatus muscle.
      Manual palpation with flat fingers and perpendicular to the fibers will be used to identify
      the tight muscle band. Once a tight muscle band has been identified, the physiotherapist will
      search within this band for a contraction node, namely the TrP. Once she had identified this
      TrP with a non-toxic black Sharpie pencil, she will validate with the patient that the
      compression of this TrP reproduces local or referred pain. This pain should correspond to the
      pain patterns known to the infraspinatus according to Simons and Travell, 1999 and reproduce
      the pain known by the patient. This pain should be at least a 1/10 intensity on the visual
      analog scale (VAS). Ineligible participants will receive advices from the physiotherapist as
      well as a prescription for exercises related to their condition and a list of
      physiotherapists they can consult.

      The research assistant will explain the nature of the project to the selected participants,
      he will make sure that the participants have no contraindications to receive DN and/or for
      transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) examination, and he will obtain written informed
      consent. Participants will then complete a questionnaire used to collect baseline medical
      information.

      Intervention (DN and Sham)

      DN will be performed by a certified clinician, experienced with the technique. She will
      explain the purpose of the intervention and she will review the contraindications and
      precautions for DN to ensure that the procedure is safe. The technique used is recommended by
      l'Ordre professionnel de la physiothérapie du Québec (OPPQ). The clinician will insert a
      sterile disposable acupuncture needle, OPTIMED (non-silicone), 40 mm x 0.30 caliber. The
      direction of the needle will be slightly oblique, directly in the TrP and in the direction of
      the muscle fibers. The production of a twitch is expected, gliding and rotation of the needle
      may be performed to produce this effect, if necessary. The needle will be removed after the
      twitch. The same procedure will be used for the sham group, except that the needle will be
      inserted at the subcutaneous level, at the depth of the superficial adipous tissues
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average number of participants recruited per month</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Exclusion rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants excluded from the study due to eligibility criteria (e.g. too narrow, are they clear)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Refusal rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 10 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who refused to participate (e.g. fear of needle, fear of transcranial magnetic stimulation)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after and 24 hours post-treatment evaluation</time_frame>
    <description>Number of loss at follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time of the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after and 24 hours post-treatment evaluation</time_frame>
    <description>Average time needed per participant (testing and intervention)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of the procedure: adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after intervention to 24 hours post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Listing of any adverse effects</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Corticospinal excitability of the infraspinatus</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, immediately after intervention, 24 hours after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Tested with transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) connected to a neuronavigation device, characterized by the active motor threshold and expressed in stimulator maximum power percentage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glenohumeral arthrokinematics</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, immediately after intervention, 24 hours after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Captured images are taken using ultrasound imaging (GE Logiq-e; linear array 5-12MHz) at 0° and 30° of external rotation. Measurements in cm included: 1) subacromial space (position of the humeral head relative to the acromion); 2) anteroposterior position of the humeral head relative to the glenoid.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pressure pain perceived</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, immediately after intervention, 24 hours after the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Obtained using an algometer (directly applied on the TrP; average of three measurements taken at 30 sec. interval), characterized by the threshold of discomfort and expressed in kg.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Trigger Point Pain, Myofascial</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Shoulder Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dry needling (DN)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intramuscular insertion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham needling (SN)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intradermal insertion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dry needling</intervention_name>
    <description>Intramuscular insertion of an OPTIMED 40mm x 0.3mm acupuncture needle in a trigger point of the infraspinatus muscle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dry needling (DN)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham needling (SN)</intervention_name>
    <description>Intradermal insertion of an OPTIMED 40mm x 0.3mm acupuncture needle over the infraspinatus region</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham needling (SN)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Unilateral, chronic non-traumatic shoulder pain (VAS ≥ 2/10; &gt;3 months)

          2. Localized pain in the shoulder region or referred according to the territory of the
             infraspinatus (Travell and Simons, 1999)

          3. Presence of a palpable nodule inside a tight muscle band reproducing the patient's
             pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cancer or metastasis in organs or tissues above the pelvis (&lt; 5 years)

          2. Shoulder capsulitis

          3. Shoulder, thorax or mastectomy surgeries

          4. Shoulder bone fracture (&lt; 6 months)

          5. C4-C5 or C6 radiculopathy

          6. Osteoporosis or excessive atrophy of the infraspinous fossa (infraspinatus &lt;10 mm)

          7. Body mass index (BMI) &gt; 28

        Exclusion (TMS security):

          1. Pregnant woman

          2. Neurological, psychiatric or epilepsy conditions

          3. Implants (e.g. Neurostimulator, pacemaker, cerebral aneurysm clip, screw or plate),
             metallic foreign body in the eye

          4. Head trauma with loss of consciousness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nathaly Gaudreault, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mélanie Morin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Guillaume Léonard, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Recherche sur le Vieillissement</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J1H 4C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bron C, Franssen J, Wensing M, Oostendorp RA. Interrater reliability of palpation of myofascial trigger points in three shoulder muscles. J Man Manip Ther. 2007;15(4):203-15.</citation>
    <PMID>19066669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tough EA, White AR, Richards S, Campbell J. Variability of criteria used to diagnose myofascial trigger point pain syndrome--evidence from a review of the literature. Clin J Pain. 2007 Mar-Apr;23(3):278-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17314589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cagnie B, Barbe T, De Ridder E, Van Oosterwijck J, Cools A, Danneels L. The influence of dry needling of the trapezius muscle on muscle blood flow and oxygenation. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2012 Nov-Dec;35(9):685-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2012.10.005.</citation>
    <PMID>23206963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunning J, Butts R, Mourad F, Young I, Flannagan S, Perreault T. Dry needling: a literature review with implications for clinical practice guidelines. Phys Ther Rev. 2014 Aug;19(4):252-265. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25143704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hidalgo-Lozano A, Fernández-de-las-Peñas C, Alonso-Blanco C, Ge HY, Arendt-Nielsen L, Arroyo-Morales M. Muscle trigger points and pressure pain hyperalgesia in the shoulder muscles in patients with unilateral shoulder impingement: a blinded, controlled study. Exp Brain Res. 2010 May;202(4):915-25. doi: 10.1007/s00221-010-2196-4. Epub 2010 Feb 26.</citation>
    <PMID>20186400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rathbone ATL, Grosman-Rimon L, Kumbhare DA. Interrater Agreement of Manual Palpation for Identification of Myofascial Trigger Points: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Clin J Pain. 2017 Aug;33(8):715-729. doi: 10.1097/AJP.0000000000000459. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28098584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tekin L, Akarsu S, Durmuş O, Cakar E, Dinçer U, Kıralp MZ. The effect of dry needling in the treatment of myofascial pain syndrome: a randomized double-blinded placebo-controlled trial. Clin Rheumatol. 2013 Mar;32(3):309-15. doi: 10.1007/s10067-012-2112-3. Epub 2012 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23138883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arias-Buría JL, Fernández-de-Las-Peñas C, Palacios-Ceña M, Koppenhaver SL, Salom-Moreno J. Exercises and Dry Needling for Subacromial Pain Syndrome: A Randomized Parallel-Group Trial. J Pain. 2017 Jan;18(1):11-18. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2016.08.013. Epub 2016 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27720812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baldry P. The integration of acupuncture within medicine in the UK--the British Medical Acupuncture Society's 25th anniversary. Acupunct Med. 2005 Mar;23(1):2-12.</citation>
    <PMID>15844434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cagnie B, Dewitte V, Coppieters I, Van Oosterwijck J, Cools A, Danneels L. Effect of ischemic compression on trigger points in the neck and shoulder muscles in office workers: a cohort study. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2013 Oct;36(8):482-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2013.07.001. Epub 2013 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23993756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen JT, Chung KC, Hou CR, Kuan TS, Chen SM, Hong CZ. Inhibitory effect of dry needling on the spontaneous electrical activity recorded from myofascial trigger spots of rabbit skeletal muscle. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2001 Oct;80(10):729-35.</citation>
    <PMID>11562554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dorsher PT. Can classical acupuncture points and trigger points be compared in the treatment of pain disorders? Birch's analysis revisited. J Altern Complement Med. 2008 May;14(4):353-9. doi: 10.1089/acm.2007.0810. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18576919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fricton JR, Kroening R, Haley D, Siegert R. Myofascial pain syndrome of the head and neck: a review of clinical characteristics of 164 patients. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol. 1985 Dec;60(6):615-23.</citation>
    <PMID>3865133</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong CZ. Lidocaine injection versus dry needling to myofascial trigger point. The importance of the local twitch response. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 1994 Jul-Aug;73(4):256-63.</citation>
    <PMID>8043247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langevin HM, Churchill DL, Cipolla MJ. Mechanical signaling through connective tissue: a mechanism for the therapeutic effect of acupuncture. FASEB J. 2001 Oct;15(12):2275-82.</citation>
    <PMID>11641255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Langevin HM, Bouffard NA, Badger GJ, Churchill DL, Howe AK. Subcutaneous tissue fibroblast cytoskeletal remodeling induced by acupuncture: evidence for a mechanotransduction-based mechanism. J Cell Physiol. 2006 Jun;207(3):767-74.</citation>
    <PMID>16511830</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lucas KR, Rich PA, Polus BI. Muscle activation patterns in the scapular positioning muscles during loaded scapular plane elevation: the effects of Latent Myofascial Trigger Points. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 2010 Oct;25(8):765-70. doi: 10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2010.05.006. Epub 2010 Jul 27.</citation>
    <PMID>20667633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lund I, Lundeberg T. Are minimal, superficial or sham acupuncture procedures acceptable as inert placebo controls? Acupunct Med. 2006 Mar;24(1):13-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16618044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah JP, Gilliams EA. Uncovering the biochemical milieu of myofascial trigger points using in vivo microdialysis: an application of muscle pain concepts to myofascial pain syndrome. J Bodyw Mov Ther. 2008 Oct;12(4):371-384. doi: 10.1016/j.jbmt.2008.06.006. Epub 2008 Aug 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19083696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah JP, Phillips TM, Danoff JV, Gerber LH. An in vivo microanalytical technique for measuring the local biochemical milieu of human skeletal muscle. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2005 Nov;99(5):1977-84. Epub 2005 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>16037403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradnam L, Shanahan EM, Hendy K, Reed A, Skipworth T, Visser A, Lennon S. Afferent inhibition and cortical silent periods in shoulder primary motor cortex and effect of a suprascapular nerve block in people experiencing chronic shoulder pain. Clin Neurophysiol. 2016 Jan;127(1):769-778. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2015.03.012. Epub 2015 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>25900020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradnam LV, Stinear CM, Lewis GN, Byblow WD. Task-dependent modulation of inputs to proximal upper limb following transcranial direct current stimulation of primary motor cortex. J Neurophysiol. 2010 May;103(5):2382-9. doi: 10.1152/jn.01046.2009. Epub 2010 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20220073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngomo S, Mercier C, Roy JS. Cortical mapping of the infraspinatus muscle in healthy individuals. BMC Neurosci. 2013 Apr 24;14:52. doi: 10.1186/1471-2202-14-52.</citation>
    <PMID>23617624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts LV, Stinear CM, Lewis GN, Byblow WD. Task-dependent modulation of propriospinal inputs to human shoulder. J Neurophysiol. 2008 Oct;100(4):2109-14. doi: 10.1152/jn.90786.2008. Epub 2008 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>18715892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alisauskiene M, Truffert A, Vaiciene N, Magistris MR. Transcranial magnetic stimulation in clinical practice. Medicina (Kaunas). 2005;41(10):813-24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16272828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker AT, Jalinous R, Freeston IL. Non-invasive magnetic stimulation of human motor cortex. Lancet. 1985 May 11;1(8437):1106-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2860322</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berth A, Pap G, Neuman W, Awiszus F. Central neuromuscular dysfunction of the deltoid muscle in patients with chronic rotator cuff tears. J Orthop Traumatol. 2009 Sep;10(3):135-41. doi: 10.1007/s10195-009-0061-7. Epub 2009 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>19690944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown SH, Brookham RL, Dickerson CR. High-pass filtering surface EMG in an attempt to better represent the signals detected at the intramuscular level. Muscle Nerve. 2010 Feb;41(2):234-9. doi: 10.1002/mus.21470.</citation>
    <PMID>19722252</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cowey A. The Ferrier Lecture 2004 what can transcranial magnetic stimulation tell us about how the brain works? Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2005 Jun 29;360(1458):1185-205.</citation>
    <PMID>16147516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobayashi M, Pascual-Leone A. Transcranial magnetic stimulation in neurology. Lancet Neurol. 2003 Mar;2(3):145-56. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12849236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moseley GL, Flor H. Targeting cortical representations in the treatment of chronic pain: a review. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2012 Jul-Aug;26(6):646-52. doi: 10.1177/1545968311433209. Epub 2012 Feb 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22331213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngomo S, Leonard G, Moffet H, Mercier C. Comparison of transcranial magnetic stimulation measures obtained at rest and under active conditions and their reliability. J Neurosci Methods. 2012 Mar 30;205(1):65-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jneumeth.2011.12.012. Epub 2011 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22227444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngomo S, Mercier C, Bouyer LJ, Savoie A, Roy JS. Alterations in central motor representation increase over time in individuals with rotator cuff tendinopathy. Clin Neurophysiol. 2015 Feb;126(2):365-71. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2014.05.035. Epub 2014 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25043198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romero JR, Ramirez DM, Aglio LS, Gugino LD. Brain mapping using transcranial magnetic stimulation. Neurosurg Clin N Am. 2011 Apr;22(2):141-52, vii. doi: 10.1016/j.nec.2010.11.002. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21435567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rossini PM, Rossi S. Transcranial magnetic stimulation: diagnostic, therapeutic, and research potential. Neurology. 2007 Feb 13;68(7):484-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17296913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nathaly Gaudreault</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Full Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dry needling</keyword>
  <keyword>Infraspinatus</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurophysiological effects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

