<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04311619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>54574</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04311619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does rTMS Induce Synaptic Plasticity?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) Induce Synaptic Plasticity?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Davidzon, Guido, M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to utilize the radioactive positron emission tomography (PET)
      tracer [11C]UCB-J to investigate the effect of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation
      (rTMS) on synaptic plasticity. UCB-J has been validated as a marker for synaptic density
      (Finnema 2016, Nabulsi 2016). We will use this tracer to examine if rTMS leads to changes in
      synaptic plasticity, specifically changes in synaptic density, in individuals receiving rTMS
      for MDD (Holmes 2019, Chervyakov 2015). If rTMS is proven effective for increasing synaptic
      plasticity, there is a significant potential of a new applicable treatment for a variety of
      diseases that affect brain physiology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Synaptic Density Quantified by Regional Binding Potential (BP_ND)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed during PET scans before and after rTMS therapy (90 minutes per scan)</time_frame>
    <description>Synaptic density change (Baseline minus Post Treatment) will be quantified between treatment responsive patients and treatment unresponsive patients with the regional binding potential (BP_ND), a measure of [11C]UCB-J binding. BP_ND will be derived by using the simplified reference tissue model (Wu &amp; Carson, 2002) and the centrum semiovale as the reference region. This method has been recently utilized by other investigators in neuropsychiatric samples (Chen et al., 2018). Both exploratory voxel-wise BP_ND and region of interest (ROI) BP_ND will be compared across groups. ROIs include the striatum, dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, hippocampus, and superior temporal cortex.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Major Depression Disorder Participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will undergo positron emission tomography-magnetic resonance (PET-MR) imaging using the [11C]UCB-J radiotracer before and after Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[11C]UCB-J radiotracer</intervention_name>
    <description>I.V. bolus administration of up to 15 mCi (equivalent to 0.3 rems) in the antecubital vein per injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Major Depression Disorder Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET-MR</intervention_name>
    <description>Positron emission tomography and magnetic resonance imaging, with a scan duration of up to 120 minutes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Major Depression Disorder Participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-70 years in age

          -  U.S. Veteran

          -  Diagnosis of MDD

          -  On a stable medication regimen for at least two weeks prior to testing

          -  Stable social environment and housing to enable regular attendance at clinic visits

          -  Ability to undergo cognitive testing, clinical assessments, and PET/MR scans

          -  Stable medical health

          -  Will undergo rTMS treatment for MDD at the VA Palo Alto

          -  Able to complete a PET-MR scan without the use of sedation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active substance use within three months of testing

          -  IQ &lt; 70

          -  Major medical neurological illness or significant head trauma

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Contraindication to MR scanning, including magnetic-resonance incompatible metal or
             hardware including pacemakers, cochlear implants, and bullets near a critical organ

          -  Weight &gt; 350 lbs or a large body habitus that MR scanner cannot accommodate

          -  History of or current claustrophobia

          -  Inability to comply with basic study requirements such as following directions and
             punctuality

          -  Acute or unstable chronic medical illness that would affect participation or
             compliance with study procedures, e.g. unstable angina

          -  Unstable psychiatric symptoms that precludes consistent participation in the study,
             e.g. active current suicidal intent or plan, severe psychosis

          -  Inability to undergo PET/MR scan, e.g. claustrophobia, presence of ferromagnetic
             objects in subject's body
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jong H Yoon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Coordinator</last_name>
    <phone>650-849-0552</phone>
    <email>stevelai@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Palo Alto Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finnema SJ, Nabulsi NB, Mercier J, Lin SF, Chen MK, Matuskey D, Gallezot JD, Henry S, Hannestad J, Huang Y, Carson RE. Kinetic evaluation and test-retest reproducibility of [(11)C]UCB-J, a novel radioligand for positron emission tomography imaging of synaptic vesicle glycoprotein 2A in humans. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2018 Nov;38(11):2041-2052. doi: 10.1177/0271678X17724947. Epub 2017 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>28792356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen MK, Mecca AP, Naganawa M, Finnema SJ, Toyonaga T, Lin SF, Najafzadeh S, Ropchan J, Lu Y, McDonald JW, Michalak HR, Nabulsi NB, Arnsten AFT, Huang Y, Carson RE, van Dyck CH. Assessing Synaptic Density in Alzheimer Disease With Synaptic Vesicle Glycoprotein 2A Positron Emission Tomographic Imaging. JAMA Neurol. 2018 Oct 1;75(10):1215-1224. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2018.1836.</citation>
    <PMID>30014145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu Y, Carson RE. Noise reduction in the simplified reference tissue model for neuroreceptor functional imaging. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2002 Dec;22(12):1440-52.</citation>
    <PMID>12468889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chervyakov AV, Chernyavsky AY, Sinitsyn DO, Piradov MA. Possible Mechanisms Underlying the Therapeutic Effects of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation. Front Hum Neurosci. 2015 Jun 16;9:303. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2015.00303. eCollection 2015. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26136672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holmes SE, Scheinost D, Finnema SJ, Naganawa M, Davis MT, DellaGioia N, Nabulsi N, Matuskey D, Angarita GA, Pietrzak RH, Duman RS, Sanacora G, Krystal JH, Carson RE, Esterlis I. Lower synaptic density is associated with depression severity and network alterations. Nat Commun. 2019 Apr 4;10(1):1529. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-09562-7.</citation>
    <PMID>30948709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jong Yoon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No current plan to share data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

