<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04312646</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ultrasound in thyroid nodules</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04312646</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Elastography in Thyroid Nodules</brief_title>
  <official_title>Added Value of Ultrasound Elasatography in Characterization of Thyroid Nodules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Thyroid nodules are a common finding in the general population,however, they are mostly
      unpalpable and usually discovered either during neck ultrasound (US) examination or by
      pathological examination at autopsy. They are found in about 8% of adults. Most thyroid
      nodules ''incidentalomas&quot; are benign, however 7% may be malignant. Early detection of thyroid
      cancer helps in early treatment and better survival US is an accurate method for detection of
      thyroid nodules; however, US has a low accuracy in differentiating between benign from
      malignant thyroid nodules . US could suggest a malignancy likelihood criteria of a thyroid
      nodule, such as hypoechogenicity, increased intranodular vascularity, irregular margins,
      microcalcifications, absent halo, and a taller-than-wide shape measured in the transverse
      dimension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      US elastography has been used to detect the nature of thyroid nodules, by measuring the
      tissue stiffness non invasively. It depends on tissue deformation strain that is caused by
      external compression.it is complementary to gray scale findings particularly in nodules with
      indeterminate US findings, also US elastography could be used to guide the follow up of
      leisons diagnosed as benign at ( FNA) fine needle aspiration .

      There are two main thyroid elastography methods in clinical practice: strain elastography
      (SE) and shear-wave elastography (SWE) .

      Elastography methods can be classified into different variants based on the excitation method
      (external force, internal force, and acoustic radiation force [ARF]), and how stiffness is
      expressed . (A) strain elastography . SE reqires mechanical stress, which results in axial
      displacement of the tissue Tissue deformation from the stress is measured and visualized on a
      screen. The main limitations of SE are operator dependence for the angle, strength, and
      duration of compression.

      (B) shear wave elastography . The acoustic pulses from the probe stimulate the target tissue,
      creating a shear wave (SW) traveling perpendicular to the conventional US waves. SWs are the
      transverse components of particle displacement that are rapidly attenuated by the tissue (1-
      10 m/sec). This transverse component is tracked and measured as a numerical value
      corresponding to the shear-wave speed (SWS).This speed is closely related to the Young
      modulus formula, in which tissue elasticity can be assessed from the SW propagation.

      US elastography is completely painless for the patient, and only requires a few extra
      minutes, with no separate patient preparation. US elastography has the potential to
      distinguish benign from malignant TNs, offering non-invasive complementary information to
      conventional US.

      It may be particularly useful in patients who have nondiagnostic or indeterminate FNA
      cytology results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the role of Elastography in differentiation between benign and malignant thyroid nodules</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>by its additional information over the classic gray scale and color Doppler ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroid Nodule</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>patients with thyroid nodules</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Elastography .</intervention_name>
    <description>Performance of US, elastography</description>
    <arm_group_label>patients with thyroid nodules</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients with solitary thyroid nodule
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  solitary nodule on clinical or ultrasound examination

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients received any medical treatment or chemo or radiotherapy.

          -  Patients underwent fine needle aspiration cytology or biopsy

          -  Nodules with calcification and cystic changes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <reference>
    <citation>Torre LA, Bray F, Siegel RL, Ferlay J, Lortet-Tieulent J, Jemal A. Global cancer statistics, 2012. CA Cancer J Clin. 2015 Mar;65(2):87-108. doi: 10.3322/caac.21262. Epub 2015 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>25651787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Omima mahran hussein abd el wadod</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Nodule</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

