<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04311073</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-08-FB-0189</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04311073</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prophylactic Tranexamic Acid During Minimally Invasive Myomectomies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Control Trial Investigating for Prophylactic Tranexamic Acid Use at Time of Minimally Invasive Myomectomies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eastern Virginia Medical School</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Eastern Virginia Medical School</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Double-blinded randomized placebo-controlled trial based at Eastern Virginia
      Medical School. Subjects who are identified in clinic having menorrhagia or abnormal Uterine
      bleeding (AUB) due to uterine fibroids and meet inclusion criteria based on the ultrasound
      (US) or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), aged 18-45 undergoing laparoscopic or Robotic
      assisted myomectomies. A total of 50 women in each arm of the study with symptomatic
      fibroids. Patients will be randomized to receive a single IV bolus injection of TXA 30mg/kg
      in 50ml of normal saline (intervention group) versus an IV bolus injection of normal saline
      of equivalent volume (placebo group) 15 minutes prior to initial surgical incision.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Double-blinded randomized placebo-controlled trial based at Eastern Virginia
      Medical School. Subjects who are identified in clinic having menorrhagia or abnormal Uterine
      bleeding (AUB) due to uterine fibroids and meet inclusion criteria based on the ultrasound
      (US) or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI), aged 18-45 undergoing laparoscopic or Robotic
      assisted myomectomies. These subjects will be then approached for consent during their pre-op
      visit 1-2 weeks prior to their surgery. The setting for consent will be in a patient
      consultation room. A total of 50 women in each arm of the study with symptomatic fibroids
      meeting any of the following criteria will be included in the study:

        1. At least one fibroid greater than or equal to 6 cm

        2. Any intramural or broad ligament fibroid greater than or equal to 4 cm

        3. At least 3 total fibroids based on preoperative imaging. Randomization will be performed
           using an automated randomization website Patients will be randomized to receive a single
           IV bolus injection of TXA 30mg/kg in 50ml of normal saline (intervention group) versus
           an IV bolus injection of normal saline of equivalent volume (placebo group) 15 minutes
           prior to initial surgical incision. This dosage will not be adjusted for patients with
           renal insufficiency as they will be excluded from the study. Preparation of the
           medications will be performed by anesthesia who have both medication and normal saline
           available to them on short notice. No prior preparation by pharmacy will be required.
           Tranexamic acid is readily available in a 10 ml vial, which does not need a pharmacist
           to prepare for administration. The vial is mixed with 50 ml of saline in the operating
           room. This is the same process that occurs outside of any study with any medication that
           is administered intra-operatively. This will in no way impact the patient's safety
           during the surgery, especially since it is administered 15 minutes prior to the start of
           the procedure.

      Both surgeon and patient will be blinded to the treatment arm. This dosage has been used
      previously in both obstetric and gynecological procedures and is the same dose recommended by
      the WHO for preventing post-partum hemorrhage The surgery itself will be scheduled at either
      Sentara Norfolk General, Sentara Leigh hospital, and Sentara Princess Anne hospital. These
      are the three sites that the investigators already perform Minimally invasive myomectomies.

      An envelope will be given to the anesthesiologist prior to the procedure informing whether
      they are to receives TXA or the placebo. Blood loss will be estimated by the surgeon
      performing the procedure. Hemoglobin and hematocrit will be obtained 24 hours post procedure.
      The patient will be assessed for reported side effects from the medication given will be
      assessed by a questionnaire that will be given at their post-op appointment at the 2 week and
      6-week mark. During these two visits a physical exam is performed, checking incision sites,
      and patient symptoms, all of which are standard of care for any minimally invasive procedure.
      The patients will be seen at the EVMS outpatient clinic for Gynecology, or depending with the
      physician who performed the surgery. Data will be collected from both Allscripts and EPIC
      charts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 14, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Double Blind Placebo clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of procedure up to 420 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated blood loss at time of procedure completion; using volume of cannister and weight of lap sponges</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Calculated blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>From post operative day 0 until postoperative day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated Blood loss, using pre-operative hematocrit, postoperative hematocrit and estimated blood volume x Body Mass Index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of blood products received</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of hospital stay up to two days</time_frame>
    <description>Number of blood products received during admission that is directly due to blood loss at time of procedure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery up to 420 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Start time of procedure until end time of procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of stay in hospital, up to two days</time_frame>
    <description>Recorded in days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of fibroids removed</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of surgery, up to 420 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of fibroids removed during procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibroid type</measure>
    <time_frame>through completion of study average 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>type of fibroid per FIGO classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight of fibroids removed</measure>
    <time_frame>duration of surgery up to 420 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>total weight of fibroids removed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain index</measure>
    <time_frame>duration of hospital stay, up to two days</time_frame>
    <description>Pain index score on postoperative day 1 and 14 Score of 0-10 0 = no pain, 10 = significant amount of pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of postoperative complication</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of hospital stay , up to two days</time_frame>
    <description>Immediate postoperative complication:
Hemorrhage Infection Fever Deep vein thrombosis Hysterectomy Re-exploration Hospital readmission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire for incidence of mild side effect of medication</measure>
    <time_frame>only on postoperative day 1 , one day</time_frame>
    <description>Reported mild effective of medication of post operative day 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire for incidence of serious side effect of medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Only on postoperative day 1, one day</time_frame>
    <description>Reported serious side effect of medication on post operative day 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibroid Uterus</condition>
  <condition>Abnormal Uterine Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Myoma;Uterus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive a single IV bolus injection of TXA 30mg/kg in 50ml of normal saline 15 minutes prior to initial surgical incision time</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive an IV bolus injection of normal saline of equivalent volume (placebo group) 15 minutes prior to initial surgical incision</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>IV Tranexamic acid in 50 ml will be given 15 minutes prior to initial surgical incision in the placebo group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic Acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>IV normal saline 50 ml will be given 15 minutes prior to initial surgical incision in the placebo group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing laparoscopic myomectomy

          -  At least one fibroid greater than or equal to 6 cm

          -  Any intramural or broad ligament fibroid greater than or equal to 4 cm

          -  At least 3 total fibroids based on preoperative imaging

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe existing medical complications involving the heart, liver, or kidney

          -  Moderate to severe renal impairment (serum creatinine &gt; 1.4)

          -  Blood clotting abnormalities

          -  Known Allergies to tranexamic acid

          -  Known Contraindications to Minimally invasive myomectomies

          -  If you are pregnant

          -  History of a prior blood clot in the lung arm or leg, known as pulmonary embolism or
             deep vein thrombosis

          -  Any active blood clots, clotting disease, pulmonary embolism, cerebral thrombosis,
             estrogen use, renal impairment, elevated creatinine level

          -  History of a stroke or mini-strokes

          -  Concurrent oral contraceptive use

          -  Contraindications to receiving Tranexamic acid

          -  In patients with acquired defective color vision, since this prohibits measuring one
             endpoint that should be followed as a measure of toxicity

          -  In patients with subarachnoid hemorrhage. Anecdotal experience indicates that cerebral
             edema and cerebral infarction may be caused by tranexamic acid in such patients.

          -  In patients with active intravascular clotting.

          -  In patients with hypersensitivity to tranexamic acid or any of the ingredients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seifeldin Sadek, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eastern Virginia Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Seifeldin Sadek, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7574467100</phone>
    <email>sadeks@evms.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Traci Ito, MD</last_name>
    <phone>7574467900</phone>
    <email>itoTE@evms.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EasternVMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23507</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Seifeldin Sadek, MD</last_name>
      <phone>757-446-7100</phone>
      <email>sadeks@evms.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Traci Ito, MD</last_name>
      <phone>7574467900</phone>
      <email>itoTE@evms.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Topsoee MF, Settnes A, Ottesen B, Bergholt T. A systematic review and meta-analysis of the effect of prophylactic tranexamic acid treatment in major benign uterine surgery. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2017 Feb;136(2):120-127. doi: 10.1002/ijgo.12047. Epub 2016 Dec 9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28099726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore EE, Moore HB, Gonzalez E, Chapman MP, Hansen KC, Sauaia A, Silliman CC, Banerjee A. Postinjury fibrinolysis shutdown: Rationale for selective tranexamic acid. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2015 Jun;78(6 Suppl 1):S65-9. doi: 10.1097/TA.0000000000000634. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26002266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hickman LC, Kotlyar A, Shue S, Falcone T. Hemostatic Techniques for Myomectomy: An Evidence-Based Approach. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2016 May-Jun;23(4):497-504. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2016.01.026. Epub 2016 Mar 9. Review. Erratum in: J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2019 Feb;26(2):373.</citation>
    <PMID>26855249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Henry DA, Carless PA, Moxey AJ, O'Connell D, Stokes BJ, Fergusson DA, Ker K. Anti-fibrinolytic use for minimising perioperative allogeneic blood transfusion. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Jan 19;(1):CD001886. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001886.pub3. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011;(3):CD001886.</citation>
    <PMID>21249650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kongnyuy EJ, Wiysonge CS. Interventions to reduce haemorrhage during myomectomy for fibroids. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2014 Aug 15;(8):CD005355. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD005355.pub5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25125317</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Opoku-Anane J, Vargas MV, Moawad G, Cherie M, Robinson JK. Use of Intravenous Tranexamic Acid During Myomectomy: A Randomized Double-Blind Placebo Controlled Trial. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2015 Nov-Dec;22(6S):S197. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2015.08.715. Epub 2015 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27679021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker WH. Uterine myomas: management. Fertil Steril. 2007 Aug;88(2):255-71. Epub 2007 Jul 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17658523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lam SJ, Best S, Kumar S. The impact of fibroid characteristics on pregnancy outcome. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2014 Oct;211(4):395.e1-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2014.03.066. Epub 2014 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24705132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Updated WHO recommendation on tranexamic acid for the treatment of postpartum haemorrhage: highlights and key messages from the World Health Organization's 2017 global recommendation. No. WHO/RHR/17.21. World Health Organization, 2017</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngichabe S, Obura T, Stones W. Intravenous tranexamic acid as an adjunct haemostat to ornipressin during open myomectomy. A randomized double blind placebo controlled trial. Ann Surg Innov Res. 2015 Oct 31;9:10. doi: 10.1186/s13022-015-0017-y. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26568770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tranexamic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Minimally Invasive</keyword>
  <keyword>Myomectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Fibroid</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leiomyoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofibroma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 2, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04311073/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 12, 2020</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/73/NCT04311073/ICF_001.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

