<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04311268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F2D</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04311268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Follow Fever to Decide</brief_title>
  <official_title>Follow Fever to Decide: Determination of an Algorithm to Quantify and Qualify the Circadian Rhythmicity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Slb Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Caen Normandie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Capital Innovation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Slb Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Body temperature is one of the markers of biological rhythms. The precise determination of
      the functioning of the biological clock for an individual is essential to understanding his
      physiological state at a given time. This condition is dependent on the &quot;timing&quot; of its
      central clock on the time scale (chronotype). The provision of a simple-to-use (F2D cuff),
      non-invasive and time-dependable temperature tool and the creation of appropriate algorithms
      would allow access to the operation of the central clock and open up many therapeutic
      applications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      While the measurement of body temperature is one of the first self-diagnosis gestures at
      home, it is unanimously agreed by healthcare professionals that the measurement of
      non-invasive body temperature performed both in a hospital setting, in the office, that at
      home is very imprecise, or even false. As a result, temperature is only an indicator and is
      of little interest. Only the rectal thermometer and the telemetric capsule (e-CELSIUS®
      capsule to be ingested that allows a reliable and continuous measurement of gastrointestinal
      temperature without the intervention of the caregiver) are reliable tools, but they remain
      invasive and do not always allow for fully reliable follow-up over time. We propose to
      develop an algorithm integrated in an external, non-invasive cuff, allowing the continuous
      recording of body temperature.

      In addition, body temperature is one of the markers of biological rhythms. The precise
      determination of the functioning of the biological clock for an individual is essential to
      understanding his physiological state at a given time. This condition is dependent on the
      &quot;timing&quot; of its central clock on the time scale (chronotype). The provision of a
      simple-to-use (F2D cuff), non-invasive and time-dependable temperature tool and the creation
      of appropriate algorithms would allow access to the operation of the central clock and open
      up many therapeutic applications.

      This work proposes to validate the tool on the one hand and on the other to use this tool to
      produce the elements necessary for monitoring the functioning of the central biological
      clock.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WP1 (body temperature)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the body temperature obtained by the e-CELSIUS® system with the body temperature obtained with the F2D system in 2 situations : during an exercice, to rise the core temperature, and during a nap taken in the afternoon to reduce it.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WP2 (body temperature)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To continuously record the internal and external body temperature obtained with the e-CELSIUS® system and the F2D cuff for 48 hours to obtain a corpus of data allowing algorithm productions being able to quantify and qualify the circadian rhythmicity and determine the chronotype of normo-weighted subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>WP3 (body temperature)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>To continuously record the internal and external body temperature obtained with the e-CELSIUS® system and the F2D cuff for 48 hours to obtain a corpus of data allowing algorithm productions being able to quantify and qualify the circadian rhythmicity and determine the chronotype of subjects with varying ages and body sizes .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">340</enrollment>
  <condition>Body Temperature Changes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observational</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Comparison of the core temperature obtained during 24-48 h with eCelsius and with F2D armband in different life situations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>F2D armband</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of the core temperature obtained during 24-48 h with eCelsius and with F2D armband in different life situations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Observational</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or female,

          -  Between 18 and 40 years of age for the WP I and II phases, and between 18 and 80 years
             of age for the WP III phase,

          -  Having an BMI within the range [18.5; 24.9] kg/m² for the Work Package I and II
             phases, and between [18.5; 34.9] kg/m² for the Work Package III phase,

          -  Beneficiary of the social security,

          -  Provided informed consent for participation in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presenting an acute pathology,

          -  Chronic pathology not followed and balanced,

          -  Having intestinal disorders (diverticles, disorders of the motility of the digestive
             tract, ...) or having undergone surgery at the gastrointestinal level,

          -  With known swallowing disorders,

          -  Having an alcohol dependence (more than 28 alcohol units per week), benzodiazepines or
             any illicit product,

          -  Smoking more than 5 cigarettes per day,

          -  Working nights or shift work,

          -  Simultaneous participation in other clinical research or participation in another
             clinical study for which the exclusion period has not ended.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ophélie Flageul</last_name>
    <phone>+33(0)299121962</phone>
    <email>o.flageul@slbpharma.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laboratoire COMETE UMR-S 1075</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caen</city>
        <zip>14000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Damien Davenne, Pr</last_name>
      <email>damien.davenne@unicaen.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hervé Normand, Pr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazerolle SM, Ganio MS, Casa DJ, Vingren J, Klau J. Is oral temperature an accurate measurement of deep body temperature? A systematic review. J Athl Train. 2011 Sep-Oct;46(5):566-73. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22488144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weed HG. Review: Peripheral thermometers do not have clinically acceptable accuracy for measuring core body temperature. Ann Intern Med. 2016 Mar 15;164(6):JC32. doi: 10.7326/ACPJC-2016-164-6-032.</citation>
    <PMID>26974732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 31, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Body Temperature</keyword>
  <keyword>Circadian Rhythm</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Body Temperature Changes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

