<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04315610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19/23041</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04315610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Personalized Mobile App for Parents of Infants With Cardiac Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>HOBS</acronym>
  <official_title>Personalized Mobile App for Parents of Infants With Cardiac Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oslo University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project implements an eHealth intervention targeted at vulnerable infants with cardiac
      disease and specifically study how this intervention impact their parents coping, stress
      levels and personal wellbeing. The intervention will be evaluated through a randomized
      controlled trial (RCT).

      The aim of this project is therefore to measure if the features of this mobile application
      are useful for parents' assessment of deterioration, decision-making and communication with
      health care providers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project is a service innovation project where the overall aim is to stimulate service
      innovation that ensures patient safety to vulnerable infants with severe cardiac disease. We
      plan to implement and evaluate an eHealth intervention, called HOBS (the Heart
      OBServation-app), that systemizes and personalizes information and teaching from nurses and
      other health personnel in order to support parents as caregivers after discharge from
      hospital. The service innovation will be studied in two consecutive studies; 1) a feasibility
      study to examine health personnel and parents in-depth perception of relevance, benefit and
      user friendliness of the application and its features, and 2) a controlled trial to measure
      the applications impact on parents stress, anxiety, coping and health literacy after
      discharge, including reasons and outcomes of contact with health services. In addition, we
      evaluate if nurses' quality of discharge teaching is affected by the application.

      In Norway, 500-600 children are born with congenital heart defects (CHD) every year. About
      25% of these children present severe problems and symptoms in need of early treatment (1),
      and 15 % of them die during the first year of life (2). Parents of infants with cardiac
      disease assume significant, comprehensive caregiving responsibilities, and have shown higher
      levels of anxiety, depression, and stress. Many parents find it difficult to recognize the
      symptoms if their child's health and wellbeing deteriorates(3).

      New, mobile technology applications and services come with novel opportunities to support
      these parents with personalized, contextual information at the point of need. For example,
      interactive functions and presentation of selected information can enable personalized
      decision-making and communication support. This can improve relevance and quality of
      discharge teaching from nurses at Neonatal Intensive Care Department (NICD) at Oslo
      University Hospital (OUH), but more importantly also support local services where CHD seldom
      occur and knowledge may be sparse. To date, the value added, appropriateness and importance
      of such opportunities for mental stress and health competence among parents of children with
      CHD has not been systematically reported. Moreover, if our study goals are achieved, the
      intervention can empower parents to recognize the early signs before deterioration in their
      infant manifests, prevent acute episodes at home after discharge, and improve rehabilitation.
      For the parents this service innovation may reduce psychological strain during a challenging
      period of life.

      Method and data collection A controlled trial with consecutive groups has been chosen to
      avoid contamination of health personnel's way of guiding and parents interaction at common
      rooms at the NICD. Even though the access to or use of the application are controlled by the
      project using a login code we accept that guidance will be affected and more systematic
      during the implementation of the application and this may affect the results. Hence, a two
      months break between the last family receiving app in the quality study at OUH and inclusion
      of the control group is planned. Inclusion of the control group will then be conducted before
      inclusion of the app group. The control group receives written information in a binder while
      the intervention group will receive the information through links in the mobile application.
      A guideline including a checklist of topics to support parents before discharge is similar to
      both groups.

      The intervention HOBS-app is developed by a project group at OUH together with parents and
      local health personnel for parents with infants with cardiac disease. Congenital heart
      disease is a complicated and individual diagnosis with varied consequences (15). Therefore,
      at first login, the diagnosis and treatments are registered. Then an algorithm in the
      application provides parents with a personalized set of observations and a list of adapted
      information to their infant`s needs. Under the guidance of nurses at the NICD at OUH, parents
      are trained using the app to assess their infant`s condition, regarding circulation,
      breathing, eating habits, well-being, wound healing and more. These observations are stored
      in the application. In this way parents become better aware of their infant's condition and
      may help parents to detect signs of deterioration at home. Contact information to local
      health services is stored before discharge. After discharge, assessments using the
      application are performed before consultations to health services or if parents are uncertain
      about deterioration in their infant. After assessments the applications` function for
      communication support can guide parents in describing a possible deterioration and
      communication with health personnel may be facilitated.

      To reach health professionals with information about HOBS a website will be established with
      guidance and tips on using the app. An e-learning course is developed and will be distributed
      nationally through similar educative portals. A link to the website and the e-learning
      courses are added to the discharge summary that follows the infant to a local hospital.

      The purpose of the controlled trial is to answer research question 3: In what ways do the
      application's content and functionality influence the parents' coping with stress, anxiety,
      distress of caring for a sick child and health literacy and contact with health services?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pediatric Inventory for Parents (PIP)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The PIP measures parental stress related to children with chronic disease (32) and is the primary endpoint after 4 months. It contains 42 items that is answered on a 5 point Likert scale within four domains: 1) communication, 2) emotional distance, 3) medical care and 4) role function. All items is answered twice, one for frequency and one for difficulty. Higher score reflects more disease related stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health literacy Questionnaire (HLQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The HLQ is a multidimensional instrument that measures health competence and has good validity and reliability (34). Scores range between 1 to 4 (for first 5 scales) and 1 to 5 (for scales 6 to 9), and higher value indicates better literacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>System Usability Scale (SUS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>This instrument consists of 10 items and is answered at a Likert scale from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). It has good validity and reliability and is translated in to Norwegian and used in studies of mobile applications (37). These data will be collected to ensure input from the users in the further implementation and to capture functionality challenges that could affect the results in the controlled trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post Discharge Coping Difficulty Scale (PDCDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>PDCDS measures parental coping after discharge and is the primary outcome after 1 month. It has good reliability and validity (31). The instrument is translated in to Norwegian and has acceptable reliability (0.71) (18) . The scale uses an 11 point format with anchor words (&quot;not at all&quot; to &quot;totally&quot;) at the 0 and 10 poles of the scale, where higher value indicates more difficulties. Five of the questions have an additional open ended question that elaborates what kind of difficulties parents' experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease in Children</condition>
  <condition>Stress, Psychological</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Access to mobile application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This application will help parents to recognize symptoms of reduced health status in their infant, provide decision-making support, increase their communication skills with health professionals, and provide easier access to quality assured information. At first login, the diagnosis, treatment, and contacts in the health service are registered to provide parents with personalized information that is adapted to their infant`s needs. Under the guidance of healthcare personnel at the Neonatal Intensive Care Department (NICD) at Oslo University Hospital (OUH), parents are trained to assess their infant`s condition, regarding circulation, breathing, eating habits, well-being, and more. In addition, before discharge, a baseline assessment of the infant`s condition is stored in the application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group receives traditional oral and written information about their child's heart defect and further follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Access to mobile phone application</intervention_name>
    <description>Under the guidance of healthcare personnel at the Neonatal Intensive Care Department (NICD) at Oslo University Hospital (OUH), parents are trained to assess their infant`s condition, regarding circulation, breathing, eating habits, well-being, and more. In addition, before discharge, a baseline assessment of the infant`s condition is stored in the application. After discharge, assessments using the application are performed if necessary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Access to mobile application</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>Active comparator group, based on traditional information and follow-up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Parents of all infants (born after week 37) diagnosed with severe heart disease at NICD at
        OUH

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Language barriers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elin Hjorth-Johansen, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+4798676884</phone>
    <email>ehjorth@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Henrik Holmstrøm, Dr Med</last_name>
    <email>hholmstr@ous-hf.no</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oslo University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Henrik Holmstrøm</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

