<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04310449</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PER8273002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04310449</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Volumetric Changes of Buccal Soft Tissue Contour Following Different Socket Management Approaches</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Volumetric Changes of Buccal Soft Tissue Contour Following Different Socket Management Approaches With or Without Immediate Implant Placement Following Tooth Extraction. A 1-year Prospective Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Misr International University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Misr International University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Statement of the problem: Tooth extraction is followed by ridge alteration and soft tissue
      contour collapse. Different strategies were proposed to limit this collapse however, the
      ability of these techniques to mimic the original soft tissue contour and to maintain long
      term stability is unclear. Purpose : The aim of this study is to evaluate the volumetric
      difference of buccal soft tissue contour as well as the radiographic changes, following tooth
      extraction with four different socket management approaches. Materials and Methods: Sixty
      patients with single maxillary anterior or premolar tooth indicated for extraction will
      participate in this study, 15 patient in each group. Group 1 (test group) will be treated by
      immediate implant placement (IIP) with connective tissue graft (CTG) and customized healing
      abutment, Group 2 (test group) IIP with particulate bone graft in the buccal gap till the
      bone crest and customized healing abutment, Group 3 (test group) particulate bone grafts in
      the socket with ovate pontic alone, while the 4th group (control) IIP with particulate bone
      grafts in the dual zone (the bone zone and the tissue zone) and customized healing abutment.
      Patient allocation is random for the 3 implant groups. Data will be collected pre-surgically
      and at follow up periods (3,6,9&amp;12 months). Extra-oral scanning of the buccal contour will be
      carried out to evaluate difference in contour gained and will be compared to the original
      contour and between treatment groups. Radiographic evaluation will be done using CBCT
      pre-operatively and at 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After administration of local anaesthesia, the tooth will be extracted by the principle
      investigator without raising flaps, as atraumatically as possible by using periotomes without
      disturbing the papillary tissues (minimal traumatic extraction technique). After the
      extraction of the tooth, the socket will be carefully cleaned to excavate the granulation
      tissue in the marginal and apical regions. The allocation will be revealed to the principle
      investigator for the 3 implant groups after implant placement.

      Group 1: extraction will occur and then followed by immediate implant placement,using
      standard implant system protocol preparation of the osteotomy will take place. Initial drill
      will be placed palatally till final drill reached. Placement of the implant without any
      raising of the flap will be performed in the correct implant position. Primary stability of
      the implant will be measured by rotational insertion torque value, to be ≥30Ncm (37).
      Connective tissue grafts will be harvested from the hard palate and placed at the implant
      sites in a supraperiosteal partial dissection (pouch technique) prepared at the buccal aspect
      without using vertical incisions and without flap elevation. Sutures will be used to
      stabilize the graft in its desired place. Followed by customized healing abutment, the
      temporary cylindrical abutment twill be screwed to the implant and then flowable composite
      will be injected at the gingival margin level to adapt to the abutment that will be
      sand-blasted previously for mechanical retention of the composite, taking the shape of the
      socket at the marginal gingiva. A buccal groove will be made after the polymerization of this
      material for easier application. The abutments will be removed for final configurations of
      the apical part mimicking the emergence profile of the extracted tooth and finishing with
      laboratory discs and burs. The custom healing screw will then be screwed to the implant with
      the correct torque.

      Group 2: Tooth extraction and immediate implant placement as mentioned, followed by
      particulate bone grafts are packed in the gap between the implant and the buccal plate of
      bone till the crest of the alveolar bone, then will be covered by a customized healing
      abutment that will be done as mentioned before.

      Group 3: The extraction will take place and then particulate bone graft will be placed in the
      socket and a fixed temporary ovate ontic (PMMA) extending 3mm inside the socket, with minimal
      occlusal contact (38), will be placed and cemented on the adjacent teeth.

      Group 4 (control group): Tooth extraction and immediate implant placement as mentioned,
      followed by particulate bone grafts are packed in the gap between the implant and the buccal
      plate of bone and the tissue (dual zone), then will be covered by a customized healing
      abutment that will be done as mentioned before but will only seal the socket without
      extending deeper apically in the soft tissue
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>• To compare the volumetric changes in the buccal soft tissue contour between immediate implants with CTG and customized healing abutments, Immediate implant with bone grafting and customized healing abutments, bone grafts in the sockets and ovate pontics and immediate implants with bone grafting in the dual zone and customized healing abutmnets</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Volumetric analysis of buccal contour to assess changes in buccal countour</measure>
    <time_frame>Before surgery - 3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Extra oral scanning + 3D viewer software</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bucco-palatal width</measure>
    <time_frame>Before surgery - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with CBCT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>Before surgery - 6 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with periodontal probe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mid facial recession to assess the changes in tissue level</measure>
    <time_frame>Before surgery - 3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with 3D Viewer software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interdental papillae height to assess changes in papilla height</measure>
    <time_frame>Before surgery - 3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with 3D Viewer software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Plaque Index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Periodontal probe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Bleeding Index</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months - 6 months - 9 months - 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Periodontal probe</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). The patients will mark their satisfaction in a non-numerical 100 mm line ranging from &quot;not at all satisfied=0&quot; (left) to &quot;very satisfied=100&quot; (right), for each implant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Implant Placement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Connective tissue graft and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediate implant placement with CTG and customized healing abutment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Immediate implant placement with bone graft till the crest of the bone and customized healing abutment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft and ovate pontic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bone grafts in the socket and ovate Pontic</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft in dual zone and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>immediate implant placement with bone grafts in the dual zone and customized healing abutment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Connective tissue graft and customized healing abutment</intervention_name>
    <description>Immediate implant placement without flap raising using standard implant system protocol preparation will take place. Connective tissue grafts from the hard palate will be placed at the implant sites in a supraperiosteal partial dissection prepared at the buccal aspect. Sutures will be used to stabilize the graft, followed by customized healing abutment. Flowable composite will be injected at the gingival margin level to adapt to the sandblasted abutment, taking the shape of the socket at the marginal gingiva. Buccal groove will be made after the polymerization of this material for easier application. The abutments will be removed for final configurations of the apical part mimicking the emergence profile of the extracted tooth and finishing with laboratory discs and burs. The custom healing screw will be screwed to the implant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Connective tissue graft and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>zimmer biomed dental implants and connective tissue grafts and customized healing abutments</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bone graft and customized healing abutment</intervention_name>
    <description>Tooth extraction and immediate implant placement as mentioned, followed by particulate bone grafts are packed in the gap between the implant and the buccal plate of bone till the crest of the alveolar bone, then will be covered by a customized healing abutment that will be done as mentioned before.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft in dual zone and customized healing abutment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zimmer biomed dental implants and Geistlich Bio-Oss bone graft and customized healing abutments</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bone graft and ovate pontic</intervention_name>
    <description>The extraction will take place and then particulate bone graft will be placed in the socket and a fixed temporary ovate pontic (PMMA) extending 3mm inside the socket, with minimal occlusal contact (38), will be placed and cemented on the adjacent teeth</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bone graft and ovate pontic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Geistlich Bio-Oss bone graft and ovate pontic</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who have at least one non-restorable maxillary anterior or premolar tooth
             with sound adjacent teeth.

          2. Adults at or above the age of 18.

          3. Intact thick biotype gingival tissue with at least 2mm band of keratinized tissue.

          4. Buccal bone thickness should be 1mm or less assessed in CBCT with good apical bone.

          5. Sagittal root position type 1 as described by Kan et al(30).

          6. Good oral hygiene

          7. Patient accepts to provide an informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Smokers

          2. Pregnant and lactating females.

          3. Medically compromised patients. , as Uncontrolled diabetic patients, patients taking
             bisphosphonates injection for treatment of osteoporosis, patients with active cardiac
             diseases, patients undergoing radiotherapy or chemotherapy, or any other medical and
             general contraindications for the surgical procedure (i.e. ASA score ≥III) (31)

          4. Patients with active infection related at the site of implant/bone graft placement.

          5. Patients with untreated active periodontal diseases.

          6. Patients with parafunctional habits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahmed I Abo El Futtouh, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinical Director of Implant Program - Misr International University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ahmed I Abo El Futtouh, Master</last_name>
    <phone>+201019999983</phone>
    <email>ahmedkey7@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Inas M El-Zayat, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>+201222361579</phone>
    <email>inas.elzayat@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Dental Contining Education Centre (IDCE)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ahmed I Abo El Futtouh, Master</last_name>
      <phone>+201019999983</phone>
      <email>ahmedkey7@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Inas M El-Zayat, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>+201222361579</phone>
      <email>inas.elzayat@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Misr International University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ahmed I Abo El Futtouh, Master</last_name>
      <phone>+201019999983</phone>
      <email>ahmedkey7@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Inas M El-Zayat, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>+201222361579</phone>
      <email>inas.elzayat@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gluckman H, Salama M, Du Toit J. Partial Extraction Therapies (PET) Part 2: Procedures and Technical Aspects. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2017 May/Jun;37(3):377-385. doi: 10.11607/prd.3111.</citation>
    <PMID>28402349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fuentealba R, Jofré J. Esthetic failure in implant dentistry. Dent Clin North Am. 2015 Jan;59(1):227-46. doi: 10.1016/j.cden.2014.08.006. Epub 2014 Sep 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25434568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esposito M, Grusovin MG, Felice P, Karatzopoulos G, Worthington HV, Coulthard P. The efficacy of horizontal and vertical bone augmentation procedures for dental implants - a Cochrane systematic review. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2009 Autumn;2(3):167-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20467628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen ST, Buser D. Esthetic outcomes following immediate and early implant placement in the anterior maxilla--a systematic review. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2014;29 Suppl:186-215. doi: 10.11607/jomi.2014suppl.g3.3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24660198</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buser D, Martin W, Belser UC. Optimizing esthetics for implant restorations in the anterior maxilla: anatomic and surgical considerations. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2004;19 Suppl:43-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15635945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grunder U, Gracis S, Capelli M. Influence of the 3-D bone-to-implant relationship on esthetics. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2005 Apr;25(2):113-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15839587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araújo MG, Lindhe J. Dimensional ridge alterations following tooth extraction. An experimental study in the dog. J Clin Periodontol. 2005 Feb;32(2):212-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15691354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araújo MG, Sukekava F, Wennström JL, Lindhe J. Tissue modeling following implant placement in fresh extraction sockets. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2006 Dec;17(6):615-24.</citation>
    <PMID>17092218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen ST, Buser D. Clinical and esthetic outcomes of implants placed in postextraction sites. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2009;24 Suppl:186-217. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19885446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horváth A, Mardas N, Mezzomo LA, Needleman IG, Donos N. Alveolar ridge preservation. A systematic review. Clin Oral Investig. 2013 Mar;17(2):341-63. doi: 10.1007/s00784-012-0758-5. Epub 2012 Jul 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22814758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masaki C, Nakamoto T, Mukaibo T, Kondo Y, Hosokawa R. Strategies for alveolar ridge reconstruction and preservation for implant therapy. J Prosthodont Res. 2015 Oct;59(4):220-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jpor.2015.04.005. Epub 2015 May 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26022542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Risi V, Clementini M, Vittorini G, Mannocci A, De Sanctis M. Alveolar ridge preservation techniques: a systematic review and meta-analysis of histological and histomorphometrical data. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2015 Jan;26(1):50-68. doi: 10.1111/clr.12288. Epub 2013 Nov 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27007188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lückerath W, Röder L, Enkling N. The Effect of Primary Stabilization of the Graft in a Combined Surgical and Prosthodontic Ridge Preservation Protocol: A Prospective Controlled Clinical Pilot Study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2018 May/Jun;38(3):e49-e58. doi: 10.11607/prd.3172.</citation>
    <PMID>29641631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kan JY, Rungcharassaeng K. Immediate placement and provisionalization of maxillary anterior single implants: a surgical and prosthodontic rationale. Pract Periodontics Aesthet Dent. 2000 Nov-Dec;12(9):817-24; quiz 826.</citation>
    <PMID>11405020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kan JYK, Rungcharassaeng K, Deflorian M, Weinstein T, Wang HL, Testori T. Immediate implant placement and provisionalization of maxillary anterior single implants. Periodontol 2000. 2018 Jun;77(1):197-212. doi: 10.1111/prd.12212. Epub 2018 Feb 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29478284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tarnow DP, Chu SJ, Salama MA, Stappert CF, Salama H, Garber DA, Sarnachiaro GO, Sarnachiaro E, Gotta SL, Saito H. Flapless postextraction socket implant placement in the esthetic zone: part 1. The effect of bone grafting and/or provisional restoration on facial-palatal ridge dimensional change-a retrospective cohort study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2014 May-Jun;34(3):323-31. doi: 10.11607/prd.1821.</citation>
    <PMID>24804283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu SJ, Salama MA, Garber DA, Salama H, Sarnachiaro GO, Sarnachiaro E, Gotta SL, Reynolds MA, Saito H, Tarnow DP. Flapless Postextraction Socket Implant Placement, Part 2: The Effects of Bone Grafting and Provisional Restoration on Peri-implant Soft Tissue Height and Thickness- A Retrospective Study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2015 Nov-Dec;35(6):803-9. doi: 10.11607/prd.2178.</citation>
    <PMID>26509983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu SJ, Saito H, Salama MA, Garber DA, Salama H, Sarnachiaro GO, Reynolds MA, Tarnow DP. Flapless Postextraction Socket Implant Placement, Part 3: The Effects of Bone Grafting and Provisional Restoration on Soft Tissue Color Change-A Retrospective Pilot Study. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2018 Jul/Aug;38(4):509-516. doi: 10.11607/prd.3571.</citation>
    <PMID>29889914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akin R. A New Concept in Maintaining the Emergence Profile in Immediate Posterior Implant Placement: The Anatomic Harmony Abutment. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2016 Dec;74(12):2385-2392. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2016.06.184. Epub 2016 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27475245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janakievski J. Case Report : Maintenance of Gingival Form Following Immediate Implant Placement — The Custom-Healing Abutment. Adv Esthet Interdiscip Dent. 2007;3(4):4-7</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mihali S. Maintaining Tissue Architecture in Immediate Implant Placement Following Extraction of Natural Teeth Using Custom Healing Screw. Biomed J Sci Tech Res. 2018</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zuiderveld EG, Meijer HJA, den Hartog L, Vissink A, Raghoebar GM. Effect of connective tissue grafting on peri-implant tissue in single immediate implant sites: A RCT. J Clin Periodontol. 2018 Feb;45(2):253-264. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12820. Epub 2017 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>28941303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kan JY, Rungcharassaeng K, Morimoto T, Lozada J. Facial gingival tissue stability after connective tissue graft with single immediate tooth replacement in the esthetic zone: consecutive case report. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2009 Nov;67(11 Suppl):40-8. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2009.07.004.</citation>
    <PMID>19835749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kolerman R, Nissan J, Mijiritsky E, Hamoudi N, Mangano C, Tal H. Esthetic assessment of immediately restored implants combined with GBR and free connective tissue graft. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2016 Nov;27(11):1414-1422. doi: 10.1111/clr.12755. Epub 2016 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>26743894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cosyn J, Eghbali A, Hermans A, Vervaeke S, De Bruyn H, Cleymaet R. A 5-year prospective study on single immediate implants in the aesthetic zone. J Clin Periodontol. 2016 Aug;43(8):702-9. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12571. Epub 2016 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27120578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu SJ, Salama MA, Salama H, Garber DA, Saito H, Sarnachiaro GO, Tarnow DP. The dual-zone therapeutic concept of managing immediate implant placement and provisional restoration in anterior extraction sockets. Compend Contin Educ Dent. 2012 Jul-Aug;33(7):524-32, 534.</citation>
    <PMID>22908601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levin BP, Chu SJ. Changes in Peri-implant Soft Tissue Thickness with Bone Grafting and Dermis Allograft: A Case Series of 15 Consecutive Patients. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2018 Sep/Oct;38(5):719-727. doi: 10.11607/prd.3561.</citation>
    <PMID>30113609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhola M, Jacobs L, Kolhatkar S. Immediate implants for aesthetic success: New guidelines. J Int Clin Dent Res Organ. 2016;7(3):138</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Nimwegen WG, Raghoebar GM, Zuiderveld EG, Jung RE, Meijer HJA, Mühlemann S. Immediate placement and provisionalization of implants in the aesthetic zone with or without a connective tissue graft: A 1-year randomized controlled trial and volumetric study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2018 Jul;29(7):671-678. doi: 10.1111/clr.13258. Epub 2018 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29806181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kan JY, Roe P, Rungcharassaeng K, Patel RD, Waki T, Lozada JL, Zimmerman G. Classification of sagittal root position in relation to the anterior maxillary osseous housing for immediate implant placement: a cone beam computed tomography study. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2011 Jul-Aug;26(4):873-6.</citation>
    <PMID>21841998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smeets EC, de Jong KJ, Abraham-Inpijn L. Detecting the medically compromised patient in dentistry by means of the medical risk-related history. A survey of 29,424 dental patients in The Netherlands. Prev Med. 1998 Jul-Aug;27(4):530-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9672946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chrcanovic BR, Kisch J, Albrektsson T, Wennerberg A. Factors Influencing Early Dental Implant Failures. J Dent Res. 2016 Aug;95(9):995-1002. doi: 10.1177/0022034516646098. Epub 2016 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>27146701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olmedo-Gaya MV, Manzano-Moreno FJ, Cañaveral-Cavero E, de Dios Luna-del Castillo J, Vallecillo-Capilla M. Risk factors associated with early implant failure: A 5-year retrospective clinical study. J Prosthet Dent. 2016 Feb;115(2):150-5. doi: 10.1016/j.prosdent.2015.07.020. Epub 2015 Nov 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26545864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vissink A, Spijkervet F, Raghoebar GM. The medically compromised patient: Are dental implants a feasible option? Oral Dis. 2018 Mar;24(1-2):253-260. doi: 10.1111/odi.12762.</citation>
    <PMID>29480621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lobbezoo F, Brouwers JE, Cune MS, Naeije M. Dental implants in patients with bruxing habits. J Oral Rehabil. 2006 Feb;33(2):152-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16457676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kan JY, Morimoto T, Rungcharassaeng K, Roe P, Smith DH. Gingival biotype assessment in the esthetic zone: visual versus direct measurement. Int J Periodontics Restorative Dent. 2010 Jun;30(3):237-43.</citation>
    <PMID>20386780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Testori T, Meltzer A, Del Fabbro M, Zuffetti F, Troiano M, Francetti L, Weinstein RL. Immediate occlusal loading of Osseotite implants in the lower edentulous jaw. A multicenter prospective study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2004 Jun;15(3):278-84.</citation>
    <PMID>15142089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spear FM. The use of implants and ovate pontics in the esthetic zone. Compend Contin Educ Dent. 2008 Mar;29(2):72-4, 76-80; quiz 81, 94.</citation>
    <PMID>18429422</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zuhr O, Bäumer D, Hürzeler M. The addition of soft tissue replacement grafts in plastic periodontal and implant surgery: critical elements in design and execution. J Clin Periodontol. 2014 Apr;41 Suppl 15:S123-42. doi: 10.1111/jcpe.12185. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24640997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueno D, Kobayashi M, Tanaka K, Watanabe T, Nakamura T, Ueda K, Nagano T. Measurement accuracy of alveolar soft tissue contour using a laboratory laser scanner. Odontology. 2018 Apr;106(2):202-207. doi: 10.1007/s10266-017-0315-4. Epub 2017 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>28770415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SH, Choi JH, Chung KR, Nelson G. Do sand blasted with large grit and acid etched surface treated mini-implants remain stationary under orthodontic forces? Angle Orthod. 2012 Mar;82(2):304-12. doi: 10.2319/032511-212.1. Epub 2011 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21830933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koerich L, Weissheimer A, Koerich LE, Luz D, Deeb JG. A Technique of Cone-Beam Computerized Tomography Superimposition in Implant Dentistry. J Oral Implantol. 2018 Oct;44(5):365-369. doi: 10.1563/aaid-joi-D-17-00282. Epub 2018 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>29717909</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cevidanes LH, Styner MA, Proffit WR. Image analysis and superimposition of 3-dimensional cone-beam computed tomography models. Am J Orthod Dentofacial Orthop. 2006 May;129(5):611-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16679201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mombelli A, van Oosten MA, Schurch E Jr, Land NP. The microbiota associated with successful or failing osseointegrated titanium implants. Oral Microbiol Immunol. 1987 Dec;2(4):145-51.</citation>
    <PMID>3507627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Misr International University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ahmed Abo El Futtouh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Director of Implant Program - Periodontology and Implantology Consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immediate implant placement</keyword>
  <keyword>Connective tissue graft</keyword>
  <keyword>particulate bone graft</keyword>
  <keyword>dual-zone therapeutic concept</keyword>
  <keyword>customized healing abutment</keyword>
  <keyword>socket management protocols</keyword>
  <keyword>buccal soft tissue contour</keyword>
  <keyword>volumetric analysis</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All data can be shared</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>One year</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Principal investigator</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

