<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04315493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BLTN-If</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04315493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Low-fat Diet on the Pharmacokinetics of Pyrotinib in Healthy Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open, Single-dose, Two-cycle, Double-sequence, Crossover Study to Investigate the Effects of a Low-fat Diet On the Pharmacokinetics of Healthy Chinese Adult Participants After Oral Administration of Pyrotinib Maleate Tablets</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jiangsu HengRui Medicine Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jiangsu HengRui Medicine Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the effect of low-fat diet on
      pharmacokinetics of healthy Chinese adult participants after oral administration of pyrotinib
      maleate tablets.

      The secondary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety of single dose of pyrotinib
      orally in healthy participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: Cmax of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax) of pyrotinib</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: AUC of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration versus time curve (AUC) of pyrotinib</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: Tmax of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Time of maximum observed concentration (Tmax) of pyrotinib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: T1/2 of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Half time (T1/2) of pyrotinib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: CL/F of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Total body clearance for extravascular administration (CL/F) of pyrotinib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics parameter: Vz/F of pyrotinib</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of distribution (Vz/F) of pyrotinib</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical study participant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Participants</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pyrotinib maleate fasted in P1, low-fat diet in P2</intervention_name>
    <description>pyrotinib maleate administration in fasted condition in period 1, pyrotinib maleate administration after low-fat diet in period 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pyrotinib maleate low-fat diet in P1, fasted in P2</intervention_name>
    <description>pyrotinib maleate administration after low-fat diet in period 1, pyrotinib maleate administration in fasted condition in period 2</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Sign the informed consent before the trial, and fully understand the trial content,
             process and possible adverse reactions;

          2. Ability to complete the study as required by the protocol;

          3. Healthy male or female subjects aged 18 to 45 (including 18 and 45) at the date of
             signing the informed consent;

          4. Have no fertility plan and agree to adopt effective contraceptive measures within 2
             weeks before the first study drug administration and up to 3 months after the last
             study drug administration. Negative pregnancy test for women of child-bearing age
             before the first study drug administration;

          5. Male body weight ≥ 50kg, female body weight ≥ 45kg, and body mass index (BMI) within
             the range of 19 ~ 26 kg/m^2 (including 19 and 26);

          6. During screening period, the comprehensive physical examination (vital signs and
             physical examination), routine laboratory examination (blood routine, urine routine,
             blood biochemistry, coagulation,etc), 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), chest X-ray,
             cardiac ultrasound, B ultrasound and other examination results must be within the
             normal range, or judged to be &quot;no clinical significance (NCS)&quot; if beyond the normal
             range;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Blood donation within 3 months before the first drug administration and blood loss
             greater than 400 mL, or receiving blood transfusion;

          2. Allergic constitution, including those with severe drug allergies or a history of drug
             allergies, or known allergy to the research drug;

          3. History of drug use, or drug abuse screening positive; history of drug abuse within
             the past five years or have used drugs 3 months before the test;

          4. Alcoholic or often drinkers (the average drinking amount is more than 14 units a week:
             1 unit= 285 ml beer or 45 ml spirits or 100 ml wine; ≥5 cigarettes per day) and can't
             quit smoking and alcohol during the study; alcohol test positive;

          5. The 12-lead ECG with female QTcF &gt; 470ms or male QTcF &gt; 450ms;

          6. Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt;50% by echocardiography;

          7. A clear medical history of important primary organ diseases such as nervous system,
             cardiovascular system, urinary system, digestive system, respiratory system,
             metabolism and musculoskeletal system.

          8. Those who have undergone any surgery within 6 months before screening;

          9. Those who have taken hepatotoxic drugs (such as dapsone, erythromycin, fluconazole,
             ketoconazole, rifampicin) for a long time within the 6 months before screening;

         10. Those who have taken any research drugs within 3 months before the first drug
             administration;

         11. Use any drugs that changes liver enzyme activity within 4 weeks before the first drug
             administration;

         12. Use any prescription or over-the-counter drug, any vitamin product, health supplement
             or herbal medicine within 2 weeks prior to first drug administration;

         13. Abnormal clinical laboratory tests and clinical significance judged by the
             investigator or other clinical findings showing the following diseases, including but
             not limited to gastrointestinal tract, kidney, liver, nerve, blood, endocrine, tumor,
             lung, immune, mental or cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases;

         14. HCV antibody positive, HIV antibody positive, HBsAg positive, and syphilis antibody
             positive;

         15. Consumption of grapefruit or grapefruit-containing products, foods or beverages
             containing caffeine, xanthine, or alcohol within 48 hours before the first drug
             administration; strenuous exercise or other factors that effect on drug absorption,
             distribution, metabolism and excretion;

         16. Have special requirements on diet and cannot comply with the diet and corresponding
             regulations provided by the test;

         17. History of dizzy needles or blood dizziness; difficulty in venous blood collection or
             inability to tolerate venipuncture;

         18. lactating women;

         19. Other factors that are not suitable for participating in the study, as judged by the
             investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yuya Wang, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>86-13918749176</phone>
    <email>wangyuya@hrglobe.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chao Lu, M.M.</last_name>
    <phone>86-18005693201</phone>
    <email>765385306@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Maleic acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

