<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04318379</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GC002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04318379</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Hepatitis C Virus Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of an Immunotherapy (HCVax™) in Chronic Hepatitis C Infected Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GeneCure Biotechnologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GeneCure Biotechnologies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      GC002 is a Phase I trial to evaluate the safety and the immune responses of a lentiviral
      based HCV immunotherapy (HCVax™) in chronic HCV patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      GC002 is a Phase I trial to evaluate the safety and the immune responses of a lentiviral
      based HCV immunotherapy (HCVax™) in chronic HCV patients. Chronic HCV patients will be
      enrolled sequentially into low dose and high dose groups. Following the vaccination subjects
      who received at least one vaccination will be followed up for safety and immunological
      response through week 28. All vaccine recipients will take part in a long-term safety
      follow-up for 6 months following the completion of the vaccine series to assess delayed
      adverse events.

      Vaccination will first start at low dose. The investigators will enroll low dose group first.
      Two subjects will be staggering enrolled every 2 weeks. Following the assessment and review
      of prior vaccinations, if no vaccine definitely or probably-related severe adverse event
      (grade 3 or above) or SAE occurs the vaccination schedule for low dose and high dose will
      continue until complete enrollment.

      Each subject will receive HCVax™ vaccine at 0, 8, 16 weeks through subcutaneous route.
      Following vaccination subjects will have clinical, immunological and virologic assessments
      throughout the 28-week study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety of a therapeutic HCV vaccine in chronic HCV patients</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and severity of adverse events, laboratory abnormalities, local and systemic reactogenicity signs and symptoms following vaccinations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the immunogenicity of a therapeutic HCV vaccine in chronic HCV patients</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Magnitude of IFN-γ &amp; IL-2 producing CD4+ and CD8+ T cells to HCV core peptides pools at weeks 8, 16, and 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Virologic response</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Sustained viral response (SVR) will be defined as negative HCV RNA result using an assay that has sensitivity of 25 IU or less per milliliter at 12 weeks after the end of vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Hepatitis C Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low dose group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic HCV patients. Fifteen subjects will receive 1.0 ml of low dose vaccine at weeks 0, 8 and 16 through subcutaneous route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High dose group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chronic HCV patients. Fifteen subjects will receive 1.0 ml of high dose vaccine at weeks 0, 8 and 16 through subcutaneous route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HCVax</intervention_name>
    <description>HCVax is a lentiviral vector encoding several HCV antigens</description>
    <arm_group_label>High dose group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low dose group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Documentation of chronic hepatitis C infection based on serum positivity for HCV RNA
             for at least 6 months interval. HCV genotype will be recorded. All genotypes will be
             eligible.

          2. Patients who are not under DAA treatment.

          3. Liver fibrosis (by Metavir stage F1 or F0) within one year of the screening visit,
             documenting extent of liver disease consistent with chronic hepatitis C with evidence
             of inflammation and/or fibrosis. Fibrosis scaling is based on an ultrasound based
             elastography (FibroScan, Echosen, Paris France) with cutoff of 7.5 kPa or liver
             biopsy.

          4. Screening laboratory values within institutional normal range, with the exception of
             liver enzymes ≤ 3 ULN and bilirubin &lt;1.5 ULN, or judged to be not clinically
             significant by clinical investigator.

          5. Ability and willingness of subject to give written informed consent.

          6. Negative pregnancy test on the day prior to each vaccination.

          7. Willingness to use adequate contraception by study participants. Subjects must agree
             not to participate in a conception process (e.g., active attempts to become pregnant
             or to impregnate, sperm donation, or in vitro fertilization), and if participating in
             sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, subjects must use a form of
             contraception as listed below while on study vaccine and for 60 days after stopping
             study vaccine. Women without reproductive potential (i.e., have reached menopause or
             undergone hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or tubal ligation) or women whose male
             partner has undergone successful vasectomy with documented azoospermia or has
             documented azoospermia for any other reason, are eligible without requiring the use of
             contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of decompensated liver disease, including but not restricted to, portal
             hypertension as manifested by a known history of gastroesophageal varices, variceal
             bleeding, ascites or encephalopathy, histopathologic or clinical evidence of
             cirrhosis, hepatocellular carcinoma, or renal impairment consistent with hepatorenal
             syndrome; history of significant other non-HCV chronic liver disease, i.e. alcoholic
             hepatitis, autoimmune hepatitis.

          2. History of hematologic disease (e.g., cryoglobulinemia, lymphoma), renal disease,
             dermatologic disease (e.g., lichen planus, porphyria cutanea tarda).

          3. Seropositive for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or HIV-1 antibody.

          4. Autoimmune diseases or clinically serious cardiac, pulmonary, gastrointestinal,
             hepatic, renal or neurologic disease, which in the opinion of the investigator will
             compromise ability to participate in the study.

          5. Previous receipt of any HCV experimental vaccine.

          6. Pregnancy and breast-feeding.

          7. Prior or current systemic cancer chemotherapy.

          8. Investigational agents and immunomodulators (cyclosporine, hematological growth
             factors, systemic corticosteroids, interleukins or interferons) within 90 days prior
             to study entry. NOTE: Subjects may not be on antiretroviral agents not yet approved by
             the FDA as part of a clinical trial or expanded access program.

          9. Anaphylaxis or allergy to vaccine components.

         10. Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the investigator,
             would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

         11. Any other serious diseases other than HCV infection including current or recent
             (within 5 years) cancers.

         12. Liver fibrosis with Metavir stage F2 or above.

         13. Subjects with diabetes mellitus, who are at higher risk for more rapid progression of
             fibrosis.

         14. Subjects who are immunocompromised or immunosuppressed due to disease or medications.

         15. Subjects with any laboratory abnormalities Grade 3 or greater.

         16. Women who are lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frank Tung, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>7702637508</phone>
    <email>frank@genecure.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gastrointestinal Specialists of Georgia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marietta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aasim Sheikh, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>678-819-4227</phone>
      <email>asheikh@gigeorgia.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gwen Barger, MPh</last_name>
      <phone>678-819-4227</phone>
      <email>gbarger@gigeorgia.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tung FY, Tung JK, Pallikkuth S, Pahwa S, Fischl MA. A therapeutic HIV-1 vaccine enhances anti-HIV-1 immune responses in patients under highly active antiretroviral therapy. Vaccine. 2016 Apr 27;34(19):2225-32. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.03.021. Epub 2016 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27002500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Therapeutic HCV vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>HCV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Final data will be published</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

