<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04342039</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H20-00414</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04342039</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epigenetic Health Benefits of Budesonide</brief_title>
  <acronym>Project Ace</acronym>
  <official_title>Epigenetic Health Benefits of Budesonide</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genome British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer Inc. (J&amp;JCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Around 40% of the world's population is now impacted by allergic disease and this figure
      continues to rise. It is now understood that allergic disease arises from complex
      interactions between genetic and environmental factors. Exposure to allergens such as dust
      mites and pollen, as well as air pollutants such as diesel exhaust particulates, can alter
      the ability of critical genes to be expressed appropriately, a process known as epigenetic
      modification. The epigenetic modifications induced by allergens and pollutants appears to be
      reversible, thus providing a mechanism by which allergic disease can be treated. Budesonide
      (Rhinocort®) is a corticosteroid nasal spray commonly used to treat allergy symptoms. While
      the anti- inflammatory and other pharmacological aspects of budesonide are well understood,
      recent studies have suggested that budesonide may also work by reversing the epigenetic
      modifications caused by allergen exposure, although this has not been examined in the context
      of real-world exposures in humans.

      This study aims to harness the power of epigenetic analysis to determine whether the
      epigenetic landscape in patients suffering from allergic disease can be modified by the
      administration of budesonide. It will fill critical gaps in understanding of epigenetic
      effects and provide information to examine the connection between environmental impacts and
      treatment effects. The research will expand the mechanistic understanding of the therapeutic
      effects of budesonide for relief of nasal rhinitis symptoms and may reveal new mechanisms
      that could improve treatment of allergies or pollution exposure, or serve as a tool for
      evaluating future therapies. If this venture is successful, it will serve as a model for
      studying and optimizing the epigenetic effects of other treatments and other diseases.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To test this, the investigators have planned for two treatment trials where participants will
      act as both the control and tester (crossover design method). Participants will be provided a
      randomized treatment order of either 1) Budesonide (Rhinocort) or 2) placebo (no medication)
      nasal spray for the treatment trial. Participants will go through a series of nasal sampling,
      symptoms questionnaires, nasal inhalation flow readings during the in-person visits at the
      hospital. Investigators will also attempt to mimic allergen and pollution exposures, and
      track how the treatment affects one's nasal responses during visits. On days where
      participants do not have in-person visits, participants will continue using the treatment
      product on a daily basis. After one cycle of treatment, participants will go through a
      wash-out period before starting the second cycle with the opposite treatment (Budesonide
      (Rhinocort)/placebo).

      Investigators are not expecting that participants' responses to the treatments or exposures
      will be noticeable to the participants. Any responses that may occur will probably only be
      detectable through careful examination of the collected nasal samples on a genetic basis.
      However, being able to understand the subtle changes will help investigators optimize and
      better understand the use of these treatments in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will visit our lab for 2 trial cycles (each cycle involves one arm):
1) Budesonide, and 2) placebo. Within each cycle, there are periods with and without pollution exposure, so there is a secondary comparison of pre- versus post-pollution exposure.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Visually indistinguishable placebo and budesonide nasal sprays will be coded by research staff not connected to the study and pre-packaged for participants. All assays will be performed by personnel who do not know the exposure conditions of individual samples.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Budesonide affect on allergic rhinitis plus allergen (48 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in DNA methylation in the budesonide group compared with placebo.
DNA methylation measurement tool:
Illumina Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (interrogates 866,895 CpG sites across the human genome)
Unit of Measure:
For each targeted CpG site, the intensity of fluorescence will be translated into a level of DNA methylation which is either represented as a β value, a number between 0 and 1 (0 = no methylated, 1 = fully methylated) for visualization and interpretation, or a logit-transformed β value &quot;M value&quot; for statistical analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Budesonide affect on allergic rhinitis plus allergen (24 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in DNA methylation in the budesonide group compared with placebo.
DNA methylation measurement tool:
Illumina Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (interrogates 866,895 CpG sites across the human genome)
Unit of Measure:
For each targeted CpG site, the intensity of fluorescence will be translated into a level of DNA methylation which is either represented as a β value, a number between 0 and 1 (0 = no methylated, 1 = fully methylated) for visualization and interpretation, or a logit-transformed β value &quot;M value&quot; for statistical analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Budesonide affect on allergic rhinitis plus pollution (48 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in DNA methylation in the budesonide group compared with placebo.
DNA methylation measurement tool:
Illumina Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (interrogates 866,895 CpG sites across the human genome)
Unit of Measure:
For each targeted CpG site, the intensity of fluorescence will be translated into a level of DNA methylation which is either represented as a β value, a number between 0 and 1 (0 = no methylated, 1 = fully methylated) for visualization and interpretation, or a logit-transformed β value &quot;M value&quot; for statistical analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Budesonide affect on allergic rhinitis plus pollution (24 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in DNA methylation in the budesonide group compared with placebo.
DNA methylation measurement tool:
Illumina Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (interrogates 866,895 CpG sites across the human genome)
Unit of Measure:
For each targeted CpG site, the intensity of fluorescence will be translated into a level of DNA methylation which is either represented as a β value, a number between 0 and 1 (0 = no methylated, 1 = fully methylated) for visualization and interpretation, or a logit-transformed β value &quot;M value&quot; for statistical analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) (30 min)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 30-minute post allergen challenge</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline in Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) in the budesonide group compared with placebo 30 minutes after first allergen challenge. TNSS is evaluated on a scale of 0 to 12; with 0 being none and 12 being severe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF) (30 min)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 30-minute post allergen challenge</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline in PNIF in the budesonide group compared with placebo 30 minutes after first allergen challenge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) (48 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) in the budesonide group compared with placebo. TNSS is evaluated on a scale of 0 to 12; with 0 being none and 12 being severe.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) (24 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline Total Nasal Symptoms Score (TNSS) in the budesonide group compared with placebo. TNSS is evaluated on a scale of 0 to 12; with 0 being none and 12 being severe.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF) (48 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline PNIF in the budesonide group compared with placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF) (24 hrs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change from allergen baseline PNIF in the budesonide group compared with placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of Budesonide vs placebo in the absence of allergen or pollution challenge.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, approximately 4 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Change from treatment naïve baseline in DNA methylation attributable to intranasal budesonide compared with placebo in the absence of a nasal allergen or pollution challenge following 14 days of treatment.
DNA methylation measurement tool:
Illumina Infinium MethylationEPIC BeadChip (interrogates 866,895 CpG sites across the human genome)
Unit of Measure:
For each targeted CpG site, the intensity of fluorescence will be translated into a level of DNA methylation which is either represented as a β value, a number between 0 and 1 (0 = no methylated, 1 = fully methylated) for visualization and interpretation, or a logit-transformed β value &quot;M value&quot; for statistical analysis.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Epigenetic Effects of Intranasal Steroids</condition>
  <condition>Environmental Exposure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will use a placebo nasal spray before being exposed to a series of allergen and pollution challenges.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Budesonide nasal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will use budesonide nasal spray before being exposed to a series of allergen and pollution challenges.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Budesonide Nasal</intervention_name>
    <description>budesonide 64 mcg/spray; 2 sprays each nostril once daily on days as indicated in the timeline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Budesonide nasal</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rhinocort</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>2 sprays each nostril daily on days as indicated in the timeline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy men and women aged 18 - 65 years. (Female subjects must be postmenopausal,
             surgically sterile or using medically accepted contraceptive means, as judged by the
             investigator).

          -  Asymptomatic subjects (not experiencing rhinitis symptoms at the time of screening).

          -  A clinical diagnosis of allergic rhinitis (dust mite, grass mix or tree mix) for at
             least the previous two years.

          -  Subjects with a need of treatment for their nasal symptoms during the pollen season of
             such severity that it required pharmacological therapy each year for the last two
             consecutive years.

          -  Willingness to participate as indicated by a signed informed consent. Signed consent
             must be obtained from the subject prior to start of any study-related procedures.

          -  Availability and ability for all planned site visits

          -  A nasal allergen challenge resulting in at least five sneezes and/or a recorded score
             of &gt;2 in either nasal obstruction or runny nose

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with confirmed hypersensitivity to budesonide.

          -  Subjects with previous or current respiratory- cardiovascular-, renal-, liver-,
             endocrinological or other diseases or conditions which may influence the subject's
             participation in the study or the result hereof, as judged by the investigator.

          -  Subjects with a planned hospitalization or planned blood-donation during the study.

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing.

          -  Diseases or conditions which might interfere with the evaluation of efficacy and
             safety:

          -  Subjects with structural abnormalities of the nose (e.g. septal deviation, nasal
             polyps) or other diseases (infectious rhinitis, sinusitis, rhinitis medicamentosa and
             atrophic or non- allergic rhinitis) which could cause significant nasal obstruction or
             other symptoms which could have any significant influence on the investigated disease
             as judged by the investigator.

          -  History of asthma.

          -  PAR (with an exception, see inclusion criterion 3).

          -  Subjects allergic to other allergens occurring during the study period.

          -  Systemic corticosteroid use within 2 months, topical corticosteroid use within 2
             weeks, antihistamine use within 1 week, leukotriene antagonist use within one week or
             immunotherapy within 2 years of baseline visit (or stop at screening)

          -  Upper respiratory infection within 2 weeks of baseline visit

          -  Use of tobacco within 1 year of baseline

          -  Chronic medical condition that could interfere with evaluation of rhinitis endpoints
             (e.g. allergic skin conditions, active infections, asthma, etc.)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Carlsten, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Agnes Yuen, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>604-875-4111</phone>
    <phone_ext>66455</phone_ext>
    <email>agnes.yuen@ubc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christopher Carlsten</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Controlled Human Exposure Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Budesonide Nasal Spray</keyword>
  <keyword>Epigenetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene Expression</keyword>
  <keyword>Allergic Rhinitis</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Budesonide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

