<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04340401</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PKUCH-R04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04340401</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Total Neoadjuvant Treatment Plus SHR1210 for High-risk Rectal Cancer and Biomarker Screening Base on Neoantigen</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Total Neoadjuvant Chmoradiation Treatment Plus SHR1210 for High-risk Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer and Biomarker Screening Base on Neoantigen</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beijing Cancer Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beijing Cancer Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is designed to test the efficacy and safety of Total Neoadjuvant Treatment plus
      SHR1210（an anti-PD-1 Inhibitor) for High-risk locally advanced Rectal Cancer, Meanwhile,
      screening effective Biomarker base on neoantigen.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The combined treatment model of neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy treatment + radical rectal
      resection + adjuvant therapy has become the standard treatment model for locally advanced
      mid-low rectal cancer, However, the existing evidence shows that this comprehensive treatment
      method has reached the upper limit of efficacy and cannot continue to reduce the metastatic
      rate and improve the survival rate.

      Recent studies have shown that PD-1 antibody inhibitors have excellent curative effects on
      the treatment of a variety of tumors and have good safety.

      This study is a single-arm, single-center, prospective, phase II clinical study. It is
      designed to test the efficacy and safety of Total Neoadjuvant chmoradiation Treatment plus
      SHR1210 for High-risk locally advanced Rectal Cancer, Meanwhile, screening effective
      Biomarker base on neoantigen.

      In this study, patients with high-risk rectal cancer will receive 3 cycles induction CapeOX
      and SHR-1210, intensity modulated radiotherapy with concurrent capecitabine and 2 cycles
      consolidation CapeOX and total mesorectal excision.

      This study is designed to recruit 25 patients in all.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 25, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pathologic complete response rate(pCR rate)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The number of patients with pCR divided by the total number of patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of TNT+SHR-1210</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after neoadjuvant treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Category and grade of adverse event during neoadjuvant chemotherapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of TCR repertoire</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week before surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Use neoantigen model to find biomarkers related to the effect of TNT+SHR1210 for patients with rectal cancer; compare and analyze the differences in TCR repertoire changes in peripheral blood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The 3-year DFS will be defined as the percentage of patients alive without local recurrence or distant metastasis of disease at 3 years measured from the date of the administration of treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical complication rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of patients who had surgical complications during the perioperative period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after the last use of SHR-1210</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be graded using the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Version 4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with high-risk locally advanced rectal cancer will receive chemotherapy and SHR-1210 before chemoradiaton, after chemoradiaton, patient will receive consolidation chemotherapy. This arm is called Total Neoadjuvant Treatment (TNT) plus SHR-1210. The neoadjuvant chemotherapy regimen is designed as 3 cycles of CapeOX ( Capecitabine + Oxaliplatin ) plus SHR-1210 over a period of approximately 8 weeks. Tumor response will be evaluated after chemotherapy. Then patients will undergo 22f-IMRT (Intensity modulated radiotherapy) with capecitabine. Patients will receive two more cycles of consolidation CapeOX if tolerable when there was no progressed disease in induction CapeOX.
Finally, patients will receive TME (Total mesorectal excision) following TNT+SHR1210 if no metastasis occurs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SHR-1210</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive 3 cycles induction CapeOX and SHR-1210</description>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Camrelizumab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>CapeOX is a combination chemotherapy regimen with OXA and CAPE, patients with high-risk rectal cancer will receive 3 cycles induction CapeOX and SHR-1210, intensity modulated radiotherapy with concurrent capecitabine and 2 cycles consolidation CapeOX and total mesorectal excision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OXA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>CapeOX is a combination chemotherapy regimen with OXA and CAPE, patients with high-risk rectal cancer will receive 3 cycles induction CapeOX and SHR-1210, intensity modulated radiotherapy with concurrent capecitabine and 2 cycles consolidation CapeOX and total mesorectal excision.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CAPE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity modulated radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>patients will receive intensity modulated radiotherapy with capecitabine</description>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Total mesorectal excision</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive TME (Total mesorectal excision) following TNT+SHR1210 if no metastasis occurs.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TNT+SHR1210</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TME</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years and ≤70 years.

          -  ECOG Performance status 0-1.

          -  Histologically confirmed diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the rectum.

          -  The distance from down verge of tumor to anal-rectal junction (ARJ) ≤8cm, or ≤12 cm
             based on sigmoidoscopy.

          -  Clinical Stage T3c, T3d, T4a or T4b, or EMVI (+) or mrN2 or MRF (+) based on MRI.

          -  No evidence of distant metastases.

          -  No prior pelvic radiation therapy.

          -  No prior chemotherapy or surgery for rectal cancer.

          -  No active infections requiring systemic antibiotic treatment.

          -  No systemic infection requiring antibiotic treatment.

          -  No immune system disease.

          -  ANC &gt; 1.5 cells/mm3, HGB &gt; 9.0 g/dL, PLT &gt; 100,000/mm3, total bilirubin≤ 1.5×ULN, AST≤
             2.5×ULN, ALT ≤ 2.5×ULN.

          -  Serum creatinine is within 1.5 times the physiological range， creatinine clearance
             rate≥50 ml/min

          -  Patients with controllable hypertension were included.

          -  Patients who did not receive anticoagulant therapy: INR, aPTT is required to be within
             the 1.5 times the physiological range;Patients who receive anticoagulant therapy: INR,
             aPTT is required to be within the physiological range.

          -  FT3, FT4, TSH are Normal or abnormal without clinical significance.

          -  ECG examination is Normal or abnormal without clinical significance; Echocardiography
             shows that LVEF＞50%.

          -  Patients must read, agree to, and sign a statement of Informed Consent prior to
             participation in this study.

          -  Patients show good adherence, follow -up on time. It is recommended that all patients
             provide tumor tissue samples (preferably fresh tissue samples) for pathological
             genetic testing prior to enrollment.

          -  Fertile men or women with potential for pregnancy must use highly effective
             contraception throughout the trial. And continue contraception for 12 months after
             treatment ends.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrent rectal cancer.

          -  Anticipated unresectable tumor after neoadjuvant treatment.

          -  Patients with a history of a prior malignancy within the past 5 years, except for
             adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer.

          -  Patients with a history of any arterial thrombotic event within the past 6 months.
             This includes angina (stable or unstable), MI, TIA, or CVA.

          -  Other Anticancer or Experimental Therapy.

          -  Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding.

          -  Patients with any other concurrent medical or psychiatric condition or disease which
             would make them inappropriate candidates for entry into this study.

          -  Patients with a history of anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, anti-PD-L2 or CEGFR TKI therapy.

          -  Patients underwent major surgery or had not recovered from the side effects of this
             surgery, received a vaccine, received immunotherapy within 4 weeks before the first
             use of the study drug, and received radiotherapy within 2 weeks.

          -  Patients who received hematopoietic stimulating factors therapy, such as G-CSF and
             erythropoietin, within 1 week before the first administration of the study drug.

          -  Patients are allergic to study medication and its ingredients.

          -  Patients have active lung disease (such as interstitial pneumonia, pneumonia,
             obstructive pulmonary disease, asthma) or active tuberculosis.

          -  Patients have any uncontrollable clinical problems, including but not limited to:

               1. Persistent or severe infection.

               2. Hypertension that can't be effectively controlled by drugs（ blood pressure
                  reading of 150 over 90）.

               3. Uncontrolled diabetes

               4. Heart disease (Class III / IV congestive heart failure or cardiac block as
                  defined by the New York Heart Association)

               5. Patient has or is suspected of having an autoimmune disease,Such as pituitary
                  inflammation, colitis, hepatitis, nephritis, hyperthyroidism, hypothyroidism,
                  etc.

          -  Patients have other serious, acute or chronic diseases or have abnormal test results,
             and the investigator judges that this may increase the patient's risk of participating
             in the trial or interfere with the results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yingjie LI</last_name>
    <phone>+86 135 2018 6618</phone>
    <email>liyingjie@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beijing Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100142</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yingjie Li, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+86 135 2018 6618</phone>
      <email>liyingjiedr@sina.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aiwen Wu, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beijing Cancer Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aiwen Wu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Unit III &amp; Ostomy Service, Gastrointestinal Cancer center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>High-risk locally advanced Rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>SHR-1210</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Neoadjuvant chmoradiation Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>pCR rate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

