<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04343209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00042364</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04343209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ammonia N-13 Myocardial Blood Flow Absolute Quantification by PET in Patients With Known or Suspected CAD (Ammonia MAP)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ammonia N-13 Myocardial Blood Flow Absolute Quantification by Positron Emission Tomography in Patients With Known or Suspected Coronary Artery Disease (Ammonia MAP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ionetix Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ionetix Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being conducted to provide access to and collect test data for an established
      nuclear medicine diagnostic imaging test called Positron Emission Tomography (PET), using a
      specific radioactive drug called Ammonia N-13 (Ammonia), referred to simply as an Ammonia PET
      scan, which is used to visualize the blood flow through the blood vessels and into the heart
      muscle in order to identify areas of restricted blood flow within the heart. The scanner used
      in this study may be a stand-alone PET scanner or a PET/CT scanner, which combines the PET
      scanner and a Computed Tomography (CT) scanner into a single device. Unless otherwise stated
      in this consent form, the term PET will be used to refer to both stand-alone PET and PET/CT
      scanners. While physicians have used the Ammonia PET test for many years to visualize (image)
      the blood flow into the heart muscle (perfusion), it is now possible to also measure the flow
      of blood into the heart muscle. Research studies have demonstrated clinical value in
      reviewing the measured blood flow values in addition to reviewing the perfusion images of
      blood flow into the heart muscle. Therefore, this study will establish a database of a large
      number of Ammonia PET measured blood flow values to serve as a future reference.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, multicenter database that will be populated by sites utilizing N-13
      Ammonia and sponsored by Ionetix. Each site with access to N-13 produced under an
      investigational new drug (IND) application will be eligible to participate. Once the site is
      activated, the site will enroll patients into the database that are scheduled for clinically
      indicated PET-MPI with N-13 (as determined by their treating physicians). PET-MPI perfusion,
      MBF, percent ischemia, pharmacologic stress agent, and gated left ventricular ejection
      fraction/function values will be collected when available, in an anonymous fashion and
      uploaded into the database. All patient health identifiers (PHI) will be removed prior to
      upload. No procedures additional to those clinically indicated will be performed for the
      purposes of this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Establish the N-13 measured MBF (ml/g/min) value range</measure>
    <time_frame>an estimated average of 2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Non-invasive measurements of myocardial blood flow (MBF) in milliliter/minute/gram using PET/CT or PET scanner will be compared to invasive cardiac angiography values (current gold standard). MBF values are obtained using image-derived time activity curves from the left ventricular blood and myocardial tissue regions. These values represent radiotracer exchange between the blood and the tissue over time. The rate of radiotracer uptake into the myocardial tissue provides an estimate of MBF. Processing software will then use the time-activity curves to calculate MBF at rest and at stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2500</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with confirmed or suspected cardiovascular disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals in this group will undergo myocardial perfusion imaging, utilizing Ammonia N-13 PET imaging agent. Each individual will receive one or two intravenous injections of Ammonia N-13 in accordance with site imaging protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Myocardial Perfusion Imaging Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of myocardial perfusion via PET imaging agent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with confirmed or suspected cardiovascular disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMMONIA N-13 37.5 mCi in 1 mL INTRAVENOUS INJECTION [Ammonia N 13]</intervention_name>
    <description>Cardiac PET imaging agent</description>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with confirmed or suspected cardiovascular disease</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Individuals with confirmed or suspected cardiovascular disease
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Adults ≥18 able to give informed consent.

        Clinical indication for PET-MPI as determined by the subject's treating physician

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Any clinical contraindication for pharmacologic stress testing per ASNC/SNMMI/ACC
        myocardial perfusion imaging guidelines when stress perfusion imaging is required
        clinically.

        Inability or unwilling to give informed consent

        Pregnant subjects
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prem Soman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Consultant</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prem Soman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-647-3435</phone>
    <email>somanp@upmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Eve, BS</last_name>
    <phone>812-972-0673</phone>
    <email>regulatoryaffairs@ionetix.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adler Institute for Advanced Imaging</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jenkintown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19046</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Paccapaniccia, MPA, PA-C</last_name>
      <phone>215-935-0030</phone>
      <email>paccapaniccia@adlerimaging.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Karel Kovnat, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-935-0030</phone>
      <email>kovnat@adlerimaging.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lee Adler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Araujo LI, Lammertsma AA, Rhodes CG, McFalls EO, Iida H, Rechavia E, Galassi A, De Silva R, Jones T, Maseri A. Noninvasive quantification of regional myocardial blood flow in coronary artery disease with oxygen-15-labeled carbon dioxide inhalation and positron emission tomography. Circulation. 1991 Mar;83(3):875-85.</citation>
    <PMID>1900224</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bergmann SR, Herrero P, Markham J, Weinheimer CJ, Walsh MN. Noninvasive quantitation of myocardial blood flow in human subjects with oxygen-15-labeled water and positron emission tomography. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1989 Sep;14(3):639-52.</citation>
    <PMID>2788669</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sdringola S, Johnson NP, Kirkeeide RL, Cid E, Gould KL. Impact of unexpected factors on quantitative myocardial perfusion and coronary flow reserve in young, asymptomatic volunteers. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2011 Apr;4(4):402-12. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2011.02.008.</citation>
    <PMID>21492816</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Merlet P, Mazoyer B, Hittinger L, Valette H, Saal JP, Bendriem B, Crozatier B, Castaigne A, Syrota A, Randé JL. Assessment of coronary reserve in man: comparison between positron emission tomography with oxygen-15-labeled water and intracoronary Doppler technique. J Nucl Med. 1993 Nov;34(11):1899-904.</citation>
    <PMID>8229231</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kern MJ, Bach RG, Mechem CJ, Caracciolo EA, Aguirre FV, Miller LW, Donohue TJ. Variations in normal coronary vasodilatory reserve stratified by artery, gender, heart transplantation and coronary artery disease. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1996 Nov 1;28(5):1154-60.</citation>
    <PMID>8890809</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gewirtz H, Fischman AJ, Abraham S, Gilson M, Strauss HW, Alpert NM. Positron emission tomographic measurements of absolute regional myocardial blood flow permits identification of nonviable myocardium in patients with chronic myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1994 Mar 15;23(4):851-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8106689</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rivas F, Cobb FR, Bache RJ, Greenfield JC Jr. Relationship between blood flow to ischemic regions and extent of myocardial infarction. Serial measurement of blood flow to ischemic regions in dogs. Circ Res. 1976 May;38(5):439-47.</citation>
    <PMID>1269083</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Renaud JM, Yip K, Guimond J, Trottier M, Pibarot P, Turcotte E, Maguire C, Lalonde L, Gulenchyn K, Farncombe T, Wisenberg G, Moody J, Lee B, Port SC, Turkington TG, Beanlands RS, deKemp RA. Characterization of 3-Dimensional PET Systems for Accurate Quantification of Myocardial Blood Flow. J Nucl Med. 2017 Jan;58(1):103-109. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.116.174565. Epub 2016 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27539843</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Murthy VL, Naya M, Foster CR, Hainer J, Gaber M, Di Carli G, Blankstein R, Dorbala S, Sitek A, Pencina MJ, Di Carli MF. Improved cardiac risk assessment with noninvasive measures of coronary flow reserve. Circulation. 2011 Nov 15;124(20):2215-24. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.050427. Epub 2011 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22007073</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ziadi MC, Dekemp RA, Williams KA, Guo A, Chow BJ, Renaud JM, Ruddy TD, Sarveswaran N, Tee RE, Beanlands RS. Impaired myocardial flow reserve on rubidium-82 positron emission tomography imaging predicts adverse outcomes in patients assessed for myocardial ischemia. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Aug 9;58(7):740-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.01.065.</citation>
    <PMID>21816311</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ammonia N-13</keyword>
  <keyword>Positron Emission Tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>MBF</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial Perfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Ammonia N 13 Injection, USP</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary Artery Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

