<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04341961</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-001683</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04341961</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Pomegranate Juice Consumption on the Health of Mothers and Infants During Breastfeeding</brief_title>
  <acronym>PomInfant</acronym>
  <official_title>Observational Pilot Study on Pomegranate Metabolism in Breastfeeding Women and Their Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast milk is universally recognized as the best food for newborns. Studies have
      scientifically shown that breastfeeding provides optimal nutrients for infants, strengthens
      their immune system, and improves mother-and-child bonding. Demonstrating health benefits of
      pomegranate consumption on infant health could lead to greater incentive for women to breast
      feed. The purpose of this research study is to determine whether pomegranate metabolites
      (products produced by breakdown) is secreted into breastmilk and whether they have an effect
      on breast-fed infants who are born vaginally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will require participants to continue with their usual diet and to avoid
      pomegranate juice (other than what is provided), berries (strawberries, blackberries,
      raspberries (red, black, yellow), cranberries), walnuts, pecans, hazelnuts, pecans,
      chestnuts, red and white guava, pomegranates, flaxseeds, dark chocolate and cocoa, coffee,
      tea, rose hip, olives, artichoke, dried herbs and beefsteak tongue mushrooms) . They will be
      asked to consume the pomegranate juice daily for 14 days. The pomegranate juice will be
      provided to participants. If the participants are unable to complete the study on the 14th
      day they will be asked to continue drinking the juice until they are able to complete the
      visit. For instance if day 14 falls on a Friday and they cannot come in until Monday
      participants will be asked to continue drinking the juice until Monday. Participants will be
      asked to collect 10ml (or 2 tsp) of breast milk; the collection materials will be provided,
      and participant will need to store the specimen in their home refrigerator and dropped off to
      the study site within 18-24 hours of the collection time. Participants will also be
      instructed to collect their stool and will be provided with the sterile collection materials
      and instructions for collection. Participants will be provided with a disposable cooler and
      ice packs to keep the specimen refrigerated during transport. Participants will also be
      provided with a urine collection container and asked to collect all of your urine over a
      24-hour period (on 2 separate occasions). Lastly, infant stool and urine will also be
      collected using collection bags with an adhesive strip.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 8, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 23, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pomegranate Juice Metabolism</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To examine the metabolism of pomegranate by analyzing blood, urine, breast milk and stool samples for ellagic acid and urolithin levels before and after administration of pomegranate extract for 2 weeks during breastfeeding in healthy mothers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether pomegranate metabolites are bioavailable to breastfed infants by analyzing ellagic acid in urine and stool from infants of mothers consuming PJ.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether pomegranate metabolites are bioavailable to breastfed infants by analyzing urolithin in urine and stool from infants of mothers consuming PJ.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Breastfeeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pom Juice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study participants will all be asked to drink pomegranate juice for 2 weeks, and 4 weeks of continued usual diet and avoid pomegranate juice (other than what is given to you), berries (strawberries, blackberries, raspberries (red, black, yellow), cranberries), walnuts, pecans, hazelnuts, pecans, chestnuts, red and white guava, pomegranates, flaxseeds, dark chocolate and cocoa, coffee, tea, rose hip, olives, artichoke, dried herbs and beefsteak tongue mushrooms).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pomegranate Juice</intervention_name>
    <description>Drinking 8 oz of pomegranate juice daily for 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pom Juice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Postpartum 6 months with full term baby born vaginally and exclusively breast feeding

          -  In good health

          -  Subjects must read and sign the Institutional Review Board-approved written informed
             consent prior to the initiation of any study specific procedures or enrollment. A
             subject will be excluded for any condition that might compromise the ability to give
             truly informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  No antibiotics or laxatives use during the 2 months before the study.

          -  Any subject consuming pre- or probiotics or anti-inflammatory medication

          -  Any subject with a screening laboratory value outside of the laboratory normal range
             that is considered clinically significant for study participation by the investigator.

          -  Any subject who is unable or unwilling to comply with the study protocol.

          -  Allergic to pomegranate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhaoping Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCLA Professor of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gail Thames</last_name>
    <phone>310-825-0453</phone>
    <email>gthames@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dina Ben-Nissan</last_name>
    <phone>310-206-2582</phone>
    <email>Dbennissan@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Center for Human Nutrition, 1000 Veteran Ave.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gail Thames</last_name>
      <email>gthames@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dina Ben-Nissan</last_name>
      <phone>310-206-2582</phone>
      <email>dbennissan@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Center for Human Nutrition, 1000 Veteran Ave.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gail Thames</last_name>
      <phone>310-825-0453</phone>
      <email>gthames@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dina Ben-Nissan</last_name>
      <phone>310-206-2582</phone>
      <email>dbennissan@mednet.ucla.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhaoping Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>pomegranate</keyword>
  <keyword>breastmilk</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

