<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04340700</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020P000055</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04340700</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterization of the Pharmacodynamic Response to Vaped THC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterization of the Pharmacodynamic Response to Vaped THC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to characterize the pharmacodynamic response to vaped THC in young adult,
      occasional cannabis users with respect to outcomes such as stimulation and sedative effects,
      mood, anxiety, and craving, as well as cognitive and objective outcomes such as heart rate
      and cortisol changes with THC vs placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Enrollees will include 120 healthy, weekly or greater MJ users, aged 18-55. The study will be
      conducted according to a double-blind, placebo-controlled, random order, cross-over design,
      consisting of one 3-hour screening visit and 2 randomized, approximately 6-hour laboratory
      sessions. At the latter visits (following confirmation of eligibility), subjects will
      complete baseline questionnaires and assessments, including a driver simulator test, a blood
      draw, vitals, and an imaging session using functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS).
      Subjects will then vape a first dose (either THC or placebo based on randomization). Vitals
      and questionnaires will then be administered throughout the visit, at baseline, and at
      approximately 15, 60, 90, 130, 165, and 210 minutes post initial dose. Subjects will also
      perform fNIRS testing at baseline, 30, and 180 minutes and driver simulator at baseline, 60,
      and 90 minutes post initial THC/placebo administration. A drug recognition expert (DRE) will
      conduct a standard field sobriety test to identify impairment at approximately 130 minutes
      post dose. Following the initial dose vaped at 0 minutes, standardized reduced doses will be
      vaped approximately 30, 60, and 90 minutes later. Given the cross-over design of this study,
      participants will be assigned to receive THC or placebo at the first laboratory visit and
      will receive the other substance at the second laboratory visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Drug Effects Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, and 15, 60, 90, 130, 165, 210 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>This 15-item questionnaire measures drug effects, behavioral/mood states, and craving. Each item is scored from 0-100, and all items are averaged for a total score from 0-100 with higher scores indicating greater drug effect.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Biphasic Alcohol Effects Scale (Modified for THC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, and 15, 60, 90, 130, 165, 210 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>This 14-item questionnaire measures stimulation and sedation. The Stimulation subscale scores range from 7-70 with higher scores indicating greater stimulation. The Sedation subscale scores range from 7-70 with higher scores indicating greater sedation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Spielberger State Anxiety Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, and 15, 60, 90, 130, 165, 210 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>This 20-item questionnaire measures state/current anxiety. Scores range from 20-80 with higher scores indicating greater state anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Driving Simulation Performance on the Divided Attention Task (DAT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, and 60 and 90 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>A computer-programmed driving simulator will assess DAT performance using percentage impaired (from 0-100%).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Functional Near-Infrared Spectroscopy (fNIRS) Brain Signal</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-dose, and 30 and 180 minutes post dose</time_frame>
    <description>fNIRS measures oxygenated hemoglobin (HbO) during both resting state and a working memory task in both THC and placebo conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaping</condition>
  <condition>THC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>THC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A standard dose of THC (8 mg or 2 mg) will be placed in a Volcano Vaporizer chamber. The first THC dose is 8 mg, followed by approximately three doses of 2 mg each.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will also be administered through a Volcano Vaporizer via inhalation. The first placebo dose is 8 mg, followed by approximately three doses of 2 mg each to match the THC procedures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>THC or Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A standard dose of THC (8 mg or 2 mg) will be placed in a Volcano Vaporizer chamber. The first THC dose is 8 mg, followed by approximately three doses of 2 mg each. Placebo will also be administered through a Volcano Vaporizer via inhalation. The first placebo dose is 8 mg, followed by approximately three doses of 2 mg each to match the THC procedures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>THC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women aged 18-55 years, inclusive.

          -  Competent and willing to provide written informed consent.

          -  Able to communicate in English language.

          -  Regular, at least weekly on average, marijuana use

          -  Self-reported ability to abstain from cannabis for 24 hours without withdrawal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any unstable, serious medical illness or cardiovascular disease/events.

          -  New or unstable psychiatric symptoms, schizophrenia, or bipolar I disorder.

          -  Diabetes, cirrhosis, renal failure, Hepatitis C, or HIV.

          -  History of syncope without an identified situational stressor, migraines &gt;1x/month, or
             head injury with prolonged unconsciousness (&gt; 24 hours).

          -  Daily use of benzodiazepines or barbiturates, antihistamines, atropine, scopolamine,
             or other strong anticholinergic agents.

          -  Current pregnancy, lactation or trying to become pregnant (confirmed by urine
             pregnancy test).

          -  History of substance abuse treatment and intent to quit or receiving treatment for
             cannabis use.

          -  Affective disorder in the past month or history of panic attacks.

          -  Smoking more than 10 tobacco cigarettes or equivalent e-cigarettes a day.

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, not able to safely participate in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gladys N Pachas, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6176431991</phone>
    <email>gpachas1@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Eden Evins, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-4699</phone>
    <email>aeevins@mgh.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>A. Eden Evins</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Center for Addiction Medicine; Professor in Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaping</keyword>
  <keyword>THC</keyword>
  <keyword>fNIRS</keyword>
  <keyword>Cannabis</keyword>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

