<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04343391</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Brief-Psychotherapies</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04343391</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Brief Psychotherapies for Emotional Disorders in Primary and Secondary Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brief Psychotherapies for Emotional Disorders in Primary and Secondary Care: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidad de Córdoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidad de Córdoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present work aims to develop a randomized clinical trial with a sample of 150 patients
      diagnosed with at least one of the following emotional disorder: somatoform disorder, panic
      disorder, generalized anxiety disorder and depression disorder. Participants are tested by
      several self-reports related to the emocional disorders mentioned in a repeated measures
      design, pre and post treatment. The investigators think this study will demonstrate that
      brief psychological treatments should be prioritized over pharmacological treatment for such
      pathologies in the Primary or Secondary Care context to improve the patient´s quality of
      life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nowadays, the heavy demands placed on health systems exceed the resources in many developed
      countries. So-called &quot;emotional disorders&quot; and their mostly pharmacological treatment are, in
      no small part, responsible for this situation. However, research indicates that psychological
      treatment should be the first step when caring for these types of problems. The investigators
      expect that the results show that brief psychological therapies are more effective than
      pharmacological interventions. Moreover, it is expected that brief individual psychotherpay
      approach delivered in secondary care is more effective than brief group psychotherapy
      delivered in primary care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-15)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire-Somatoform Disorder is a self-administered version of the PRIME-MD diagnostic instrument for common mental disorders.The PHQ-15 is the somatization module, which scores each DSM-IV criteria as &quot;0&quot; (not bothered at all) to &quot;2&quot; (bothered a lot). The more score the more severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory is a commonly used measure of trait and state anxiety (Spielberger, Gorsuch, Lushene, Vagg, &amp; Jacobs, 1983). It can be used in clinical settings to diagnose anxiety and to distinguish it from depressive syndromes. It also is often used in research as an indicator of caregiver distress AnxietyForm Y, its most popular version, has 20 items for assessing trait anxiety and 20 for state anxiety. All items are rated on a 4-point scale (e.g., from &quot;Almost Never&quot; to &quot;Almost Always&quot;). Higher scores indicate greater anxiety. The STAI is appropriate for those who have at least a sixth-grade reading level. Internal consistency coefficients for the scale have ranged from .86 to .95; test-retest reliability coefficients have ranged from .65 to .75 over a 2-month interval (Spielberger et al., 1983).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Beck Depression Inventory (second edition) is a widely used 21-item self-report inventory measuring the severity of depression in adolescents and adults. The BDI-II was revised in 1996 to be more consistent with DSM-IV criteria for depression. For example, individuals are asked to respond to each question based on a two-week time period rather than the one-week timeframe on the BDI. The BDI-II is widely used as an indicator of the severity of depression, but not as a diagnostic tool, and numerous studies provide evidence for its reliability and validity across different populations and cultural groups. The more score the more depression severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire-Depression is a self-administered version of the PRIME-MD diagnostic instrument for common mental disorders.The PHQ-9 is the depression module, which scores each of the 9 DSM-IV criteria as &quot;0&quot; (not at all) to &quot;3&quot; (nearly every day). The more score the more severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-PD)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire-Panic Disorder is a self-administered version of the PRIME-MD diagnostic instrument for common mental disorders.The PHQ-PD is the panic disorder module, which scores each DSM-IV criteria as &quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot;. Higher scores mean greater severity of panic disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalized Anxiety Disorder score (GAD-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Generalized Anxiety Disorder score is calculated by assigning scores of 0, 1, 2, and 3, to the response categories of 'not at all', 'several days', 'more than half the days', and 'nearly every day', respectively, and adding together the scores for the seven questions. Scores of 5, 10, and 15 are taken as the cut-off points for mild, moderate and severe anxiety, respectively. When used as a screening tool, further evaluation is recommended when the score is 10 or greater. Using the threshold score of 10, the GAD-7 has a sensitivity of 89% and a specificity of 82% for GAD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI-18)</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Symptom Inventory contains the three six-item scales somatization, depression, and anxiety as well as the Global Severity Index (GSI), including all 18 items. The BSI-18 is the latest and shortest of the multidimensional versions of the Symptom-Checklist 90-R. The more score the more symptoms patients report.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Emotional Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brief Individual Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individual brief psychological intervention by adaptation of the Guide NICE &quot;Common Mental Health Disorders&quot; (ISBN 978-1-84936-585-7) and the unified protocol for the trasndiagnostic treatment of the emotional disorders of Barlow (Boisseau, Farchione, Fairholme, Ellard, y Barlow, 2010). This intervention is provided by clinical psychologist in secondary care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brief Group Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group brief psychological intervention by adaptation of the Guide NICE &quot;Common Mental Health Disorders&quot; (ISBN 978-1-84936-585-7) and the unified protocol for the trasndiagnostic treatment of the emotional disorders of Barlow (Boisseau, Farchione, Fairholme, Ellard, y Barlow, 2010). This intervention is provided by clinical psychologist in primary care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Medication provided by a general practitioner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Brief transdiagnostic cognitive-behavioral therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Time-limited transdiagnostic evidence-based psychological treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Brief Group Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Brief Individual Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment as usual in PC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as usual</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Emotional Disorder

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe mental disorder

          -  Substance use disorder

          -  Severe depression
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidad de Córdoba</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cordoba</city>
        <state>Córdoba</state>
        <zip>14071</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidad de Córdoba</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jorge Corpas López</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Reseracher in Clinical Psychology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

