<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04341077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHR3162-I-114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04341077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Single-Dose Fluzoparib in Healthy Chinese Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, One-Center Study to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Single-Dose Fluzoparib in Healthy Chinese Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jiangsu HengRui Medicine Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jiangsu HengRui Medicine Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study to Evaluate the Safety and Pharmacokinetics of Single-Dose Fluzoparib in Healthy
      Chinese Subjects
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a single-center, open-label, single dosing Fluzoparib study in healthy
      Chinese subjects to evaluate the pharmacokinetics and safety
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 20, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Time of the observed maximum plasma concentration of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed plasma concentration of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from the time zero to the last quantifiable concentration of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>• Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero extrapolated to infinity of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>T1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal plasma elimination half-life of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CL/F</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent clearance of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vz/F</measure>
    <time_frame>from Day1 to Day4</time_frame>
    <description>Apparent volume of distribution of SHR3162</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Adult Male and Female Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SHR3162</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single dose of fluzoparib was administered orally</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SHR3162</intervention_name>
    <description>A single oral dose of fluzoparib on Day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>SHR3162</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy Chinese subjects, male and female, 18 to 45 years of age, inclusive, and in
             good health as determined by past medical history, physical examination, vital signs,
             electrocardiogram, and laboratory tests;

          -  Male body weight ≥50 kg, female body weight ≥45 kg, body mass index (BMI) between
             ≥18.0 and ≤29.0 kg/m2, inclusive;

          -  Female subjects agree not to be pregnant or lactating from beginning of the study
             screening to 90 days after trial completion:

               -  A negative blood and urine pregnancy test for females of childbearing potential
                  at Screening and at Check-in, respectively;

               -  Females of reproductive potential are willing and able to employ a highly
                  effective method of birth control/contraception to prevent pregnancy; A highly
                  effective method of contraception is defined as one that results in a low failure
                  rate (ie, less than 1% per year), when used consistently and correctly. Females
                  of non-childbearing potential will not be required to use contraception. Females
                  of non-child bearing potential are defined as permanently sterile (eg, due to
                  hysterectomy) or postmenopausal (defined as at least 12 months following
                  cessation of menses without an alternative medical cause and serum FSH levels &gt;25
                  IU/L).

          -  Males agree to refrain from donating sperm and fathering a child during the study and
             for at least 90 days after fluzoparib administration; male participants must agree to
             remain abstinent or must ensure a condom is used for all sexual activity (with a male
             or female partner) for this same duration.

          -  Able and willing to refrain from caffeine or caffeine-containing products, alcohol,
             fruit juices, and smoking/tobacco products from at least 48 hours prior to Check-In
             until the end of Safety Follow Up;

          -  Able and willing to refrain from eating and drinking poppy seed-containing products
             and grapefruit-related citrus fruits (eg, Seville oranges, pomelos) within 7 days
             prior to dosing until after collection of the final PK blood sample (Day 4);

          -  Able and willing to refrain from strenuous exercise (heavy lifting, weight training,
             calisthenics, aerobics) within 7 days prior to dosing until after collection of the
             final PK blood sample (Day 4);

          -  Willing and able to comply with all scheduled visits, study procedures, and provides
             written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence or history of clinically significant hematological, renal, endocrine,
             pulmonary, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, hepatic, neuropsychiatric disease, or any
             condition that may affect drug absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion;

          -  Had a severe infection, trauma or major surgery within 4 weeks of screening and at
             Check-In; plan to have a surgery during the trial;

          -  A past medical history of ECG abnormalities, documented cardiac arrhythmias, or
             cardiovascular disease; or QTcF interval &gt;450 msec for males, &gt;470 msec for females,
             or &lt;300 msec;

          -  Subject's systolic blood pressure (SBP) is &gt;140 or &lt;90 mmHg, diastolic blood pressure
             (DBP) is &gt;90 or &lt;50 mmHg, resting heart rate &lt;40 or &gt;100 bpm, and respiratory rate &lt;10
             or &gt;20 breaths/min at Screening or Check-in after resting in a semi-supine position
             for 5 minutes. Vitals can be repeated twice (a minimum of 1 to 2 minutes apart) based
             on the investigator's judgment;

          -  History of immunodeficiency including seropositivity for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV), or other acquired or congenital immune-deficient disease, or any active
             systemic viral infection requiring therapy (eg, hepatitis B or C);

          -  Subject has a history of type 1 hypersensitivity to any medication;

          -  Subject has evidence of substance abuse, a history of substance abuse, or is positive
             for drugs of abuse (eg, methamphetamines, opiates, methadone, cocaine, amphetamines,
             cannabinoids, tricyclic antidepressants, phencyclidine, barbiturates,
             benzodiazepines), or alcohol at Screening and Check-in (Day -1);

          -  History of symptomatic hypoglycemia;

          -  Subjects who smoke more than 5 cigarettes per day or will not refrain from smoking
             starting from at least 48 hours prior to screening and check-in on Day -1, and during
             the study;

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption in the past 3 months exceeding an average
             weekly intake of 14 standard drinks; 1 drink=5 ounces [150 mL] of wine or 12 ounces
             [360 mL] of beer or 1.5 ounces [45 mL] of hard liquor;

          -  Subject has used prescription medications within 14 days or, as per PI discretion,
             over-the-counter medications, dietary/nutritional supplements (except hormonal
             contraceptives, paracetamol under 2 grams/day, vitamin supplements) within 7 days or 5
             half-lives prior to fluzoparib administration;

          -  Treatment with any investigational drug within 3 months (or 5 half-lives, whichever is
             longer) of dosing;

          -  Use of medications affecting liver metabolism within 1 month of screening;

          -  Blood donation or loss of more than 200 mL of blood within 1 month of screening; or
             blood donation or loss of more than 400 mL of blood within 3 months of screening; or
             received blood within 8 weeks of screening;

          -  Any other major illness/condition that, in the investigator's judgment, substantially
             increased the risk associated with the subject's participation in and completion of
             the study or could preclude the evaluation of the subject's response.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yuya Wang, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+86-13918749176</phone>
    <email>wangyuya@hrglobe.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jie Sun</last_name>
    <phone>+86-15921538635</phone>
    <email>sunjie@hrglobe.cn</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

