<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04340752</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-01995</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04340752</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal Dosing of IC-Green for Visualization of Rotator Cuff Vascularity Using Advanced Imaging Modality Arthroscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimal Dosing of IC-Green for Visualization of Rotator Cuff Vascularity Using Advanced Imaging Modality Arthroscopy: A Prospective, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NYU Langone Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NYU Langone Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rotator cuff re-tear is a common delayed complication of arthroscopic rotator cuff repair.
      This process of re-tear is multifactorial and there has not been any readily identifiable
      perioperative measure that is predictive of subsequent rotator cuff failure. There have been
      no human studies looking at intraoperative assessment of rotator cuff vascularity, nor the
      predictive value that vascularity may have for rotator cuff re-tear. Indocyanine Green (ICG)
      has been safely used in patients for visualization purposes and has real potential for
      identifying vascularity in arthroscopic surgical patients. The aim of this study is to
      establish a standard dosing protocol for ICG in the arthroscopic visualization of rotator
      cuff vascularity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary study objective is to determine optimal dosing of an intravenous fluorescence
      solution (IC-Green) for arthroscopic evaluation of rotator cuff vascularity. The primary
      endpoint is surgeon's ability to assess vascularity within the rotator cuff based on a
      5-point likert scale. The likert values from each of the three doses will undergo an ANOVA
      test to compare means of the three doses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Optimal dosing of an intravenous fluorescence solution (ICG) for arthroscopic evaluation of rotator cuff vascularity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months post operative visit</time_frame>
    <description>Advanced Imaging Modality (AIM) arthroscopy videos for each dosing arm will be collected and five signal intensity readings will be collected from the rotator cuff within each video. The ability to visualize rotator cuff vascularity will be graded by surgeons blinded to the ICG dosing using a 5 point Likert scale where 1 indicates worst visibility and 5 indicates best visibility. Post-hoc ANOVA analysis of surgeons' responses to determine what dose of ICG is optimal for the surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Tears</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1:ICG 7.5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group are randomized to receive 7.5 mg dose of Indocyanine Green (ICG) intravenously during the clinical surgery. ICG is a substance that binds to proteins in the blood and allows surgery teams to view blood vessels with greater precision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2:ICG 12.5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group are randomized to receive 12.5 mg dose of Indocyanine Green (ICG) intravenously during the clinical surgery. ICG is a substance that binds to proteins in the blood and allows surgery teams to view blood vessels with greater precision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: ICG 25 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this group are randomized to receive 25 mg dose of Indocyanine Green (ICG) intravenously during the clinical surgery. ICG is a substance that binds to proteins in the blood and allows surgery teams to view blood vessels with greater precision.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indocyanine Green</intervention_name>
    <description>ICG is an injectable fluorescent pigment that binds to proteins in the blood and allows surgery teams to view blood vessels with greater precision. The ICG will not affect the course of the operative or postoperative period, and will be injected intravenously prior to the actual repair</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1:ICG 7.5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2:ICG 12.5 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: ICG 25 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients has full or partial thickness rotator cuff tear and is scheduled to undergo
             arthroscopic rotator cuff repair

          -  Patient is at least 18 years of age and less than 80 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is less than 18 years of age or greater than 79 years of age

          -  Patient has a documented allergy to iodides

          -  Patients who have had iodide based radiology studies within the last seven (7) days
             prior to surgery

          -  Patient is pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirk Campbell</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eoghan Hurley</last_name>
    <phone>646-467-0851</phone>
    <email>Eoghan.Hurley@nyulangone.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie the results reported in this article, after deidentification (text, tables, figures, and appendices).</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 9 months and ending 36 months following article publication or as required by a condition of awards and agreements supporting the research.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The investigator who proposed to use the data. Upon reasonable request. Requests should be directed to kirk.campbell@nyulangone.org. To gain access, data requestors will need to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

