<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04346706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FMD124</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04346706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immediate Implant Placement in Fresh Extraction Sockets and Delayed Implants in Healed Sockets.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Radiographic Evaluation of Marginal Bone Level, Buccal and Palatal Plate Thickness Alteration, and Implant Stability After Placement in Healed Ridges and Fresh Extraction Sockets: A 6 Months Prospective Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saint-Joseph University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saint-Joseph University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this prospective clinical study was to compare in delayed and immediately
      placed implants, the marginal vertical bone loss at 4 sides of the implant (buccal, palatal,
      mesial and distal), as well as the buccal and palatal bone thickness reduction at 3 months
      after loading.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty-four patients were consecutively selected and enrolled in this study based on the
      aforementioned exclusion and inclusion criteria. Clinical examination was done by a different
      clinician than the operator, and according to the treatment indication, patients were
      allocated to the delayed implant placement group (Control), or the immediate implant
      placement group (Test). Thus, 15 implants were placed in healed extraction sites and
      immediately temporized (Control group), and 15 implants were placed in immediate extraction
      sites with immediate temporization (Test group).

      Provisional acrylic crowns were prepared. All patients were placed on a prophylactic
      antibiotic regimen, starting one day prior to surgery as they were asked to take amoxicillin
      500 mg; three times a day for 10 days or clindamycin 300 mg twice daily for 10 days for
      penicillin-allergic patients.

      For the test group, tooth extractions were carried out atraumatically using periotomes. In
      both groups, the implant site preparation was completed in compliance with the general
      surgical principles and protocols defined by the manufacturer and screw-shaped implants
      (UFII, DIO™) were inserted at no less than 35 Ncm.

      Temporary abutments were connected to the implants and torqued at 20 Ncm, and then temporary
      crowns were cemented on top of the abutments after checking and reducing occlusion to
      non-existent in both centric and lateral excursions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 25, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The radiographic measurements were done by a different clinician than the surgeon</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of marginal vertical bone level at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Following procedure at day 0 (implant insertion) and 6 months (post-implantation)</time_frame>
    <description>Marginal vertical bone level changes at 4 sides of the implant (buccal, palatal, mesial and distal) on Cone Beam Computed Tomography (CBCT) images</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of bone plate thickness at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Following procedure at day 0 (implant insertion) and 6 months (post-implantation)</time_frame>
    <description>Buccal and palatal bone thickness at 4 levels : 0 mm, 2 mm, 4 mm and 6 mm from the implant platform on CBCT images</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline of implant stability quotient at 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Following procedure at day 0 (implant insertion) and 3 months (post-implantation)</time_frame>
    <description>Measurements of implant stability quotient (ISQ) following implant insertion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Record of insertion torque</measure>
    <time_frame>Following procedure at day 0 (implant insertion)</time_frame>
    <description>Insertion torque value at implant placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Tooth Extraction</condition>
  <condition>Dental Implantation</condition>
  <condition>Bone Remodeling</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate implantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tooth extraction, immediate insertion of an implant with immediate temporization</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed implantation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implant inserted in a healed socket with immediate temporization</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extraction and Implant insertion (test)</intervention_name>
    <description>The surgical procedure was conducted under local anesthesia. Intrasulcular incisions were performed around the mesial and distal tooth to the implant recipient site. Buccal and palatal mucoperiosteal flaps were elevated. Tooth extractions were carried out atraumatically using periotomes. Implant site preparation was completed in compliance with the general surgical principles and protocols defined by the manufacturer and screw-shaped implants (UFII, DIO™) were inserted at no less than 35 Ncm. Final insertion torque (IT) was measured and recorded using a manual hand wrench (DIO™). Resonance frequency analysis (RFA) was performed using an Osstell device (Sävedalen, Sweden). For each implant, three Implant Stability Quotient (ISQ) readings were recorded by the same operator to calculate the mean ISQ, at implant placement (T0) and 3 months after implant insertion (T3) prior to final abutment torque and crown cementation.
Absorbable interrupted 4.0 sutures were used for flap closure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate implantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Implant insertion (control)</intervention_name>
    <description>The surgical procedure was conducted under local anesthesia. Intrasulcular incisions were performed around the mesial and distal tooth to the implant recipient site. Buccal and palatal mucoperiosteal flaps were elevated, the implant site preparation was completed in compliance with the general surgical principles and protocols defined by the manufacturer and screw-shaped implants (UFII, DIO™) were inserted at no less than 35 Ncm. Final insertion torque (IT) was measured and recorded using a manual hand wrench (DIO™). Resonance frequency analysis (RFA) was performed using an Osstell device (Sävedalen, Sweden). For each implant, three Implant Stability Quotient (ISQ) readings were recorded by the same operator to calculate the mean ISQ. This was done at implant placement (T0) and 3 months after implant insertion (T3) prior to final abutment torque and crown cementation.
Absorbable interrupted 4.0 sutures were used for flap closure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Delayed implantation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults over 18 years old, compliant (willing to show up to all their follow-up
             visits), and able to read, understand and sign an informed consent. All patients were
             to have good oral hygiene levels (full mouth plaque scores (FMPS) &lt;15-20%, and full
             mouth bleeding index (FMBI) &lt;15-20%), requiring implant insertion in a maxillary
             premolar site either immediately or in a healed &quot;pristine bone&quot;.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of major contraindications to implant surgery, patients that had received
             head and neck radiation for cancer treatment, immunosuppressed or immunocompromised
             patients, uncontrolled diabetes, pregnant or breast-feeding woman, untreated
             periodontitis and/or poor oral hygiene and motivation, presence of buccal dehiscence,
             and finally previous bone grafting or ridge preservation in the studied area.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nada Naaman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Saint-Joseph University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint-Joseph University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beirut</city>
        <zip>1104 2020</zip>
        <country>Lebanon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lebanon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peñarrocha-Diago M, Demarchi CL, Maestre-Ferrín L, Carrillo C, Peñarrocha-Oltra D, Peñarrocha-Diago MA. A retrospective comparison of 1,022 implants: immediate versus nonimmediate. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2012 Mar-Apr;27(2):421-7.</citation>
    <PMID>22442783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim JK, Yoon HJ. Clinical and radiographic outcomes of immediate and delayed placement of dental implants in molar and premolar regions. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2017 Aug;19(4):703-709. doi: 10.1111/cid.12496. Epub 2017 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28517552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atieh MA, Alsabeeha NH, Duncan WJ, de Silva RK, Cullinan MP, Schwass D, Payne AG. Immediate single implant restorations in mandibular molar extraction sockets: a controlled clinical trial. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2013 May;24(5):484-96. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0501.2011.02415.x. Epub 2012 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22276690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mello CC, Lemos CAA, Verri FR, Dos Santos DM, Goiato MC, Pellizzer EP. Immediate implant placement into fresh extraction sockets versus delayed implants into healed sockets: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2017 Sep;46(9):1162-1177. doi: 10.1016/j.ijom.2017.03.016. Epub 2017 May 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28478869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindeboom JA, Tjiook Y, Kroon FH. Immediate placement of implants in periapical infected sites: a prospective randomized study in 50 patients. Oral Surg Oral Med Oral Pathol Oral Radiol Endod. 2006 Jun;101(6):705-10. Epub 2006 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>16731387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowan M, Lee D, Pi-Anfruns J, Shiffler P, Aghaloo T, Moy PK. Mechanical versus biological stability of immediate and delayed implant placement using resonance frequency analysis. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2015 Feb;73(2):253-7. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2014.09.024. Epub 2014 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25579008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esposito M, Zucchelli G, Cannizzaro G, Checchi L, Barausse C, Trullenque-Eriksson A, Felice P. Immediate, immediate-delayed (6 weeks) and delayed (4 months) post-extractive single implants: 1-year post-loading data from a randomised controlled trial. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2017;10(1):11-26.</citation>
    <PMID>28327692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berberi AN, Sabbagh JM, Aboushelib MN, Noujeim ZF, Salameh ZA. A 5-year comparison of marginal bone level following immediate loading of single-tooth implants placed in healed alveolar ridges and extraction sockets in the maxilla. Front Physiol. 2014 Jan 31;5:29. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2014.00029. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>24550840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buser D, Janner SF, Wittneben JG, Brägger U, Ramseier CA, Salvi GE. 10-year survival and success rates of 511 titanium implants with a sandblasted and acid-etched surface: a retrospective study in 303 partially edentulous patients. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2012 Dec;14(6):839-51.</citation>
    <PMID>22897683</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Östman PO, Hellman M, Sennerby L. Ten years later. Results from a prospective single-centre clinical study on 121 oxidized (TiUnite™) Brånemark implants in 46 patients. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2012 Dec;14(6):852-60. doi: 10.1111/j.1708-8208.2012.00453.x. Epub 2012 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22642261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romeo E, Lops D, Margutti E, Ghisolfi M, Chiapasco M, Vogel G. Long-term survival and success of oral implants in the treatment of full and partial arches: a 7-year prospective study with the ITI dental implant system. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2004 Mar-Apr;19(2):247-59.</citation>
    <PMID>15101597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Covani U, Chiappe G, Bosco M, Orlando B, Quaranta A, Barone A. A 10-year evaluation of implants placed in fresh extraction sockets: a prospective cohort study. J Periodontol. 2012 Oct;83(10):1226-34. Epub 2012 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22220768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fugazzotto PA. Implant placement at the time of mandibular molar extraction: description of technique and preliminary results of 341 cases. J Periodontol. 2008 Apr;79(4):737-47. doi: 10.1902/jop.2008.070293 .</citation>
    <PMID>18380569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gher ME, Quintero G, Assad D, Monaco E, Richardson AC. Bone grafting and guided bone regeneration for immediate dental implants in humans. J Periodontol. 1994 Sep;65(9):881-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7990026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz-Arad D, Chaushu G. Placement of implants into fresh extraction sites: 4 to 7 years retrospective evaluation of 95 immediate implants. J Periodontol. 1997 Nov;68(11):1110-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9407405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atsumi M, Park SH, Wang HL. Methods used to assess implant stability: current status. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2007 Sep-Oct;22(5):743-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17974108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meredith N, Shagaldi F, Alleyne D, Sennerby L, Cawley P. The application of resonance frequency measurements to study the stability of titanium implants during healing in the rabbit tibia. Clin Oral Implants Res. 1997 Jun;8(3):234-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9586468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orlando B, Barone A, Giorno TM, Giacomelli L, Tonelli P, Covani U. Insertion torque in different bone models with different screw pitch: an in vitro study. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 2010 Sep-Oct;25(5):883-7.</citation>
    <PMID>20862400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmermann J, Sommer M, Grize L, Stubinger S. Marginal bone loss 1 year after implantation: a systematic review for fixed and removable restorations. Clin Cosmet Investig Dent. 2019 Jul 16;11:195-218. doi: 10.2147/CCIDE.S208076. eCollection 2019. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>31406478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galindo-Moreno P, León-Cano A, Ortega-Oller I, Monje A, O Valle F, Catena A. Marginal bone loss as success criterion in implant dentistry: beyond 2 mm. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2015 Apr;26(4):e28-e34. doi: 10.1111/clr.12324. Epub 2014 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24383987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vignoletti F, Sanz-Esporrin J, Sanz-Martin I, Nuñez J, Luengo F, Sanz M. Ridge alterations after implant placement in fresh extraction sockets or in healed crests: An experimental in vivo investigation. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2019 Apr;30(4):353-363. doi: 10.1111/clr.13421. Epub 2019 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>30864234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juodzbalys G, Wang HL. Esthetic index for anterior maxillary implant-supported restorations. J Periodontol. 2010 Jan;81(1):34-42. doi: 10.1902/jop.2009.090385.</citation>
    <PMID>20059415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buser D, Wittneben J, Bornstein MM, Grütter L, Chappuis V, Belser UC. Stability of contour augmentation and esthetic outcomes of implant-supported single crowns in the esthetic zone: 3-year results of a prospective study with early implant placement postextraction. J Periodontol. 2011 Mar;82(3):342-9. doi: 10.1902/jop.2010.100408. Epub 2010 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20831371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esposito M, Klinge B, Meyle J, Mombelli A, Rompen E, van Steenberghe D, Van Dyke T, Wang HL, van Winkelhoff AJ. Working Group on the Treatment Options for the Maintenance of Marginal Bone Around Endosseous Oral Implants, Stockholm, Sweden, 8 and 9 September 2011. Consensus statements. Eur J Oral Implantol. 2012;5 Suppl:S105-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22834399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ormianer Z, Piek D, Livne S, Lavi D, Zafrir G, Palti A, Harel N. Retrospective clinical evaluation of tapered implants: 10-year follow-up of delayed and immediate placement of maxillary implants. Implant Dent. 2012 Aug;21(4):350-6. doi: 10.1097/ID.0b013e31825feb16.</citation>
    <PMID>22814562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araújo MG, Lindhe J. Dimensional ridge alterations following tooth extraction. An experimental study in the dog. J Clin Periodontol. 2005 Feb;32(2):212-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15691354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Araújo MG, Sukekava F, Wennström JL, Lindhe J. Ridge alterations following implant placement in fresh extraction sockets: an experimental study in the dog. J Clin Periodontol. 2005 Jun;32(6):645-52.</citation>
    <PMID>15882225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Botticelli D, Berglundh T, Lindhe J. Hard-tissue alterations following immediate implant placement in extraction sites. J Clin Periodontol. 2004 Oct;31(10):820-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15367183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tarnow DP, Cho SC, Wallace SS. The effect of inter-implant distance on the height of inter-implant bone crest. J Periodontol. 2000 Apr;71(4):546-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10807116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hermann JS, Cochran DL, Nummikoski PV, Buser D. Crestal bone changes around titanium implants. A radiographic evaluation of unloaded nonsubmerged and submerged implants in the canine mandible. J Periodontol. 1997 Nov;68(11):1117-30.</citation>
    <PMID>9407406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albrektsson T, Zarb G, Worthington P, Eriksson AR. The long-term efficacy of currently used dental implants: a review and proposed criteria of success. Int J Oral Maxillofac Implants. 1986 Summer;1(1):11-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>3527955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puisys A, Auzbikaviciute V, Minkauskaite A, Simkunaite-Rizgeliene R, Razukevicius D, Linkevicius R, Linkevicius T. Early crestal bone loss: Is it really loss? Clin Case Rep. 2019 Aug 27;7(10):1913-1915. doi: 10.1002/ccr3.2376. eCollection 2019 Oct.</citation>
    <PMID>31624607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Sullivan D, Sennerby L, Jagger D, Meredith N. A comparison of two methods of enhancing implant primary stability. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2004;6(1):48-57.</citation>
    <PMID>15595709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nedir R, Bischof M, Szmukler-Moncler S, Bernard JP, Samson J. Predicting osseointegration by means of implant primary stability. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2004 Oct;15(5):520-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15355393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lages FS, Douglas-de Oliveira DW, Costa FO. Relationship between implant stability measurements obtained by insertion torque and resonance frequency analysis: A systematic review. Clin Implant Dent Relat Res. 2018 Feb;20(1):26-33. doi: 10.1111/cid.12565. Epub 2017 Dec 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29194944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berglundh T, Lindhe J. Healing around implants placed in bone defects treated with Bio-Oss. An experimental study in the dog. Clin Oral Implants Res. 1997 Apr;8(2):117-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9758962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee DW, Choi YS, Park KH, Kim CS, Moon IS. Effect of microthread on the maintenance of marginal bone level: a 3-year prospective study. Clin Oral Implants Res. 2007 Aug;18(4):465-70. Epub 2007 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17441983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Saint-Joseph University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nada BOU ABBOUD NAAMAN</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental implantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Immediate dental implant loading</keyword>
  <keyword>Marginal bone remodeling</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient characteristics. Outcome measures</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>6 months after publication for 10 years</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>The complete dataset can be available for researchers working on a meta-analysis</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

