<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04342923</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI 20-1679</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04342923</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early POstoperative BIomarkers in PancreatoDuodenectomy: a Spanish Nationwide Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>EPOBIPD</acronym>
  <official_title>Early POstoperative BIomarkers in PancreatoDuodenectomy as Predictors of Complications: a Spanish Nationwide Multicentric Validation Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valladolid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valladolid</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      AIMS: To recruit a large nationwide Spanish series in order to register PF rate and other
      common morbidity after PD, and to perform external validation of the aforementioned score, as
      well as to analyze other postoperative blood parameters and biomarkers associated with
      complications.

      METHODS: Observational prospective and multicentric cohort study to perform external
      validation of the above-mentioned score. All Spanish centers/units performing PD are invited
      to include participants. Patients will be consecutively recruited during an 8-10 months
      period, regardless of their annual volume of pancreatic surgery.

      Study variables will be hemogram parameters on POD1 and POD2 (specifically lymphocytes),
      other parameters and biomarkers (RCP, lactate, procalcitonin, amylase, lipase, albumin) and
      the common variables concerning PD studies.

      LIMITATIONS: Heterogeneity in perioperative management and in blood analysis measuring since
      this is a multicenter study. Possibility of underestimating the PF rate in patients without
      surgical drainage. Finally, the cases of mini-invasive approach or pancreatogastrostomy will
      receive a specific subgroup analysis since the score was designed on a series of open PD and
      pancreatojejunostomy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Complications after pancreatoduodenectomy (PD) are common and pancreatic fistula
      (PF) is among the most relevant ones. There are few studies analyzing blood parameters
      determined in the early postoperative period which behave as morbidity predictors. One of
      them defined a new and simple prognostic score based on lymphocytes count on the first
      postoperative day (POD1) and reactive C protein (RCP) on POD2. The internal validation
      statistics of the score designed in the mentioned work were satisfactory. However, that score
      was described in a short unicentric series

      EXPECTED SAMPLE SIZE: Expected sample size is approximately 500 patients, which will show
      error &lt;7.2% (with 95% confidence) for estimation score´s sensitivity and specificity. We have
      assumed that the PF rate is around 30%.

      QUALITY CONTROL: The STrengthening the Reporting of OBservational studies in Epidemiology
      (STROBE) guidelines for the correct communication and publication of observational studies
      will be followed. Likewise, in order to validate the aforementioned score, Transparent
      Reporting of a Multivariable Prediction Model for Individual Prognosis or Diagnosis (TRIPOD)
      will be added. The only expected failure of the 20 items that compose the TRIPOD is 6b
      (&quot;notify the actions for masking the analysis&quot;), since it is not applicable in our case.

      The inclusion of patients operated on with a mini-invasive approach (laparoscopic or robotic)
      or the use of other anastomoses (pancreatogastrostomy) or reconstruction (Roux-en-Y) differs
      from the technique used in the series with which the score was originally defined (allof
      them, open PD with pancreato-jejunostomy and, mostly part, tutored ducto-mucosal suture and
      Child's single loop reconstruction). If discrepancies are detected, the corresponding
      subgroup analysis will be performed. Cases of conversion from a mini-invasive to open
      approach will be counted as such (intention-to-treat analysis).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pancreatic fistula rate</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Pancreatic fistula including biochemical, grade B and grade C according to ISGPS updated criteria 2016</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically relevant pancreatic fistula</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Pancreatic fistula including grade B and grade C according to ISGPS updated criteria 2016</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall complications</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of any kind of complications including grades I to V according to Dindo-Clavien Classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severe morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of any kind of complications including grades IIIa to V according to Dindo-Clavien Classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Patient´s death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehensive Complication Index</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days since PD</time_frame>
    <description>Postoperative morbidity index (0-100 points) obteined by using formula described by Slankamenac et al Ann Surg 2013</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">525</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreaticoduodenectomy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Complete cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients undergoing PD during study period in all participating center/units in Spain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood analysis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Complete cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing PD in Spain
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  benign or malignant condition requiring surgical treatment by PD.

          -  Signing the informed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Intra-operative findings of unresectability (pancreatic resection not be completed or
             palliative procedure performed)

          -  Other types of pancreatic resection (enucleations, distal and total pancreatectomies),
             as well as multivisceral resective procedures.

          -  Intraoperative radiotherapy

          -  ASA IV patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mario Rodriguez-Lopez, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Clinico Universitario de Valladolid (España)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mario Rodriguez-Lopez, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>983420000</phone>
    <phone_ext>86266</phone_ext>
    <email>mariorodriguezlopez@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carlos A Jezieniecki-Fernandez, MD</last_name>
    <phone>983420000</phone>
    <phone_ext>86266</phone_ext>
    <email>carlos.jezieniecki@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rodriguez-Lopez M, Tejero-Pintor FJ, Bailon-Cuadrado M, Barrera-Rebollo A, Perez-Saborido B, Pacheco-Sanchez D. Impaired immune reaction and increased lactate and C-reactive protein for early prediction of severe morbidity and pancreatic fistula after pancreatoduodenectomy. Hepatobiliary Pancreat Dis Int. 2020 Feb;19(1):58-67. doi: 10.1016/j.hbpd.2019.05.003. Epub 2019 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>31153788</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valladolid</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mario Rodriguez-Lopez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>General and Digestive Surgeon, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PANCREATICODUODENECTOMY</keyword>
  <keyword>COMPLICATIONS</keyword>
  <keyword>PANCREATIC FISTULA</keyword>
  <keyword>SCORE</keyword>
  <keyword>BIOMARKERS</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

