<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04224636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AIO-HEP-0418</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-002430-36</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04224636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atezolizumab/Bevacizumab Followed by On-demand TACE or Initial Synchronous Treatment With TACE and Atezolizumab/Bevacizumab</brief_title>
  <acronym>DEMAND</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, 2-arm Non-comparative Phase II Study on the Efficacy of Atezolizumab and Roche Bevacizumab (Atezo/Bev) Followed by On-demand Selective TACE (sdTACE) Upon Detection of Disease Progression or of Initial Synchronous Treatment With TACE and Atezo/Bev on 24-months Survival Rate in the Treatment of Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the study is to evaluate the efficacy of up-front atezolizumab/ bevacizumab
      (Atezo/Bev) followed by on-demand selective transarterial chemoembolization (sdTACE) and of
      initial synchronous treatment with TACE and Atezo/Bev in the treatment of unresectable HCC
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>24-months survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients alive after 24 months since randomization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median overall survival (mOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from treatment initiation until death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression is defined according RECIST 1.1 and mRECIST</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Response is defined by RECIST 1.1 and mRECIST</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate (CRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined by the percentage of patients with disappearance of tumor manifestation at radiological evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the percentage of patients who have achieved complete response, partial response and stable disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to deterioration of liver function</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as time from randomization to worsening of CTCAE grade for any of these parameters: aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), total bilirubin, albumin, and international normalized ratio (INR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to untreatable progression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as time from randomization to progression not amenable to local treatment as per protocol, occurrence of vascular invasion or of extrahepatic spread, worsening of liver function to Child-Pugh score 8 or higher</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to stage-progression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as time from randomization to disease progression to BCLC C stage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first TACE (arm A)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as time from randomization to disease to the first TACE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized assessment will be performed by using EORTC QLQ-C30 - European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - Quality of Life Core Questionnaire 30 items</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized assessment will be performed by using EORTC QLQ-HCC18 - European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - Quality of Life Core Questionnaire - Hepatocellular carcinoma module 18</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Participants With Treatment-Related Adverse Events as Assessed by CTCAE v5.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">106</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma Non-resectable</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Up-front Atezo/Bev, then TACE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive atezolizumab and bevacizumab iv every three weeks for up to 24 months. Upon detection of at least one unequivocal progressive hepatic lesion, selective TACE directed against progressive lesion(s) (sdTACE) will be performed. RFA or MWA are permitted as alternative to TACE to treat one or more lesion that cannot be reasonably selectively targeted by TACE</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Atezo/Bev combined with TACE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>First TACE will be performed as selectively as possible against all viable tumor lesions. Atezo/Bev will be initiated within three days from TACE. Upon detection of at least one unequivocal progressive hepatic lesion, treatment with Atezo/Bev will be continued if RFA or MWA can be used to treat this/these progressive lesion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atezolizumab Injection, Bevacizumab Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>Atezolizumab and Bevacizumab will be administered prior to or in combination with TACE</description>
    <arm_group_label>Atezo/Bev combined with TACE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Up-front Atezo/Bev, then TACE</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chemoembolisation (TACE)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria

          1. Patient's signed informed consent

          2. Age ≥18 years at time of signing Informed Consent Form

          3. Ability to comply with the study protocol, according to investigator's judgement

          4. Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          5. HCC with histologically confirmed diagnosis

          6. Disease that is not amenable to curative surgical and/or local ablation but eligible
             for TACE

          7. ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1

          8. Child-Pugh class A or B7

          9. Adequate hematologic and end-organ function

         10. Negative HIV test at screening

        Key Exclusion Criteria

          1. Diffuse HCC or presence of vascular invasion or extrahepatic spread or more than 7
             lesions or at least one lesion &gt;= 7 cm

          2. Clinically relevant ascites

          3. Uncontrolled pleural effusion or pericardial effusion

          4. History or presence of hepatic encephalopathy

          5. Co-infection of HBV and HCV

          6. Patients on a liver transplantation list.

          7. Prior systemic therapy for HCC

          8. Prior treatment with TACE or selective internal radiation treatment (SIRT)

          9. Any condition representing a contraindication to TACE

         10. Major gastrointestinal bleeding within 4 weeks prior to randomization, untreated or
             incompletely treated varices with bleeding or high-risk for bleeding.

         11. Active or history of autoimmune disease or immune deficiency

         12. Prior allogeneic stem cell or solid organ transplantation

         13. History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis, organizing pneumonia (e.g., bronchiolitis
             obliterans), drug-induced pneumonitis, or idiopathic pneumonitis, or evidence of
             active pneumonitis on screening chest computed tomography (CT) scan

         14. Active tuberculosis

         15. Severe infection requiring antibiotics within 4 weeks prior to randomization

         16. Significant cardiovascular disease

         17. History of congenital long QT syndrome or corrected QT interval &gt;500 ms at screening
             ECG

         18. Inadequately controlled arterial hypertension or prior history of hypertensive crisis
             or hypertensive encephalopathy

         19. Significant vascular disease including aortic aneurysm requiring surgical repair or
             peripheral arterial thrombosis with 6 months prior to randomization

         20. History of abdominal or tracheoesophageal fistula or gastrointestinal perforation, or
             intra-abdominal abscess within 6 months prior to randomization.

         21. History or clinical signs of gastrointestinal obstruction or requirement for routine
             parenteral hydration, parenteral nutrition, or tube feeding. Evidence of abdominal
             free air that is not explained by paracentesis or recent surgical procedure

         22. History of intra-abdominal inflammatory process within 6 months prior to
             randomization, including but not limited to peptic ulcer disease, diverticulitis, or
             colitis

         23. Evidence of bleeding diathesis or significant coagulopathy

         24. Any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or clinical
             laboratory finding that contraindicates the use of an investigational drug, may affect
             the interpretation of the results, or may render the patient at high risk from
             treatment complications.

         25. Uncontrolled tumor-related pain. Patients requiring pain medication must be on a
             stable regimen at enrollment.

         26. Severe, non healing or dehisced wound, active ulcer, or untreated bone fracture

         27. History of malignancy other than HCC, with the exception of patients who have been
             disease-free for at least five years before enrollment or patients with adequately
             treated and completely resected basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ
             cervical, breast or prostate cancer, stage I uterine cancer

         28. Current or recent (within 10 days of randomization) use of acetylsalicyclic acid or
             treatment with dipyramidole, ticlopidine, clopidogrel, and cilostazol

         29. Current or recent (within 10 days prior to randomization) use of full dose oral or
             parenteral anticoagulants or thrombolytic agents for therapeutic purpose.

         30. Chronic daily treatment with a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID). Occasional
             use of NSAIDs for the symptomatic relief of medical conditions such as headache or
             fever is allowed.

         31. Treatment with a live, attenuated vaccine within 4 weeks prior to randomization, or
             anticipation of need for such a vaccine during atezolizumab treatment or within 5
             months after the last dose of atezolizumab

         32. Prior treatment with CD137 agonists or immune checkpoint blockade therapies, including
             anti-CTLA-4, anti-PD-1, and antiPD-L1 therapeutic antibodies

         33. Hypersensitivity to atezolizumab or bevacizumab or any of the excipients, known
             hypersensitivity to Chinese hamster ovary cell products, known hypersensitivity to
             human or humanized antibodies

         34. Treatment with systemic immunostimulatory agents (including, but not limited to,
             interferon and interleukin 2 [IL-2]) within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives of the drug
             (whichever is longer) prior to randomization

         35. Treatment with systemic immunosuppressive medication within 2 weeks prior to
             randomization, or anticipation of need for systemic immunosuppressive medication
             during study treatment, with the following exceptions:

             Patients who received acute, low-dose systemic immunosuppressant medication or a
             one-time pulse dose of systemic immunosuppressant medication (e.g., 48 hours of
             corticosteroids for a contrast allergy) are eligible.

             Inhaled corticosteroids for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or bronchial asthma,
             supplemental mineralocorticosteroids or low-dose corticosteroids for adrenalcortical
             insufficiency are allowed.

         36. Major surgical procedure other than for diagnosis, open biopsy, or significant
             traumatic injury within 28 days prior to randomization, or abdominal surgery,
             abdominal interventions or significant abdominal traumatic injury within 60 days prior
             to randomization or anticipation of need for major surgical procedure during the
             course of the study or non-recovery from side effects of any such procedure

         37. Core biopsy or other minor surgical procedure, excluding placement of a vascular
             access device, within 3 days prior to the first dose of bevacizumab

         38. Pregnant or breastfeeding females

         39. Participation in a clinical trial or experimental drug treatment within 28 days prior
             to inclusion in the clinical trial or within a period of 5 half-lives of the
             substances administered in a clinical trial or during an experimental drug treatment
             prior to inclusion in the clinical trial, depending on which period is longest, or
             simultaneous participation in another clinical trial while taking part in this
             clinical trial.

         40. Patient committed to an institution by virtue of an order issued either by the
             judicial or the administrative authorities

         41. Patient possibly dependent from the investigator including the spouse, children and
             close relatives of any investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Najib Ben Khaled, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+49 89 4400 78160</phone>
    <email>najib.benkhaled@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Munich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Munich</city>
        <zip>81377</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Enrico N De Toni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+49 (0)894400-0</phone>
      <email>enrico.detoni@med.uni-muenchen.de</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Enrico N De Toni, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jens Ricke, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julia Mayerle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Toni EN. Immune checkpoint inhibitors: use them early, combined and instead of TACE? Gut. 2019 Oct 14. pii: gutjnl-2019-319658. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2019-319658. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>31611301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ludwig-Maximilians - University of Munich</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Enrico De Toni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atezolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

