<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04226651</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DIS-217</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04226651</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effectiveness of Audiovisual Distraction Behavior Guidance Technique in Children With Dental Anxiety</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy Affect Children's Dental Anxiety, Pain, and Behaviour? A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Cross-Over Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cumhuriyet University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cumhuriyet University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, two‐armed, placebo-controlled, cross-over, controlled trial aimed to
      evaluate the effect of virtual reality exposure therapy (VRET) on dental anxiety, pain, and
      behaviour among children undergoing dental treatment under local anaesthesia. The null
      hypotheses were as follows: VRET has no effect on reducing dental anxiety and dental pain
      scores of participants; and there is no difference between subjective and objective measure
      scores of dental anxiety and pain when VRET and attention palcebo-controlled (APC) groups are
      used to reduce anxiety in children undergoing dental treatment with local anaesthesia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, two‐armed, placebo-controlled, cross-over, controlled trial adhered to the
      principles of the Declaration of Helsinki, good clinical practice guidelines, and applicable
      regulatory requirements. Ethics approval was obtained from the Health Ethics Committee of
      Sivas Cumhuriyet University (Sivas, Turkey; ID: 2018-02/08). All parents or guardians of
      children were educated about the study before enrollment and provided informed written
      consent to participate. The trial adhered to the Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials
      (CONSORT) guidelines.

      The parameters used to calculate the sample size included a 95% confidence interval (CI), 80%
      statistical power, and a standard deviation of 1.90; accordingly, at least 64 subjects were
      required. This number was adjusted to 76 subjects to compensate for a projected loss of
      approximately 20% during follow-up. Thus, 76 healthy subjects between 7 and 11 years of age
      were included in the study. Participants who fulfilled the following criteria were included:
      systemically and mentally healthy; required restorative treatment for first mandibular
      permanent molar tooth with dentin caries in each mandibular quadrant with a bilateral
      inferior alveolar nerve block; absence of co‐operative disability; and Frankl Scale score 2
      or 3 during first dental examination. Patients with systemic or mental illnesses, reduced
      audiovisual capabilities, acute dental pain or trauma, those with previous painful or
      negative dental experience, and those who were extremely uncooperative were excluded.

      The present randomized, two‐armed, within-subject, cross-over, controlled trial included
      patients who applied to Department of Pediatric Dentistry, Cumhuriyet University, for routine
      dental treatment.The study comprised three visits: V0, baseline dental examination and
      inclusion; V1, first restorative treatment session; and V2, second restorative treatment
      session for symmetrical teeth. The initial oral and radiographic examination and Frankl
      Behaviour Scale scoring of all patients were performed by one experienced and pre-calibrated
      researcher. A dental assistant not participating in the study used a random-order generator
      (http://www.random.org) to randomize patients to the experimental group according to block
      randomization.

      Eligible participants were treated in two different appointments: protective glasses only,
      without distraction (APC); or with the treatment condition (VRET). All procedures were
      performed by a single experienced and calibrated paediatric dentist (BB).

      Participants were randomly assigned by a computer algorithm to receive VR with the first or
      second sequential dental treatment session and with protective glasses for the other
      treatment session. The investigators were blinded to treatment sequence until before the
      first dental treatment was to begin. Before VRET, the VR headset was shown to the patients,
      who were permitted to handle it. This enabled the patient to recognize the device and be
      familiar with it before treatment. Before starting treatment, the VR headset was placed on
      each patient's head, and the patient was asked whether the device caused pain or discomfort,
      and the patient's consent was confirmed. In the APC group, each patient was informed about
      the dental procedure and was provided with protective glasses. All patients were told that
      they were wearing these glasses to ensure a pain- and stress-free treatment, and that the
      dentist would devote additional attention to the treatment. This aimed to provide the patient
      with feeling like being in an experimental session. The reason for choosing an APC group with
      the routine protective glasses without distraction was to mitigate possible Hawthorne
      effects.

      Regardless of experimental group, in the first treatment session, the mandibular first
      permanent molar tooth of each patient was restored with composite filling under local
      anaesthesia, while the opposite symmetrical tooth was treated in the second session. The
      duration of treatment in each session was noted and defined as the time from the subject sat
      on the chair to occlusal adjustment of restoration. First, the teeth were cleaned using
      fluoride-free prophylactic paste. The preparation was limited to removal of the caries,
      followed by rounding of the inner line and point angles. Cavity preparation was performed
      using an 80 µm grit diamond bur and completed using a 25 µm grit diamond bur (Intensiv,
      Viganello-Lugano, Switzerland). Isolation and contamination were controlled with suction and
      cotton rollers. In cases for which this was not sufficient, a rubber dam was used. Metal
      matrix bands and wooden wedges were also used where necessary.

      Statistical analyses were performed using SPSS version 22.0 (IBM Corporation, Armonk, NY,
      USA). Descriptive analysis was used to summarize demographic characteristics and responses of
      the participants on each scale. The chi-squared test was used to compare age and sex
      differences at baseline. Repeated measures ANOVA was performed to analyse changes according
      treatment group, dental visit sequence and time point of treatment procedure. Differences
      with p &lt; 0.05 were considered to be statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 18, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized, two‐armed, within-subject, cross-over, controlled</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Time 0: a minute after sitting in the dental unit ; Time 1: 1 min before local anaesthesia; Time 2: 1 min after local anaesthesia; Time 3: 1 min before end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Dental anxiety will be assessed using the Heart Rate with a portable pulse oximetry device</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Visit 0: 5 min before first inclusion visit, Visit 1: 5 min before first dental treatment visit,Visit 2: 5 min before second dental treatment visit,</time_frame>
    <description>Dental anxiety was assessed using the Children's Fear Survey Schedule-Dental Subscale (CFSS-DS) and Facial Image Scale (FIS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Time 0: a minute after sitting in the dental unit ; Time 1: 1 min before local anaesthesia; Time 2: 1 min after local anaesthesia; Time 3: 1 min before end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Dental pain will be assessed using the Heart Rate with a portable pulse oximetry device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Time 2: 1 min after local anaesthesia; Time 3: 1 min before end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Dental pain will be assessed using the Wong-Bakers Faces Pain Scale (WBS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Time 3: 1 min before end of the treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Dental pain will be assessed using the Frankl Behaviour Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Dental Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Dental Pain and Sensation Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>First dental visit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Second Dental Visit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Protective Glasses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Reality Device</intervention_name>
    <description>The Virtual Reality system (PlayStation 4 VR, Sony Inc.) is a simple and easy to use distraction device. The system consists of a screen mounted on a binocular headset connected to a console or personal computer. The head-mounted display provides a high-resolution visual display and unmutes the sound from the headphones using a soundproof mechanism that provides clear sound.</description>
    <arm_group_label>First dental visit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Protective glasses</intervention_name>
    <description>Each patient was informed about the dental procedure and was provided with protective glasses. All patients were told that they were wearing these glasses to ensure a pain- and stress-free treatment, and that the dentist would devote additional attention to the treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Second Dental Visit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Requiring restorative treatment for first mandibular permanent molar tooth with dentin
             caries in each mandibular quadrant with a bilateral inferior alveolar nerve block

          -  Co‐operative ability

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemic or mental illnesses

          -  Limited audiovisual capabilities

          -  Acute dental pain or trauma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Burak Buldur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sivas</city>
        <state>Kampus</state>
        <zip>58140</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cumhuriyet University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>BURAK BULDUR</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sensation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Not planned yet.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

