<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04228588</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SDC 4863/19/082</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ISS 212936</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04228588</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pragmatic Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Mepolizumab in Severe Uncontrolled Asthma in Brazil</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pragmatic Study to Investigate the Efficacy and Safety of Mepolizumab in Severe Uncontrolled Asthma in Brazil</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The anti-interleukin-5 monoclonal antibody mepolizumab is approved as an add-on therapy in
      Europe, Canada, USA, and other countries, to standard of care for the treatment of patients
      with severe eosinophilic asthma. Mepolizumab has been shown to reduce exacerbation rates and
      dependency on oral corticosteroid use in clinical trials in patients with severe eosinophilic
      asthma compared with placebo, both in addition to standard of care. Other trials had also
      showed that treatment with mepolizumab resulted in significant improvements in quality of
      life (SGRQ) and asthma control (ACQ-5 score) . Mepolizumab has only recently been approved in
      Brazil. There is still no data regarding its efficacy and safety in the Brazilian population
      and it is important to emphasize that no Brazilian center participated in the previous large,
      international and multicentric phase III mepolizumab studies. Therefore, it is crucial to
      perform a local study in order to validate external results in the Brazilian population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Severe asthma is associated with substantial morbidity, mortality, health-care costs, and
      impaired quality of life. Recurrent asthma exacerbations are a major problem in some patients
      and can predominate in a subgroup with eosinophilic airway inflammation. Mepolizumab is a
      humanised monoclonal antibody against interleukin 5 that effectively inhibits eosinophilic
      airway inflammation.

      The anti-interleukin-5 monoclonal antibody mepolizumab is approved as an add-on therapy in
      Europe, Canada, USA, and other countries, to standard of care for the treatment of patients
      with severe eosinophilic asthma. Mepolizumab has been shown to reduce exacerbation rates and
      dependency on oral corticosteroid use in clinical trials in patients with severe eosinophilic
      asthma compared with placebo, both in addition to standard of care. Other trials had also
      showed that treatment with mepolizumab resulted in significant improvements in quality of
      life (SGRQ) and asthma control (ACQ-5 score).

      Mepolizumab has only recently been approved in Brazil. There is still no data regarding its
      efficacy and safety in the Brazilian population and it is important to emphasize that no
      Brazilian center participated in the previous large, international and multicentric phase III
      mepolizumab studies. Therefore, it is crucial to perform a local study in order to validate
      external results in the Brazilian population.

      Our group belongs to a public academic institution with a focus on assistance, teaching and
      research. It is a tertiary-referral hospital with an outpatient clinic specializing severe
      asthma patients. In 2012, the investigators published the first study with the clinical
      characterization of their cohort of severe asthma and its respective phenotypes. Since then,
      the investigators have carried out several studies in order to identify prognostic factors
      and interventions that could improve the control and quality of life of this population.
      Among them, there are the impact of weight control in asthma symptoms, evaluation of
      standardized and systematic protocol based on high doses of inhaled corticosteroid plus LABA
      and 2 weeks course of oral corticosteroids and pathophysiological studies based on bronchial
      biopsy samples from patients with severe asthma. Since obesity is a serious and prevalent
      problem in several severe asthma cohorts, another area of interest of the group is to assess
      the impact of physical activity on this population. Finally, it is important to mention the
      commitment of the group to evaluate the incorporation of new treatments in the severe asthma
      population within the Brazilian scenario as done in a specific publication to systematically
      evaluate the use of omalizumab in our center.

      Therefore, the investigators consider that our center has full capacity to conduct a
      systematic evaluation study of the use of mepolizumab in the population of severe asthma. The
      investigators aimed to examine the effects of mepolizumab on quality of life, lung function,
      asthma symptoms and exacerbation rate in patients with severe eosinophilic asthma in a
      tertiary reference center in Brazil based on real world data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 9, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 9, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Phase IV, single-arm study Number of visits: 13 (W-4, W0, W4, W8, W12, W16, W20, W24, W28, W32, W36, W40, W44, W48) (W = week)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total score of Saint George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ) between Week 0 and Week 48</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This scales varies from 0 to 100. Higher values means worse quality of life.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number of clinically significant exacerbations of asthma as defined by: worsening of asthma which requires use of systemic corticosteroids* and/or hospitalisation and/or Emergency Department (ED) visits.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>significant exacerbations are definied as those requiring at least 3 days of systemic corticosteroids</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lung function (Forced expiratory volume in first second - FEV1)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by spirometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of asthma control measured by Asthma control questionnaire (ACQ) 5</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ACQ varies from 0 to 5 with higher values meaning worse asthma control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety measured by the number of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>number of all adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of asthma control measured by Asthma Control Test (ACT)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ACT varies from 5 to 25 with higher values meaning better asthma control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change of small airway involvement measured by forced oscillometry technique (R5-R20)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by forced oscillometry technique</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change of quality of life measured by Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (AQLQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Scores range 1-7, with higher scores indicating better quality of life.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change of airway inflammation measured by fraction of exhaled nitric oxide (FeNO)</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Higher levels of FeNO means higher inflammation in the airways</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change of airway inflammation measured by percentage of eosinophils in induced sputum</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Higher values of sputum eosinophils means higher inflammation in the airways</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Eosinophilic Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mepolizumab 100mg, SC, every 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mepolizumab 100 MG [Nucala]</intervention_name>
    <description>Mepolizumab 100mg, SC, every 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mepolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older with severe eosinophilic asthma

          -  Regular use of high-dose inhaled corticosteroids plus other controller medicines

          -  Non-controlled asthma characterized by ACQ-5 &gt; 1.5 OR chronic oral corticosteroids
             asthmatic patients (Prednisone 5mg or more for at least 3 months) even if ACQ-5 &lt; 1.5

          -  History of at least one exacerbation requiring treatment with systemic corticosteroids
             in the previous 12 months before screening OR chronic oral corticosteroids asthmatic
             patients (Prednisone 5mg or more for at least 3 months) even without exacerbations

          -  Blood eosinophil count of at least 300 cells per μL within the 12 months before
             screening OR a blood eosinophil count of at least 150 cells per μL at screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current smokers or former smokers with a history of at least ten pack-years

          -  Individuals with a concurrent respiratory disease

          -  Those who had received omalizumab within 30 days before screening

          -  Patients with severe or clinically significant cardiovascular disease, or other
             eosinophilic diseases.

          -  Patients with asthma exacerbation 4 weeks before screening for the study

          -  Patients with parasitic infection in the 6 months before study entry.

          -  Patients with substantial uncontrolled comorbidity, possibility of pregnancy

          -  Patients with history of poor treatment adherence
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rodrigo A Athanazio, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical Assistant</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rodrigo A Athanazio, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+551126615000</phone>
    <phone_ext>5685</phone_ext>
    <email>rathanazio@yahoo.com.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Luciana Cassimiro</last_name>
    <phone>+551126615109</phone>
    <email>luciana.cassimiro@incor.usp.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of São Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>05403-900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rodrigo Athanazio</last_name>
      <phone>+55 11 2661-5000</phone>
      <phone_ext>5685</phone_ext>
      <email>rathanazio@yahoo.com.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>severe asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>mepolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>anti IL-5 monoclonal antibody</keyword>
  <keyword>pragmatic study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Eosinophilia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

