<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04222452</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH20707</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04222452</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The PORTRAIT Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>PORTRAIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Clinical Consequences of Adults Presenting With hyPophOsphatasia With Special Focus on Gait, Bone micRosTRucture And cognITion: The PORTRAIT Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical Consequences of Adults Presenting with Hypophosphatasia with Special Focus on Gait,
      Bone Microstructure and Cognition: The PORTRAIT study Hypophosphatasia (HPP) is an inherited
      condition that leads to weak bones. Early childhood forms are severe and easily recognized.
      Adult forms can vary in severity. HPP is often missed by doctors or confused with
      osteoporosis. This is important because the usual osteoporosis treatments may be harmful to
      patients with HPP and increase the risk of broken bones. One of the reasons it is missed is a
      lack of research describing the typical features of HPP, so doctors don't recognize the
      signs, and don't know when or how to test for it. The PORTRAIT Study will help increase
      understanding of the burden of disease of HPP on patients. The aim is to examine the effects
      of HPP on bone structure and strength, physical functioning, cognition, and quality of life.
      Researchers will study adults with HPP and healthy age- and gender-matched individuals. Blood
      samples will be collected after an overnight fast. Researchers will use these samples to
      measure markers of HPP and bone health. Medical history and lifestyle, quality of life and
      cognitive function will be assessed using questionnaires. Bone mineral density, body
      composition and bone structure and strength will be measured using dual energy x-ray
      absorptiometry and high resolution peripheral quantitative computed tomography. Physical
      functioning will be assessed as participants perform a series of physical performance and
      gait tests. Magnetic resonance images of the lower limbs will be matched-up with the physical
      functioning data to create patient-specific musculoskeletal models. Cognitive function tests
      will be performed to assess cognition and mental health. To reveal the burden of disease of
      HPP, the data collected from patients with HPP will be compared to that collected from
      healthy controls.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hypophosphatasia (HPP) is caused by mutations in the tissue non-specific alkaline phosphatase
      (TNSALP) gene with deficiency in TNSALP activity. This leads to accumulation of inorganic
      pyrophosphate, a potent inhibitor of bone mineralization, which causes rickets and
      osteomalacia, and of pyridoxal 5-phosphate (PLP) which causes seizures in neonates but no
      harm in adults. HPP is also associated with muscle weakness (which is very severe in
      perinatal and infantile forms) and early tooth loss. The most severe forms of HPP present in
      infancy, and were fatal until the recent development of TNSALP enzyme replacement therapy,
      Asfotase Alpha. Adult-onset HPP is less severe. It often presents with fractures of the femur
      or metatarsals, and so is likely to be misdiagnosed as osteoporosis. Correct diagnosis of HPP
      is important as the usual osteoporosis treatments, for example bisphosphonates, may be
      harmful and increase the risk of fracture.

      High resolution peripheral quantitative computed tomography (HR-pQCT) is an imaging technique
      that allows the detailed assessment of BMD, microstructure and strength. HR-pQCT could reveal
      important information about the effects of HPP on bone microstructural properties.

      HPP can also have a significant effect on physical functioning. In infantile HPP, motor
      function delay is usual but in adult-onset HPP effects on physical functioning are less
      apparent. These effects can be explored through the use of physical function testing and
      clinical gait analysis. Cognitive function may be affected by low levels of or inactivity of
      ALP in the neural tissue (TNALP). Patients with HPP have reported forgetfulness and
      'fogginess'.

      The aims of the study are to examine the effects of HPP on (i) bone structure and strength,
      (ii) physical functioning, (iii) cognition and (iv) quality of life (QoL). Researchers will
      study adults with HPP and healthy individuals. The results will help to determine if there
      should be a trial of a new drug treatment for adults with HPP. This study forms part of our
      wider programme of research into HPP.

      Researchers will recruit 7 patients with childhood- or adult-presenting HPP (cases), who are
      known to the Metabolic Bone Clinic at the Metabolic Bone Centre (MBC), Northern General
      Hospital (NGH), Sheffield. Researchers will also recruit 7 healthy controls matched to the
      cases by gender and age. Researchers will approach first degree relatives (with their
      permission) of patients with HPP to offer them genetic testing for HPP. If HPP is confirmed,
      approach these first degree relatives to invite them to participate in the study, Fasting
      blood samples will be obtained for measurement of serum or plasma bone alkaline phosphatase
      (bone ALP), PLP, procollagen type I N-propeptide (PINP), C-terminal telopeptide (CTX) and
      genetic testing (if not already performed).

      Medical history and lifestyle, quality of life and cognitive function will be assessed using
      questionnaires.

      Bone mineral density (BMD) of the lumbar spine, proximal femur and whole body will be
      measured using dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA). Whole body composition will also be
      determined by DXA. Trabecular and cortical BMD and bone microstructure and strength will be
      examining using HR-pQCT of the distal radius and tibia.

      Physical functioning will also be assessed. Participants will undergo a series of physical
      performance tests/gait analysis tests. Chair rises (sit to stand), a timed up and go test. A
      10 m walking test and a 4 stair climb will be used to assess muscle strength. A modified
      performance oriented mobility assessment-gait (MPOMA-G) will also be performed. Recordings of
      the kinematics, ground reaction forces, electromyography (EMG) data and muscle function will
      be made using a motion capture system. This will allow the quantification of joint kinematics
      and kinetics and of muscular pattern activation during the execution of a number of different
      motor skills. Lower limb magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), with the participants dressed in a
      set of MRI visible markers, will allow the registration of the MRI and physical
      functioning/gait data enhancing the participant's specific musculoskeletal modelling.

      Cognitive function tests (a Montreal Cognitive Assessment) will be performed to assess the
      burden of disease of HPP on cognitive and mental health as forgetfulness and 'fogginess' have
      been reported by patients.

      The results from the various assessments performed will be compared between the age-gender
      matched cases and controls using paired samples t-tests. For each test, the mean difference,
      95% confidence interval and associated p-value will be reported. In the event of the
      normality assumption of the paired samples t-test being violated comparisons will be made
      using the non-parametric Wilcoxon signed rank test. The burden of disease of HPP on bone
      quality (i.e. BMD, bone structure and strength), mental health, cognition, QoL, pain,
      physical functioning and gait will be examined using Spearman Rank Correlation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical consequences and disease burden of HPP on the total score (balance + Gait) achieved during the Tinetti Performance Oriented Mobility Assessment (POMA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in gait: HPP patients versus healthy controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical consequences and disease burden of HPP on volumetric Bone Mineral Density (vBMD, in g/cm3)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in bone microstructure: HPP patients versus healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical consequences and disease burden of HPP on the total score achieved during the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, average 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in cognitive function: HPP patients versus healthy controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypophosphatasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypophosphatasia patients (HPP)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with known hypophosphatasia (HPP) as diagnosed using genetic testing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy individuals (controls) matched to the cases by gender and age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples (full blood and serum)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with HPP (cases) and healthy individuals (controls)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        HPP PATIENTS (CASES)

          -  Clinical diagnosis of HPP (with or without previous genetic test confirmation)

          -  Evidence of burden of disease (HPP) including abnormal gait, muscle weakness, pain,
             recurring fractures, slow healing fractures and/or bone deformities

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Able and willing to participate in the study

          -  Able to give written informed consent

        HEALTHY INDIVIDUALS (CONTROLS)

          -  Healthy men and women with normal bone mineral density (defined as a DXA bone mineral
             density T- score at the lumbar spine or total hip greater than -1).

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Able and willing to participate in the study

          -  Able to give written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        HPP PATIENTS (CASES)

          -  Individuals with BMI&lt;18, or BMI&gt;30 kg/m2

          -  Other conditions known to affect serum ALP and PLP

          -  Coeliac disease, B12 deficiency, untreated hypothyroidism, Wilson's disease

          -  Taking nutritional supplements containing vitamin B6 within past two weeks

          -  History of, or current:

        Severe ischaemic heart disease, rheumatoid arthritis, ankylosing spondylitis, cancer
        (concurrent)

          -  History of, or current neurological diseases affecting the neuromuscular system
             including Parkinson's disease, CVA, muscular dystrophy, myasthenia, cerebral trauma,
             peripheral neuropathy

          -  Treatment for more than 3 months in a year or under treatment with oral
             corticosteroids

          -  History of any long term immobilization (duration greater than three months)

          -  Conditions or surgery which prevent the acquisition or analysis of musculoskeletal
             images

          -  Use of medications or treatment known to affect bone metabolism other than
             calcium/vitamin D supplementation.

          -  Alcohol intake greater than 21 units per week

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

        HEALTHY INDIVIDUALS (CONTROLS)

          -  Individuals with BMI&lt;18, or BMI&gt;30 kg/m2

          -  Other conditions known to affect serum ALP and PLP

          -  Coeliac disease, B12 deficiency, untreated hypothyroidism, Wilson's disease

          -  Taking nutritional supplements containing vitamin B6 within the past two weeks

          -  Bilateral fractures of the distal radius and/or distal tibia

          -  History of, or current conditions known to affect bone metabolism and bone mineral
             density including diagnosed skeletal disease or arthritis, chronic hepatic or renal
             disease, Coeliac and/or other malabsorption syndromes, hyperparathyroidism,
             hyperthyroidism and/or diagnosed endocrine disorders, hypocalcaemia or hypercalcemia,
             diagnosed restrictive eating disorder, diabetes mellitus

          -  History of, or current severe ischaemic heart disease, rheumatoid arthritis,
             ankylosing spondylitis, cancer (concurrent)

          -  History of, or current neurological diseases affecting the neuromuscular system
             including Parkinson's disease, CVA, muscular dystrophy, myopathies, myasthenia,
             cerebral trauma, peripheral neuropathy

          -  Treatment for more than 3 months in a year or under treatment with oral
             corticosteroids

          -  History of any long term immobilization (duration greater than three months)

          -  Conditions or surgery which prevent the acquisition or analysis of musculoskeletal
             images

          -  Use of medications or treatment known to affect bone metabolism other than
             calcium/vitamin D supplementation.

          -  Alcohol intake greater than 21 units per week

          -  Conditions that currently impact on gait

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Eastell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sheffield</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Richard Eastell, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 0114 2159694</phone>
    <phone_ext>01142159697</phone_ext>
    <email>r.eastell@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Margaret Paggiosi, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+44 0114 2159697</phone>
    <phone_ext>01142159697</phone_ext>
    <email>m.a.paggiosi@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Sheffield</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>South Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S5 7AU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Eastell, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4401142159694</phone>
      <email>r.eastell@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Margaret Paggiosi, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+4401142159697</phone>
      <email>m.a.paggiosi@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 23, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Burden of disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone microstructure</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognition</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical functioning</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypophosphatasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

