<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04221204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3D185-CN-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04221204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Monotherapy in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics Profiles and Preliminary Efficacy of 3D185 Monotherapy in Subjects With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>3D Medicines (Sichuan) Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>3D Medicines (Sichuan) Co., Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Phase 1 Study of the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics Profiles, and Preliminary
      Efficacy of 3D185 Monotherapy in Subjects with Advanced Solid Tumors
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects with advanced solid tumors who have no available standard therapy or who have failed
      standard therapies.

      This is an open-label, global multicenter, dose-escalation phase 1 study of safety,
      tolerability, preliminary PK profile, and preliminary efficacy of 3D185 monotherapy in
      subjects with advanced solid tumors.

      The starting dose in this dose-escalation study is 25 mg, and the preset 7 dose-escalation
      cohorts are 25 mg, 50 mg, 100 mg, 150 mg, 200 mg, 250 mg, and 300 mg, respectively.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The starting dose in this dose-escalation study is 25 mg, and the preset 7 dose-escalation cohorts are 25 mg, 50 mg, 100 mg, 150 mg, 200 mg, 250 mg, and 300 mg, respectively.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety Evaluation: frequency and severity of AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated based on the frequency and severity of AEs according to NCI CTCAE v4.03.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability Evaluation: frequency and severity of AEs</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>based on the frequency and severity of AEs according to NCI CTCAE v4.03.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy evaluation: Complete Response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria in Solid tumors v 1.1 (RECIST) assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics (PK) evaluation: Cmax (mg/L)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test of PK samples will be performed by central laboratory. The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK evaluation: Tmax (minutes)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test of PK samples will be performed by central laboratory. The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK evaluation: AUC0-24 h, AUC0-96 h, AUC0-∞,</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK evaluation: t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test of PK samples will be performed by central laboratory. The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK evaluation: Clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test of PK samples will be performed by central laboratory. The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PK evaluation: Vd.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The test of PK samples will be performed by central laboratory. The PK parameters will be calculated using standard non-compartment models and WinNonlin® Professional 6.4 or higher version (Certara, Princeton, NJ, USA) or SAS® 9.3 or higher version (SAS Institute, Inc., Cary, North Carolina) to fully reflect the drug absorption, distribution and elimination characteristics in the human body. The interim PK parameters will be calculated using the planned blood collection time, and the final PK parameters will be calculated using the actual blood collection time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progressive Disease evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>assessed by analyzing the change in serum phosphate levels relative to baseline level over time (Serum biochemistry test).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy evaluation: Partial Response</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria in Solid tumors v 1.1 (RECIST) assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy evaluation: Stable Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria in Solid tumors v 1.1 (RECIST) assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy evaluation: Disease Progression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>assessed by analyzing the change in serum phosphate levels relative to baseline level over time (Serum biochemistry test).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rale (ORR) (CR+PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria in Solid tumors v 1.1 (RECIST) assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>disease control rate (DCR) (CR+PR+SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria Per RECIST version 1.1 criteria in Solid tumors v 1.1 (RECIST) assessed by investigator</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor, Adult</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open-Label, Dose-Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>To explore the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and the recommended dose for subsequent studies (RPTD) of 3D185 monotherapy in subject with advanced solid tumors.
The starting dose in this dose-escalation study is 25 mg, and the preset 7 dose-escalation cohorts are 25 mg, 50 mg, 100 mg, 150 mg, 200 mg, 250 mg, and 300 mg, respectively. This study adopts a combination of accelerated titration and i3+3[1] for dose escalation. All subjects in each cohort will receive a single oral dose of 3D185, followed by a 7-day washout period (i.e. single-dose PK study period). Then, subjects will receive consecutive daily doses (Once daily [QD], 28 days/cycle) until disease progression, death, unacceptable toxicity, or withdraw of informed consent, whichever comes first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Highly selective FGFR1-3 inhibitor</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects in each cohort will receive a single oral dose of 3D185, followed by a 7-day washout period (i.e. single-dose PK study period). Then, subjects will receive consecutive daily doses (Once daily [QD], 28 days/cycle) until disease progression, death, unacceptable toxicity, or withdraw of informed consent, whichever comes first. The dose limiting toxicity (DLT) evaluation period includes the single-dose PK study period and the first treatment cycle (within 35 days after the first dose). The enrolled subjects will be sequentially assigned to the planned dose cohorts according to the protocol and receive 3D185 treatment to observe the occurrence of DLT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Open-Label, Dose-Escalation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Study Population:

        In the study, male or female adult subjects ≥ 18 years of age, with advanced solid tumors
        with no prior standard therapy or failed to establish standard therapies are eligible.

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must be male or female and ≥ 18 years of age on the day of enrollment.

          2. Subjects must have a histological diagnosis of locally advanced or metastatic
             malignant solid tumors. Subjects must have failed or have been intolerant to
             established standard therapies, or standard therapies did not exist or were no longer
             effective for a given tumor type, or in the opinion of the Investigator have been
             considered ineligible for a particular form of standard therapy on medical grounds.

          3. Subjects must have at least one evaluable lesion (according to RECIST 1.1, see
             Appendix 1);

          4. ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1.

          5. Life expectancy ≥ 12 weeks.

          6. Subjects must have normal levels of total serum calcium and total phosphate.

          7. Subjects must have adequate organ and bone marrow function (no hematopoietic growth
             factor, blood transfusion, or platelet therapy within 1 week before the first dose):

               -  CBC: neutrophils ≥ 1.5 × 109/L, platelets ≥ 100 × 109/L, hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL.

               -  Liver function: total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × ULN; ALT/AST ≤ 2.5 × ULN without liver
                  metastasis; ALT/AST ≤ 5 × ULN with liver metastasis;

               -  Coagulation: International normalized ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 × ULN and activated
                  partial thromboplastin time (APTT) ≤ 1.5 × ULN (for patients undergoing
                  anticoagulant therapy. The Investigator will judge that the INR and APTT are
                  within a safe and effective treatment range).

               -  Renal function: serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 × ULN, or creatinine clearance ≥ 60
                  mL/min/1.73 m2 in the condition of creatinine level &gt; ULN; urine protein
                  qualitative ≤ 1 + (if ≥ 2+, 24 hours of urine protein test is required, if 24
                  hours urine protein &lt;1 g, then allowed to enroll);

               -  Adequate cardiac function left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &gt; 50% for 2
                  dimensional cardiac ultrasound;

          8. Subjects must have signed and dated an IRB/IEC approved written informed consent form
             that under regulatory and institutional guidelines, and this must be obtained before
             the performance of any protocol-related procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria should be excluded from the study:

          1. Subjects who received other investigational products or devices in other clinical
             trials within 4 weeks before the first dose;

          2. Subjects who received anti-tumor therapy (except for mitomycin, nitrosourea, and
             fluorouracil oral drugs) within 4 weeks before the first dose, including but not
             limited to chemotherapy, radiotherapy (palliative radiotherapy is completed at least 2
             weeks before the first dose can enroll), targeted therapy or immunotherapy.

             Note: Mitomycin and nitrosourea have been treated within 6 weeks after the last dose;
             oral fluorouracil such as tegafur and capecitabine has been treated within 2 weeks
             after the last dose.

          3. Subjects who previously received FGFR1-3 specific inhibitor therapy.

          4. Subjects who have previous toxicity of anti-tumor therapy that has not been returned
             to level 0 or 1. (Alopecia, chemotherapy-induced peripheral neurotoxicity and
             ototoxicity ≤ Grade 2 can enroll);

          5. Subjects who received a CYP3A4 and/or CYP2C8 strong inhibitor or a CYP3A4 strong
             inducer (see Appendix 6) within 7 days prior to the first dose, and need to continue
             using these drugs;

          6. Subjects who have any of the following eye diseases/conditions:

               -  History of retinal pigment epithelial detachment (RPED);

               -  History of laser treatment or intraocular injection for macular degeneration;

               -  History of dry or wet age-related macular degeneration;

               -  History of retinal vein occlusion (RVO);

               -  History of retinal degenerative diseases;

               -  History of chorioretinal lesions;

          7. Subjects who received clinical intervention for biliary obstruction 14 days prior to
             the first dose or the Investigator judges that the symptoms had not resolved or
             required anti-infective treatment.

          8. Subjects who have gastrointestinal disorders that will affect oral administration or
             the Investigator judges that the absorption of 3D185 will be interfered.

          9. Subjects underwent major surgery (except biopsy), or the surgical incision has not
             completely healed within 4 weeks prior to the first dose.

         10. Subjects who had clinically uncontrollable pleural effusion, ascites, or pericardial
             effusion within 2 weeks prior to the first dose.

         11. Subjects who have symptomatic brain metastases or spinal cord compression. Subjects
             who have previously treatment for brain metastases, if the clinical condition is
             stable and imaging evidence does not show disease progression within 4 weeks prior to
             the first dose, and do not need corticosteroid treatment within 2 weeks prior to the
             first dose, can enroll.

         12. Subjects who have active bacterial or fungal infections (CTCAE ≥ 2) that required
             systemic treatment within 14 days prior to the first dose.

         13. Subjects who have active HBV infection (Tests should include assessment of HBsAg and
             HBc IgG antibody. If one parameter is positive, determine HBV-DNA to confirm acute
             infection. Patients with positive results for HBsAg and/or HBV-DNA are considered
             active HBV infection) and/or active HCV infection (HCV antibody testing positive);

         14. Subjects who have clinically significant cardiovascular diseases that occurred 6
             months prior to enrollment. Cardiovascular diseases include, but not limited to
             follows:

               -  Acute myocardial infarction;

               -  Severe/unstable angina;

               -  Cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack;

               -  Congestive heart failure (New York Heart Association &gt; Class II, see Appendix 3);

               -  Arrhythmias that require antiarrhythmic treatment except for beta blockers or
                  digoxin;

               -  Repeated ECG with QTc interval &gt; 450 ms;

               -  High blood pressure that cannot be controlled by antihypertensive drugs (systolic
                  blood pressure &gt; 150 mm Hg, diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg).

         15. Subjects who have clinically significant abnormal serum electrolytes (Patients must
             have corrected calcium and phosphate &lt; institutional ULN).

         16. Subjects who are receiving warfarin (low-dose warfarin as 2 mg/day is acceptable); or
             receiving antiplatelet anticoagulant therapy (aspirin at dose ≥300 mg/day, clopidogrel
             at dose ≥75 mg/day).

         17. Female subjects in pregnancy or lactation. Male subjects or female subjects at
             reproductive ages who are unwilling to receive effective contraceptive measures.

         18. Subjects who are judged by the Investigator to be unsuitable for this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Er Xiao</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>3D Medicines (Beijing) Co., Ltd.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Silong Xiang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>( 86)15901312398</phone>
    <email>silong.xiang@3dmedcare.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Regina Jones, B.S.</last_name>
    <phone>9197039920</phone>
    <phone_ext>9197039920</phone_ext>
    <email>jones@3dmedcare.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Affiliated Hospital of Military academy of medical sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100071</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xu Jianming, Dr.</last_name>
      <phone>86-10-66947176</phone>
      <email>jmxu2003@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 18, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/04/NCT04221204/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

