<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04220086</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TNASD1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04220086</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Massage for Children With Autism Spectrum Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effectiveness and Brain-related Mechanism of Pediatric Massage for Children With Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD): A Randomized, Waiting-list Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shenzhen Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study was designed as a randomized controlled clinical trial of pediatric massage for
      children with Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD). 72 ASD children will be recruited and randomly
      divided into two groups: the treatment group (pediatric massage + usual care, n=36) and the
      control group (usual care/waitlist group, n=36). Children in the treatment group will
      received 12 weeks pediatric massage by doctors and their own parents.

      The Autism Behavior Checklist (ABC), Childhood Autism Rating Scale (CARS), Social
      Responsiveness Scale-Second Edition (SRS-2), Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ) and
      Eysenck Personality Questionnaire (EPQ) will be used to assess the clinical behavioral
      changes of all participants, and to analyze the clinical effectiveness and safety of
      pediatric massage for children with ASD.

      Electroencephalography (EEG) and brain functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) will be
      recorded before and after treatment, to observe the potential brain target of pediatric
      massage for children with ASD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by deﬁcits in
      social interactions and communication skills, both verbal and non-verbal, restricted
      interests, and stereotypical behaviors. However, at present, there is no drug has proven
      effective in alleviating the core symptoms of social and communication difficulties in ASD.

      ASD families are becoming turn to complementary and alternative medicine (CAM). They use CAM
      to treat symptoms of autism in general, comorbid symptoms (such as attention, hyperactivity,
      irritability, moodiness, gastrointestinal symptoms, seizures, sleep and tactile sensitivity).
      In addition, some families report that the use of CAM has less negative side effects compared
      with conventional treatments.

      As a traditional TCM therapy, pediatric massage has been used in treating various pediatric
      diseases including ASD. A large number of clinical studies have shown that pediatric massage
      can improve ASD and its accompanied symptoms effectively. However, its exact effectiveness
      and mechanism need to be further explored.

      In the proposed study, pediatric massage will be employed to treat children with ASD, to
      confirm the effectiveness and safety of pediatric massage therapy for children with ASD, and
      to explore the potential mechanism and target of pediatric massage for ASD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Autism Behavior Checklist (ABC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 week, 8 week, 12 week, and follow-up assessment at the week of 4, 8, 12 after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>ABC is a scale used for nonadaptive behaviors created to screen and indicate the probability of a diagnosis of autism. The questionnaire including 57 items related to five areas: sensorial, relational, use of body and objects, and social skills. Scale score＞ 67 strongly suggests the presence of autism. Changes in the ABC from baseline to endpoint will be observed. Assessments will be conducted at baseline and once every four weeks thereafter.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Childhood Autism Rating Scale (CARS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 week, 8 week, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>CARS assesses the child on a scale from 1 to 4 in each of 15 dimensions or symptoms (including the ability to relate to people, emotional response, imitation, body use, object use, listening response, fear or nervousness, verbal communication, nonverbal communication, activity level, level and reliability of intellectual response, adaptation to changes, visual response, taste, smell and touch responses and general impressions). A total score of at least 30 strongly suggests the presence of autism. Children with score between 30 and 36 have mild-to-moderate autism while those with score between 37 and 60 have severe autism. Change in CARS from Baseline to Endpoint will be observed. Assessments will be conducted at baseline and once every four weeks thereafter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Social Responsiveness Scale - Second Edition (SRS-2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 week, 8 week, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>The Social Responsiveness Scale is a parent- and/or teacher-reported 65 question scale designed to measure social competence. Each question on the scale inquires about an observed aspect of reciprocal social behavior that is rated from &quot;0&quot; to &quot;3&quot;, where 0 is best possible behavior and 3 is the worst possible behavior. The total SRS score may range from 0 to 195 where higher values represent the worse outcome. Assessments will be conducted at baseline and once every four weeks thereafter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 week, 8 week, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>The Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ) is a parental report sleep screening instrument designed for preschool- and school-aged children. The scale yields both a total score and 8 subscales reflecting the following sleep domains:1) bedtime resistance, 2) sleep onset delay, 3) sleep duration, 4) sleep anxiety, 5) night wakings, 6) parasomnias, 7) sleep-disordered breathing, 8) daytime sleepiness. Each item is answered with 1 of 3 markers: &quot;usually&quot; for 5 or more times a week, &quot;sometimes&quot; for 2-4 times a week, and &quot;rarely&quot; for never or 1 time a week. Higher scores reflect more disturbed sleep behavior. Assessments will be conducted at baseline and once every four weeks thereafter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the Eysenck Personality Questionnaire (EPQ) - adult version</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The EPQ is a three dimensional personality assessment tool to assess the personality traits of a person, including the Psychoticism (P), Extraversion (E), Neuroticism (N), and Lie (L) scales. Assessments will be conducted at baseline for parents to access parents' personality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in electroencephalography (EEG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>EEG is a useful indicator of cortical connectivity between functional areas in the brain. Continuous resting-state electroencephalography (EEG) was recorded before and after the 12-week treatment and the delta (δ), theta (θ), alpha (α), beta (β) and gamma (γ) bands frequency will be used for EEG analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) of the brain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>Functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) is a non-invasive neuroimaging procedure used to measure hemodynamic changes (oxyhemoglobin, deoxyhemoglobin and total haemoglobin), it will be measured at baseline and after the12-week treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with non-serious and serious adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety assessment. Adverse events that are related to treatment will be recorded once AE happens throughout the whole study. Adverse events rate will be assessed in all patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with abnormal laboratory values in blood routine examination.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>Safety assessment. Blood routine examination (including RBC, WBC, Hb, HCT, PLT, MCV, MCH, MCHC, W-SCR, W-LCR, W-SCC, W-LCC, RDW-CV, PDW, and MPV levels) will be conducted before and after treatment to evaluate if there is infection or anemia. Number of participants with abnormal laboratory values will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Children with ASD will receive pediatric massage for 12 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Waitlist control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pediatric massage therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Children with ASD will receive pediatric massage therapy twice a week for 12 consecutive weeks by professional pediatric massage doctor. In addition, they will receive parent provided pediatric massage therapy at home after their parents received the professional pediatric massage therapy training. The frequency of pediatric massage will not be more than once every day and each session last about 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric massage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual care</intervention_name>
    <description>Including Applied Behavior Analysis (ABA), Educational intervention, Interpersonal development intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pediatric massage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) has been diagnosed and a diagnosis certificate has been
             provided. The diagnostic criteria is based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of
             Mental Disorders fifth version (DSM-V) criteria of Autism Spectrum Disorder. Score of
             CARS≥30;

          2. Aged 3-10, right-handedness ；

          3. The parents (or other legal guardians) of participants to give consent and to
             cooperate with the treatment and data collection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The conventional treatment accepted currently does not belong to the following three
             categories: Applied Behavior Analysis (ABA), Educational intervention or Interpersonal
             development intervention;

          2. Patients with any major treatment changes within 4 weeks prior to joining the study;

          3. Patients or their parents with other neurodevelopmental disorders, severe psychiatric
             diseases, genetic disease, or other severe systemic disease (such as history of severe
             head trauma, or stroke);

          4. Seizure within the last year prior to enrolment, or the need for seizure medications
             either at present or in the past;

          5. Being involved in other clinical trials;

          6. Patients received pediatric massage therapy in the past two months, or are receiving
             pediatric massage;

          7. During the study period, parents will be required not to initiate any new
             interventions or modify current interventions unless absolutely necessary. If a change
             must be made, the parent is required to inform investigator, who decides whether the
             subject should stop participating in the study based on situation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>10 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhang-Jin Zhang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong-Shenzhen Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xin-Jing Yang</last_name>
    <phone>+852 39176471</phone>
    <email>yangxj@hku.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shenzhen Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenzhen</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>518038</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cong KOU</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18923838509</phone>
      <email>koucong1982@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cong KOU</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Chinese Medicine, The University of Hong Kong-Shenzhen Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shenzhen</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>518053</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shui-Yan ZHANG</last_name>
      <phone>+86 13826569649</phone>
      <email>zhangsy9@hku-szh.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Zhang-Jin ZHANG</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Zhang Zhang-Jin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

