<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227652</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FNO-KARIM-13-COVERSEP</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RVO-FNOs/2013-2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227652</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Control of Fever in Septic Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>COVERSEP</acronym>
  <official_title>Control of Fever in Septic Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Ostrava</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Ostrava</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The benefits of fever treatment in critically ill patients remains unclear. The aim of the
      prospective, randomized clinical trial was to verify the hypothesis that the administration
      of ibuprofen in order to decrease the fever in septic patients without limited
      cardiorespiratory reserve leads to decreasing their prognosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fever is a frequently observed part of the organism's response to infection, and it is a
      well-known fact that it has positive effects, as it inhibits the growth of microorganisms,
      and potentiates the activity of anti-microbial agents. On the other hand, fever increases the
      demand of tissues for oxygen and increases the production of carbon dioxide in tissues.
      Adapting to these metabolic changes requires an efficient cardiorespiratory apparatus. In
      other words, in patients with a limited cardiorespiratory reserve (typically patients of
      higher age or patients with a serious disease of the heart or lungs), the beneficial
      anti-microbial effect of fever may be masked with cardiorespiratory maladaptation to
      fever-induced metabolic changes. Indeed, one of the randomized clinical trials investigating
      the effect of &quot;aggressive&quot; antipyretic strategy used in practice (administration of
      acetaminophen at the temperature &gt; 38.5 degrees Celsius, and addition of physical cooling
      should the temperature exceed 39.5 degrees Celsius upon the prognosis of critically ill
      patients showed that the &quot;aggressive&quot; treatment of fever may result in higher mortality when
      compared with a &quot;permissive&quot; approach, i.e. an approach when the treatment of fever is
      initiated only after the body temperature has exceeded 40 degrees Celsius. The study differs
      remarkably from other studies performed among the population of critically ill patients, and
      also from studies, which did not manifest the effect of fever treatment upon the mortality of
      patients, with the age of patients. The average age of patients in both arms of the study was
      only 47 years of age, whereas the average age of patients in other studies was usually around
      60 years of age. It is thus possible to presume that, due to the lower age, the patients in
      this study possessed a sufficient cardiorespiratory reserve for adaptation to metabolic
      changes induced with fever, which may have enabled a full manifestation of its anti-microbial
      effect, and may have led to better patient prognosis. The mortality rate in the group of
      patients with the &quot;permissive&quot; approach to fever treatment was only 2.6 percent, whereas, in
      the group of patients with the &quot;aggressive&quot; treatment, the mortality rate was 15.9 percent
      (p=0.06); due to this fact, the study was prematurely terminated by the Ethics Committee.
      Based on this study, we decided to test the hypothesis that the administration of ibuprofen
      in order to decrease the fever would lead to a worsening of the patient prognosis. Ibuprofen
      was selected due to its potent antipyretic effect, and also due to the fact that the
      favorable effect of its anti-inflammatory effect upon the prognosis of patients with sepsis
      has not been fully demonstrated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study subjects were enrolled in two parallel groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>No masking was used in the study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SOFA score value</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The SOFA score (Sequential Organ Failure Assessment) was measured on Day 3 and Day 7</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum interleukin-6 level</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The serum interleukin-6 level was measured on Day 3 and Day 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum procalcitonine level</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The serum procalcitonine level was measured on Day 3 and Day 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum lactate level</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The serum lactate level was measured on Day 3 and Day 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Central venous oxygen saturation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>The central venous oxygen saturation was measured on Day 3 and Day 7</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of artificial ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of artificial ventilation in days was observed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of vasopressor support</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of vasopressor support in days was observed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of ICU stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The length of ICU stay in days was observed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The length of hospital stay in days was observed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Severe Sepsis</condition>
  <condition>Septic Shock</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive treatment strategy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The antipyretic strategy was initiated immediately upon increase of the temperature above 38.3°C. The antipyretic strategy consisted of administration of ibuprofen (per-orally or into the nasogastric tube, or rectal administration in the form of a suppository) in therapeutical dose, alway supplemented with physical cooling in cases when the temperature exceeded 39.5°C. The body temperature was measured in the urinary bladder.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative treatment strategy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The antipyretic strategy was initiated only after the body temperature exceeded 39.5°C. The antipyretic strategy consisted of administration of ibuprofen (per-orally or into the nasogastric tube, or rectal administration in the form of a suppository) in therapeutical dose, alway supplemented with physical cooling in cases when the temperature exceeded 39.5°C. The body temperature was measured in the urinary bladder.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ibuprofen administration</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of ibuprofen, according to treatment recommendations - per orally, into the nasogastric tube, or in the form of a suppository</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aggressive treatment strategy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Conservative treatment strategy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt;18 years of age

          -  body temperature &gt;38.3°C within 2 consecutive hours

          -  anti-microbial therapy for a known or suspected infection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients admitted after successful cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR)

          -  acute myocardial infarction

          -  brain injury (traumatic and non-traumatic)

          -  transfer from another ICU after 72 hours

          -  pregnancy

          -  antipyretic medication prior to randomization

          -  non-obtaining the informed consent

          -  moribund condition

          -  high risk of hemodynamic or respiratory maladaptation on the metabolic effect of fever
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roman Kula, MD,CSc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Ostrava</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Ostrava</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ostrava</city>
        <state>Moravian-Silesian Region</state>
        <zip>70852</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schulman CI, Namias N, Doherty J, Manning RJ, Li P, Elhaddad A, Lasko D, Amortegui J, Dy CJ, Dlugasch L, Baracco G, Cohn SM. The effect of antipyretic therapy upon outcomes in critically ill patients: a randomized, prospective study. Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2005 Winter;6(4):369-75. Erratum in: Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2010 Oct;11(5):495. Li, Pam [corrected to Li, Pamela]; Alhaddad, Ahmed [corrected to Elhaddad, Ahmed].</citation>
    <PMID>16433601</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young P, Saxena M, Bellomo R, Freebairn R, Hammond N, van Haren F, Holliday M, Henderson S, Mackle D, McArthur C, McGuinness S, Myburgh J, Weatherall M, Webb S, Beasley R; HEAT Investigators; Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Society Clinical Trials Group. Acetaminophen for Fever in Critically Ill Patients with Suspected Infection. N Engl J Med. 2015 Dec 3;373(23):2215-24. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1508375. Epub 2015 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26436473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ye S, Xu D, Zhang C, Li M, Zhang Y. Effect of Antipyretic Therapy on Mortality in Critically Ill Patients with Sepsis Receiving Mechanical Ventilation Treatment. Can Respir J. 2017;2017:3087505. doi: 10.1155/2017/3087505. Epub 2017 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28386165</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernard GR, Wheeler AP, Russell JA, Schein R, Summer WR, Steinberg KP, Fulkerson WJ, Wright PE, Christman BW, Dupont WD, Higgins SB, Swindell BB. The effects of ibuprofen on the physiology and survival of patients with sepsis. The Ibuprofen in Sepsis Study Group. N Engl J Med. 1997 Mar 27;336(13):912-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9070471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>severe sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>septic shock</keyword>
  <keyword>fever</keyword>
  <keyword>ibuprofen</keyword>
  <keyword>physiological reserves</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sepsis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Toxemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ibuprofen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There exists no plan to make individual participant data available to other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

