<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04224454</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RECHMPL19_0612</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04224454</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Coverage and Primary Sjögren'Syndrome</brief_title>
  <acronym>VACGREN</acronym>
  <official_title>Influenza, Pneumococcal and Diphtheria-tetanus-poliomyelitis Vaccine Coverage in Patients With Primary Sjögren's Syndrome: a Cross-sectional Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Montpellier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Montpellier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of vaccination coverage for influenza, pneumococcus and DTP in patients with pSS
      and investigated the reasons for non-vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A cross-sectional study was performed in pSS patients from two different French tertiary
      referral centers for autoimmune diseases (Paris-Bicêtre and Montpellier). From January 2016
      to November 2017, questionnaires were randomly delivered to patients with pSS according to
      European-American Diagnostic Criteria (2002). Before completing the questionnaire, patients
      gave their consent to participate. This questionnaire was adapted from questionnaires used by
      the French national agency &quot;Institut de Veille Sanitaire&quot; to study vaccination coverage and
      were completed with the assistance of one fellow (HL) to limit missing data.

      Data collected in the questionnaire included previous vaccinations, reasons for
      non-vaccination, sources of vaccine proposition, and sociodemographic data including
      education level (Bachelor degree, and post-Bachelor degree education) and presence of young
      child(ren) (inferior 10 years old) at home. The following data was collected from the medical
      file: European-American Diagnostic Criteria (2002) for pSS, the most recent EULAR Sjögren's
      syndrome disease activity index (ESSDAI), comorbidities (chronic lung diseases, diabetes,
      chronic kidney diseases, chronic liver diseases, chronic heart diseases, cardiovascular
      comorbidities [coronary or cerebral ischemia] and severe neurological or muscle diseases),
      history of severe A cross-sectional study was performed in pSS patients from two different
      French tertiary referral centers for autoimmune diseases (Paris-Bicêtre and Montpellier).
      From January 2016 to November 2017, questionnaires were randomly delivered to patients with
      pSS according to European-American Diagnostic Criteria (2002). Before completing the
      questionnaire, patients gave their consent to participate. This questionnaire was adapted
      from questionnaires used by the French national agency &quot;Institut de Veille Sanitaire&quot; to
      study vaccination coverage and were completed with the assistance of one fellow (HL) to limit
      missing data. Data collected in the questionnaire included previous vaccinations, reasons for
      non-vaccination, sources of vaccine proposition, and sociodemographic data including
      education level (Bachelor degree, and post-Bachelor degree education) and presence of young
      child(ren) (inferior 10 years old) at home. The following data was collected from the medical
      file: European-American Diagnostic Criteria (2002) for pSS, the most recent EULAR Sjögren's
      syndrome disease activity index (ESSDAI), comorbidities (chronic lung diseases, diabetes,
      chronic kidney diseases, chronic liver diseases, chronic heart diseases, cardiovascular
      comorbidities [coronary or cerebral ischemia] and severe neurological or muscle diseases),
      history of severe infection (requiring intravenous antibiotics or hospital admission),
      current smoking status, treatments used for pSS including hydroxychloroquine,
      immunosuppressive drugs (methotrexate, leflunomide, ciclosporine, azathioprine, mycophenolate
      mofetil) and biological disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs (bDMARDs).

      For descriptive statistical analysis, mean more or less SD were used for continuous variables
      and frequencies (percentage) for categorical variables. To evaluate factors associated with
      up-to-date vaccination, the investigators compared categorical variables between patients
      with updated and non-updated influenza, pneumococcal or DTP vaccines by using the Fisher
      exact test or chi-square test as appropriate. Continuous variables (age, ESSDAI) were
      compared by Student t test. A binary logistic regression model was used for multivariate
      analysis to estimate the odds ratio (OR) of being vaccinated with the 95% confidence interval
      (CI). p&lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. All statistical analyses were
      performed with IBM SPSS 15 software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against influenzae virus</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against influenzae virus: number of patients vaccinated against influenzae virus within 1 year divided to the number of patients not vaccinated against influenzae virus within 1 year</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against streptococcus pneumoniae</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against streptococcus pneumoniae: number of patients vaccinated against streptococcus pneumoniae within 5 years divided to the number of patients not vaccinated against streptococcus pneumoniae within 5 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against DTP</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of patients with Sjögren's syndrome vaccinated against DTP : number of patients vaccinated for DTP within 10 years divided to the number of patients not vaccinated for DTP within 10 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the reasons for non-vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the reasons for non-vaccination : The questionnaire was adapted from questionnaires used by the French national agency &quot;Institut de Veille Sanitaire&quot; to study vaccination coverage and were completed with the assistance of one fellow (HL) to limit missing data (18). Data collected in the questionnaire included previous vaccinations, reasons for non-vaccination, sources of vaccine proposition, and sociodemographic data including education level (Bachelor degree, and post-Bachelor degree education) and presence of young child(ren) (&lt;10 years old) at home.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">111</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Sjögren Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Sjögren's syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>111 consecutive patients with primary Sjögren's syndrome (European-American 2002 criteria)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaire was adapted from questionnaires used by the French national agency &quot;Institut de Veille Sanitaire&quot; to study vaccination coverage and were completed with the assistance of one fellow to limit missing data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Primary Sjögren's syndrome</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients with primary Sjögren'syndrome
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        - patients with pSS according to European-American Diagnostic Criteria

        Exclusion criteria:

        - Refusal to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacques MOREL, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uhmontpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gluthmann J FL, Bonmarin I, Levy-Bruhl D. Enquête nationale de couverture vaccinale, France, janvier 2011. http://www.invs.sante.fr. . 2001.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 2, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Coverage</keyword>
  <keyword>Sjögren's syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sjogren's Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>NC</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

