<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04226859</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRAJAKT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04226859</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trajectories of Glomerular Filtration Rate and Progression to End Stage Renal Disease After Kidney Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRAJAKT</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicenter International Observational Study to Identify eGFR Trajectories and Their Determinants, and to Build a Multidimensional Prediction System to Predict the Probabilities of Belonging to eGFR Trajectories</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Paris Translational Research Center for Organ Transplantation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Paris Translational Research Center for Organ Transplantation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The gold standard for characterizing chronic kidney disease (CKD) is the glomerular
      filtration rate (GFR), which is commonly estimated in both native and transplanted kidneys
      for patient monitoring and therapeutic management and ultimately guides decision-making about
      whether a patient needs renal replacement therapy. In particular, the National Kidney
      Foundation has defined CKD stages according to estimated GFR (eGFR) values and in several
      studies, the eGFR slope or change has been found to be strongly associated with end stage
      renal disease (ESRD).

      However, little is known about the heterogeneity of eGFR evolution in time - i.e. eGFR
      trajectories - and the related progression to ESRD and death. To date, no studies have
      investigated eGFR trajectories in diversified cohorts and populations worldwide, although
      this approach could provide a better understanding of CKD evolution and hence improve risk
      stratification. In addition, determinants of eGFR trajectories remain poorly described.

      An unsupervised approach could allow examining eGFR trajectories over time and could lead to
      the identification of patient groups according to the probability of the progression of their
      kidney disease.

      Therefore, this study aims:

        1. To identify the long-term eGFR trajectories after kidney transplantation using latent
           class mixed models;

        2. To identify the clinical, immunological, histological and functional determinants of the
           eGFR trajectories using multinomial regressions;

        3. To investigate the associations of the eGFR trajectories with the progression to ESRD
           and death.

      Based on the results, the investigators will provide an easily accessible tool to calculate
      personalized probabilities of belonging to eGFR trajectories after kidney transplantation, by
      using datasets from prospective cohorts and post hoc analysis of randomized control trial
      datasets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Chronic kidney disease (CKD) now affects 850 million individuals worldwide, exceeding the
      global prevalence of diabetes, cancer and HIV/AIDS. In addition, end-stage renal disease
      affects 7.4 million individuals and mortality rate for individuals burdened by kidney disease
      is now estimated at 5 to 10 million individuals each year. Therefore, developing better
      diagnostic and treatment approaches for the kidney disease epidemic is a global priority, as
      leading professional societies and health agencies have emphasized (the US Food &amp; Drug
      Administration, the National Kidney Foundation, the European Medicines Agency, the European
      Society of Organ Transplantation, the American Society for Transplantation and the American
      Society of Transplant Surgeons).

      However, current approaches for investigating the relationship between eGFR course and
      outcomes such as ESRD and mortality have been limited by registries with an overall lack on
      granular data, including infrequent eGFR measurements for a single patient and convenience
      clinical samples. An unsupervised longitudinal approach to determine patient eGFR evolution
      may bring an original perspective to the traditional clinical interpretation of kidney
      function based on limited eGFR measurements, short-term follow-up, and standard statistical
      approach.

      Main Outcome(s) and Measure(s)

        -  eGFR trajectories

        -  Determinants of eGFR trajectories

        -  Associations of eGFR trajectories with ESRD and death

        -  Prediction system that will provide the personalized probabilities of belonging to eGFR
           trajectories
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>eGFR trajectories</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 10 years after kidney transplantation</time_frame>
    <description>eGFR trajectories probabilities, calculated from a prediction system (based on clinical, histological, immunological, and functional factors) assessed at 1-year post transplantation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">14000</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Transplant Failure</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Function Issue</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Kidney recipients aged over 18 and of all sexes recruited from 2000 in European and North American centers, who have eGFR follow-up and data from protocol and for cause biopsies available for allograft survival assessment; Randomized controlled trials conducted over the past 20 years with available data on protocol biopsy within the first year and follow up clinical, biological and histological data.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Kidney recipients aged over 18 and of all sexes recruited from 2000 in European and North
        American centers, who have eGFR repeated measurements, data from protocol and for cause
        biopsies, as well as immunological, clinical, functional parameters and survival data for
        allograft and patient survival assessment. Additional kidney recipients from RCTs with
        longitudinal data including baseline and follow-up clinical, functional, immunological and
        histological data.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Kidney recipients transplanted after 2000

          -  Kidney recipients over 18 years of age

          -  Kidney recipients with at least two eGFR measurements after transplantation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Combined transplantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexandre Loupy, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Paris Translational Research Center for Organ Transplantation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandre Loupy, Professor</last_name>
    <email>alexandre.loupy@inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marc Raynaud</last_name>
    <phone>+33613493009</phone>
    <email>mrayna06@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Medicine, Division of Nephrology, Comprehensive Transplant Center, Cedars Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Surgery, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>William J. von Liebig Center for Transplantation and Clinical Regeneration, Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Renal Division Montefiore Medical Center, Kidney Transplantation Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>980663</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Nephrology and Renal Transplantation, University Hospitals Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Nephrology, Arterial Hypertension, Dialysis and Transplantation, University Hospital Centre Zagreb, School od Medicine University of Zagreb</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zagreb</city>
        <zip>10000</zip>
        <country>Croatia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Nephrology, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nephrology Dialysis Transplantation Department, University of Lorraine, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nancy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nancy</city>
        <zip>54035</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Nantes</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nantes</city>
        <zip>44093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kidney Transplant Department, Saint-Louis Hospital, Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75010</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carmen Lefaucheur, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kidney Transplant Department, Necker Hospital, Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75015</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexandre Loupy, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+33612491082</phone>
      <email>alexandre.loupy@inserm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Transplantation, Nephrology and Clinical Immunology, Hôpital Foch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Suresnes</city>
        <zip>92150</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Nephrology and Organ Transplantation, Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Rangueil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bretonneau Hospital, Nephrology and Immunology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tours</city>
        <zip>37000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Enrolling by invitation</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Croatia</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.paristransplantgroup.org</url>
    <description>Paris Transplant Group Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft Survival</keyword>
  <keyword>Glomerular Filtration Rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Trajectories</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

