<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04221191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FRA-BGT-18-11469</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04221191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF, Tecfidera®) Persistence in RR-MS Patients Included in the French Patient Support Program OroSEP</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEC-ADHERE</acronym>
  <official_title>Study on the Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF, Tecfidera®) Persistence of Remitting-relapsing Multiple Sclerosis (RR-MS) Patients Included in the French Patient Support Program (PSP) OroSEP</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biogen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biogen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective is to compare oral dimethyl fumarate (DMF) persistence at six months in
      relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (RR-MS) participants initiating DMF with and without
      OroSEP patient support program (PSP), respectively.

      The secondary objectives are: to compare oral DMF persistence at one month and three months
      in RR-MS participants initiating DMF with and without OroSEP PSP, respectively; To compare
      oral DMF adherence at six months in RR-MS participants initiating DMF with and without OroSEP
      PSP; To compare at three months and six months the reason of oral DMF discontinuation, in the
      two groups; To describe the percentage of participants with treatment-related adverse events
      globally and by class of adverse events, in the two groups of participants; To assess the
      evolution of participants' anxiety globally and to compare it at inclusion and at six months
      in participants with and without OroSEP PSP, respectively; To describe participants'
      satisfaction regarding oral DMF initiation and follow-up globally at six months and to
      compare it in patients with and without OroSEP PSP, respectively;

      For OroSEP PSP group: To assess participants' satisfaction regarding their participation in
      OroSEP PSP at six months; To assess neurologists' satisfaction regarding their participation
      in OroSEP PSP, after the last participant last visit of center.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 19, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 19, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Oral Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF) Persistence at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Persistence is defined as the percentage of participant still being treated by oral DMF at 6 months, according to routine visit.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Oral Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF) Persistence at Both 1 Month and 3 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Persistence is defined as the percentage of participants still being treated by oral DMF at both 1 month and 3 months, according to routine practice.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participant's with Adherence at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant's adherence is assessed through the validated Girerd questionnaire. This is a 6-item self-questionnaire completed by participants with a scale of 0 for &quot;Yes&quot; and 1 for &quot;No&quot; for each question. Points for each question are summed up to obtain a global score between 0 if all the questions are ticked with &quot;Yes&quot; (reflecting a bad adherence), and 6 if all questions are ticked &quot;No&quot; (reflecting a good adherence).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants by Reason of Oral Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF) Discontinuation at 3 Months and 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 month and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Discontinuation of DMF therapy is defined by the presence of any of the following criteria: definitive discontinuation declared by the physician during routine follow-up visit through electronic case report form (eCRF); a temporary stop declared by the physician during routine visit at 3 months, without DMF resumption declared at 6 months by the physician; a switch to another DMT declared by the physician during routine follow-up visit through eCRF.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient or clinical investigation participant administered a pharmaceutical product and that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (including an abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal (investigational) product, whether or not related to the medicinal (investigational) product.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) Related to Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) Leading to Treatment Discontinuation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Adverse Events (AEs) of Interest</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>AEs of interest includes gastrointestinal disorders, flush, lymphopenia.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant's Anxiety at Inclusion and at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>0 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant's anxiety is assessed through the Generalized Anxiety Disorder - 7 (GAD-7) self-questionnaire. The GAD-7 is a questionnaire that is used primarily to detect possible generalized anxiety disorders, disorders of panic, social anxiety and post-traumatic stress disorder. It is more specifically a self-questionnaire (completed by the participant) consisting of 7 items rated from 0 to 3. The total score is obtained by adding the score obtained to each item (score ranging from 0 to 21). A total score greater than 7 is suggestive of a generalized anxiety disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant's Satisfaction Regarding Dimethyl Fumarate (DMF) Treatment at 6 Months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant's satisfaction regarding DMF treatment is assessed through the validated Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire for Medication (TSQM-9) score completed by the participant. The TSQM-9, a 9-items questionnaire, designed as a general measure of treatment satisfaction with medication. TSQM items are answered on 5- or 7-point Likert type scale and cover three domains, corresponding to distinct aspects related to the satisfaction of participants with their treatment (effectiveness, convenience and global satisfaction). A score can be obtained for each domain by summing the corresponding items transformed on a 0-100 scale. Higher value indicates more satisfaction, better perceived effectiveness, lower burden associated with better convenience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant's Satisfaction Regarding their Participation in OroSEP Patient Support Program (PSP)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Participant's satisfaction is assessed at Month 6 using a questionnaire completed by the participant consisting of 3 questions. Questions 1 and 2 are assessed using a Likert scale (1-5) with scale range 1= Strongly disagree to 5= Strongly agree. Question 3 is assessed using the net promoter scale (1-7), where 1 indicates &quot;not at all likely&quot; and 7 indicates &quot;extremely likely&quot;. Higher values indicate higher satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurologists' Satisfaction Regarding their Participation in OroSEP Patient Support Program (PSP)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Neurologist's satisfaction is assessed after the last participant last visit of the site center using a 10-item questionnaire, completed by the physician. Question (Q) 1, Q3, Q4, Q6, Q7, Q8= is answered &quot;Yes/No&quot;; Q2= Lack of time, Lack of interest, Patient refused, Forget, No registration form available, Registration process too complicated / Other: specify; Q5= The availability of the call center, The monitoring of patient compliance, The coordination of biological assessments, Other: specify; Q9: 1 bad satisfaction, 10 good satisfaction and Q10 was an open answer.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SoC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>SoC neurologists will include and follow-up all study participants who receive DMF according to their standard of care practice (non-coached participants).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OroSEP PSP (OPSP) Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>OPSP neurologists will include and follow-up all study participants who receive DMF according to their standard of care practice and the OroSEP PSP (coached participants).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dimethyl Fumarate</intervention_name>
    <description>DMF as prescribed as standard of care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OroSEP PSP (OPSP) Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SoC) Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tecfidera®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PSP</intervention_name>
    <description>PSPs is to support patient care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OroSEP PSP (OPSP) Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population included participants with RR-MS treated with DMF in clinical practice.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to understand the purpose and risks of the study and giving oral informed
             consent regarding TEC-ADHERE study and authorization to use protected health
             information (PHI) in accordance with national and local participant privacy
             regulations;

          -  Diagnosis of RR-MS;

          -  Initiating oral DMF according to Summary of Product Characteristics (SmPC) at the
             inclusion visit;

          -  Expanded Disability Status Score (EDSS) under 6.

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants with progressive form of Multiple Sclerosis (MS);

          -  With memory or psychiatric disorders preventing them to complete questionnaires in the
             study.

        Note: Other protocol defined Inclusion/Exclusion criteria may apply.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biogen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US Biogen Clinical Trial Center</last_name>
    <phone>866-633-4636</phone>
    <email>clinicaltrials@biogen.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Global Biogen Clinical Trial Center</last_name>
    <email>clinicaltrials@biogen.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Agen</city>
        <zip>47000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albi</city>
        <zip>81013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Annecy</city>
        <zip>74000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antibes</city>
        <zip>6600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bayonne</city>
        <zip>64100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carcassonne</city>
        <zip>11000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Corbeil-Essonnes</city>
        <zip>91100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cornebarrieu</city>
        <zip>31700</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dax</city>
        <zip>40100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Douai</city>
        <zip>59500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Rochelle</city>
        <zip>17000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Seyne-sur-Mer</city>
        <zip>83500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Limoges</city>
        <zip>87000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69006</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montauban</city>
        <zip>82000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34090</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mornant</city>
        <zip>69440</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muret</city>
        <zip>31600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nimes</city>
        <zip>30900</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Perpignan</city>
        <zip>66000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pessac</city>
        <zip>33600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poissy</city>
        <zip>78300</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roubaix</city>
        <zip>59100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rueil-Malmaison</city>
        <zip>92500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Talence</city>
        <zip>33400</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse cedex 9</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vesoul Cedex</city>
        <zip>7000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dimethyl Fumarate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>In accordance with Biogen's Clinical Trial Transparency and Data Sharing Policy on http://clinicalresearch.biogen.com/</ipd_description>
    <ipd_url>http://www.biogenclinicaldatarequest.com/</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

