<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04224090</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Cor001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04224090</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnostic Performance of a New Method for the Echocardiographic Assessment of Coronary Arteries Abnormalities</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnostic Performance of a Rational and Standardized New Method for the Echocardiographic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ITAB - Institute for Advanced Biomedical Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ospedali Riuniti Ancona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ITAB - Institute for Advanced Biomedical Technologies</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery anomalies (CAA) are a rare congenital condition, accounting abnormalities of
      origin, course, destination, size, and number of the coronary vessels. In normal hearts, the
      coronary arteries, the left and right coronary arteries (LCA and RCA, respectively) originate
      from the two facing aortic sinuses of Valsalva, so-called left and right. To overcome the
      echocardiographic limitations, the investigators designed, studied and implemented in our
      Institute a specific echocardiographic-based two-dimensional non-Doppler 4-views approach for
      the diagnosis of CAA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The method consisted of 4-CAA-focused specific views, routinely available from any
      echocardiographic exam: parasternal short-axis (PSAX), parasternal long-axis (PLAX), apical
      4/5-chambers views. PSAX, the traditional approach, along with the PLAX, and the apical
      4/5-chambers views.

      A hallmark of CAA was considered the absence of a proper visualization of the origin of the
      coronary arteries from the aortic root. In addition, the presence of the ring sign,
      visualized from the PLAX was considered as abnormal. This sign is of interest when an
      aberrant left or right CAA is suspected. A coronary artery originating from the contralateral
      aortic sinus, along its intramural course, crosses the mid-anterior line of the circular
      aorta to reach the sinus of Valsalva of its intended origin. Consequently, its cross-section
      should be visible in an orthogonal view traversing the mid-long axis of the aorta, namely the
      parasternal long-axis view.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CAA</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the routine echocardiography assessment</time_frame>
    <description>The number of coronary arteries anomalies echocardiographically detected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4000</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Anomaly</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Congenita coronary abnormalities (CAA)</arm_group_label>
    <description>All the coronary arteries were differing from the definition of &quot;normal&quot;: when do not arise from the appropriate sinus of Valsalva (right or left) and not present a proper course and termination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Echocardiographic assessment of coronary arteries origin and proximal course</intervention_name>
    <description>Echocardiographic assessment of CAA utilizing 4 specific echocardiographic acoustic windows: parasternal short-axis (PSAX), parasternal long-axis (PLAX), apical 4/5-chambers views.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Congenita coronary abnormalities (CAA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Outpatients (neonates, pediatrics, adolescents and young adults) undergoing routine
        echocardiography in our department
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients undergoing their first echocardiographic examination

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  already known congenital heart disease and cardiomyopathies
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francesco Bianco, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+39 071 596 5316</phone>
    <email>francesco.bianco@ospedaliriuniti.marche.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedali Riuniti</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ancona</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Francesco Bianco, MD</last_name>
      <email>francesco.bianco@ospedaliriuniti.marche.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Valentina Bucciarelli, MD</last_name>
      <email>valentina.bucciarelli@ospedaliriuniti.marche.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheezum MK, Liberthson RR, Shah NR, Villines TC, O'Gara PT, Landzberg MJ, Blankstein R. Anomalous Aortic Origin of a Coronary Artery From the Inappropriate Sinus of Valsalva. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2017 Mar 28;69(12):1592-1608. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2017.01.031. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28335843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angelini P. Normal and anomalous coronary arteries in humans. In. Coronary artery anomalies: A comprehensive approach. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pérez-Pomares JM, de la Pompa JL, Franco D, Henderson D, Ho SY, Houyel L, Kelly RG, Sedmera D, Sheppard M, Sperling S, Thiene G, van den Hoff M, Basso C. Congenital coronary artery anomalies: a bridge from embryology to anatomy and pathophysiology--a position statement of the development, anatomy, and pathology ESC Working Group. Cardiovasc Res. 2016 Feb 1;109(2):204-16. doi: 10.1093/cvr/cvv251. Epub 2016 Jan 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26811390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basso C, Maron BJ, Corrado D, Thiene G. Clinical profile of congenital coronary artery anomalies with origin from the wrong aortic sinus leading to sudden death in young competitive athletes. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2000 May;35(6):1493-501. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10807452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maron BJ, Doerer JJ, Haas TS, Tierney DM, Mueller FO. Sudden deaths in young competitive athletes: analysis of 1866 deaths in the United States, 1980-2006. Circulation. 2009 Mar 3;119(8):1085-92. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.108.804617. Epub 2009 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19221222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lang RM, Badano LP, Mor-Avi V, Afilalo J, Armstrong A, Ernande L, Flachskampf FA, Foster E, Goldstein SA, Kuznetsova T, Lancellotti P, Muraru D, Picard MH, Rietzschel ER, Rudski L, Spencer KT, Tsang W, Voigt JU. Recommendations for cardiac chamber quantification by echocardiography in adults: an update from the American Society of Echocardiography and the European Association of Cardiovascular Imaging. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2015 Jan;28(1):1-39.e14. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2014.10.003.</citation>
    <PMID>25559473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jureidini SB, Marino CJ, Singh GK, Balfour IC, Rao PS, Chen SC. Aberrant coronary arteries: a reliable echocardiographic screening method. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2003 Jul;16(7):756-63.</citation>
    <PMID>12835663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown LM, Duffy CE, Mitchell C, Young L. A practical guide to pediatric coronary artery imaging with echocardiography. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2015 Apr;28(4):379-91. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2015.01.008. Epub 2015 Feb 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25691000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>ITAB - Institute for Advanced Biomedical Technologies</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Bianco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Coronary arteries abnormalities</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary arteries anomaly</keyword>
  <keyword>Coronary origin from the wrong sinus of Valsalva</keyword>
  <keyword>Echocardiography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Congenital Abnormalities</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

