<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227444</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R1033/19-IEO1088</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227444</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Evaluation of Pulmonary Vascular Anatomy by Holograms</brief_title>
  <acronym>Holo-lungs</acronym>
  <official_title>Preoperative Evaluation of Pulmonary Vascular Anatomy by Augmented Reality (Holograms) in Patients Undergoing Lung Resection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Institute of Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Institute of Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary vascular anatomy represents a constant challenge during lung resection, because of
      its variability in terms of vascular branches and anatomical variations.

      Preoperative standard computed tomography is not always sufficient to foresee tricky
      abnormalities; augmented reality, thanks to holograms creation, may offer additional data on
      pulmonary vascular anatomy and its relation with neoplastic tissue. The aim of this study is
      to assess the possibility of correctly predict number, location and potential anomalies of
      pulmonary vascular anatomy of the lobe to be resected in patients undergoing lung resection
      for cancer.

      Patients will receive standard preoperative oncologic and functional assessment. Preoperative
      computed tomography (CT) - performed according to a specific protocol - will be performed. CT
      images will be subsequently elaborated to generate 3D images (holograms). Two radiologists
      and two thoracic surgeons will analyze CT images and report number of artery and vein
      branches for the lobe to be resected. Moreover they will report every anatomical variation,
      according to the normal anatomy. After that, the same two radiologists and thoracic surgeons
      will analyze the holograms and perform the same analysis as quoted above. Patients will
      undergo to the planned surgical resection. The operating team will report the exact number of
      artery and vein branches of the resected lobe as well as every anatomical variation.
      Preoperative CT and holographic findings of the radiologists and the thoracic surgeons will
      be matched with the report of the operating team.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An augmented reality (AR) system provides the surgeon with computer processed imaging data in
      real-time via dedicated hardware and software. The projection of AR is made possible by using
      displays, projectors, cameras, trackers, or other specialized equipment.

      At present, the applications of AR are limited by the essential requisite of preoperative 3D
      reconstructions of medical images. It is possible to create these reconstructions by using
      commercial or self-made software from the Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine
      (DICOM) format . The quality of a reconstruction depends on the quality of input data and the
      accuracy of the reconstruction system. Such reconstructions can be used for virtual
      exploration of target areas, planning an elective surgical approach in advance, and for
      better orientation and navigation in the operative ﬁeld. AR is especially useful in
      visualizing critical structures such as major vessels, nerves, or other vital tissues. By
      projecting these structures directly onto the patient, AR increases safety and reduces the
      time required to complete the procedure. Moreover Augmented reality proved to be an eﬀective
      tool for training and skill assessment of surgery residents, other medical staﬀ, or students.
      Augmented reality can be used eﬀectively for preoperative planning and completion of the
      actual surgery in timely fashion. The preoperative 3D reconstructed images can be modiﬁed and
      prepared for display in AR systems. Commonly, AR is used for tailoring individually preferred
      incisions and cutting planes, optimal placement of trocars, or to generally improve safety by
      displaying positions of major organ components. Another beneﬁt of AR is the ability to aid
      surgeons in diﬃcult terrain after a neoadjuvant chemotherapy or radiotherapy.

      Studies suggest that AR systems are becoming comparable to traditional navigation techniques,
      with precision and safety suﬃcient for routine clinical practice. Most problems faced
      presently will be solved by further medical and technological research. Augmented reality
      appears to be a powerful tool possibly capable of changing the ﬁeld of surgery through a
      rational use. In the future, AR will likely serve as an advanced human-computer interface,
      working in symbiosis with surgeons, allowing them to achieve even better results.
      Nevertheless, further advancement is much needed to achieve maximum potential and
      cost-eﬀectiveness of augmented reality.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prediction of the exact number of pulmonary arteries and veins of the lobe to be resected.</measure>
    <time_frame>2020 - 2022</time_frame>
    <description>Two different investigator (1 senior radiologist and 1 senior thoracic surgery) evaluate standard preoperative CT scan and indicate the number of pulmonary artery and veins of the lobe to be resected; this will be reported in a dedicated registry. After that, the same investigators will evaluate holograms of the same patients and will report the number of arteries and veins of the lobe to be resected; they will then register these data in the same registry. After the operation, the operating surgeon will report - as usual - the number of the arteries and veins resected during the procedure. Finally the prediction of the investigators obtained only by CT scan evaluation or bay CT scan + holograms evaluation, will be compared with the operatory report.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hologram</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient undergoing elective anatomical resection for lung cancer will receive standard preoperative CT scan of the chest (as usual); CT images will be subsequently elaborated by a Holographic computer to generate 3D images (holograms).Two radiologists and two thoracic surgeons will analyze CT images in a standard modality and report number of artery and vein branches for the lobe to be resected, moreover they will report every anatomical variation, according to the normal anatomy.
After that, the same two radiologists and thoracic surgeons will analyze 3D images by the use of Microsoft Hololens and perform the same analysis as quoted above.
For each review of the exam performed will be written a digitally signed clinical report to certify the timing of the evaluation and to be able to trace the analysis and any subsequent modifications of the interpretation of the CT images results.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients suffering from (any) lung cancer scheduled for anatomical lung resection
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Planned anatomical resection for lung cancer

          -  Signed and dated informed consent indicating that the patient has been informed of all
             pertinent aspects of the study.

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age younger than 18 years

          -  Contraindications to general anesthesia

          -  Poor general clinical conditions ( ECOG PS &gt;=2)

          -  Patients unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Francesco Petrella, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>00390294372921</phone>
    <email>francesco.petrella@ieo.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vávra P, Roman J, Zonča P, Ihnát P, Němec M, Kumar J, Habib N, El-Gendi A. Recent Development of Augmented Reality in Surgery: A Review. J Healthc Eng. 2017;2017:4574172. doi: 10.1155/2017/4574172. Epub 2017 Aug 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29065604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pessaux P, Diana M, Soler L, Piardi T, Mutter D, Marescaux J. Towards cybernetic surgery: robotic and augmented reality-assisted liver segmentectomy. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2015 Apr;400(3):381-5. doi: 10.1007/s00423-014-1256-9. Epub 2014 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25392120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Inoue D, Cho B, Mori M, Kikkawa Y, Amano T, Nakamizo A, Yoshimoto K, Mizoguchi M, Tomikawa M, Hong J, Hashizume M, Sasaki T. Preliminary study on the clinical application of augmented reality neuronavigation. J Neurol Surg A Cent Eur Neurosurg. 2013 Mar;74(2):71-6. doi: 10.1055/s-0032-1333415. Epub 2013 Feb 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23404553</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pessaux P, Diana M, Soler L, Piardi T, Mutter D, Marescaux J. Robotic duodenopancreatectomy assisted with augmented reality and real-time fluorescence guidance. Surg Endosc. 2014 Aug;28(8):2493-8. doi: 10.1007/s00464-014-3465-2. Epub 2014 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24609700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shakur SF, Luciano CJ, Kania P, Roitberg BZ, Banerjee PP, Slavin KV, Sorenson J, Charbel FT, Alaraj A. Usefulness of a Virtual Reality Percutaneous Trigeminal Rhizotomy Simulator in Neurosurgical Training. Neurosurgery. 2015 Sep;11 Suppl 3:420-5; discussion 425. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000000853.</citation>
    <PMID>26103444</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lahanas V, Loukas C, Smailis N, Georgiou E. A novel augmented reality simulator for skills assessment in minimal invasive surgery. Surg Endosc. 2015 Aug;29(8):2224-34. doi: 10.1007/s00464-014-3930-y. Epub 2014 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25303925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qu M, Hou Y, Xu Y, Shen C, Zhu M, Xie L, Wang H, Zhang Y, Chai G. Precise positioning of an intraoral distractor using augmented reality in patients with hemifacial microsomia. J Craniomaxillofac Surg. 2015 Jan;43(1):106-12. doi: 10.1016/j.jcms.2014.10.019. Epub 2014 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25465484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller M, Rassweiler MC, Klein J, Seitel A, Gondan M, Baumhauer M, Teber D, Rassweiler JJ, Meinzer HP, Maier-Hein L. Mobile augmented reality for computer-assisted percutaneous nephrolithotomy. Int J Comput Assist Radiol Surg. 2013 Jul;8(4):663-75. doi: 10.1007/s11548-013-0828-4. Epub 2013 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>23526436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volonté F, Pugin F, Bucher P, Sugimoto M, Ratib O, Morel P. Augmented reality and image overlay navigation with OsiriX in laparoscopic and robotic surgery: not only a matter of fashion. J Hepatobiliary Pancreat Sci. 2011 Jul;18(4):506-9. doi: 10.1007/s00534-011-0385-6.</citation>
    <PMID>21487758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Souzaki R, Ieiri S, Uemura M, Ohuchida K, Tomikawa M, Kinoshita Y, Koga Y, Suminoe A, Kohashi K, Oda Y, Hara T, Hashizume M, Taguchi T. An augmented reality navigation system for pediatric oncologic surgery based on preoperative CT and MRI images. J Pediatr Surg. 2013 Dec;48(12):2479-83. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2013.08.025.</citation>
    <PMID>24314190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

