<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04221789</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12112019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04221789</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TB Treatment Support Tool Interactive Mobile App and Direct Adherence Monitoring on TB Treatment Outcomes</brief_title>
  <acronym>TB-TST</acronym>
  <official_title>TB Treatment Support Tools: Refinement and Evaluation of an Interactive Mobile App and Direct Adherence Monitoring on TB Treatment Outcomes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute for Clinical Effectiveness and Health Policy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute for Clinical Effectiveness and Health Policy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of this study is to conduct a Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT) to evaluate a
      tuberculosis treatment support tool (TB-TST), a cellular phone app developed using
      user-centered design principles and a paper-based drug metabolite urine test strip modified
      for home use for testing the presence of isoniazid drug metabolites in urine to directly
      monitor adherence to treatment, to improve treatment outcomes for patients with TB receiving
      self-administered treatment (SAT).

      Poor medication adherence to TB regimens, along with challenges in monitoring patients and
      returning them to treatment, are important contributing factors to poor outcomes and the
      development of drug resistance. With advances and proliferation of mobile technology
      platforms, there is substantial interest in the possible use of mobile health (mHealth)
      interventions to address these challenges. Of the mHealth approaches under investigation for
      TB adherence monitoring, drug metabolite testing has been identified as the most promising,
      ethical, and accurate, and the least intrusive and stigmatizing strategy compared to other
      mobile solutions, yet its potential remains largely unexplored. Additionally, mobile
      applications (apps) may provide personalized treatment supervision, increase patients'
      self-management and improve patient-provider communication by offering more advanced
      functionalities for patient support and monitoring.

      The existing version of the TB-TST app offers education on TB and its treatment,
      communication with a care-coordinator, tracks treatment adherence (both by self-reporting and
      direct metabolite test strip images), self-reports treatment side-effects, and retains
      patient's &quot;diary&quot; notes. This proposal builds on preliminary work to: 1) Refine the TB-TST
      intervention based on pilot study findings and apply principles of user-centered design; 2)
      Evaluate the impact of the TB-TST on treatment outcomes compared to usual care; 3) Assess
      patient and provider perceptions of the facilitators and barriers to implementation of the
      TB-TST and synthesize lessons learned with stakeholders and policy makers. Primary outcome
      will be treatment success. Secondary outcomes will include: treatment default rates,
      self-reported adherence, technology use and usability. Findings have broader implications not
      only for TB adherence but disease management more generally and will improve our
      understanding of how to support patients facing challenging treatment regimens
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tuberculosis remains one of the top ten causes of death globally despite it being largely
      curable. Patients face many challenges to adhere to treatment and mobile health (mHealth)
      interventions may address these challenges and support patients to complete their treatment.
      We will improve an interactive intervention based on the combined input from patients and TB
      experts and evaluate the intervention's impact on treatment outcomes in a randomized clinical
      trial. Findings have broader implications not only for TB adherence but disease management
      more generally and will improve our understanding of how to support patients in challenging
      treatment regimens.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Data analysts will not be aware of group allocation</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment success</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Completion of treatment and or cure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment default</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Abandonment of treatment for at least 2 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <condition>Treatment Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>intervention: TB treatment assistant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving instructions to use phone application</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receiving instructions for usual care self administered treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TB treatment assistant</intervention_name>
    <description>Cell phone app to support self administered treatment and monitor adherence</description>
    <arm_group_label>intervention: TB treatment assistant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TB-TST (Treatment Support Tools)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be at least 18 years old,

          -  have a new diagnosis of drug-susceptible TB,

          -  First treatment

          -  have regular access to a smartphone, and

          -  be able to operate the phone or have someone able to assist.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children up to 17years old

          -  Retreatment (default or previous treatment failure)

          -  Patients who are severely ill (i.e., requiring hospitalization)

          -  Patients who reside in the same household with another study participant

          -  Inability to operate a smartphone

          -  Illiteracy (inability to read and write)

          -  Patients with known drug resistance

          -  Patients with known HIV co-infection will be excluded because their care is managed
             separately.

          -  Screened patients who do not meet study eligibility will have specific screening data
             (including gender, age and reason for exclusion) entered into the study database to
             examine reasons for exclusion and feasibility of enrollment criteria.

        Case definition: TB confirmed by smear‐positive sputum or diagnosis of pulmonary TB based
        on radiological findings and clinical signs and symptoms but with negative sputum smear.
        The diagnosis may be confirmed by other methods, such as, MGIT960, BACTEC 9000 or MB Bact,
        nucleic acid amplification (PCR) or ELISA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fernando A Rubinstein, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute for Clinical Effectiveness and Health Policy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fernando A Rubinstein, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+54 11 47778767</phone>
    <email>frubinstein@iecs.org.ar</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah Iribarren, RN PhD</last_name>
    <phone>206 543 5211</phone>
    <email>sjiribar@uw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. The top 10 causes of death worldwide. Geneva, 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Global Tuberculosis Report, 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Tuberculosis: fact sheet no. 104, Reviewed March 2016, 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>All Party Parliamentary Group on Global TB. The price of a pandemic:counting the cost of MDR-TB, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. End TB Strategy. 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Digital Health for the End TB Strategy: An Agenda for Action Geneva, Switzerland, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Digital health for the End TB strategy: progress since 2015 and future perspectives. Geneva: World Health Organization, 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiStefano MJ, Schmidt H. mHealth for Tuberculosis Treatment Adherence: A Framework to Guide Ethical Planning, Implementation, and Evaluation. Glob Health Sci Pract. 2016 Jun 27;4(2):211-21. doi: 10.9745/GHSP-D-16-00018. Print 2016 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27353615</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnall R, Bakken S, Brown Iii W, Carballo-Dieguez A, Iribarren S. Usabilty Evaluation of a Prototype Mobile App for Health Management for Persons Living with HIV. Stud Health Technol Inform. 2016;225:481-5.</citation>
    <PMID>27332247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guerra RL, Conde MB, Efron A, Loredo C, Bastos G, Chaisson RE, Golub JE. Point-of-care Arkansas method for measuring adherence to treatment with isoniazid. Respir Med. 2010 May;104(5):754-7. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2010.02.001. Epub 2010 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20202806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schraufnagel DE, Stoner R, Whiting E, Snukst-Torbeck G, Werhane MJ. Testing for isoniazid. An evaluation of the Arkansas method. Chest. 1990 Aug;98(2):314-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2376164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kilburn JO, Beam RE, David HL, Sanchez E, Corpe RF, Dunn W. Reagent-impregnated paper strip for detection of metabolic products of isoniazid in urine. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1972 Dec;106(6):923-4.</citation>
    <PMID>4641228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Global Tuberculosis Report, 2016. Geneva: World Health Organization, 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher JD, Amico KR, Fisher WA, Harman JJ. The information-motivation-behavioral skills model of antiretroviral adherence and its applications. Curr HIV/AIDS Rep. 2008 Nov;5(4):193-203. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18838059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnall R, Rojas M, Bakken S, Brown W, Carballo-Dieguez A, Carry M, Gelaude D, Mosley JP, Travers J. A user-centered model for designing consumer mobile health (mHealth) applications (apps). J Biomed Inform. 2016 Apr;60:243-51. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2016.02.002. Epub 2016 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>26903153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Center for Desease Control and Prevention. Tuberculosis Data and Statistics, 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maartens G, Wilkinson RJ. Tuberculosis. Lancet. 2007 Dec 15;370(9604):2030-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17719083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Osterberg L, Blaschke T. Adherence to medication. N Engl J Med. 2005 Aug 4;353(5):487-97. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16079372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ray TK, Sharma N, Singh MM, Ingle GK. Economic burden of tuberculosis in patients attending DOT centres in Delhi. J Commun Dis. 2005 Jun;37(2):93-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16749271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbett EL, Watt CJ, Walker N, Maher D, Williams BG, Raviglione MC, Dye C. The growing burden of tuberculosis: global trends and interactions with the HIV epidemic. Arch Intern Med. 2003 May 12;163(9):1009-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12742798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iribarren SJ, Rubinstein F, Discacciati V, Pearce PF. Listening to Those at the Frontline: Patient and Healthcare Personnel Perspectives on Tuberculosis Treatment Barriers and Facilitators in High TB Burden Regions of Argentina. Tuberc Res Treat. 2014;2014:135823. doi: 10.1155/2014/135823. Epub 2014 Sep 28.</citation>
    <PMID>25328701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirpa S, Medhin G, Girma B, Melese M, Mekonen A, Suarez P, Ameni G. Determinants of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in patients who underwent first-line treatment in Addis Ababa: a case control study. BMC Public Health. 2013 Aug 28;13:782. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-13-782.</citation>
    <PMID>23981845</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchison DA. How drug resistance emerges as a result of poor compliance during short course chemotherapy for tuberculosis. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 1998 Jan;2(1):10-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9562106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Center for Desease Control and Prevention. The costly burden of drug-resistant TB in the U.S., 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Global Plan to End TB: The Paradigm Shift 2016-2020. Geneva, Switzerland, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. What is DOTS? A guide to understanding the WHO-recommended TB control strategy known as DOTS, 1999.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karumbi J, Garner P. Directly observed therapy for treating tuberculosis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 May 29;(5):CD003343. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003343.pub4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26022367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pope DS, Chaisson RE. TB treatment: as simple as DOT? Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2003 Jul;7(7):611-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12870680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volmink J, Garner P. Directly observed therapy for treating tuberculosis. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2006 Apr 19;(2):CD003343. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2007;(4):CD003343.</citation>
    <PMID>16625579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuberculosis Coalition for Technical Assistance. International Standards for Tuberculosis Care (ISTC). Diagnosis, Treatment, Public Health. 2nd ed. The Hague, 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Global Tuberculosis Report 2015. Geneva, Switzerland: WHO, 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Respiratorias</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. TB country profile Argentina, 2017. 2018. http://www.who.int/tb/country/data/profiles/en/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>United Nations. Sustainable Development Goals. 2015. http://www.un.org/sustainabledevelopment/sustainable-development-goals/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>International telecommunication Union. The World in 2016: ICT Facts &amp; Figures. 2016. http://www.itu.int/en/ITU-D/Statistics/Documents/facts/ICTFactsFigures2016.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman JA, Cunningham JR, Suleh AJ, Sundsmo A, Dekker D, Vago F, Munly K, Igonya EK, Hunt-Glassman J. Mobile direct observation treatment for tuberculosis patients: a technical feasibility pilot using mobile phones in Nairobi, Kenya. Am J Prev Med. 2010 Jul;39(1):78-80. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2010.02.018. Epub 2010 May 26.</citation>
    <PMID>20537846</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wade VA, Karnon J, Eliott JA, Hiller JE. Home videophones improve direct observation in tuberculosis treatment: a mixed methods evaluation. PLoS One. 2012;7(11):e50155. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0050155. Epub 2012 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23226243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Belknap R, Weis S, Brookens A, Au-Yeung KY, Moon G, DiCarlo L, Reves R. Feasibility of an ingestible sensor-based system for monitoring adherence to tuberculosis therapy. PLoS One. 2013;8(1):e53373. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0053373. Epub 2013 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>23308203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soobratty MR, Whitfield R, Subramaniam K, Grove G, Carver A, O'Donovan GV, Wu HH, Lee OY, Swaminathan R, Cope GF, Milburn HJ. Point-of-care urine test for assessing adherence to isoniazid treatment for tuberculosis. Eur Respir J. 2014 May;43(5):1519-22. doi: 10.1183/09031936.00132613. Epub 2014 Jan 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24435008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singer E. TB Drug Compliance. Paper drug test and text messaging could help thwart the most deadly strains of tuberculosis. 2009. https://www.technologyreview.com/s/412203/tb-drug-compliance/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meissner PE, Musoke P, Okwera A, Bunn JE, Coulter JB. The value of urine testing for verifying adherence to anti-tuberculosis chemotherapy in children and adults in Uganda. Int J Tuberc Lung Dis. 2002 Oct;6(10):903-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12365577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iribarren SJ, Sward KA, Beck SL, Pearce PF, Thurston D, Chirico C. Qualitative evaluation of a text messaging intervention to support patients with active tuberculosis: implementation considerations. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2015 Feb 27;3(1):e21. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.3971.</citation>
    <PMID>25802968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iribarren S, Beck S, Pearce PF, Chirico C, Etchevarria M, Cardinale D, Rubinstein F. TextTB: A Mixed Method Pilot Study Evaluating Acceptance, Feasibility, and Exploring Initial Efficacy of a Text Messaging Intervention to Support TB Treatment Adherence. Tuberc Res Treat. 2013;2013:349394. doi: 10.1155/2013/349394. Epub 2013 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24455238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iribarren SJ, Beck SL, Pearce PF, Chirico C, Etchevarria M, Rubinstein F. MHEALTH INTERVENTION DEVELOPMENT TO SUPPORT PATIENTS WITH ACTIVE TUBERCULOSIS. J Mob Technol Med. 2014;3(2):16-27.</citation>
    <PMID>26246859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubinstein F, Iribarren, SJ. Effectiveness of different usual regimens treatment delivery strategies on Tuberculosis treatment success and default rates in Argentina: A Prospective Cohort Study (under review). 2017.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rubinstein F, Bernachea, M.P., Klein, K, Zurbrigk, F, Iribarren, S, Chirico, C, Gibbons, L,. TB treatment strategies and risk of default: a quasi-experimental study The International Journal of Tuberculosis and Lung Disease; 2016; Liverpool, UK; 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fisher JD, Fisher WA, Amico KR, Harman JJ. An information-motivation-behavioral skills model of adherence to antiretroviral therapy. Health Psychol. 2006 Jul;25(4):462-73.</citation>
    <PMID>16846321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munro S, Lewin S, Swart T, Volmink J. A review of health behaviour theories: how useful are these for developing interventions to promote long-term medication adherence for TB and HIV/AIDS? BMC Public Health. 2007 Jun 11;7:104. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17561997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McReynolds J, Crane, H, Berry, D, Lober, WB. Open Source Computerized Patient Reported Outcomes: Research and Practice across Three Domains. AMIA; 2013; Washington DC; 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mandel JC, Kreda DA, Mandl KD, Kohane IS, Ramoni RB. SMART on FHIR: a standards-based, interoperable apps platform for electronic health records. J Am Med Inform Assoc. 2016 Sep;23(5):899-908. doi: 10.1093/jamia/ocv189. Epub 2016 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26911829</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banos O, Villalonga C, Garcia R, Saez A, Damas M, Holgado-Terriza JA, Lee S, Pomares H, Rojas I. Design, implementation and validation of a novel open framework for agile development of mobile health applications. Biomed Eng Online. 2015;14 Suppl 2:S6. doi: 10.1186/1475-925X-14-S2-S6. Epub 2015 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26329639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flood D, Chary A, Austad K, Diaz AK, García P, Martinez B, Canú WL, Rohloff P. Insights into Global Health Practice from the Agile Software Development Movement. Glob Health Action. 2016 Apr 29;9:29836. doi: 10.3402/gha.v9.29836. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27134081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ngwatu BK, Nsengiyumva NP, Oxlade O, Mappin-Kasirer B, Nguyen NL, Jaramillo E, Falzon D, Schwartzman K; Collaborative group on the impact of digital technologies on TB. The impact of digital health technologies on tuberculosis treatment: a systematic review. Eur Respir J. 2018 Jan 11;51(1). pii: 1701596. doi: 10.1183/13993003.01596-2017. Print 2018 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>29326332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alipanah N, Jarlsberg L, Miller C, Linh NN, Falzon D, Jaramillo E, Nahid P. Adherence interventions and outcomes of tuberculosis treatment: A systematic review and meta-analysis of trials and observational studies. PLoS Med. 2018 Jul 3;15(7):e1002595. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1002595. eCollection 2018 Jul.</citation>
    <PMID>29969463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iribarren S, Schnall R. Call for Increased Patient Support Focus: Review and Evaluation of Mobile Apps for Tuberculosis Prevention and Treatment. Stud Health Technol Inform. 2016;225:936-7.</citation>
    <PMID>27332418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>eMarketer. Smartphone uptake is on the rise in Argentina. 4G is becoming more common. Aug 4, 2016 2016. https://www.emarketer.com/Article/Smartphone-Uptake-on-Rise-Argentina/1014300 (accessed Aug 17 2018).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atun R, Weil DE, Eang MT, Mwakyusa D. Health-system strengthening and tuberculosis control. Lancet. 2010 Jun 19;375(9732):2169-78. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60493-X. Epub 2010 May 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20488514</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lönnroth K, Jaramillo E, Williams BG, Dye C, Raviglione M. Drivers of tuberculosis epidemics: the role of risk factors and social determinants. Soc Sci Med. 2009 Jun;68(12):2240-6. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2009.03.041. Epub 2009 Apr 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19394122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volpp K. A healthcare revolution: Behavioral economics for behavior change and preventive medicine. NIH Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research; 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masterson Creber RM, Maurer MS, Reading M, Hiraldo G, Hickey KT, Iribarren S. Review and Analysis of Existing Mobile Phone Apps to Support Heart Failure Symptom Monitoring and Self-Care Management Using the Mobile Application Rating Scale (MARS). JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2016 Jun 14;4(2):e74. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.5882.</citation>
    <PMID>27302310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berry DL, Hong F, Halpenny B, Partridge A, Fox E, Fann JR, Wolpin S, Lober WB, Bush N, Parvathaneni U, Amtmann D, Ford R. The electronic self report assessment and intervention for cancer: promoting patient verbal reporting of symptom and quality of life issues in a randomized controlled trial. BMC Cancer. 2014 Jul 12;14:513. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-14-513.</citation>
    <PMID>25014995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Evans HL, Lober WB. A Pilot Use of Patient-Generated Wound Data to Improve Postdischarge Surgical Site Infection Monitoring. JAMA Surg. 2017 Jun 1;152(6):595-596. doi: 10.1001/jamasurg.2017.0568. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28423162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fredericksen RJ, Tufano J, Ralston J, McReynolds J, Stewart M, Lober WB, Mayer KH, Mathews WC, Mugavero MJ, Crane PK, Crane HM. Provider perceptions of the value of same-day, electronic patient-reported measures for use in clinical HIV care. AIDS Care. 2016 Nov;28(11):1428-33. doi: 10.1080/09540121.2016.1189501. Epub 2016 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>27237187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chirico C, Kuriger A, Etchevarria M, Casamajor L, Morcillo N. Is the DOTS strategy a useful tool to fight against Tuberculosis in a median incidence area of Buenos Aires Province? Int J Tuberc Lung Dis 2005.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chirico C, Kuriger A, Fernández H, Morcillo N. [Tuberculosis in the V Sanitary Zone of Buenos Aires Province. Analysis of its trends between 1984 and 1996]. Medicina (B Aires). 1999;59(4):332-8. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>10752196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chirico C, Sanjurjo M, Iribarren S, Zerbini E, Echevarrria M. Tuberculosis infantil: estudio de tendencia en la region sanitaria v de la provincia de buenos aires, años 2000-2014. Medicina Infantil 2016; XXIII: 217-23.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chirico C, Sanjurjo M, Iribarren S, Appendino A, Zerbini E, Etchevarria M. [Trends of tuberculosis in the Fifth Health Region, Buenos Aires Province, years 2000-2011]. Medicina (B Aires). 2015;75(3):147-54. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>26117604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>mPOWEr - University of Washington. mPOWEr. 2016. http://mpowercare.org/ (accessed Sept 4 2016).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stoyanov SR, Hides L, Kavanagh DJ, Zelenko O, Tjondronegoro D, Mani M. Mobile app rating scale: a new tool for assessing the quality of health mobile apps. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2015 Mar 11;3(1):e27. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.3422.</citation>
    <PMID>25760773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akraa S, Tran Tama, A, Shena, H, Tang, Y, Tang, B.Z, Li, J, Walker, S. A smartphone-based point-of-care quantitative urinalysis device for chronic kidney disease patients. Journal of Network and Computer Applications 2018; 115(2018): 59-69.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris PA, Taylor R, Thielke R, Payne J, Gonzalez N, Conde JG. Research electronic data capture (REDCap)--a metadata-driven methodology and workflow process for providing translational research informatics support. J Biomed Inform. 2009 Apr;42(2):377-81. doi: 10.1016/j.jbi.2008.08.010. Epub 2008 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18929686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Statista. Smartphone users as share of the population in Argentina from 2015 to 2022. 2018. https://www.statista.com/statistics/621034/smartphone-user-penetration-in-argentina/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Instituto Nacional de Enfermedades Respiratorias. Programa Nacional de Control de la tuberculosis. Normas tecnicas (National Tuberculosis Program. Technical standards), 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knobel H, Alonso J, Casado JL, Collazos J, González J, Ruiz I, Kindelan JM, Carmona A, Juega J, Ocampo A; GEEMA Study Group. Validation of a simplified medication adherence questionnaire in a large cohort of HIV-infected patients: the GEEMA Study. AIDS. 2002 Mar 8;16(4):605-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11873004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Treatment for Tuberculosis: Guidelines (4rd Edition) WHO/HTM/TB/2009.420, 2010.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guest G, Namey, E, Taylor, J, Eley, N &amp; McKenna, K. Comparing focus groups and individual interviews: findings from a randomized study. International Journal of Social Research Methodology 2017; 20(6): 693-708.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mani M, Kavanagh DJ, Hides L, Stoyanov SR. Review and Evaluation of Mindfulness-Based iPhone Apps. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. 2015 Aug 19;3(3):e82. doi: 10.2196/mhealth.4328.</citation>
    <PMID>26290327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lincoln Y, Guba E. Naturalistic Inquiry. Newbury Park, CA: Sage Publications; 1985.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Creswell JW, Klassen, A. C., Plano-Clark, V. L., Smith, K. C., for Office of Behavioral and Social Sciences Research. Best practices for mixed method research in the health sciences. Washington, DC: NIH National Institutes of Health, 2011.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson RB, Onwuegbuzie AJ. Mixed methods research: A research paradigm whose time has come Educational Researcher 2004; 33(7): 14-26.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas DR. A General Inductive Approach for Analyzing Qualitative Evaluation Data. American Journal of Evaluation 2006; 27(2): 237-46.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>treatment supervision, success default</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

