<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227769</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EKNZ 2019-02307</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227769</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>IL-1-receptor Antagonist During Cephalic Phase of Insulin Secretion in Health and Type 2 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cephalira</acronym>
  <official_title>IL-1-receptor Antagonist During Cephalic Phase of Insulin Secretion in Health and Type 2 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A prospective, randomized, mixed double- and single-blinded, placebo-controlled, cross-over
      clinical trial to test whether acute treatment with an IL-1 receptor antagonist impacts
      insulin secretion over time during the cephalic phase, defined as the first 10 minutes after
      the first sensorial contact to food, in healthy individuals in healthy humans (Group 1) and
      in obese patients with type 2 diabetes (Group 2).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The role of the immune system in metabolism has been extensively investigated in pancreatic
      islets and insulin sensitive tissues. However little attention has been given to a potential
      role of the innate immune system in the cephalic phase of insulin secretion. In humans, the
      cephalic phase of insulin secretion appear reduced in obesity and in patients with type 2
      diabetes.

      In this prospective, randomized, mixed double- and single-blinded, placebo-controlled,
      cross-over clinical trial we aim to test whether acute treatment with an IL-1 receptor
      antagonist impacts insulin secretion over time during the cephalic phase, defined as the
      first 10 minutes after the first sensorial contact to food, in healthy individuals in healthy
      humans (Group 1) and in obese patients with type 2 diabetes (Group 2).

      Group 1: After screening, subjects will be randomized to two crossover visits with a washout
      period of at least 4 days in-between visits and at most two weeks: A) subcutaneous saline
      injection 3h before an oral standardized meal, B) subcutaneous injection of 100 mg of the
      IL-1 receptor antagonist anakinra 3h before an oral standardized meal. Treatments will be
      placebo controlled, crossover, double blinded. The study will be performed in a population of
      healthy individuals.

      Group 2: Same as for Group 1 with the following addition: after the second study day,
      participant in group 2 will be trained to self-inject the medication for 6 days. On the 7th
      day, an oral standardized meal test will be performed.

      Healthy subjects from group 1 will be matched for sex and age to the diabetic cohort from
      group 2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 13, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomized, double-blinded and open-label, placebo-controlled, partly cross-over clinical trial</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in insulin concentration in blood during the cephalic phase of insulin secretion in healthy individuals</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin concentration in blood at 0, 3,6 and 10 minutes after ingestion of a standardized meal in healthy individuals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in insulin concentration in blood during the cephalic phase of insulin secretion in obese patients with type 2 diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Insulin concentration in blood at 0, 3, 6 and 10 minutes after ingestion of a standardized meal in healthy individuals in obese patients with type 2 diabetes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of C-peptide</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of c-peptide before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of insulin before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of glucose before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of glucagon</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of glucagon before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of GLP-1</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of GLP-1 before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of pancreatic polypeptide</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of pancreatic polypeptide before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of IL-1β</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of IL-1β before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of IL-6</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of IL-6 before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of IL-1Ra</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of IL-1Ra before and after a meal through nasogastric tube or with anakinra or placebo after a standardized meal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of TNFa</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma level of TNFa before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in hunger</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analogue scale (VAS) for hunger (from minimum value = not hungry at all to maximum value = extremely hungry) before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in autonomic function</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Change in heart-rate variability during a continuous ECG as indirect measure of measure of the autonomic function before and after a standardized meal after acute treatment or repeated treatment with anakinra or placebo. Repeated Treatment applies only to anakinra and to Group 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus Type 2 in Obese</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Disease</condition>
  <condition>Glucose Metabolism Disorders (Including Diabetes Mellitus)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy individuals</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two crossover visits with a washout period of at least 4 days in-between visits and at most two weeks: A) subcutaneous saline injection 3h before an oral standardized meal, B) subcutaneous injection of 100 mg of the IL-1 receptor antagonist anakinra 3h before an oral standardized meal. Treatments will be placebo controlled, crossover, double blinded. Standard dose of Anakinra (Kineret®; r-metHuIL-1ra, Swedish Orphan Biovitrum AB), i. e. 100 mg/ 0.67 ml s. c. or 0.67 ml of saline s. c. (placebo)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>obese patients with type 2 diabetes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Three crossover visits with a washout period of at least 4 days in-between: A) subcutaneous saline injection 3h before an oral standardized meal, B) subcutaneous injection of 100 mg of the IL-1 receptor antagonist anakinra 3h before an oral standardized meal, C) Additionally, after the second study day, participant in group 2 will be trained to self-inject the medication for 6 days. On the 7th day, an oral standardized meal test will be performed. Standard dose of Anakinra (Kineret®; r-metHuIL-1ra, Swedish Orphan Biovitrum AB), i. e. 100 mg/ 0.67 ml s. c. or 0.67 ml of saline s. c. (placebo)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anakinra Prefilled Syringe</intervention_name>
    <description>Subcutaneous injection of 100 mg/ 0.67 ml of Kineret or placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy individuals</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>obese patients with type 2 diabetes</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kineret</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        Main inclusion criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 70 years at screening

          -  Male or female of non-child-bearing potential (meaning for women: not currently
             pregnant, post-menopausal female or using condoms and either intrauterine devices or
             3-monthly contraceptive injection or birth-control pill.)

        Healthy subjects:

          -  No apparent disease requiring medication

          -  BMI &lt; 25 kg/ m2

          -  C-reactive protein ≤ 2 mg/L

        Obese diabetic type 2 subjects:

          -  Type 2 diabetes

          -  HbA1c 7.0 -10.0%

          -  BMI ≥ 30.0 kg/m2

          -  C-reactive protein ≥ 2 mg/L

        Exclusion criteria:

        Subjects will be excluded from the study if they meet any of the following criteria:

          -  Mental incapacity, unwillingness or language barriers precluding adequate
             understanding or cooperation

          -  Aversion or allergy to paracetamol or any component of the meal.

          -  Known history of allergy or hypersensitivity to any component of the investigational
             product formulations

          -  Concomitant treatment with GLP-1 agonists, DPP-4 inhibitors, insulin or insulin
             derivative

          -  Change in diabetes medication within the last 30 days

          -  Any biologic drugs targeting the immune system

          -  Fever, or other signs of infection requiring antibiotics within 3 weeks prior to
             screening, history of recurrent infection, immunodeficiency, known HIV or tuberculosis
             infection, active foot ulcer

          -  Participation in another study with investigational drug within 30 days prior to
             Screening and during the present study

          -  eGFR &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73m2 per MDRD formula or kidney transplant (regardless of renal
             function)

          -  Known active or recurrent hepatic disorder (including cirrhosis, hepatitis B and
             hepatitis C, or confirmed ALAT/ASAT levels &gt; 3 times ULN or total bilirubin &gt; 2 times
             ULN),

          -  Haemoglobin &lt;10.0 g/dL, white blood cell &lt;3.0 x 103/mm3, platelet count &lt;125 x 103/mm3

          -  Atrial fibrillation and/or a pacemaker
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Y Donath, Prof. Dr. MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Basel, Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marc Y Donath, Prof.Dr. MD</last_name>
    <phone>061 265 5078</phone>
    <phone_ext>+41</phone_ext>
    <email>marc.donath@usb.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonathan M Mudry, Dr. MD</last_name>
    <phone>0612652525</phone>
    <phone_ext>+41</phone_ext>
    <email>jonathan.mudry@usb.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Basel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <state>Basel BS</state>
        <zip>4031</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marc Y Donath, Prof. Dr. MD</last_name>
      <phone>+41 061 265 5078</phone>
      <email>marc.donath@usb.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anakinra</keyword>
  <keyword>cephalic phase of insulin secretion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Interleukin 1 Receptor Antagonist Protein</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

