<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227704</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201910191</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227704</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ketamine to Prevent PPD After Cesarean</brief_title>
  <acronym>PoCKet</acronym>
  <official_title>Postpartum Depression After Cesarean Delivery: Ketamine as a Preventative Intervention: A Feasibility Pilot-study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators plan to randomise participants to receive ketamine or placebo control
      subcutaneously or by 40-minute intravenous infusions and will follow them up for 42 days to
      assess the incidence of postpartum depression. This feasibility pilot study is designed to
      explore the adequacy of the study procedures and tolerability of the interventions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postpartum depression (PPD)

      PPD is one of the most common perinatal medical complications and can have a detrimental
      effect on both mother and baby. Suicide exceeds hemorrhage and hypertensive disorders as a
      cause of maternal mortality and maternal psychopathology interferes with the parent-infant
      relationship. It has been estimated to have a period prevalence of 19.2% in the first 3
      postpartum months. The rapid decline in reproductive hormones is thought to contribute to the
      development of PPD in susceptible women, although the specific pathogenesis is unknown. The
      American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists recommend that all women should be
      routinely screened for depressive symptoms in the perinatal period.

      Risk factors for PPD include:

        -  Depression during pregnancy • Breastfeeding problems

        -  Preterm birth/infant admission to neonatal intensive care (NICU)

        -  Traumatic birth experience

        -  History of depression

        -  Anxiety during pregnancy

      Ketamine's anti-depressant effect

      Ketamine, a phencyclidine derivative, is a non-competitive antagonist at the
      N-methyl-D-aspartic acid (NMDA) receptor that is commonly used as an anesthetic or sedative
      agent and has proven analgesic effect after a variety of surgeries including CD, where it has
      also been shown to reduce shivering. It has been demonstrated to have a rapid anti-depressant
      effect in treatment-resistant depression outside of pregnancy. The most commonly employed
      intravenous (IV) dose for this purpose is 0.5 mg/kg over 40 minutes, as single or repeated
      infusions. It has been postulated that prolonged blockade of NMDA receptors causes long-term
      changes in signal transduction leading to sustained clinical improvement, some investigators
      have explored longer term infusions such as those used to treat chronic pain. A recent pilot
      study assessing the feasibility of a 96-hour (~0.5mg/kg/hr) infusion compared with a single
      40-minute (0.5 mg/kg) infusion suggested a trend toward greater efficacy in the prolonged
      infusion but confirmation of a statistically significant result is awaited.

      Ketamine and PPD

      This promising anti-depressant effect has prompted investigation of ketamine as a
      preventative measure in patients undergoing CD. There have been 2 studies to date, one which
      failed to demonstrate any benefit from a bolus dose of 0.25 mg/kg and one which documented a
      large reduction (1 and 22% in the treatment and control, respectively) in the (6 week) period
      prevalence of postpartum depression after a 4 mg/kg dose of ketamine over 50 hours (~0.08
      mg/kg/hr).

      The prolonged IV infusion, was achieved by adding the ketamine to a sufentanil
      patient-controlled analgesic (PCA) pump with a background infusion. This PCA pump is a
      standard part of their post-cesarean analgesic regimen. In our institution, it is standard
      practice to discontinue IV infusions and to remove IV cannulae as early as it is safe to do
      so. This practice is essential to the attempts to enhance postoperative recovery and aid
      mother's bonding with their babies and facilitate their early-life care. This reflects
      patients' expectations and preferences and is in line with other maternity units across North
      America and Europe.

      The natural course of PPD varies and, although it may resolve spontaneously within weeks,
      approximately 20% of women with PPD still have depression at 12 months and beyond. As many as
      13% will still have depressive symptoms at 2 years and 40% will have a relapse. Considering
      the maternal suffering, disruption to the family, potential impairment of the social,
      emotional, and cognitive development of the child, and the rare cases of infanticide and
      suicide caused by PPD, the impact on families and society as a whole is difficult to
      overemphasize. An intervention that promises such a large reduction in this devastating
      disease warrants extensive research. In an attempt to achieve the benefit whilst employing
      methods more acceptable to our patients we have designed a pilot study to assess the
      feasibility of our study design and collect preliminary tolerability and efficacy data on
      ketamine administered by two alternative routes: 40-minute IV infusion (i.v.) and
      subcutaneous (s.c.) injection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomised to one of three groups (two interventional and one control).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The ketamine and placebo study injectates (subcutaneous and intravenous) will be prepared, in way that does not allow differentiation, by pharmacy staff who are otherwise uninvolved in the study. Participants will be allocated to groups using a random sequence generator. The patients, investigators and outcome assessors will remain unaware of their group until data collection is complete for all participants.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of PPD, as defined as EPDS greater than 10 out of 30</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Establish a sufficient burden of disease (&gt;10%) in our population to warrant a full RCT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of eligible patients consenting to participation</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Establish a recruitment rate of greater than 50% to confirm the feasibility of conducting an RCT in our population</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with a complete dataset</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Ensure that the design of assessments and data collection make it possible to achieve a complete dataset in &gt;90% of participants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients in study arms experiencing one or more severe side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Ascertain that neither of the chosen routes of administration of ketamine are intolerable to patients, as defined as the incidence of one or more severe side effects experienced by &gt;10% of participants in that study arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of opiate analgesics administered</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Intraoperative supplementary analgesia in morphine milligram equivalents</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose of ketorolac administered</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Intraoperative supplementary analgesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of intraoperative hypotension of a systolic BP of less than 90</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of systolic BP less than 90 mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum intraoperative pain (NRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Reported maximal level of intraoperative pain on the numerical rating scale 0 - 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative and 2 and 6 hours postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and severity (mild, moderate or severe) of nausea, vomiting, pruritus, dizziness, sedation, shivering, anxiety, euphoria, hallucinations, amnesia, blurred vision, diplopia, nystagmus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of ketamine</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and approximately 20, 40 and 100 minutes postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Assays of venous blood samples</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total opiate consumption in morphine equivalents</measure>
    <time_frame>In the first 2 days postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Morphine equivalents</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical site pain: numerical rating scale (NRS 0-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2, 6, 24 and 48 hours after delivery and on postpartum days 21 and 42</time_frame>
    <description>On a numerical rating scale (NRS 0-10)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Edinburgh Postpartum Depression Scale (0 - 30, a higher score represents greater depressive symptomatology)</measure>
    <time_frame>On postpartum days 1, 2, 21 and 42</time_frame>
    <description>Validated measure of depressive symptoms in the postpartum period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apgar scores</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1 and 5 minutes after delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Score out of 10, of neonatal status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Admission to NICU</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of admission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeeding success</measure>
    <time_frame>Postpartum days 1 and 2</time_frame>
    <description>Yes or no</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of intraoperative hypertension of a systolic BP greater than 140 mmHg</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic hypertension of greater than 140 mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of intraoperative bradycardia of less than 40 bpm</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Bradycardia less than 40 bpm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of intraoperative tachycardia of greater than 110 bpm</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative phase</time_frame>
    <description>Tachycardia greater than 110 bpm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Anxiety on the Generalized Anxiety Disorder- 7 item scaleGAD-7</measure>
    <time_frame>On day of surgery, and postpartum days 1, 2, 21 and 42</time_frame>
    <description>Validated scale for anxiety. Score out of 21.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Postpartum Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Shortly after cesarean delivery of their baby, participants will receive a subcutaneous injection and 40-minute intravenous infusion of 0.9% sodium chloride.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine SC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Shortly after cesarean delivery of their baby, participants will receive a subcutaneous injection of 0.5 mg/kg of ketamine and a 40-minute intravenous infusion of 0.9% sodium chloride.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine IVI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Shortly after cesarean delivery of their baby, participants will receive a subcutaneous injection of 0.9% sodium chloride and a 40-minute intravenous infusion of 0.5 mg/kg ketamine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine 50 MG/ML</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of a 0.5 mg/kg dose of ketamine at cesarean delivery by one of two routes (subcutaneous or 40-minute IV infusion).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine IVI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine SC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Administration of 0.9% Sodium Chloride (N/S)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine IVI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine SC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Term pregnancy

          -  Age 18-45 years of age

          -  Scheduled cesarean delivery under neuraxial anesthesia

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  ASA classification IV or V

          -  History of psychotic episodes

          -  History of allergy to ketamine

          -  Inability to communicate in English or any other barrier to providing informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ben Swan</last_name>
    <phone>314-273-8257</phone>
    <email>bswan@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kristi Kraus, RN</last_name>
    <phone>314-273-7921</phone>
    <email>kristinkraus@wustl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University in St. Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David T Monks, MBChB FRCA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression, Postpartum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

