<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04221984</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00000379</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04221984</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wingspan One Year Vascular Imaging Events and Neurologic Outcomes</brief_title>
  <acronym>WOVEN</acronym>
  <official_title>Wingspan One Year Vascular Imaging Events and Neurologic Outcomes (WOVEN)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine the one-year post stenting outcomes in patients who
      were treated with the Wingspan stent on-label in the WEAVE trial. This includes both the
      assessment of any stroke, hemorrhage, or death, as well as assessment of delayed imaging
      results to determine the re-stenosis rate of the stents in these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current study is a retrospective chart and imaging review of the 152 patients enrolled in
      the WEAVE trial to determine the one-year outcomes for these patients.

      This includes both the assessment of any stroke, hemorrhage, or death, as well as assessment
      of delayed imaging results to determine the re-stenosis rate of the stents in these patients
      and the medication regimen in those patients who had symptomatic re-stenosis.

      The subjects for this study are pre-defined as the 152 patients who had placement of a
      Wingspan stent for treatment of their intracranial artery stenosis that had symptoms of
      stroke and 70% or greater arterial stenosis. The study will be conducted at 24 sites in the
      United States. It is expected that up to 152 patients' records will be assessed for follow up
      data analysis. Patient's information will be included in the study if they were enrolled in
      the WEAVE Trial and had placement of a Wingspan stent in its on-label usage indication
      between 12/1/2013 and 10/31/2017. Follow up information from the patients' charts will be
      extracted out to the one-year interval following stenting up to December 2018.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year stroke rate following placement of Wingspan stent in this patient cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>1-year stroke rate following placement of Wingspan stent in this patient cohort</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1-year death rate following placement of Wingspan stent in this patient cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>1-year death rate following placement of Wingspan stent in this patient cohort</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic re-stenosis rates of the patient group.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Symptomatic re-stenosis rates of the patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of the strokes/index event that occurred in that patient group.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Severity of the strokes/index event that occurred in that patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Intracranial Atherosclerotic Disease (ICAD)</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        152 patients stented on-label in the WEAVE trial.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for this study are the 152 patients stented in the WEAVE trial
             on-label.

        The patients had the following inclusion criteria:

          -  Age 18-80

          -  Intracranial artery stenosis greater or equal to 70% stenosis

          -  Target artery 2 mm or larger

          -  Presented with stroke while on medical therapy for stroke prevention

          -  Prior stroke in the target territory

          -  Modified Rankin Score of 3 or better (neurologic function)

          -  Treated greater than 7 days after their last stroke

          -  Treated with the Wingspan stent by an approved trial NeuroInterventionalist

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients treated outside of the trial or who did not meet the entry criteria.

          -  Patients that had stent treatment for arterial dissection

          -  Patients that had extra-cranial stenosis

          -  Patients outside the age range of the study

          -  Patients treated less than 8 days from their stroke.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J Alexander, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexander MJ, Zauner A, Chaloupka JC, Baxter B, Callison RC, Gupta R, Song SS, Yu W; WEAVE Trial Sites and Interventionalists. WEAVE Trial: Final Results in 152 On-Label Patients. Stroke. 2019 Apr;50(4):889-894. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.118.023996.</citation>
    <PMID>31125298</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bose A, Hartmann M, Henkes H, Liu HM, Teng MM, Szikora I, Berlis A, Reul J, Yu SC, Forsting M, Lui M, Lim W, Sit SP. A novel, self-expanding, nitinol stent in medically refractory intracranial atherosclerotic stenoses: the Wingspan study. Stroke. 2007 May;38(5):1531-7. Epub 2007 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17395864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chimowitz MI, Lynn MJ, Derdeyn CP, Turan TN, Fiorella D, Lane BF, Janis LS, Lutsep HL, Barnwell SL, Waters MF, Hoh BL, Hourihane JM, Levy EI, Alexandrov AV, Harrigan MR, Chiu D, Klucznik RP, Clark JM, McDougall CG, Johnson MD, Pride GL Jr, Torbey MT, Zaidat OO, Rumboldt Z, Cloft HJ; SAMMPRIS Trial Investigators. Stenting versus aggressive medical therapy for intracranial arterial stenosis. N Engl J Med. 2011 Sep 15;365(11):993-1003. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1105335. Epub 2011 Sep 7. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2012 Jul 5;367(1):93.</citation>
    <PMID>21899409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael J. Alexander, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Vice Chairman, Department of Neurosurgery, Director of the Cedars-Sinai Neurovascular Center, Co-Director, Comprehensive Stroke Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

