<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04229485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C-CRISS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04229485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chinese Chronic Renal Insufficiency Study: Based on Smartphone Platform</brief_title>
  <acronym>C-CRISS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Chinese Cohort Study of Chronic Kidney Disease Patients Followed on Smartphone Platform, a Multi-center Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Limeng Chen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Hospital of China Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>People's Hospital of Xinjiang Autonomous Region</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fujian Provincial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shandong Provincial Qianfoshan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>First Affiliated Hospital Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Seventh Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>People's Hospital of Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center prospective cohort study. The purpose of this study is to investigate
      the relationship between bone metabolic markers and other non-traditional risk factors with
      kidney function progression, cardiovascular and cerebrovascular diseases, and bone loss in
      patients with CKD G3-5ND. In the meantime, this study is to explore a new mode of management
      and complication monitoring through mobile communication in chronic kidney disease patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Abnormal mineral bone metabolism of chronic kidney disease (CKD-MBD) is the most common
      complication of CKD. It involves kidney, bone metabolism, parathyroid gland, cardiovascular
      and cerebrovascular organs. It is an independent risk factor for progression of CKD to
      end-stage renal disease (ESRD), vascular and cardiac valve calcification, and cardiovascular
      and cerebrovascular events. However, less data concerning the relationship between bone
      metabolic index, such as high blood phosphorus and cardiovascular diseases, bone mass
      reduction and fracture is available in Chinese adult patients. This study is a multi-center
      prospective cohort study to explore the relationship between bone metabolic markers and other
      non-traditional risk factors with renal function progression, cardiovascular and
      cerebrovascular diseases, and bone loss in patients with CKD G3-5ND. Based on the sample size
      estimation, 3360 subjects should be enrolled in this study. The primary outcome is
      progression to ESRD (start dialysis or kidney transplantation) or doubling of serum
      creatinine, as well as cardiovascular events and all-cause mortality.

      At present, the follow-up and the management of complications of CKD patients are not enough.
      The popularity of mobile communication in China provide the possibility to strengthen the
      follow-up and complications management in CKD patients and save human resources. This study
      is to explore a new mode of collecting datas through mobile communication in chronic kidney
      disease patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>incidence of progression to ESRD</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year</time_frame>
    <description>begin to dialysis and kidney transplantation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cardiovascular event and all-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>2 year</time_frame>
    <description>diagnose as myocardial infarction, heart failure, stroke and cerebral hemorrhage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the rate of eGFR decline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>the rate of eGFR decline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>bone mass change</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>the bone mass change based on DXR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative-Short Form 36</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>the scores change of Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative- Short Form 36 The score of Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative-Short Form 36 is between 0 and 100. The higher score means a better self-evaluation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>frailty</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>A frailty phenotype was established with five variables: unintentional weight loss, self-reported exhaustion, low energy expenditure, weak grip strength and low gait speed. Those with three or more of the five factors were judged to be frail, those with one or two factors as pre-frail, and those with no factors as not frail.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the way of dialysis initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>record if the patient start dialysis with urgency and mode of dialysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3360</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Kidney Diseases</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      blood, 24 hour urine
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        CKD patients stage 3-5ND
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  at least two measurements of serum Cr (with a minimum interval of 3 months), ,
             10≤eGFR≤60ml/min/1.73m^2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable or unwilling to provide informed consent

          -  Patients attending oncology, psychiatry, human immunodeficiency virus/acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome (HIV/AIDS), viral hepatitis (HBV or HCV) services

          -  Acute mycardial infarction within the last six months

          -  NYHA Class III or IV heart failure at baseline

          -  Ongoing chemotherapy or immunosuppressive therapy (in the preceding 6 months to treat
             renal or immune disease)

          -  Current renal replacement therapy

          -  Current pregnancy or breastfeeding women

          -  Any organ transplantation

          -  Currently participation in an interventional clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Limeng Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Nephrology, Peking Union Medical College Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiaohong Fan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-13811559757</phone>
    <email>fxhcmu@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Xuehan Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86-18612550476</phone>
    <email>zxhzpp@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100730</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xiaohong Fan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>86-13811559757</phone>
      <email>fxhcmu@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Limeng Chen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes (KDIGO) CKD-MBD Update Work Group. KDIGO 2017 Clinical Practice Guideline Update for the Diagnosis, Evaluation, Prevention, and Treatment of Chronic Kidney Disease-Mineral and Bone Disorder (CKD-MBD). Kidney Int Suppl (2011). 2017 Jul;7(1):1-59. doi: 10.1016/j.kisu.2017.04.001. Epub 2017 Jun 21. Erratum in: Kidney Int Suppl (2011). 2017 Dec;7(3):e1.</citation>
    <PMID>30675420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bello AK, Alrukhaimi M, Ashuntantang GE, Basnet S, Rotter RC, Douthat WG, Kazancioglu R, Köttgen A, Nangaku M, Powe NR, White SL, Wheeler DC, Moe O. Complications of chronic kidney disease: current state, knowledge gaps, and strategy for action. Kidney Int Suppl (2011). 2017 Oct;7(2):122-129. doi: 10.1016/j.kisu.2017.07.007. Epub 2017 Sep 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30675426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dienemann T, Fujii N, Orlandi P, Nessel L, Furth SL, Hoy WE, Matsuo S, Mayer G, Methven S, Schaefer F, Schaeffner ES, Solá L, Stengel B, Wanner C, Zhang L, Levin A, Eckardt KU, Feldman HI. International Network of Chronic Kidney Disease cohort studies (iNET-CKD): a global network of chronic kidney disease cohorts. BMC Nephrol. 2016 Sep 2;17(1):121. doi: 10.1186/s12882-016-0335-2.</citation>
    <PMID>27590182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou C, Wang F, Wang JW, Zhang LX, Zhao MH. Mineral and Bone Disorder and Its Association with Cardiovascular Parameters in Chinese Patients with Chronic Kidney Disease. Chin Med J (Engl). 2016 Oct 5;129(19):2275-80. doi: 10.4103/0366-6999.190678.</citation>
    <PMID>27647184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking Union Medical College Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Limeng Chen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine, Associate Chief of Nephrology Division</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic kidney diseae</keyword>
  <keyword>mineral bone disease</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular events</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile communication</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>To comply with laws in China, local regulations and hospital policy, IPD sharing might be restricted</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

