<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227106</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EB-101-CL-301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227106</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase 3, Open-label Clinical Trial of EB-101 for the Treatment of Recessive Dystrophic Epidermolysis Bullosa (RDEB)</brief_title>
  <official_title>VIITAL: A Phase 3 Study of EB-101 for the Treatment of Recessive Dystrophic Epidermolysis Bullosa (RDEB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Abeona Therapeutics, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Abeona Therapeutics, Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this trial is to evaluate safety and efficacy of surgical application of
      EB-101 (autologous, gene-corrected keratinocyte sheets) as a treatment of recessive
      dystrophic epidermolysis bullosa (RDEB).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recessive dystrophic epidermolysis bullosa (RDEB) is an ultra-rare, severe inherited
      blistering skin disease caused by the absence of a protein known as type 7 collagen (C7).
      There is no approved treatment for RDEB. Only supportive care is currently possible.

      This open-label, controlled study will evaluate the efficacy and safety of EB-101 for the
      treatment of large, chronic, RDEB wounds. The study intervention consists of One-time
      surgical application of approximately 30 autologous, gene-corrected keratinocyte sheets
      (EB-101) for the treatment of RDEB wound sites in up to approximately 15 participants. A
      single EB-101 sheet is able to provide healing to a wound area up to approximately 40cm2. Up
      to 6 (six) EB-101 sheets may be applied to each patient, depending on the area of existing
      wounds. Treatment effect will be measured as wound healing at 3 months, with follow up to 6
      months post treatment, comparing treated versus matched untreated wound sites. Wound healing
      will be adjudicated by an independent committee not involved in the study conduct.
      Patient-reported outcomes and safety will also be collected throughout the study.

      The primary analysis for efficacy will be assessed when all patients reach Week 12. Safety
      and efficacy assessments will be conducted at regular intervals and completed when last
      patient reaches Week 24 post-treatment.

      Upon completion of the 6-month study period, patients will be monitored annually as per
      standard of care for up to 15 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound Healing</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of RDEB wound sites with ≥50% healing from Baseline in treated versus untreated intra-participant wound sites</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Epidermolysis Bullosa</condition>
  <condition>Recessive Dystrophic Epidermolysis Bullosa</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EB-101</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One-time surgical application of EB-101 on up to 6 chronic, RDEB wounds</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EB-101</intervention_name>
    <description>autologous RDEB keratinocytes isolated from skin biopsies and transduced with a recombinant retrovirus containing a full-length COL7A1 expression cassette for C7</description>
    <arm_group_label>EB-101</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LZRSE-Col7A1 Engineered Autologous Epidermal Sheets [LEAES]</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of RDEB;

          -  Age 6 years or older, willing and able to give consent/assent;

          -  If under the age of 18, guardian(s) is/are willing and able to give consent;

          -  Positive expression of the non-collagenous region 1 of the type 7 collagen protein
             (NC1+) in the skin;

          -  Two confirmed RDEB C7 mutations with recessive inheritance patterns (or confirmation
             that parents don't have any evidence of dominant disease);

          -  At least 40 cm2 areas of chronically wounded area on the trunk and/or extremities
             suitable for EB-101 application (open erosions);

          -  Able to undergo adequate anesthesia during EB-101 application;

          -  Must have at least two matched, eligible wound sites (one pair);

               -  Wound sites must:

                    -  Have an area ≥20 cm2,

                    -  Present for ≥6 months, and

                    -  Stage 2 wound;

          -  Women of childbearing potential must use a reliable birth control method throughout
             the duration of the study and for 6 months post treatment;

          -  Negative pregnancy test;

          -  Must be on stable pain medication regimen at least 30 days prior to Screening

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical instability limiting ability to travel to the study site;

          -  The presence of medical illness expected to complicate participation and/or compromise
             the safety of this technique, such as active infection with human immunodeficiency
             virus (HIV), hepatitis B or hepatitis C;

          -  Evidence of immune response to C7 by indirect immunofluorescence (IIF);

          -  Evidence of systemic infection;

          -  Current evidence or a history of squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) in the area that will
             undergo EB-101 application;

          -  Active drug or alcohol addiction;

          -  Hypersensitivity to vancomycin or amikacin;

          -  Receipt of chemical or biological study product for the specific treatment of RDEB in
             the past 3 months;

          -  Positive pregnancy test or breast-feeding;

          -  Clinically significant medical or laboratory abnormalities as determined by the
             Principal Investigator;

          -  Inability to properly follow protocol and protect keratinocyte sheet sites, as
             determined by the Principal Investigator;

          -  Grade 3 clinical event or laboratory abnormality at Day 0. Abnormalities such as
             esophageal strictures, anemia, low albumin, and pain/itch are expected in RDEB
             patients. These abnormalities will not exclude a participant; and

          -  Inability to culture participant's keratinocytes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean Tang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Abeona Clinical Operations</last_name>
    <phone>+1-646-813-4701</phone>
    <email>eb@abeonatherapeutics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Redwood City</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94063</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Irene Bailey</last_name>
      <phone>650-721-7149</phone>
      <email>baileyhi@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean Tang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Marinkovich, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic wounds</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epidermolysis Bullosa</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epidermolysis Bullosa Dystrophica</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

