<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04229173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC31/19/0161</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04229173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History and Disease Progression Biomarkers of Multiple System Atrophy</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASPIRE-MSA</acronym>
  <official_title>Natural History and Disease Progression Biomarkers of Multiple System Atrophy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple system atrophy (MSA) is a rare and fatal neurodegenerative disease characterised by
      a variable combination of parkinsonism, cerebellar impairment and autonomic dysfunction. The
      neuropathological hallmark is the accumulation of alpha-synuclein in oligodendrocytes. While
      some symptomatic treatments exist, neuroprotective treatments for MSA remain an urgent, unmet
      need. Moreover, at present there is not a single surrogate biomarker of MSA which could be
      used to inform clinical trials.

      This study seeks to characterise the natural history of MSA on a panel of candidate
      biomarkers, pre-selected for being putative surrogates of the underlying neurodegenerative
      process
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Surrogate biomarkers are objectively measured characteristics of a disease which act as
      indicators of the underlying pathophysiological processes responsible for disease
      progression. Reduced grey matter volume in putamen, cerebellum and brainstem as measured with
      MRI have been consistently reported to differentiate MSA from other parkinsonian disorders.
      However, to date, there are no longitudinal studies examining the natural history of MSA on
      these structural neuroimaging markers over time. The magnitude of the abnormalities observed
      cross-sectionally in MSA compared to other parkinsonian disorders and the fast clinical
      progression of the disease make it very likely that structural changes can be observed even
      over short periods of time. There is also a strong scientific rationale for the potential of
      measures reflecting white matter integrity, cerebral iron deposition and presynaptic
      dopaminergic dysfunction, as well as levels of neurofilament light chain (NfL),
      alpha-synuclein and other proteins involved in the neurodegenerative process in MSA, to serve
      as progression biomarkers of the disease, although supporting evidence remains limited. A
      better understanding of the natural history of MSA over 6 and 12 months on a panel of
      candidate surrogate biomarkers is needed to better understand the disease, help optimise
      future trial designs in terms of patient selection, sample size and trial duration, and
      improve the ability to measure the therapeutic effects of novel treatments.

      In evaluating potential progression markers of a neurodegenerative disease such as MSA, it is
      important to control for the normal effects of aging. Studies in healthy volunteers have
      shown regionally distinct effects of aging on both brain volume and dopamine transporter
      density, justifying the inclusion of healthy controls with a similar age and gender
      distribution than patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change putamen, cerebellum and brainstem volume measured on MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>volume measured with T1-3D MRI, unit : Volume (mm3), Fer: R2* (s−1), diffusion: mean diffusivity (mm2s−1)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of disease progression on other measures of brain structural integrity and iron accumulation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>volume measured with T1-3D MRI, unit : Volume (mm3), Fer: R2* (s−1), diffusion: mean diffusivity (mm2s−1)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of disease progression on the loss of presynaptic dopaminergic terminals in the striatum integrity and iron accumulation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>volume measured with DAT SPECT (Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography), unit : binding potential (e.g ratio striatum/brain activity)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of disease progression on axonal damage as evidenced in biofluids</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>biomarkers dosages in blood and Cerebral Spinal Fluid total Concentration unit : pg/ml.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple System Atrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSA patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with multiple system atrophy will be examined at baseline, 6 months and 12 months via the following procedures performed at all 3 visits:
a clinical examination;
blood and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) (optional) sampling for the assessment of selected fluid biomarkers;
MRI for the assessment of brain volume, white matter integrity and cerebral iron deposition; DAT-SPECT (Dopamine Transporter, Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography) for the assessment of presynaptic dopaminergic function</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>healthy. Controls will undergo an MRI scan at baseline, 6 months and 12 months, and a DAT-SPECT(Dopamine Transporter, Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography) scan at baseline and 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI acquisition</intervention_name>
    <description>MRI acquisition</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MSA patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DAT-SPECT</intervention_name>
    <description>Imaging with DAT SPECT (Dopamine Transporter, Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography)</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSA patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blood sample, cerebrospinal fluid (optional)</intervention_name>
    <description>blood sample, cerebrospinal fluid</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSA patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evaluations about motor abilities, depression, cognition and lifestyle</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluations about motor abilities (UMSAR scale), depression (BDI scale), cognition (MoCA scale) and lifestyle (MSA- QoL)</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSA patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evaluation about depression cognition</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluations about depression (BDI scale), cognition (MoCA scale)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Applicable to MSA patients:

          -  Patients with possible or probable MSA according to consensus diagnosis criteria
             [Gilman et al., 2008]

          -  Patients aged between 30 and 80 years

          -  Patients at the early stages of the disease, defined as maximum 3 years since the
             onset of one of the following symptoms associated to MSA:

        Parkinsonism Ataxia Orthostatic hypotension and/or urinary dysfunction - Patients with an
        anticipated survival of at least 3 years on the basis of Investigators' clinical judgment

        Applicable to healthy controls:

          -  Participants with a similar age (+/- 5 years) and gender distribution compared to MSA
             patients

          -  Participants with absence of neurological pathology

          -  Patients aged between 25 and &lt; 80 years

        Applicable to both patients and healthy controls:

        - Participants who voluntarily sign the written informed consent form, indicating that they
        understand the purpose of and procedures required for the study and are willing to
        participate in it Participants affiliated to the French social security health system

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Applicable to MSA patients:

          -  Speech impairment (score of ≥3 on UMSARS (Unified Multiple System Atrophy Rating
             Scale) question 1);

          -  Impairment in ambulation (score of ≥3 on UMSARS (Unified Multiple System Atrophy
             Rating Scale) question 7)

          -  Falling more frequently than once per week (score of ≥3 on UMSARS (Unified Multiple
             System Atrophy Rating Scale) question 8)

        Applicable to both MSA patients and healthy controls:

          -  Participants with significant cognitive impairment (MoCA score &lt;21)

          -  Any major medical or psychiatric condition which may compromise participation in the
             study or the safety, at the discretion of the Investigator

          -  Contraindications for MRI imaging, including claustrophobia and presence of metallic
             implants such as cardiac or auditory prostheses, pacemakers or cerebral clips

          -  Contraindications to obtain a FP-CIT SPECT(Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography)
             (i.e. known hypersensitivity to the active substance or to any of the excipients, or
             to iodine)

          -  Current pharmacological treatments that may alter the DAT(dopamine transporter ) SPECT
             (Single Photon Emission Computed Tomography) reading, including amphetamines,
             benzatropine, buproprion (amfebutamone), cocaine, mazindol, methylphenidate,
             phentermine or sertraline

          -  Females who are pregnant, breast feeding or of child bearing age without effective
             contraception

          -  Participants who lack the capacity to give informed consent

          -  Participants taking any investigational products within 3 months before baseline
             assessment

          -  Participant under adult autonomy protection system, legal guardianship or
             incapacitation.

        Additional exclusion criteria concerning only patients consenting to the lumbar puncture:

          -  Coagulopathy and/or anticoagulant treatment

          -  Thrombocytopenia

          -  Intracranial hypertension

          -  Severe degenerative arthritis of the lumbar spine Patients failing to meet these
             criteria can still participate in the study and all other study assessments (with the
             exception of lumbar puncture) as appropriate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olivier RASCOL, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>OLIVIER RASCOL, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>0033561779103</phone>
    <phone_ext>33</phone_ext>
    <email>olivier.rascol@univ-tlse3.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wassilios MEISNER, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>33557821253</phone>
    <email>wassilios.meissner@chu-bordeaux.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>MSA</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Dat spect</keyword>
  <keyword>Atrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple System Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shy-Drager Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

