<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04229537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SCT-I10A-X102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04229537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of SCT-I10A Combined SCT200 or SCT-I10A Combined SCT200 Plus Chemotherapy in ESCC and CRC</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of SCT-I10A Combined SCT200 or SCT-I10A Combined SCT200 Plus Chemotherapy in Advanced Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma and Colorectal Cancer: a Phase Ⅰb, Open-label, Multicenter Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sinocelltech Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sinocelltech Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of SCT-I10A combined SCT200
      or SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus chemotherapy in advanced esophageal squamous cell carcinoma
      and colorectal cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a open label, multicenter, phase III study designed to evaluate the safety and
      efficacy in advanced esophageal squamous cell carcinoma and colorectal cancer treated with
      SCT-I10A combined SCT200 or SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Including adverse events and safety of laboratory tests</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR is defined as proportion of patients achieving complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) according to RECIST v1.1 or Lugano 2014 criteria during trial treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>DOR is defined as time from the date when a patient first meets the criteria for CR or PR according to RECIST v1.1 or Lugano 2014 criteria, until the date that progressive disease (PD) is objectively documented or death, whichever occurs first</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The achievement of any a stable response（SD）, partial response (PR) or complete response (CR), according to RECIST v1.1 or Lugano 2014 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the time from first dose of SCT200 until the date of first documentation of progression or date of death, whichever occurs first,according to RECIST v1.1 or Lugano 2014 criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as time from first dose of SCT200 until the date of death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in ESCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SCT-I10A: 200 mg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q3W. SCT200: 6mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of QW, then 8mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q2W</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in CRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SCT-I10A: 200 mg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q3W. SCT200: 6mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of QW, then 8mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q2W</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus Chemotherapy in CRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SCT-I10A: 200 mg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q3W. SCT200: 6mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of QW, then 8mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q2W.
Chemotherapy: Capecitabine and Oxaliplatin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SCT-I10A</intervention_name>
    <description>200 mg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q3W.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in CRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in ESCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus Chemotherapy in CRC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SCT200</intervention_name>
    <description>6mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of QW, then 8mg/kg intravenous (IV) on Day 1 of Q2W</description>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in CRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 in ESCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus Chemotherapy in CRC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Capecitabine and Oxaliplatin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SCT-I10A combined SCT200 plus Chemotherapy in CRC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Able to provide written informed consent before screening；

          -  Males or females. Aged 18 to 75 years old;

          -  Life expectancy≥12 weeks before starting treatment (clinical assessment);

          -  With an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1;

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced esophageal squamous cell carcinoma
             or colorectal cancer;

          -  Patients with advanced esophageal squamous cell carcinoma undergoing first-line
             systemic chemotherapy progression or intolerance were included in Arm 1; Patients with
             RAS and BRAF wild-type advanced colorectal cancer undergoing at least second line
             systemic chemotherapy progression or intolerance were included in Arm 2; Patients with
             RAS and BRAF wild-type advanced colorectal cancer untreated with cetuximab were
             included in Arm 3;

          -  According to RECIST 1.1, patients must have at least one measurable lesion that can be
             accurately assessed;

          -  Adequate organ and bone marrow function as defined below:

        Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than/equal to 1.5×l09/L; Platelets greater
        than/equal to 100×109/L; Hemoglobin greater than/equal to 90g/L; Aspartate aminotransferase
        (AST)/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than/equal to 3 times ULN, or less than/equal to
        5 times ULN if known liver metastases; Total bilirubin less than/equal to 1.5 times ULN;
        Serum creatinine less than/equal to 1.5 times ULN or Ccr&gt;60ml/min; Thyroid stimulating
        hormone (TSH) hormone levels less than/equal to ULN; Serum magnesium greater than/equal to
        ULN; APTT, INR, PT less than/equal to 1.5 times ULN.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who were allergic to analogue of SCT-I10A/SCT200 and/or its inactive
             ingredients, Patients who were allergic to Capecitabine and/or Oxaliplatin were also
             excluded in cohort3;

          -  Patients have been treated with anti-PD-L1/PD-L2 or anti-PD-1, EGFR antibody or
             EGFR-TKI;

          -  Within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have received
             anti-tumor drugs (such as chemotherapy, endocrine therapy, targeted therapy, immune
             therapy, tumor embolization). Within 6 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug,
             patients have been treated with biological products, nitrosourea or mitomycin C.
             Within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have been treated with
             tumor embolization or radiotherapy;

          -  Within 2 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have received
             corticosteroids or other immunosuppressive agents;

          -  Within 1 month prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have received live
             attenuated vaccine (LAV);

          -  Patients are currently enrolled in other research devices or in research drugs, or
             less than 4 weeks from other research drugs or devices;

          -  Patients with significant malnutrition. Patients will be excluded if they are
             receiving intravenous hyperalimentation, or require continuous infusion therapy with
             hospitalization. Patients whose nutrition has been well controlled for ≥ 28 days prior
             to randomization may be enrolled.

          -  Within 4 weeks prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have received major
             surgery, or had wounds, ulcers or fractures that haven't healed; Within 6 weeks prior
             to the first dose of study drug, patients were suffering with gastrointestinal
             perforation or fistula;

          -  Has active infection or fever of unknown origin(&gt; 38.5℃)；

          -  Has invaded large vessels and weasand

          -  Active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous meningitis;
             subjects with previous treated brain metastases may participate provided they are
             stable for at least 2 weeks prior to the first dose of study medication, have no
             evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using steroids for at least
             14 days prior to trial treatment. Subjects with asymptomatic brain metastases (without
             neurological symptoms, not using steroids, tumor lesions≤1.5cm) may participate in
             condition that the tumor lesion should be regularly evaluated using identical imaging
             modality for each assessment, either MRI or CT scans;

          -  Patients with clinical symptoms, required clinical intervention or stable time less
             than 4 weeks of serous cavity effusion (such as pleural effusion and ascites);

          -  Poorly controlled hypetension. Within 6 months prior to study, patients had
             uncontrolled concurrent diseases, including but not limited to acute myocardial
             infarction, unstable angina pectoris, stroke, or transient ischemic attack, congestive
             heart failure (NYHA, greater than II), left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt;50%,
             and with related heart disease.

          -  Patients who have interstitial lung disease or imaging features of interstitial
             pneumonia, or who have history of non-infectious pneumonia treated with
             corticosteroids.

          -  Patients with an active, known or suspected autoimmune disease or a history of
             autoimmune disease;

          -  Within 5 year prior to the first dose of study drug, patients have other primary
             malignancies;

          -  Have a history of HIV;

          -  Patients with a history of allogeneic organ transplantation or allogeneic
             hematopoietic stem cell transplantation;

          -  Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g. HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C(e.g. HCV RNA
             [quantitative] is detected);

          -  Prior to the first dose of study drug, patients had toxicity due to previous
             anti-tumor treatment, which hasn't return to Grade 0-1 according to the NCI CTCAE
             v5.0;

          -  Has known with alcohol or drug addiction;

          -  Pregnant or lactating women;

          -  Patients who were not willing to accept effective contraceptive measures during
             treatment and within 6 months after treatment;

          -  Subjects who are considered not suitable for the study by investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yi Ba, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tianjin Medical University Cancer Institute and Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Foxiao Qiao, Ph D</last_name>
    <phone>18911165421</phone>
    <email>Foxiao_qiao@sinocelltech.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SCT-I10A</keyword>
  <keyword>SCT200</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

