<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04227366</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BCD-089-3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04227366</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Efficacy and Safety of BCD-089 in Combination With Methotrexate in Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <acronym>SOLAR</acronym>
  <official_title>An International, Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Clinical Study of the Efficacy and Safety of BCD-089 (JSC BIOCAD, Russia) in Combination With Methotrexate in Patients With Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biocad</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biocad</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BCD-089 is the original therapeutic monoclonal antibody binding the alpha subunit of the IL-6
      receptor.

      The aim of the study is to demonstrate the efficacy and safety of BCD-089 in combination with
      methotrexate in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis resistant to monotherapy with
      methotrexate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BCD-089-3/SOLAR is the international, multicenter, double blind, placebo-controlled phase III
      clinical study.

      The main period of the study (Weeks 0-24) is blinded; study subjects will receive
      BCD-089/placebo.

      At Week 24 the study will become open-label and all patients will receive BCD-089 once a week
      for 4 weeks. At week 28 patients who achieved the RA remission at week 24 will be switched to
      BCD-089 Q2W dosing regimen and will receive it through Week 51. Patients who failed to
      achieve remission at week 24 will receive BCD-089 once a week through Week 51.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 19, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR 20 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of ACR 20 responders</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Low disease activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients with low disease activity according to DAS28-CRP(4) (&lt; 3,2)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for rescue therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who required rescue therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RA remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved RA remission according to DAS28-CRP(4) (&lt; 2.6)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RA remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved RA remission according to CDAI (≤ 2.8)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RA remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved RA remission according to SDAI (≤ 3.3)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Remission according to the ACR/EULAR 2011 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved remission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR20 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of ACR20 responders</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR50 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of ACR50 responders</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ACR70 response</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of ACR70 responders</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low RA activity according to DAS28-ESR(4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved low RA activity according to DAS28-ESR(4) (&lt; 3.2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low RA activity according to CDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of patients who achieved low RA activity according to CDAI (≤ 10)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low RA activity according to SDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients who achieved low RA activity according to SDAI (≤ 11)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the DAS28-CRP(4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the DAS28-CRP(4)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the CDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the CDAI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the SDAI</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the SDAI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moderate/good response according to the EULAR criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of patients with moderate/good response according to the EULAR criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in concentration of C-reactive protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24.</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the concentration of C-reactive protein in serum</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the ESR</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the quality of life measured with SF-36</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the patient's quality of life measured with the SF-36 score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the quality of life measured with the EQ-5D-3L</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change from baseline in the patient's quality of life measured with the EQ-5D-3L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy - Fatigue (FACIT-F) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change in the FACIT-F score. The level of fatigue is measured on a four point Likert scale (4 = not at all fatigued to 0 = very much fatigued) (Webster et al., 2003)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 12, 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change in functional activity according to the HAQ-DI (Health Assessment Questionnaire without Didability Index) score. The value of the HAQ-DI index can be interpreted in terms of three categories:
from 0 to 1: mild difficulties to moderate disability, from 1 to 2: disability moderate to severe, from 2 to 3: severe to very severe disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>X-ray assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The change in mTSS score according to Sharp/van der Heijde (SvH) scoring method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BCD-089</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BCD-089</intervention_name>
    <description>BCD-089 162 mg SC</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo (for BCD-089)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexat</intervention_name>
    <description>15 to 25 mg/week</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed informed consent form (ICF).

          2. Men and women aged 18 years or older on the day of signing the ICF.

          3. Verified rheumatoid arthritis according to the ACR 2010 criteria diagnosed at least 24
             weeks before signing the ICF .

          4. Use of methotrexate for the last 12 weeks before signing the ICF.

          5. Use of a stable dose of methotrexate for the last 4 weeks before signing the ICF (the
             dose of methotrexate should be 15 to 25 mg per week). Methotrexate can be used at a
             dose of 10 mg in the case of intolerability/toxicity of higher doses.

          6. Inefficacy of methotrexate used for the last 12 weeks before signing the ICF (in the
             opinion of the Investigator).

          7. Active rheumatoid arthritis at randomization in the study.

          8. The ability of the patient (in the Investigator's opinion) to follow the Protocol
             procedures.

          9. Patients and their sexual partners of childbearing potential agree to use reliable
             contraceptive methods starting from signing the ICF, during the study and for 8 weeks
             from the last injection of the investigational product. This requirement does not
             apply to patients and their partners who underwent surgical sterilization and to women
             who are post-menopausal for at least 2 years. Reliable contraceptive methods include
             one barrier method in combination with one of the following: spermicides, intrauterine
             device/oral contraceptives.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous exposure to tocilizumab or other anti-IL6 or anti-IL-6R monoclonal
             antibodies.

          2. Previous exposure to JAK inhibitors.

          3. Previous exposure to rituximab or other B-cell depleting/suppressing agents.

          4. Felty's syndrome (regardless of clinical form).

          5. Patient's functional status: class IV according to the ACR 1991 classification.

          6. Known allergy to or intolerance of any ingredients of BCD-089 or placebo.

          7. Use of any of the following concomitant therapies:

               -  Oral prednisolone or its equivalent in a dose more than 10 mg/day;

               -  Need in oral prednisolone (or its equivalent) ≤ 10 mg if its dose was not stable
                  during the last 4 weeks before signing the ICF (patients who used topical
                  glucocorticoids are allowed to participate in the study);

               -  Need in NSAIDs if the dose was not stable during the last 4 weeks before signing
                  the ICF (patients who have occasionally used NSAIDs for fever or allergy syndrome
                  associated with an intercurrent disease can be included in the study);

               -  Use of alkylating agents any time within 12 months before signing the ICF.

               -  Intra-articular use of corticosteroids within 4 weeks before signing the ICF.

               -  Vaccination with live or attenuated vaccines any time within 8 weeks before
                  signing the ICF.

               -  Use of leflunomide within 8 weeks before signing the ICF.

               -  Use of TNFα inhibitors or T-cell costimulation blockers within 8 weeks before
                  signing the ICF.

          8. Any of the following laboratory values at screening:

               -  Hemoglobin level &lt; 80 g/L;

               -  Leukocyte count &lt; 3.0 × 109/L;

               -  Platelet count &lt; 100 × 109/L;

               -  Neutrophil count &lt; 2 × 109/L;

               -  AST and ALT ≥ 1.5×ULN (based on the reference limits used by the laboratory);

               -  Serum creatinine ≥ 1.7 × ULN (based on the reference limits used by the
                  laboratory).

          9. Positive pregnancy urine test in female subjects at screening (no test is required in
             women who are post-menopausal for at least 2 years and in surgically sterile women).

         10. Current diagnosis or a history of a severe immunodeficiency of any other origin.

         11. Diagnosed HIV, hepatitis B, hepatitis C, or syphilis ;

         12. Tuberculosis now or in the past.

         13. Latent TB forms (positive Diaskintest®, QuantiFERON®-TB Gold or T-SPOT.TB test with no
             radiographic signs of pulmonary TB).

         14. Herpes zoster infection now or in the past .

         15. Documented chickenpox within 30 days before signing the ICF.

         16. Definite diagnosis of any other chronic infection (e.g. sepsis, invasive mycoses,
             histoplasmosis, etc.) that, in the Investigator's opinion, can increase the risk of
             infectious complications.

         17. Any acute infection or aggravation of a chronic infection within 30 days before
             signing the ICF if this condition may, in the Investigator's opinion, increase the
             risk of infectious complications.

         18. Severe infections (including those that required hospitalization or parenteral
             antibacterial/antimycotic/antiprotozoal treatment) within 6 months before signing the
             ICF.

         19. Systemic antibacterial/antimycotic/antiprotozoal treatments used within 8 weeks before
             the signing the ICF.

         20. More than 4 episodes of respiratory infections within 6 months before signing the ICF.

         21. A major surgery within 30 days before signing the ICF or a major surgery scheduled at
             any time during the study.

         22. History of epileptic attacks or seizures.

         23. History of severe depression, suicidal thoughts or suicide attempts .

         24. Diverticulosis and/or diverticulitis .

         25. Alcohol, drug or psychoactive substance dependence or medication abuse now or in the
             past, signs of alcohol/drug dependence.

         26. Other documented medical conditions that can increase a risk of adverse events during
             the study treatment, affect the assessment of the main disease severity, mask,
             aggravate, affect symptoms of the main disease, or result in the same clinical and
             laboratory instrumental symptoms as those of rheumatoid arthritis:

               -  Diabetes mellitus with inadequate glycemic control ;

               -  Severe treatment-resistant hypertension ;

               -  Current or a history of inflammatory joint diseases other than rheumatoid
                  arthritis (including ankylosing spondylitis, gout, psoriatic arthritis, Lyme
                  disease etc. ) or other systemic autoimmune diseases (including systemic lupus
                  erythematosus, Crohn's disease, non-specific ulcerative colitis, systemic
                  scleroderma, inflammatory myopathy, mixed connective tissue disease, overlap
                  syndrome, fibromyalgia etc.);

               -  Malignant neoplasms except for cured basal-cell carcinoma and cancer of the
                  cervix in situ (complete remission ≥ 5 years); cured basal-cell carcinoma of the
                  skin (complete remission ≥ 5 years); cured ductal breast cancer (complete
                  remission ≥ 5 years);

               -  Decompensated liver or kidney diseases;

               -  Unstable angina;

               -  Chronic heart failure of NYHA class III-IV;

               -  Myocardial infarction within 1 year before signing the ICF;

               -  History of organ transplantation;

               -  History of angioedema;

               -  Respiratory system disorders with decompensated respiratory insufficiency;

               -  Definite diagnosis of multiple sclerosis, Devic's disease, or Guillain-Barre
                  syndrome;

               -  Nervous system disorders with motor and/or sensitivity abnormalities.

         27. Pregnancy , planned pregnancy less than 8 weeks after the last injection of the
             investigational product; lactation.

         28. Current participation in other clinical studies; previous participation in other
             clinical studies within 3 calendar months before signing the ICF (except for
             screenouts); previous participation in this study (except for screenouts).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yulia Linkova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>JSC BIOCAD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anton Lutckii, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+7 812 380 49 33</phone>
    <phone_ext>311</phone_ext>
    <email>lutskii@biocad.ru</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maria Morozova, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+7 (495) 992 66 28</phone>
    <phone_ext>8436</phone_ext>
    <email>morozovama@biocad.ru</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute of Rheumotology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Evgeniy Zotkin</last_name>
      <phone>+7 (495) 109 21 44</phone>
      <email>ezotkin@mail.ru</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 13, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>anti-IL-6R</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-6 receptor inhibitors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

