<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04220684</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OSU-18336</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2019-05150</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016058</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04220684</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Off-the-shelf Third Party Expanded NK Cells in Treating Patients With Recurrent or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia or Myelodysplastic Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Clinical Trial Testing the Safety of IL-21-Expanded, Off-the-Shelf, Third-Party Natural Killer Cells for Relapsed/Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sumithira Vasu</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects of donor natural killer (NK) cell therapy in
      treating patients with acute myeloid leukemia that has come back (recurrent) or has not
      responded to treatment (refractory), or myelodysplastic syndrome. Natural killer cells are a
      type of immune cell. Immunotherapy with genetically modified NK cells from donors may induce
      changes in the body?s immune system and may interfere with the ability of cancer cells to
      grow and spread.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To determine the safety of adoptive NK cell therapy using membrane-bound interleukin-21
      (mbIL21)-expanded, off-the-shelf, third-party donor-derived NK cells in patients with
      relapsed/refractory acute myeloid leukemia (AML).

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate the complete response (CR, CR with incomplete hematologic recovery [CRi] &amp;
      morphologic leukemia-free state [MLFS]).

      II. Estimate the median relapse free survival. III. Estimate the median time to neutrophil
      and platelet count recovery. IV. Estimate the median duration of remission. V. Estimate the
      incidence of infectious complications. VI. Estimate percentage of patients receiving this
      regimen who are rendered transplant-eligible.

      CORRELATIVE OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the persistence of ex-vivo expanded, off-the-shelf, third-party NK cells.

      II. Characterize in vivo expansion of third-party NK cells and if it differs based on the
      conditioning regimen as defined by NK chimerism assay.

      III. Determine the immunophenotype and function of expanded cells. IV. Chimerism analysis in
      patients who have had post-transplant relapses.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of membrane-bound interleukin-21-expanded
      haploidentical natural killer cells.

      INDUCTION: Patients are assigned to 1 of 2 arms.

      COHORT I: Patients who are &lt; 60 years old, are able to tolerate intensive chemotherapy, and
      not insensitive to cytarabine receive fludarabine intravenously (IV) and cytarabine IV on
      days -6 to -2 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      COHORT II: Patients who are &gt;= 60 years old, unable/unwilling to tolerate intensive
      chemotherapy, or disease insensitive to cytarabine (tp53, TET2 mutations) receive fludarabine
      IV on days -5 to -2 and decitabine IV on days -6 to -2 in the absence of disease progression
      or unacceptable toxicity.

      All patients receive membrane-bound interleukin-21-expanded haploidentical natural killer
      cells via infusion on days 0, 2, 4, 7, 9, and 11.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up to day 56.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of membrane-bound interleukin-21-expanded haploidentical natural killer (NK) cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 63 days</time_frame>
    <description>The MTD will be defined as the highest safely tolerated dose where at most one patient in six experiences dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) during DLT observation period. DLT is defined as any steroid refractory acute graft versus host disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicities will be assessed by type and grade using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 5.0 and displayed in summary form by cohort and overall. Toxicities will be summarized and reported regardless of attribution and also only those attributed to NK cells.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response (CR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate with a 95% confidence interval (CI) will be reported for all evaluable patients, assuming a binomial distribution. Response rate will also be reported for those who received all 6 doses of NK cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CR with incomplete hematologic recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate with a 95% CI will be reported for all evaluable patients, assuming a binomial distribution. Response rate will also be reported for those who received all 6 doses of NK cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morphologic leukemia-free state</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Response rate with a 95% CI will be reported for all evaluable patients, assuming a binomial distribution. Response rate will also be reported for those who received all 6 doses of NK cells.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median relapse free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Will use descriptive statistics to summarize the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients on this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median time to neutrophil and platelet count recovery</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Will use descriptive statistics to summarize the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients on this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median duration of remission</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Will use descriptive statistics to summarize the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients on this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of infectious complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Will use descriptive statistics to summarize the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients on this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients receiving the regimen who are rendered transplant-eligible</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Will use descriptive statistics to summarize the demographic and clinical characteristics of the patients on this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of In-vivo expansion of NK cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral blood will be obtained before therapy, during the NK cell treatment period, and after NK cell treatment. The studies may include flow cytometry analyses and sorting and molecular studies. Donor NK-cell expansion will be defined as an absolute circulating donor-derived NK cell count that increases above the post-infusion level.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Chimerism analysis to determine origin and number of circulating NK cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Chimerism may be determined by flow cytometry using haplotype-specific antibodies. Chimerism may be determined by short tandem repeat polymorphisms. When there is a sex-mismatch between the donor and the recipient, assays based on determining the frequency of sex-chromosomes may be used. Testing may be altered by principal investigator or designee.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of donor human leukocyte antigen (HLA) detection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 56</time_frame>
    <description>Donors with distinct HLA A or B antigens that can be detected by flow cytometry will be chosen. This will enable tracking of infused cells.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant Recipient</condition>
  <condition>Blasts 10 Percent or More of Bone Marrow Nucleated Cells</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who are &lt; 60 years old, are able to tolerate intensive chemotherapy, and not insensitive to cytarabine receive fludarabine IV and cytarabine IV on days -6 to -2 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. All patients receive membrane-bound interleukin-21-expanded haploidentical natural killer cells via infusion on days 0, 2, 4, 7, 9, and 11.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (fludarabine, decitabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients who are &gt;= 60 years old, unable/unwilling to tolerate intensive chemotherapy, or disease insensitive to cytarabine (tp53, TET2 mutations) receive fludarabine IV on days -5 to -2 and decitabine IV on days -6 to -2 in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. All patients receive membrane-bound interleukin-21-expanded haploidentical natural killer cells via infusion on days 0, 2, 4, 7, 9, and 11.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>.beta.-Cytosine arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>1-.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosyl-4-amino-2(1H)pyrimidinone</other_name>
    <other_name>1-.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>1-Beta-D-arabinofuranosyl-4-amino-2(1H)pyrimidinone</other_name>
    <other_name>1-Beta-D-arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>1.beta.-D-Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>2(1H)-Pyrimidinone, 4-Amino-1-beta-D-arabinofuranosyl-</other_name>
    <other_name>2(1H)-Pyrimidinone, 4-amino-1.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl-</other_name>
    <other_name>Alexan</other_name>
    <other_name>Ara-C</other_name>
    <other_name>ARA-cell</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabine</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinofuranosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinosylcytosine</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytin</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytine</other_name>
    <other_name>Beta-cytosine Arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>CHX-3311</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarabinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytarbel</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine Arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine-.beta.-arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine-beta-arabinoside</other_name>
    <other_name>Erpalfa</other_name>
    <other_name>Starasid</other_name>
    <other_name>Tarabine PFS</other_name>
    <other_name>U 19920</other_name>
    <other_name>U-19920</other_name>
    <other_name>Udicil</other_name>
    <other_name>WR-28453</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cytarabine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ara-C HCl</other_name>
    <other_name>Arabinosylcytosine Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Aracytidine Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>CHX-3311</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosar Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Cytosine Arabinosine Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>U-19920A</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (fludarabine, decitabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-Aza-2''-deoxycytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Dacogen</other_name>
    <other_name>Decitabine for Injection</other_name>
    <other_name>Deoxyazacytidine</other_name>
    <other_name>Dezocitidine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (fludarabine, decitabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fluradosa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (fludarabine, decitabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>9H-Purin-6-amine, 2-fluoro-9-(5-O-phosphono-.beta.-D-arabinofuranosyl)-</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
    <other_name>SH T 586</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Membrane-bound Interleukin-21-Expanded Haploidentical Natural Killer Cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Given via infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort I (fludarabine, cytarabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort II (fludarabine, decitabine, NK cell therapy)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(mbIL21)-expanded Haploidentical NK Cells</other_name>
    <other_name>Donor mbIL21-expanded NK Cells</other_name>
    <other_name>mbIL21-expanded Haploidentical NK Cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with one of the following diagnoses:

               -  Relapsed or primary refractory acute myeloid leukemia (AML), including

                    -  Patients with relapsed AML after allogeneic stem cells transplantation,
                       including those who have received donor lymphocyte infusions

                    -  Isolated central nervous system (CNS) or extramedullary disease

                    -  Note: a response monitoring plan must be developed a priori for subjects
                       with extramedullary disease

               -  Myelodysplastic syndrome

                    -  &gt;= 10% blasts, including patients who have received prior hypomethylating
                       agents

          -  Karnofsky or Lansky performance scale (PS) greater or equal to 70

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 2 mg/dl or creatinine clearance greater or equal than 40 cc/min.
             Creatinine for pediatric patients =&lt; 2 mg/dl or =&lt; 2 times upper limit of normal for
             age (whichever is less)

          -  Forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1), forced vital capacity (FVC) and
             diffusion capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) &gt;= 50% of expected,
             corrected for hemoglobin. For pediatric patients, if unable to perform pulmonary
             function tests (most children &lt; 7 years of age), pulse oximetry &gt;= 92% on room air by
             pulse oximetry

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 2 mg/dl or =&lt; 2.5 x upper limit or normal (ULN) for age (unless
             Gilbert's syndrome)

          -  Serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 2.5 x
             ULN for age

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction &gt;= 40%

          -  Patients with seizure disorder may be eligible if seizures well controlled

          -  Negative serum test to rule out pregnancy within 2 weeks prior to enrollment in
             females of childbearing potential (non-childbearing potential defined as premenarchal,
             greater than one year post-menopausal, or surgically sterilized)

          -  Sexually active males and females of childbearing potential must agree to use a form
             of contraception considered effective and medically acceptable by the investigator

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign the written informed consent document

          -  Negative serology for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Investigational therapies in the 2 weeks prior to beginning treatment on this protocol

          -  Any comorbidities that in the opinion of the investigator will preclude receiving
             fludarabine, decitabine or cytarabine

          -  Uncontrolled infection, defined as an infection which has not resolved spontaneously
             or does not show evidence of significant resolution after initiating appropriate
             therapy. Asymptomatic viremia such as cytomegalovirus (CMV), human papillomavirus
             (HPV), BK virus, hepatitis C virus (HCV), etc. is NOT considered as an exclusion
             criteria

          -  Uncontrolled arrhythmias or uncontrolled symptomatic cardiac disease

          -  Active graft versus host disease (GVHD)

          -  Patient on corticosteroids to control GvHD
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sumithira Vasu, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>The Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-293-5066</phone>
    <email>OSUCCCClinicaltrials@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicole Szuminski</last_name>
    <phone>614-688-9796</phone>
    <email>Nicole.Szuminski@osumc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sumithira Vasu, MBBS</last_name>
      <phone>614-293-8197</phone>
      <email>Sumithira.Vasu@osumc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sumithira Vasu, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cancer.osu.edu</url>
    <description>The Jamesline</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>September 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University Comprehensive Cancer Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sumithira Vasu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Recurrent Acute Myeloid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cytarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Decitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

