<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04229342</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>POEM001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04229342</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Post-POEM GERD in Patients Undergoing Conventional Versus Oblique Fibers Sparing Posterior Myotomy for Achalasia Cardia</brief_title>
  <acronym>POEM</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of Gastroesophageal Reflux Between Conventional Versus Oblique Fibers Sparing Endoscopic Myotomy for Achalasia Cardia - A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, we will evaluate the incidence of reflux esophagitis between two different
      techniques of posterior per-oral endoscopic myotomy (POEM) i.e. conventional POEM versus
      oblique/ sling fiber sparing POEM. This is a randomized trial where the patients with
      idiopathic achalasia will be randomized in two groups in 1:1 fashion into groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this randomized trial, patients with idiopathic achalasia will undergo POEM using two
      techniques as follows. In the first technique, a conventional posterior POEM will be
      performed where the sling or oblique fibers will not be spared during POEM. Sling or oblique
      fibers will be recognized using the configuration of fibers below the gastroesophaeal
      junction and by identifying the border between the sling fibers and the circular fibers which
      is formed by the penetrating vessels. In the second group (Oblique fiber group), the sling
      fibers will be selectively spared and only the circular fibers will be spared.

      The other steps of the POEM procedure will be the same as described in the standard technique
      of POEM. These include submucosal injection of saline mixed with indigo carmine dye, mucosal
      incision, submucosal tunneling using triangular knife in spray coagulation mode (Effect 2,
      Watts 50), myotomy extending upto 2-4 cm below the gastroesophageal junction and the closure
      of mucosal incision using endoclips.

      Post POEM management: All the patients will be kept nil per oral for about 24-hours after the
      procedure. A timed barium swallow will be performed the next day and oral liquids will be
      started. A soft puried diet will be started from day 3 onwards.

      Oral proton pump inhibitors (PPIs) equivalent to 40 mg of Pantoprazole per day will be
      prescribed to all the patients unless a contraindication exists.

      Follow-up: The first evaluation will be performed at 2-months after POEM. During this
      evaluation, the following parameters will be recorded: symptom relief, reflux symptoms, and
      esophageal acid exposure. PPIs will be stopped for 1-2 weeks prior to the evaluation of GERD.

      Subsequent evaluation will be at 6-months for reflux symptoms and symptoms of achalasia using
      Eckardt scores.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 6, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 14, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reflux Esophagitis, Los Angeles grade (minimum grade: A, maximum grade: D)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of reflux esophagitis will be done at 8 weeks post procedure using Los Angeles grading system (grade A to D)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Success, Eckardt Score (minimum: 0, maximum: 12), Eckardt Score≤3: success, &gt;3: failure</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success will be evaluated using Eckardt scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical success using Eckardt Score (minimum:0, maximum: 12)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical success will be evaluated using Eckardt scores. Eckardt Score≤3 will be considered as clinical success and &gt;3 will be considered as clinical failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Esophageal manometry</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Esophageal manometry will be performed at 8 weeks and Integrated relaxation pressure will be calculated and presented in mmHg 5. Change in IRP pressure by Manometry ( Assessed at pre procedure &amp; 8 weeks).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barium column height on Timed barium swallow; Success: &gt;50% reduction in barium column height</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Timed barium swallow will be performed after POEM procedure and Esophageal emptying will be seen and compared with pre-POEM timed barium esophagogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Esophageal acid exposure, Acid exposure time&gt;6 abnormal, &lt;4: normal, 4-6: inconclusive</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>24-hour pH impedance study will be performed at 8-weeks and esophageal acid exposure will be calculated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reflux Symptoms, GERD HRQL score (minimum score: 0, maximum score: 50)</measure>
    <time_frame>8-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The symptoms of gastroesophageal reflux will be evaluated using symptom scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastroesophageal reflux with DeMeester score at 8-weeks: DeMeester score≥14.7 abnormal, &lt;14.7: normal</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>DeMeester scores will be calculated at 8 weeks after the POEM procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>GERD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the &quot;conventional group&quot;, standard posterior myotomy will be performed and the sling or the oblique fibers will not be spared beyond the gastroesophageal junction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oblique or sling fiber sparing group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the oblique or sling fiber group, only the circular muscle fibers will be severed selectively and the sling fibers will be spared</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Per-oral endoscopic myotomy</intervention_name>
    <description>Per-oral endoscopic myotomy (POEM) is an endoscopic modality for the management of achalasia cardia. In this study, we will evaluate the impact of two different techniques of posterior POEM on the incidence of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD).
Posterior POEM will be performed using the standard technique. The myotomy beyond the GEJ will be different in the two groups. In one group, the sling fibers will not be spared from dissection and in the second group, the sling fibers will be selectively spared from myotomy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oblique or sling fiber sparing group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with type 1 and 2 achalasia with Eckardt score &gt;3 (0-12 scale achalasia).

          2. Patients with age 18-75 years.

          3. Patients who are treatment naïve or have a history of pneumatic balloon dilatation.

          4. Patients who are willing and able to comply with the study procedures and provide
             written informed consent form to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with type 3 achalasia cardia or any other esophageal motility disorder,

          2. Patients who have undergone previous surgery of the esophagus or stomach,

          3. Patients with active severe esophagitis,

          4. Patients with large lower esophageal diverticula,

          5. Patients with large ( &gt; 3cm ) hiatal hernia,

          6. Patients with sigmoid oesophagus,
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Vincy Chandran, MBBS,MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asian institute of Gastroenterology/AIG Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hyderabad</city>
        <state>Telangana</state>
        <zip>500082</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asian Institute of Gastroenterology, India</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohan Ramchandani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Achalasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

