<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04220281</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RGAbusinna</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04220281</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison Between Two Drugs (Propofol and Nitroglycerin as a Hypotensive Agents During Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>prop</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Hypotensive Efficacy of Propofol Infusion Versus Nitroglycerin Infusion in Functional Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and Objectives: FESS is a common minimally invasive surgery that requires a clear
      field to be performed well. Hypotensive anesthesia is one of the most common maneuvers
      performed to help in keeping the field clear. An ideal drug for hypotensive anesthesia should
      be cheap and familial to the anesthesiologist. So being familial with propofol and by using
      its cardio-depressant action the idea of the research was developed and comparing it with
      nitroglycerin (a hypotensive agent in our protocol). Methods: The patients agreed to
      participate in the research were classified into two groups for comparison. Propofol group;
      received propofol infusion all over the procedure, and nitroglycerin group; received
      nitroglycerin infusion all over the procedure. Duration of surgery, visibility of surgical
      field and amount of blood loss were recorded. Pulse/min and MAP were recorded at baseline and
      every 5 min. Results: The mean duration of surgery was longer in the NTG to propofol group.
      There was high statistical significance in the average blood loss in the propofol group
      compared to NTG group. The visibility of the operative field also was significant in the
      propofol group as compared to NTG group. The mean heart rate in the NTG group is higher than
      the mean heart rate in the propofol group. The MAP in both groups is within a close range.
      Conclusion: Propofol and NTG can produce a safe and effective controlled hypotension during
      FESS. Whereas, propofol has; a better surgical field visibility, less surgical bleeding and
      less tachycardia during FESS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. INTRODUCTION FESS (functional endoscopic sinus surgery) is a popular minimally invasive
           surgical technique for management of patient with sinus pathological conditions. The aim
           of this sinus endoscopic surgery is to restore a normal mucociliary clearing function
           and drainage of sinuses. Although, it is a minimally invasive surgery but it can lead to
           a serious complications such as optic nerve injury, orbital cellulitis, meningitis, and
           rhino-oral fistulas. Bleeding is one of the obstacles that is associated with this
           technique that can decrease the surgical field visualization and increase the
           probability of complications.

           One of the most important maneuvers used to minimize this bleeding is hypotensive
           anesthesia. The ideal hypotensive agent for anesthetist must be a familiar drug, easy to
           use, rapid onset and offset and with minimal side effects. Nitroglycerin infusion is a
           frequently used drug to produce controlled hypotension, as it is cheap and easy to use
           drug rapid onset and offset time. But a common side effect is reflex tachycardia and
           venous congestion which may also obscures the surgical filed and decreases surgeon
           satisfaction.

           Total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA) using propofol and remifentanil is a common
           procedure used in western countries. In Egypt remifentanil is not freely available. So
           this study will be designed to use inhalational anesthesia and use propofol infusion as
           a hypotensive agent and to determine whether controlled hypotension, surgeon's
           satisfaction and better operative filed can be achieved when compared to nitroglycerine
           infusion.

        2. AIM OF THE WORK The aim of the study is to identify the efficacy of propofol infusion as
           a hypotensive agent in comparison with nitroglycerin infusion during FESS.

      Study Design

      A total of 40 adult patients undergoing FESS procedure for sinusitis. Written informed
      consent will be obtained from all patients before randomization. Patients will be divided
      equally into two groups the first 20 patients will be assigned to propofol group (Prop group)
      and the other group to nitroglycerin group (NTG group). Group assignment, preparation and
      administration of drugs will be performed by a junior anesthetist who is neither involved nor
      interested by any means in the study. The patients, the ENT surgeon, and the anesthetist
      collecting data all were blind to the groups. The anesthetist performing the general
      anesthesia was not blinded to the drug given but he was not one of the study participants.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    the number of patients needed for the study have been collected
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 12, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 12, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy of propofol infusion as a hypotensive agent in comparison with nitroglycerin infusion in FESS surgeries under general anesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>the study data collected during the time of surgery ranging from 1-2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>measuring MAP every 5 min all over the time of surgery comparing the two study groups (propofol infusion versus nitroglycerin infusion)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>measuring the pulse rate</measure>
    <time_frame>the study data collected during the time of surgery ranging from 1-2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>comparing the pulse rate (beat/min) every 5 min all over the time of surgery comparing the two study groups (propofol infusion versus nitroglycerin infusion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>visibility of the surgical field by using the Average Category Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>done by the surgeon immediately after the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>evaluation of the visibility of the operative field during surgery by using the average category scale. minimum is grade 0 and maximum grade 5. the less the grade the better the visibility of the surgical field.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>amount of blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>done by the anesthetist every 1 hour during the surgery</time_frame>
    <description>measuring the amount of blood lost during the surgery by ml/hr</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypotensive Anesthesia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>propofol group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>propofol group will receive propofol infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nitroglycerin group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>will receive nitroglycerin infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>propofol infusion during surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>propofol group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>prop</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nitroglycerin</intervention_name>
    <description>nitroglycerin infusion during surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>nitroglycerin group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NTG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ASA I and II diagnosed for chronic sinusitis

          -  Age range between 18-60 years, undergoing elective FESS without septoplasty under
             general anesthesia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  included any patient with bleeding disorder, on anticoagulant therapy

          -  renal, hepatic or cardiac dysfunction

          -  history of cerebrovascular stroke

          -  peripheral vascular diseases

          -  allergic to any of the study drugs

          -  hypertension

          -  morbid obesity and

          -  recurrent endoscopic sinus surgeries
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rasha G Abusinna, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ain Shams University Hospitals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain Shams University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <state>EL Abassia</state>
        <zip>11591</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rasha Gamal Abusinna</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>lecturer of anesthesia and intensive care, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>propofol</keyword>
  <keyword>nitroglycerin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nitroglycerin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

