<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04228172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MJFF grant 16325</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04228172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genotypic Influences on Network Progression in Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genotypic Influences on Network Progression in Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwell Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Silverstein Foundation for Parkinson's with GBA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwell Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this longitudinal study, the investigators will follow Parkinson's disease (PD) patients
      with and without glucocerebrosidase (GBA) mutations. The investigators hypothesize that the
      rate of increase in brain network activity over time (network progression rate) is faster in
      patients with GBA gene mutations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) patients with mutations in the glucocerebrosidase gene (GBA) tend to
      have a more aggressive disease course. GBA may therefore provide a target for disease
      modifying therapies in mutation carriers. Using positron emission tomography (PET) and
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain imaging to measure network progression rates in
      mutation carriers will allow for the assessment of the potential disease modifying effects of
      new anti-GBA therapies.

      The investigators will also determine whether magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) network
      methods, which are less invasive and more broadly available than positron emission tomography
      (PET), produce comparable network progression measurements in individual patients. These
      determinations will be critical for the design of clinical trials of new disease-modifying
      drugs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 24, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in PD related metabolic pattern expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 18 months later</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in PD related and PD cognition related pattern expression in 18F-2-fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose (FDG) PET scans</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in PD related functional pattern expression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 18 months later</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in PD related and PD cognition related pattern expression in resting state functional magnetic resonance imaging (rs-fMRI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in motor function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 18 months later</time_frame>
    <description>Change in motor function assessed with Movement Disorder Society Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS) III (The sum score ranges between 0-132 points. Higher scores indicate more severe impairment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 18 months later</time_frame>
    <description>Change in cognitive function assessed with neuropsychological testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parkinson's disease subjects with GBA mutation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) non glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parkinson's disease subjects without GBA mutation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DNA/GeneticTesting</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be tested for GBA and LRRK2 mutation status at baseline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) non glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDG PET scan</intervention_name>
    <description>18F-Fluoro-2-deoxy-glucose (FDG) PET scan is a nuclear medicine test that measures glucose metabolism (energy) in your brain at baseline and 18 months later.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) non glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MRI scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) is a noninvasive scan which produces detailed pictures of the brain using a magnetic field. In addition, a special type of MRI, called resting state functional MRI (rs-fMRI), will measure and map brain activity. Conducted at baseline and 18 months later.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) non glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical and neuropsychological assessments</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigator will evaluate subjects according to the Movement Disorder Society-Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale (MDS-UPDRS), the standard clinical tool used to measure the severity and progression of PD. Neuropsychological evaluation will assess how one's brain functions (via pencil and paper testing), which indirectly yields information about the structural and functional integrity of the brain. Conducted at baseline and 18 months later.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's disease (PD) non glucocerebrosidase (GBA) carriers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Potential subjects may undergo DNA testing for GBA and LRRK2 PD mutations. A portion of each
      subjects sample will be collected and processed for storage for possible use in future
      studies. The samples will be banked in the Center for Genomics &amp; Human Genetics in The Boas
      Center Biorepository (BCB).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will be recruited through local movement disorders centers in the
        tri-state area, prior PD studies, The Michael J. Fox Trial Finder, community outreach
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of PD made according to United Kingdom (UK) Parkinson's Disease Society
             Brain Bank Criteria

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent

          -  Age 40-75

          -  Stable dose of antiparkinsonian medication for &gt;1 month prior to study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with pathogenic mutations in LRRK2

          -  History of known causative factors such as encephalitis or neuroleptic treatment

          -  Patients with dementia (defined as Mini-Mental Status Exam score &lt;24 or a Telephone
             Interview for Cognitive Status score &lt;26)

          -  Atypical parkinsonian features including oculomotor abnormalities,incontinence,
             ataxia, sensory loss, or pyramidal signs

          -  Known structural brain lesions

          -  Patients with history of stroke, head injury, high intracranial pressure or severe
             headaches

          -  Psychiatric disorder, including a history of major depression in the past 36 months

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women (female subjects of child-bearing potential will be
             screened for pregnancy before imaging).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Eidelberg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Head, Center for Neurosciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Loreta Quartarolo, BS</last_name>
    <phone>516-562-1168</phone>
    <email>lquartar@northwell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Toni Fitzpatrick, MA</last_name>
    <phone>516-562-2685</phone>
    <email>tfitzpatrick@northwell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Feinstein Institutes for Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manhasset</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Loreta Quartarolo, BS</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-1168</phone>
      <email>lquartar@northwell.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Toni Fitzpatrick, MA</last_name>
      <phone>516-562-2685</phone>
      <email>tfitzpatrick@northwell.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Eidelberg, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davis MY, Johnson CO, Leverenz JB, Weintraub D, Trojanowski JQ, Chen-Plotkin A, Van Deerlin VM, Quinn JF, Chung KA, Peterson-Hiller AL, Rosenthal LS, Dawson TM, Albert MS, Goldman JG, Stebbins GT, Bernard B, Wszolek ZK, Ross OA, Dickson DW, Eidelberg D, Mattis PJ, Niethammer M, Yearout D, Hu SC, Cholerton BA, Smith M, Mata IF, Montine TJ, Edwards KL, Zabetian CP. Association of GBA Mutations and the E326K Polymorphism With Motor and Cognitive Progression in Parkinson Disease. JAMA Neurol. 2016 Oct 1;73(10):1217-1224. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2016.2245.</citation>
    <PMID>27571329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cilia R, Tunesi S, Marotta G, Cereda E, Siri C, Tesei S, Zecchinelli AL, Canesi M, Mariani CB, Meucci N, Sacilotto G, Zini M, Barichella M, Magnani C, Duga S, Asselta R, Soldà G, Seresini A, Seia M, Pezzoli G, Goldwurm S. Survival and dementia in GBA-associated Parkinson's disease: The mutation matters. Ann Neurol. 2016 Nov;80(5):662-673. doi: 10.1002/ana.24777. Epub 2016 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27632223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sidransky E, Lopez G. The link between the GBA gene and parkinsonism. Lancet Neurol. 2012 Nov;11(11):986-98. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(12)70190-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23079555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schindlbeck KA, Eidelberg D. Network imaging biomarkers: insights and clinical applications in Parkinson's disease. Lancet Neurol. 2018 Jul;17(7):629-640. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(18)30169-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29914708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neumann J, Bras J, Deas E, O'Sullivan SS, Parkkinen L, Lachmann RH, Li A, Holton J, Guerreiro R, Paudel R, Segarane B, Singleton A, Lees A, Hardy J, Houlden H, Revesz T, Wood NW. Glucocerebrosidase mutations in clinical and pathologically proven Parkinson's disease. Brain. 2009 Jul;132(Pt 7):1783-94. doi: 10.1093/brain/awp044. Epub 2009 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19286695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winder-Rhodes SE, Evans JR, Ban M, Mason SL, Williams-Gray CH, Foltynie T, Duran R, Mencacci NE, Sawcer SJ, Barker RA. Glucocerebrosidase mutations influence the natural history of Parkinson's disease in a community-based incident cohort. Brain. 2013 Feb;136(Pt 2):392-9. doi: 10.1093/brain/aws318.</citation>
    <PMID>23413260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alcalay RN, Levy OA, Waters CC, Fahn S, Ford B, Kuo SH, Mazzoni P, Pauciulo MW, Nichols WC, Gan-Or Z, Rouleau GA, Chung WK, Wolf P, Oliva P, Keutzer J, Marder K, Zhang X. Glucocerebrosidase activity in Parkinson's disease with and without GBA mutations. Brain. 2015 Sep;138(Pt 9):2648-58. doi: 10.1093/brain/awv179. Epub 2015 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>26117366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzulli JR, Xu YH, Sun Y, Knight AL, McLean PJ, Caldwell GA, Sidransky E, Grabowski GA, Krainc D. Gaucher disease glucocerebrosidase and α-synuclein form a bidirectional pathogenic loop in synucleinopathies. Cell. 2011 Jul 8;146(1):37-52. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2011.06.001. Epub 2011 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>21700325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McNeill A, Magalhaes J, Shen C, Chau KY, Hughes D, Mehta A, Foltynie T, Cooper JM, Abramov AY, Gegg M, Schapira AH. Ambroxol improves lysosomal biochemistry in glucocerebrosidase mutation-linked Parkinson disease cells. Brain. 2014 May;137(Pt 5):1481-95. doi: 10.1093/brain/awu020. Epub 2014 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24574503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sardi SP, Clarke J, Viel C, Chan M, Tamsett TJ, Treleaven CM, Bu J, Sweet L, Passini MA, Dodge JC, Yu WH, Sidman RL, Cheng SH, Shihabuddin LS. Augmenting CNS glucocerebrosidase activity as a therapeutic strategy for parkinsonism and other Gaucher-related synucleinopathies. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013 Feb 26;110(9):3537-42. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1220464110. Epub 2013 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>23297226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feigin A, Kaplitt MG, Tang C, Lin T, Mattis P, Dhawan V, During MJ, Eidelberg D. Modulation of metabolic brain networks after subthalamic gene therapy for Parkinson's disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2007 Dec 4;104(49):19559-64. Epub 2007 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18042721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niethammer M, Eidelberg D. Metabolic brain networks in translational neurology: concepts and applications. Ann Neurol. 2012 Nov;72(5):635-47. doi: 10.1002/ana.23631. Epub 2012 Aug 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22941893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eidelberg D. Metabolic brain networks in neurodegenerative disorders: a functional imaging approach. Trends Neurosci. 2009 Oct;32(10):548-57. doi: 10.1016/j.tins.2009.06.003. Epub 2009 Sep 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19765835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vo A, Sako W, Fujita K, Peng S, Mattis PJ, Skidmore FM, Ma Y, Uluğ AM, Eidelberg D. Parkinson's disease-related network topographies characterized with resting state functional MRI. Hum Brain Mapp. 2017 Feb;38(2):617-630. doi: 10.1002/hbm.23260. Epub 2016 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27207613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schindlbeck, K.A. et al., Multicenter validation of disease-related Parkinson's disease pattern with resting state fMRI. 21st International Congress of Parkinson's Disease and Movement Disorders, June 8, 2018, Vancouver, Canada</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schindlbeck, K.A. et al., Cognition-related Parkinson's disease pattern with functional MRI - Validation and clinical correlates. 62nd Congress of the German Society for Clinical Neurophysiology and Functional Imaging (DGKN), Berlin, Germany, March 15, 2018</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang C, Tang C, Feigin A, Lesser M, Ma Y, Pourfar M, Dhawan V, Eidelberg D. Changes in network activity with the progression of Parkinson's disease. Brain. 2007 Jul;130(Pt 7):1834-46. Epub 2007 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>17470495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang CC, Poston KL, Dhawan V, Eidelberg D. Abnormalities in metabolic network activity precede the onset of motor symptoms in Parkinson's disease. J Neurosci. 2010 Jan 20;30(3):1049-56. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4188-09.2010.</citation>
    <PMID>20089913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niethammer M, Tang CC, LeWitt PA, Rezai AR, Leehey MA, Ojemann SG, Flaherty AW, Eskandar EN, Kostyk SK, Sarkar A, Siddiqui MS, Tatter SB, Schwalb JM, Poston KL, Henderson JM, Kurlan RM, Richard IH, Sapan CV, Eidelberg D, During MJ, Kaplitt MG, Feigin A. Long-term follow-up of a randomized AAV2-GAD gene therapy trial for Parkinson's disease. JCI Insight. 2017 Apr 6;2(7):e90133. doi: 10.1172/jci.insight.90133.</citation>
    <PMID>28405611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spetsieris PG, Ko JH, Tang CC, Nazem A, Sako W, Peng S, Ma Y, Dhawan V, Eidelberg D. Metabolic resting-state brain networks in health and disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2015 Feb 24;112(8):2563-8. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1411011112. Epub 2015 Feb 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25675473</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattis PJ, Tang CC, Ma Y, Dhawan V, Eidelberg D. Network correlates of the cognitive response to levodopa in Parkinson disease. Neurology. 2011 Aug 30;77(9):858-65. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e31822c6224. Epub 2011 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21849641</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang CC, Feigin A, Ma Y, Habeck C, Paulsen JS, Leenders KL, Teune LK, van Oostrom JC, Guttman M, Dhawan V, Eidelberg D. Metabolic network as a progression biomarker of premanifest Huntington's disease. J Clin Invest. 2013 Sep;123(9):4076-88. doi: 10.1172/JCI69411. Epub 2013 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23985564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 10, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 14, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwell Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Eidelberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor &amp; Head, Feinstein Center for Neurosciences, Feinstein Institutes for Medical Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GBA</keyword>
  <keyword>genetic</keyword>
  <keyword>progression</keyword>
  <keyword>PD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Progression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

