<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03212170</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-0533</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UW17034</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>A539300</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>SMPH\RADIOLOGY\RADIOLOGY</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>4UL1TR000427-10</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1UL1TR002373-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03212170</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FFNP-PET/MR Imaging of Progesterone Receptor Expression in Invasive Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>[18F]Fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) PET/MR Imaging of Progesterone Receptor Expression in Invasive Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this research is to test the accuracy of PET/MRI imaging with
      18F-fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) for measuring progesterone receptor (PR) expression
      in patients with invasive breast cancer. The hypothesis is that FFNP SUVmax from PET/MRI will
      correlate well against the semi-quantitative PR immunohistochemistry score.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Integrated whole-body magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)-positron emission tomography (PET)
      scanners have recently been introduced for clinical use. This technology combines the
      anatomic and perfusion data obtained with dynamic contrast enhanced (DCE) MRI with functional
      imaging data obtained from PET. For breast imaging, the combination of MRI and PET has
      important potential to improve diagnostic accuracy and provide molecular characterization of
      breast cancer. The overall purpose of this research is to test the accuracy of PET/MRI
      imaging with 18F-fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) for measuring progesterone receptor (PR)
      expression in patients with invasive breast cancer.

      This is a prospective, one-arm, observational study which will enroll patients with newly
      diagnosed breast cancer scheduled for diagnostic breast MRI for preoperative staging/extent
      of disease evaluation as part of standard of care. Participation in this research study
      includes a directed breast PET/MRI with the investigational radiopharmaceutical, FFNP. FFNP
      uptake of the known, biopsy-proven malignancy will be measured on the PET/MRI examinations
      using standardized uptake values (SUV) and tumor-to-normal tissue ratios.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Suspended due to COVID-19
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FFNP Uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>To compare FFNP uptake of biopsy-proven primary PR+ breast malignancies measured using PET/MRI with the reference standard of PR immunohistochemistry (IHC) using a semi-quantitative score obtained by using the Allred score (0-8; the higher the score, the more receptors were found). The correlation of the two measures will be evaluated with Pearson's correlation coefficient. The null hypothesis is H0: p0=0.50 and the alternative hypothesis is H1: p1 =0.75.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Test-Retest Reproducibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor uptake of FFNP and the ability to reproduce this measure, will be quantified in the 5 subjects who elect to undergo a second imaging session, using summary statistics of tumor FFNP uptake for each reading for PET/MRI. The analysis will be done separately for each reader.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra and Inter-Observer Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The variability of observer assessment of tumor FFNP uptake will be measured. The intra- and inter-reader agreement of SUV values for tumor FFNP uptake will be analyzed with Bland-Altman plots and 95% limits of agreement. Analyses will be conducted on a per-lesion basis, and repeat tumors within the same patient will be assumed to be independent.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of tumor FFNP uptake with Oncotype DX score</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Estimate the association of tumor FFNP uptake (continuous SUVmax) with research-based Oncotype DX scores (0-100). The risk score (0-100) is generated from expression levels of sixteen cancer related genes and five reference genes. Scores are further categorized as low-risk (0-17), intermediate-risk (18-30), and high-risk (31-100). Pearson's or Spearman's rank correlation will be used to evaluate the association between FFNP uptake and research-based Oncotype DX score. The correlation coefficient (rho) and 95% confidence interval will be reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distinguishing between PR Negative and PR Positive Breast Cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the optimal cut-point of FFNP uptake for distinguishing between PR-negative and PR-positive invasive breast cancer. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve analysis will be performed to determine the optimal cut-point for FFNP uptake to distinguish PR-positive from PR-negative invasive breast cancer, as defined by the clinical pathology report. The area under the curve for the ROCs and their respective two-sided 95% confidence intervals will be calculated using logistic regression. The optimal cut-off point will be determined by considering the FFNP uptake value with the maximum sensitivity and specificity. The analysis will be done separately for each reader</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Invasive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FFNP PET/MRI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>18F-Fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) administration for PET/MRI imaging to assess biopsy-proven primary PR+ breast malignancies.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[18F]Fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) PET/MR Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>18F-Fluorofuranylnorprogesterone (FFNP) PET/MR Imaging tracer</description>
    <arm_group_label>FFNP PET/MRI</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FFNP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women 18 years of age or older

          -  Diagnosis of biopsy-proven invasive breast cancer measuring at least 1.0 cm in
             diameter by any imaging modality

          -  Biopsy-proven PR-positive (N=23) or PR-negative (N=5) invasive breast cancer

          -  Undergoing diagnostic breast MRI ordered by the referring clinician for staging and
             extent of disease

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability or unwillingness to provide informed consent to the study

          -  Participants currently undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy/endocrine therapy or those
             who have received chemotherapy/endocrine therapy within 6 months prior to the MRI

          -  Participants who have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy/endocrine therapy, surgical
             intervention, or radiation for the current biopsy-proven malignancy

          -  Participants with breast expanders

          -  Participants who are or might be pregnant or lactating

          -  Participant girth exceeds the bore of the PET/MRI scanner

          -  Participants with a contraindication to gadolinium based contrast agents, including
             allergy or impaired renal function (per University of Wisconsin Health Guidelines)

          -  Participants with a history of allergic reaction attributable to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to FFNP

          -  Participants in liver failure as judged by the patient's physician

          -  Participants with standard contraindications to MRI, including claustrophobia and
             metallic implants incompatible with MRI

          -  Participants requiring intravenous (IV) conscious sedation for imaging are not
             eligible; participants requiring mild, oral anxiolytics for the clinical MRI will be
             allowed to participate as long as the following criteria are met:

               -  The subject has their own prescription for the medication

               -  The informed consent process is conducted prior to the self-administration of
                  this medication

               -  They come to the research visit with a driver

          -  Participants unable to lie prone for 30 minutes for imaging
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Only women are being targeted for this research as breast MRI is not utilized for male breast cancer patients which comprises only 1% of all breast cancer cases.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Fowler, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin, Madison</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Invasive Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastatic Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>PR Positive Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

