<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02067780</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COPD levofloxacine Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02067780</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short Antibiotic Treatment Versus Duration Guided by Markers of Inflammation in the Treatment of AECOPD</brief_title>
  <acronym>AECOPD</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Two Strategies of Antibiotic Treatment With Levofloxacin in Acute Exacerbation of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease: Short Treatment-versus Treatment Guided by Markers of Inflammation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Monastir</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Monastir</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is one of the most common diseases in the world.
      In a recent study, we showed that administration of levofloxacin is superior to placebo in
      the treatment of decompensation of COPD; it is accompanied by a substantial reduction in
      mortality and a significant reduction in the residence time in hospital.

      In Tunisia, few data are available on the epidemiology of COPD decompensation. The choice of
      antibiotic to be used in this situation is challenging to the clinician who must choose
      between traditional antibiotics (cyclins, aminopenicillins, cotrimoxazole...) and new
      antimicrobial agents. Recently, it has been emphasized the selection of patients for
      treatment according to the degree of systemic inflammation (C-Reactive Protein). Indeed,
      there would have a correlation between the tracheobronchial infection and elevated
      inflammatory markers. As the elevation of these markers is proportional to the intensity of
      the inflammatory reaction of the body, is based on the kinetics of these biomarkers in
      antibiotic treatment seems logical. Thus, C-Reactive Protein allowed not only knowing when to
      start antibiotics, but also through their kinetic, these markers can guide the duration of
      therapy and shorten the duration of antibiotic therapy: a rate cut would ensure that the
      antibiotic treatment was adopted. Available guidelines stated that antibiotic treatment
      should be maintained at an average of 7 to 10 days while some studies showed no clinical
      inferiority of courses as short as 3 days. Further reduction of the duration of
      antibiotherapy was even suggested in order to reduce the risk of adverse events and the
      pressure that drives bacterial resistance. Hence, we conducted this study using an algorithm
      to comprehensively evaluate the role of CRP-guided antibiotic prescription in optimizing
      treatment duration in AECOPD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, randomized, double blind controlled study including patients
      admitted to the emergency department (ED) with AECOPD. Patients were randomly assigned (1:1)
      to receive treatment either according to guidance based on serum CRP level (CRP-guided group)
      or the standard of care (control group). The randomisation sequence was generated using the
      sealed envelope sequence generator stratified according to investigator site. Online
      inclusion of patients according to the concealed sequence was done with an independent,
      centralised web-based system (DACIMA Tunisia; https://www.dacimasoftware.com).

      Patients were assigned to one of the two treatment arms:

        1. the intervention (CRP-guided) group: 500 mg (one tablet) of oral levofloxacin daily of
           levofloxacin for 7 days unless the serum CRP decrease by at least 50% from baseline
           value. Measurements of serum CRP were done at ED admission, at day-2, day-4 and day-6
           and made available to the attending physicians.

        2. the standard care (control) group: 500 mg of levofloxacin per day for the first two
           days. Thereafter, oral tablet of placebo was prescribed according to CRP values as in
           CRP guided group to keep the blindness of the study. Also, in order to ensure blinding,
           active drug as well as placebo tablets were encapsulated for identical appearance and
           placed in sealed envelopes.

      The study is approved by ethics committees of all participating centers prior to
      implementation, and all included patients provided their written informed consent. The study
      was. The study protocol has been prepared in accordance with the revised Helsinki Declaration
      for Biomedical Research Involving Human Subjects and Guidelines for Good Clinical Practice.

      After verification of inclusion and exclusion criteria as well the informed consent,
      demographic, clinical and biological data were collected at baseline. These included patient
      comorbidities, number of exacerbations in the past year, physical examination findings, blood
      gas analysis, and standard laboratory tests results. Expectorated sputum samples were
      collected for pathogen culture. All data were recorded in standardized electronic case report
      forms. All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS software, version 20.0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after starting protocol</time_frame>
    <description>By hospital Data and telephonic calling.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of additional antibiotherapy course</measure>
    <time_frame>During hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>The frequency of additional antibiotherapy course indicated to treat COPD patients during the hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>During hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in the hospital for those hospitalized immediately</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The intervention (CRP-guided) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 mg (one tablet) of oral levofloxacin daily of levofloxacin for 7 days unless the serum CRP decrease by at least 50% from baseline value. Measurements of serum CRP were done at ED admission, at day-2, day-4 and day-6 and made available to the attending physicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The standard care (control) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 mg of levofloxacin per day for the first two days. Thereafter, oral tablet of placebo was prescribed according to CRP values as in CRP guided group to keep the blindness of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Levofloxacin 500mg</intervention_name>
    <description>One tablet per day for 7days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>The intervention (CRP-guided) group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>The standard care (control) group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo Levofloxacin 500mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients having COPD (according to the definition of the American Thoracic Society) in
             acute exacerbation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pneumonia

          -  Antibiotic treatment in the previous days

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Immunodeficiency

          -  Concomitant infection

          -  intubation immediately
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Semir Nouira, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Research Laboratory (LR12SP18) University of Monastir 5000 Tunisia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Semir Nouira, Pr</last_name>
    <phone>73106000</phone>
    <email>semir.nouira@rns.tn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emergency department of university hospital Fattouma Bourguiba of Monastir</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monastir</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Tunisia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Semir Nouira, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+21698677343</phone>
      <email>semir.nouira@rns.tn</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tunisia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.urgencemonastir.com</url>
    <description>officiel site</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Monastir</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pr. Semir Nouira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Levofloxacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ofloxacin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

