<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04012190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1000063899</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04012190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SEPSIS Observational Cohort Study in Young Infants in Bangladesh</brief_title>
  <official_title>Severe Infections and the Intestinal Microbiome in Young Infants in Dhaka, Bangladesh: an Observational Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Child Health Research Foundation, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>McGill University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hospital for Sick Children</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Globally, infectious diseases such as sepsis, meningitis and pneumonia are among the leading
      causes of neonatal deaths. A recent observational study in South Asia highlighted the
      contribution of both bacterial and viral infections to the burden of illness in infants &lt;60
      days of age; however, there remains a need to quantify the risk of severe infection (SI)
      among newborns in a Bangladeshi population. In collaboration with researchers in Bangladesh,
      investigators aim to generate knowledge regarding the incidence and risk factors of SI,
      including the composition of the intestinal microbiome, in young infants (birth to 60 days of
      age) in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Data will support the design and implementation of future trials
      to test the efficacy of novel interventions for the prevention of SI in young infants, to
      promote optimal growth and development, and to determine effects on other health outcomes in
      early infancy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Globally, infectious diseases including sepsis, meningitis, and pneumonia are among the
      leading causes of neonatal deaths. In 2017, these three conditions were estimated to account
      for 540,000 newborn deaths worldwide, approximately 21% of all neonatal deaths globally.
      Previous studies have suggested that South Asia has a relatively high incidence of possible
      serious bacterial infection (pSBI) in young infants, particularly in areas where neonatal and
      under-five mortality rates are highest.

      A large body of evidence from inpatient neonatal populations, and the recent evidence from
      the Panigrahi et al. community trial in India, support an important role of intestinal
      dysbiosis in the pathogenesis of sepsis/SI in young infants. This mechanism may be
      particularly important in low- and middle-income countries in Africa and South Asia, where
      low-cost routine interventions to reduce the burden of SI (e.g., probiotics or synbiotics)
      could have an important impact on the burden of morbidity and mortality in young infants.
      However, there are limited data regarding the composition of the early postnatal microbiome
      in the general population of infants (rather than selected groups of preterm or hospitalized
      newborns) in South Asia and the role of the microbiome in modulating the risk of SI.

      This observational study will generate new knowledge about the incidence and risk factors of
      SI, including the composition of the intestinal microbiome, in young infants (birth to 60
      days of age) in Dhaka, Bangladesh. The aims of this study are to:

        1. Estimate the incidence of SI in a facility-recruited cohort of Bangladeshi newborns
           during the first 60 days of life, and examine the sensitivity of the estimates to
           variations in SI case definitions;

        2. Explore the associations between maternal-infant characteristics (e.g., mode of
           delivery, feeding practices, gestational age, antibiotic exposure) and the risk of SI in
           the first 60 days of life;

        3. Estimate the absolute and relative stool abundances and age at initial colonization of
           Bifidobacterium longum subspecies (ssp.) infantis (B. infantis), Bifidobacterium longum
           ssp. longum (B. longum longum), Bifidobacterium breve (B. breve) and all bifidobacteria
           species combined during the first 60 days of life in Bangladeshi newborns, overall and
           within sub-groups defined by: mode of delivery, feeding practices, prior or current
           infant exposure to antibiotics, and whether there is colonization with the specific
           bacterial species or subspecies;

        4. Explore the associations between maternal-infant characteristics (e.g., mode of
           delivery, feeding practices, gestational age, antibiotic use) and stool abundance (or
           age at initial colonization) of B. infantis, B. longum longum, and B. breve;

        5. Estimate the association between stool abundance of B. infantis and SI in Bangladeshi
           newborns during the first 60 days of life;

        6. Describe the composition, diversity, and stability of the microbiome in Bangladeshi
           newborns at multiple time-points during the first 60-days of life, and examine how the
           composition, diversity, and stability varies by mode of delivery and other
           maternal-infant and household characteristics;

        7. In a facility-recruited cohort of Bangladeshi newborns, estimate the incidence
           proportions and/or incidence rates and/or prevalence of the following clinical outcomes
           up to 7 days, 28 days, 60 days of life, 3 months, and 6 months of age:

             1. Hospitalization for any reason other than for routine postnatal care

             2. Upper respiratory tract infections (URTI);

             3. Lower respiratory tract infections (LRTI);

             4. Acute or persistent diarrhea;

             5. Infant cry/fuss (only up to 3 months of age);

             6. Significant neurological impairment or disability diagnosed by 6 months of age;
                and,

             7. All-cause and non-injury-related mortality

        8. Describe child anthropometry (length, weight, and head circumference) and standardized
           anthropometric indices (length-for-age, weight-for age, and weight-for-height, and head
           circumference-for-age z-scores) up to 60 days of age in a facility-recruited cohort of
           Bangladeshi newborns;

        9. Describe ages of attainment of developmental milestones up to 6 months of age in a
           facility-recruited cohort of Bangladeshi newborns;

       10. Estimate the cohort accrual rates of eligible newborns at two public maternal-child
           health care facilities in Dhaka, Bangladesh;

       11. Enumerate the health facilities within the study catchment area that provide maternal
           and child care services to pregnant women and newborns.

      Study personnel will conduct active and passive clinical surveillance and routine specimen
      collection (e.g. stool, nasal, skin and oral swabs etc.). Additional specimen collection may
      also be triggered in the event of physician-confirmed clinical severe infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 12, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of severe infection (SI) and/or non-injury death</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days of age</time_frame>
    <description>Severe infection is defined as at least one of the signs of clinical severe infection (CSI) as observed and documented by a physician (i.e., poor feeding, lethargy, convulsions, severe chest in-drawing, fever, or hypothermia) and/or admission to hospital with a physician diagnosis of sepsis or another serious bacterial infection; and at least one of the following two conditions: physician decision to admit to hospital, administration of at least one dose of a parenteral antibiotic on the day when CSI is first ascertained, and treatment and/or physician intention to treat with parenteral antibiotics for at least 5 days or blood and/or cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) culture positive for a pathogenic bacterial or fungal organism.
Non-injury death refers to death due to any cause except death that was directly caused by physical trauma (medically certified cause of death and/or verbal autopsy).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute abundance of Bifidobacterium infantis, Bifidobacterium longum longum and Bifidobacterium breve in stool</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days of age</time_frame>
    <description>Absolute abundance (AA) of specific bacteria in stool will be expressed as the log number of cells of a particular bacterial species or subspecies per gram (g) of stool, as detected by quantitative polymerase chair reaction (qPCR). If a direct cell count is unfeasible, AA will be expressed as log colony forming units of a particular bacterial species or subspecies per gram of stool.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative abundance of Bifidobacterium infantis, Bifidobacterium longum longum and Bifidobacterium breve in stool</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days of age</time_frame>
    <description>Relative abundance (RA) will be expressed as the number of gene copies from a particular genus/species/sub-species of interest proportional to the total number of 16S rRNA gene copies per gram (g) of stool. For total bifidobacteria, only RA will be expressed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant age at initial colonization with bacterial strains</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days of age</time_frame>
    <description>Age at initial colonization can only be defined at the level of the infant and will refer to each infant's first age (in days) at which colonization was detected or predicted to have occurred. This age may be derived empirically or using longitudinal modeling of infant-specific abundance trajectories. Colonization is a dichotomous variable that will be defined as an absolute abundance of a particular organism that exceeds a specified threshold. The term colonization refers here to the empirical detection of bacterial DNA at or above a particular level of abundance in stool, and will be used as a surrogate of intestinal colonization (in the absence of direct measurement of specific sites within the intestine).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Severe Infection and Non-injury Death</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Routine specimen collection:

        1. Infant: stool, nasal, skin, oral swabs, blood

        2. Maternal: stool, nasal, skin, oral and vaginal swabs, breast milk.

        3. Stool sample from a sibling closest in age to the participant (excluding
           twin/multiples).

        4. Household: dust

      Specimen collection triggered by presence of clinical severe infection (CSI): infant stool,
      nasal swab, blood, urine, skin swabs and cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) at treating physician's
      discretion.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy Bangladeshi newborns, delivered at two public hospitals (Maternal and Child Health
        Training Institute and Mohammadpur Fertility Services and Training Centre), and their
        mothers in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Newborns will be enrolled prenatally (n=75) or between 0 and
        4 days postnatal age (n=2,925).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Infant Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants up to and including 4 days of age

          -  Infants delivered at a study hospital

          -  Orally feeding currently

          -  Informed consent by parent or guardian

          -  Intends to maintain residence within the defined catchment areas (upon discharge from
             hospital) until 60 days of age

        Maternal Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Woman is admitted in early-labour, or for induction or C-section, to the labour and
             delivery ward at a study hospital

          -  Estimated gestational age greater than or equal to 32 weeks

          -  Mother and baby intend to maintain residence within the defined catchment areas (upon
             discharge from hospital) until 60 days of age

        Infant Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Birth weight &lt;1500g

          -  Death or major surgery considered to be highly probable within first week of life

          -  Major congenital anomaly of the gastrointestinal tract

          -  Maternal HIV infection and/or history of mother ever receiving anti-retroviral drug(s)
             for presumed HIV infection

          -  Current mechanical ventilation and/or cardiac support (e.g., inotropes) and/or
             administration/prescription of parenteral antibiotics

          -  Any prenatal use of non-dietary probiotic supplement by mother (during current
             pregnancy)

          -  Any postnatal administration of non-dietary probiotic or prebiotic supplements to
             infant

          -  Enrolment of infant in any other clinical trial involving the administration of
             probiotics and/or prebiotics

          -  Resides in the same household as another infant previously enrolled in the study, or
             any study within the research platform, who is currently &lt;60 days of age; however,
             twins/multiples may all be enrolled simultaneously.

        Maternal Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Attending physician has concern of fetal distress during labour plus at least one of
             the following: sustained fetal tachycardia or bradycardia, or meconium-stained
             amniotic fluid

          -  Documented intrauterine death (either clinical diagnosis or based on ultrasound)

          -  Any use of non-dietary probiotic supplement by woman during current pregnancy

          -  Woman has enrolled the newborn in another clinical trial involving the administration
             of probiotics and/or prebiotics

          -  Maternal HIV infection and/or history of mother ever receiving anti-retroviral drug(s)
             for presumed HIV infection

          -  Resides in the same household as another infant previously enrolled in the study, or
             any sub-study within the research platform, who is currently &lt;60 days of age; however,
             twins/multiples may all be enrolled simultaneously.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Roth, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maternal Child Health Training Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mohammadpur Fertility Services Training Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Roth</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Severe infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>Bangladesh</keyword>
  <keyword>Young infants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

