<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04019340</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>venous leg ulcer education</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04019340</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of a Pluridisciplinary Education Program on Venous Leg Ulcer Size Reduction</brief_title>
  <acronym>vened</acronym>
  <official_title>The Impact of a Pluridisciplinary Education Program on Venous Leg Ulcer Size Reduction: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>School of Health Sciences Geneva</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>School of Health Sciences Geneva</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background and rationale: Venous leg ulcers (VLU) are slow healing wounds with a recurrence
      rate of 70% and a 60% risk of becoming chronic. The estimated VLU prevalence in the general
      population is 3%. Current therapeutic approaches are multifaceted and focus on reducing wound
      size and improving wound healing as well as preventing ulcer recurrence. They require a
      pluridisciplinary team of health care professionals from the domains of nursing, medicine,
      physiotherapy and nutrition. Approximately 70% of VLU patients have a knowledge deficit in
      regards to therapeutic measures and have difficulties with adherence to treatment protocols.
      However, there are no published studies describing and evaluating the impact of
      pluridisciplinary educational interventions on adherence to the treatment plan and wound size
      reduction in VLU patients.

      Overall objectives: The objectives of the projected study are to evaluate the effectiveness
      of nurse-led intervention for high-risk patients with VLU in terms of patient
      knowledge/therapy adherence and to measure the impact of this intervention on wound size
      reduction and its evolution over time.

      Methodology of the planned study: An international multicenter randomized controlled trial
      with 248 participants in three Swiss French (n= 124) and two Australian (n=124) wound clinics
      is proposed. The sample size assumptions are based on a two-sided alpha level of 0.05, power
      of 0.8, and a medium effect size. Univariate and bivariate analysis will be conducted
      according to the data level and distribution.

      Expected results and impact: The findings of this study will generate new knowledge and the
      results will contribute to VLU clinical practice guidelines to enhance patient adherence to
      therapy. Our results will not only help improving patients' quality of life, but also
      contribute to reducing health expenditure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and rationale: Venous leg ulcers (VLU) are slow healing wounds with a recurrence
      rate of 70% and a 60% risk of becoming chronic. Signs and symptoms such as pain or exudate
      are not only a burden on those affected but also on the health care system and society in
      general. The estimated VLU prevalence in the general population is 3%. Treatment cost for VLU
      is estimated to be 3% of overall health expenditure. Current therapeutic approaches are
      multifaceted and focus on reducing wound size and improving wound healing as well as
      preventing ulcer recurrence. Such approaches include compression therapy, leg elevation,
      specific ankle-exercises and a protein rich diet. They require a pluridisciplinary team of
      health care professionals from the domains of nursing, medicine, physiotherapy and nutrition.
      Approximately 70% of VLU patients have a knowledge deficit in regards to therapeutic measures
      and have difficulties with adherence to treatment protocols. Therefore, it is of utmost
      importance that the treatment team provides effective patient education and support during
      the learning phase. However, there are no published studies describing and evaluating the
      impact of pluridisciplinary educational interventions on adherence to the treatment plan and
      wound size reduction in VLU patients.

      Overall objectives: The objectives of the projected study are to evaluate the effectiveness
      of nurse-led intervention for high-risk patients with VLU in terms of patient
      knowledge/therapy adherence and to measure the impact of this intervention on wound size
      reduction and its evolution over time.

      Specific aims: The effectiveness of the intervention will be defined in terms of changes in
      behavior (altered adherence to compression therapy, elevation therapy, physical activity
      therapy, ankle exercise therapy, and protein supplement therapy), and in terms of VLU basic
      awareness acquisition and wound status evaluation. In addition, occurrence of recurrence
      after healing and incidence of complications (re-hospitalizations) will be measured
      (frequency and cost).

      Methodology of the planned study: An international multicenter randomized controlled trial
      with 248 participants in three Swiss French (n= 124) and two Australian (n=124) wound clinics
      is proposed. The study participants will be consecutive patients of the participating clinics
      who fulfill the inclusion criteria. Wound care will be performed according to the hospital's
      standard clinical practice guidelines. Allocation to the intervention group (IG) or the
      control group (CG) will be concealed. The intervention will consist of VLU patient education
      care bundle giving patients an opportunity to learn about the use of compression bandages,
      wearing and putting on compression stockings, and will include the importance of physical
      activity, ankle exercises, leg elevation and a high-protein diet to healing outcomes. An
      educational brochure summarizing these aspects will be given to the patients of the IG. This
      group will be supervised by a study nurse, who will not be identical with the nurse in charge
      of the control group. Due to the intervention being an educational program, the study cannot
      be blinded either for the participants or the staff performing the intervention. The sample
      size assumptions are based on a two-sided alpha level of 0.05, power of 0.8, and a medium
      effect size. Univariate and bivariate analysis will be conducted according to the data level
      and distribution.

      Expected results and impact: The findings of this study will generate new knowledge and the
      results will contribute to VLU clinical practice guidelines to enhance patient adherence to
      therapy. Our results will not only help improving patients' quality of life, but also
      contribute to reducing health expenditure. Additionally, it is in alignment with the National
      Strategy on the Prevention of Non-Communicable Diseases 2017 - 2024 establishing prevention
      work for people with enhanced risks and chronic conditions reinforcing protective factors
      such as diet and exercise. This pluridisciplinary study (engaging experts in nursing,
      physiotherapy and nutrition) associates two research centers with high-level expertise in the
      field of wound care that both successfully conducted and published research results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wound size reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the impact of a pluridisciplinary educative program on the relative Reduction (in %) of wound size in patients with VLU. Wound size will be measured using WoundWorks® imaging device</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-care</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Self-care score will be evaluated using the validated self care questionnaire (VeLUSET©_FR),</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effective activity</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Effective activity will be measured using GeneActiv device</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>wound evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Wound will be evaluated in terms of exudative status, smell, infection status and pain felt. The TIME strategy (T = tissue removal; I = infection control; M = moisture balance; E = edge advancement) proposed by the European Wound Management Association will be applied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to lifestyle</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to lifestyle prescriptions, including physical activity, leg elevation, ankle exercises, wearing compression stockings, will be evaluated using a short health questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>general nutritional status</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>General nutritional status of patients will be measured using the MNA® questionnaire, a validated assessment tool that identifies people malnourished or at risk of malnutrition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>protein intake</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>Daily protein intake of participants in g/kg of body weight will be estimated using FFQ questionnaire, a validated tool developed to assess mean nutrient intakes in the population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">148</enrollment>
  <condition>Patient Empowerment</condition>
  <condition>Venous Leg Ulcer</condition>
  <condition>Interdisciplinary Communication</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care for patients in the CG is defined as visiting the outpatient wound clinic as prescribed by the physician. Wound size measurement, wound care (including dressing and inspection), and questionnaires will be provided by the institute's nurses.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care as described for the CG will also be provided to the IG (visit to the outpatient wound clinic as prescribed by the physician). Wound size measurement, wound care (including dressing and inspection), and questionnaires will be provided by the institute's nurses. After baseline data collection (T0) and random allocation to the intervention group, this usual care will be enhanced by a pluridisciplinary educational program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Usual care as described for the CG will also be provided to the IG. Wound size measurement, wound care, and questionnaires will be provided by the institute's nurses. Usual care will be enhanced by a pluridisciplinary educational program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older,

          -  an existing diagnosed open VLU,

          -  ulcer surface &gt;5 cm2 and &gt; 15 cm2,

          -  proficiency in the French language

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Valid informed consent is not or cannot be given
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sebastian E Probst, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Applied Sciences and Arts Western Switzerland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sebastian E Probst, Prof</last_name>
    <phone>022 3885600</phone>
    <phone_ext>5709</phone_ext>
    <email>sebastian.probst@hesge.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cité Génération Maison de santé</name>
      <address>
        <city>Onex</city>
        <state>GE</state>
        <zip>1213</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chantal Rosset, RN</last_name>
      <phone>022 709 00 00</phone>
      <email>chantal.rosset@hesge.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre hospitalier universitaire vaudois</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <state>VD</state>
        <zip>1005</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucie Charbonneau, RN</last_name>
      <phone>+41 21 314 11 11</phone>
      <email>Lucie.Charbonneau@chuv.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Geneva</name>
      <address>
        <city>Geneva</city>
        <zip>1206</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Martine Szewczyk, RN</last_name>
      <phone>+41 (0)22 372 33 11</phone>
      <email>Martine.Szewczyk@hcuge.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Probst S, Allet L, Depeyre J, Colin S, Buehrer Skinner M. A targeted interprofessional educational intervention to address therapeutic adherence of venous leg ulcer persons (TIEIVLU): study protocol for a randomized controlled trial. Trials. 2019 Apr 29;20(1):243. doi: 10.1186/s13063-019-3333-4.</citation>
    <PMID>31036037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>School of Health Sciences Geneva</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sebastian Probst</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor in tissue viability and wound care</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>patient education</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

