<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04019925</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19-061</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04019925</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing the Wear Rates of the ADM/MDM Hips Using 3D X-ray Analysis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing the Wear Rates of the ADM/MDM Dual Mobility Hips Manufactured by Stryker Orthopaedics Using 3D X-ray Analysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stryker Orthopaedics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A common complication post hip replacement is hip dislocation or hip instability which can
      lead to the hip implants being revised. A new generation of Dual Mobility hips was designed
      to minimize hip dislocation/hip instability and polyethylene wear thus increasing the
      longevity of the hip prosthesis and reducing the number of re-operations for a patient. In
      this study we will be assessing 2 dual mobility hips manufactured by Stryker Orthopaedics
      Inc. The ADM and the MDM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hip replacement is a procedure in which the hip joint is replaced by a prosthetic implant or
      prosthesis. Post op hip dislocation or hip instability is a common complication which can
      lead to the hip implants being revised. There are many types of hip prostheses manufactured
      with the aim of prolonging longevity of the prosthesis and minimizing postoperative
      complications. One of these is a new generation of dual mobility hip manufactured by Stryker
      Orthopaedics. The Anatomic Dual Mobility (ADM) and the Modular Dual Mobility (MDM) were
      designed to minimize hip dislocation/hip instability and polyethylene wear thus increasing
      the longevity of the hip prosthesis and reducing the number of re-operations for a patient.
      In this study we will be assessing the outcome of the ADM and MDM hip system.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the change in polyethylene wear of Dual Mobility hip implants using Stryker Orthopaedics ADM &amp; MDM prostheses</measure>
    <time_frame>before the patient's discharge home, 6 weeks postop, and the most recent x-ray taken up to 5 years postop.</time_frame>
    <description>This study will assess the change in linear and volumetric wear using 3D x-ray analysis. Measurements will be taken of x-rays obtained before the patient's discharge home, 6 weeks postop, and the most recent x-ray taken more than 3 years postop.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To review the number of postop hip dislocations/hip instabilities</measure>
    <time_frame>first 5 years post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Dislocations and the post op time for each occurrence per patient will be collected in tabular format. This in turn will be used to calculate percent of cases/subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthroplasty, Replacement, Hip</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADM/MDM hip prosthesis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Type of prosthesis participant received.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADM/MDM hip</intervention_name>
    <description>Dual Mobility Hip prosthesis manufactured by Stryker Orthopaedics: ADM/MDM</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADM/MDM hip prosthesis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dual Mobility Hip</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or non-pregnant female

          -  Skeletally mature

          -  18 to 75 years old

          -  Stryker Dual Mobility Hip prosthesis

          -  BMI between 20 and 35

          -  Follow-up x-rays between 3 years and 6 years postop

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dual Mobility Hip implant that is not the ADM or MDM

          -  BMI that is 19 or less

          -  BMI that is greater than 36

          -  Most recent x-rays less than 3 years postop
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amit Atrey, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Unity Health Toronto, St. Michael's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kerry Ann K. Griffith-Cunningham</last_name>
    <phone>416 864-6060</phone>
    <phone_ext>2273</phone_ext>
    <email>griffithk@smh.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unity Health Toronto, St. Michael's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5B 1W8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cihi.ca/sites/default/files/document/cjrr-annual-report-2018-en.pdf</url>
    <description>Canadian Joint Replacement Registry Annual Report. Hip &amp; Knee Replacements in Canada 2016-2017.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huo MH, Parvizi J, Bal BS, Mont MA. What's new in total hip arthroplasty. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009 Oct;91(10):2522-34. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.I.00801. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19797590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barrack RL. Dislocation after total hip arthroplasty: implant design and orientation. J Am Acad Orthop Surg. 2003 Mar-Apr;11(2):89-99. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12670135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khatod M, Barber T, Paxton E, Namba R, Fithian D. An analysis of the risk of hip dislocation with a contemporary total joint registry. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2006 Jun;447:19-23.</citation>
    <PMID>16741469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goel A, Lau EC, Ong KL, Berry DJ, Malkani AL. Dislocation rates following primary total hip arthroplasty have plateaued in the Medicare population. J Arthroplasty. 2015 May;30(5):743-6. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2014.11.012. Epub 2014 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25573179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hailer NP, Weiss RJ, Stark A, Kärrholm J. The risk of revision due to dislocation after total hip arthroplasty depends on surgical approach, femoral head size, sex, and primary diagnosis. An analysis of 78,098 operations in the Swedish Hip Arthroplasty Register. Acta Orthop. 2012 Oct;83(5):442-8. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2012.733919. Epub 2012 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>23039167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kostensalo I, Junnila M, Virolainen P, Remes V, Matilainen M, Vahlberg T, Pulkkinen P, Eskelinen A, Mäkelä KT. Effect of femoral head size on risk of revision for dislocation after total hip arthroplasty: a population-based analysis of 42,379 primary procedures from the Finnish Arthroplasty Register. Acta Orthop. 2013 Aug;84(4):342-7. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2013.810518. Epub 2013 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23799348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Philippot R, Camilleri JP, Boyer B, Adam P, Farizon F. The use of a dual-articulation acetabular cup system to prevent dislocation after primary total hip arthroplasty: analysis of 384 cases at a mean follow-up of 15 years. Int Orthop. 2009 Aug;33(4):927-32. doi: 10.1007/s00264-008-0589-9. Epub 2008 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18521598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Darrith B, Courtney PM, Della Valle CJ. Outcomes of dual mobility components in total hip arthroplasty: a systematic review of the literature. Bone Joint J. 2018 Jan;100-B(1):11-19. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.100B1.BJJ-2017-0462.R1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29305445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Martino I, D'Apolito R, Soranoglou VG, Poultsides LA, Sculco PK, Sculco TP. Dislocation following total hip arthroplasty using dual mobility acetabular components: a systematic review. Bone Joint J. 2017 Jan;99-B(ASuppl1):18-24. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.99B1.BJJ-2016-0398.R1. Review. Erratum in: Bone Joint J. 2017 May;99-B(5):702-704.</citation>
    <PMID>28042114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harwin SF, Sultan AA, Khlopas A, Chughtai M, Sodhi N, Piuzzi NS, Mont MA. Mid-Term Outcomes of Dual Mobility Acetabular Cups for Revision Total Hip Arthroplasty. J Arthroplasty. 2018 May;33(5):1494-1500. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2017.12.008. Epub 2017 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29307678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loving L, Lee RK, Herrera L, Essner AP, Nevelos JE. Wear performance evaluation of a contemporary dual mobility hip bearing using multiple hip simulator testing conditions. J Arthroplasty. 2013 Jun;28(6):1041-6. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2012.09.011. Epub 2013 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23434106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Apuzzo MR, Koch CN, Esposito CI, Elpers ME, Wright TM, Westrich GH. Assessment of Damage on a Dual Mobility Acetabular System. J Arthroplasty. 2016 Aug;31(8):1828-35. doi: 10.1016/j.arth.2016.01.039. Epub 2016 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26897488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

