<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04010539</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>116577</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04010539</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating Efficacy and Safety of Gepotidacin Compared With Ceftriaxone Plus Azithromycin in the Treatment of Uncomplicated Urogenital Gonorrhea</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Randomized, Multicenter, Open-Label Study in Adolescent and Adult Participants Comparing the Efficacy and Safety of Gepotidacin to Ceftriaxone Plus Azithromycin in the Treatment of Uncomplicated Urogenital Gonorrhea Caused by Neisseria Gonorrhoeae</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase III, randomized, multicenter, open-label study which will be performed to
      evaluate efficacy and safety of oral Gepotidacin compared to intramuscular (IM) ceftriaxone
      plus oral azithromycin for the treatment of uncomplicated urogenital infection caused by
      Neisseria gonorrhoeae in adolescent and adult subjects. In this study, subjects will be
      randomly assigned to receive either oral gepotidacin or IM ceftriaxone plus oral
      azithromycin. Approximately 600 subjects will be randomized to receive study treatment. The
      duration of the study will be approximately 21 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 22, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 28, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 28, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of Neisseria gonorrhoeae from the urogenital site at the Test-of-Cure (TOC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-treatment urogenital swab specimen will be obtained for bacteriological culture for N. gonorrhoea. Test-of-Cure is defined by urogenital site as culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of N. gonorrhoea observed 3 to 7 days post-treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of Neisseria gonorrhoeae from the rectal site at the TOC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-treatment rectal swab specimen will be obtained for bacteriological culture for N. gonorrhoea. Test-of-Cure is defined by rectal site as culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of N. gonorrhoea observed 3 to 7 days post-treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of Neisseria gonorrhoeae from the pharyngeal site at the TOC</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-treatment pharyngeal swab specimen will be obtained for bacteriological culture for N. gonorrhoea. Test-of-Cure is defined by pharyngeal site as culture-confirmed bacterial eradication of N. gonorrhoea observed 3 to 7 days post-treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with treatment-emergent adverse events and serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 21</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event (AE) is any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical study subject, temporally associated with the use of a study treatment, whether or not considered related to the study treatment. An SAE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence that, at any dose; results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in persistent disability or incapacity, is a congenital anomaly or birth defect, any other situation that require medical or scientific judgment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in neutrophil count, lymphocyte count, monocyte count, eosinophil count, basophil count and platelet count</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of neutrophil count, lymphocyte count, monocyte count, eosinophil count, basophil count and platelet count. All parameters have &quot;Giga cells per Liter&quot; as unit of measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in hemoglobin level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of hemoglobin level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in hematocrit level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of hematocrit level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in red blood cell (RBC) count</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of RBC count.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of MCH.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in mean corpuscular volume (MCV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of MCV.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in blood urea nitrogen, glucose non-fasting, calcium, chloride, sodium and potassium levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of blood urea nitrogen, glucose non-fasting, calcium, chloride, sodium and potassium levels. All parameters have &quot;Millimole per Liter&quot; as unit of measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in total bilirubin, direct bilirubin and creatinine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of total bilirubin, direct bilirubin and creatinine levels. All parameters have &quot;Micromoles per liter&quot; as unit of measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in albumin and total protein levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of albumin and total protein levels. All parameters have &quot;Gram per liter&quot; as unit of measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and alkaline phosphatase levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected for the assessment of AST, ALT and alkaline phosphatase levels. All parameters have &quot;International units per Liter&quot; as unit of measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with abnormal urinalysis Dipstick results</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be collected to assess pH, glucose, protein, blood and ketones by Dipstick method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in specific gravity of urine</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be collected for the measurement of specific gravity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in systolic blood pressure (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>SBP and DBP will be assessed in the semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in pulse rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Pulse measurements will be assessed in the semi-supine position after 5 minutes rest.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in body temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and up to Day 8</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in body temperature from Baseline will be assessed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Gonorrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gepotidacin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive Gepotidacin orally at the study site during the Baseline (Day 1) visit followed by self-administration of a second oral dose as an outpatient 6 to 12 hours after the first dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone plus Azithromycin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single IM dose of Ceftriaxone plus a single oral dose of Azithromycin at the study site during the Baseline (Day 1) visit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gepotidacin</intervention_name>
    <description>Gepotidacin will be administered as 3000 milligram (mg) oral dose (4 X 750 mg tablets) at the study site followed by 3000 mg oral dose (4 X 750 mg tablets) as an outpatient. Each dose should be taken after food consumption and with water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gepotidacin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceftriaxone</intervention_name>
    <description>Ceftriaxone is available as sterile powder for reconstitution. It will be administered as one 500-mg IM dose at the study site.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone plus Azithromycin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Azithromycin</intervention_name>
    <description>Azithromycin will be administered as 1000 mg oral dose (2 X 500 mg tablets) at the study site. Dose should be taken after food consumption and with water.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftriaxone plus Azithromycin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be &gt;=12 years of age at the time of signing the informed consent.

          -  Subjects having body weight of &gt;45 kilogram (kg).

          -  Subjects having clinical suspicion of a urogenital gonococcal infection with or
             without pharyngeal and/or rectal gonococcal infection and have one of the following: a
             prior positive culture for Neisseria gonorrhoeae from up to 5 days before screening
             (as long as the subject has not received any treatment for this infection) or a Gram
             stain (urogenital specimens only) positive or presumptive for Gram-negative
             intracellular diplococci from up to 5 days before screening (as long as the subject
             has not received any treatment for this infection) or a prior positive nucleic acid
             amplification test assay for Neisseria gonorrhoeae from up to 7 days before screening
             (as long as the subject has not received any treatment for this infection).

          -  Subjects who are willing to avoid anal, oral, and vaginal sexual intercourse or use
             condoms for all forms of intercourse from the Baseline Visit through the TOC Visit.

          -  Male or female subjects having his or her original urogenital anatomy at birth.

          -  Male subject must agree to use contraception (male condoms) during intercourse from
             the Baseline Visit through completion of the TOC Visit.

          -  Female subject is eligible to participate if she is not pregnant, not breastfeeding,
             and at least 1 of the following conditions applies: Not a woman of childbearing
             potential (WOCBP) or WOCBP who agrees to follow the contraceptive guidance (male
             partners of WOCBP must use a male condom during intercourse) from the Baseline Visit
             through completion of the TOC Visit.

          -  Subjects who are capable of giving signed informed consent or assent, which includes
             compliance with the requirements and restrictions listed in the informed consent form
             (ICF) or assent form and in study protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Male subjects with a current diagnosis of epididymitis and/or orchitis at the time of
             the Baseline Visit.

          -  Subject who is suspected or confirmed to have a Chlamydia trachomatis infection and
             per the investigator's judgement standard-of-care treatment for this infection cannot
             be safely postponed until the TOC Visit.

          -  Subject has a body mass index &gt;=40 kilogram per square meter (kg/m^2) or has a body
             mass index &gt;=35.0 kg/m^2 and is experiencing obesity-related health conditions such as
             high blood pressure or diabetes.

          -  Subject has a history of sensitivity to the study treatments, or components thereof,
             or a history of a drug (including erythromycin and any macrolide or ketolide drug) or
             other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or medical monitor,
             contraindicates his or her participation.

          -  Subject is immunocompromised or has altered immune defenses that may predispose the
             subject to a higher risk of treatment failure and/or complications. For example,
             subjects with diabetes, renal transplant recipients, subjects with clinically
             significant persistent granulocytopenia (absolute neutrophil count &lt;1000 per
             microliter [μL]) and subjects receiving immunosuppressive therapy, including
             corticosteroid therapy (&gt;40 mg per day prednisolone or equivalent for &gt;1 week, &gt;=20 mg
             per day prednisolone or equivalent for &gt;2 weeks, or prednisolone or equivalent &gt;=10 mg
             per day for &gt;6 weeks). Subjects with a known cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4) count
             of &lt;200 cells per cubic millimeter (cells/mm^3) should not be enrolled.

          -  Subject has a medical condition that requires medication that may be impacted by
             inhibition of acetylcholinesterase, such as, poorly controlled asthma or chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease at the Baseline Visit and, in the opinion of the
             investigator, not stable on current therapy, acute severe pain, uncontrolled with
             conventional medical management, active peptic ulcer disease, Parkinson disease,
             Myasthenia gravis, a history of seizure disorder requiring medications for control
             (this does not include a history of childhood febrile seizures) or subject has any
             surgical or medical condition (active or chronic) that may interfere with drug
             absorption, distribution, metabolism, or excretion of the study treatment (For
             example., ileostomy or malabsorption syndrome).

          -  Subject has known anuria, oliguria, or severe impairment of renal function (creatinine
             clearance &lt;30 milliliter per minute [mL/min] or clinically significant elevated serum
             creatinine as determined by the investigator).

          -  Subject in the judgment of the investigator, would not be able or willing to comply
             with the protocol or complete study follow-up.

          -  Subject has a serious underlying disease that could be imminently life threatening, or
             the subject is unlikely to survive for the duration of the study period.

          -  Subject has congenital long QT syndrome or known prolongation of corrected QT interval
             (QTc).

          -  Subject has uncompensated heart failure.

          -  Subject has severe left ventricular hypertrophy.

          -  Subject has a family history of QT prolongation or sudden death.

          -  Subject has a recent history of vasovagal syncope or episodes of symptomatic
             bradycardia or bradyarrhythmia within the last 12 months.

          -  With the exception of azithromycin study treatment, the subject is taking
             QT-prolonging drugs or drugs known to increase the risk of torsades de pointes (TdP)
             per the www.crediblemeds.org &quot;Known Risk of TdP&quot; category at the time of his or her
             Baseline Visit, which cannot be safely discontinued from the Baseline Visit to the TOC
             Visit; or the subject is taking a strong cytochrome P450 enzyme 3A4 (CYP3A4) inhibitor
             or a strong P-glycoprotein (P-gp) inhibitor.

          -  For any subject &gt;=12 to &lt;18 years, the subject has an abnormal electrocardiogram (ECG)
             reading.

          -  The subject has a QTc &gt;450 millisecond (msec) or a QTc &gt;480 msec for subjects with
             bundle-branch block.

          -  Subject has a documented or recent history of uncorrected hypokalemia within the past
             3 months.

          -  Subject has a known history of cholestatic jaundice or hepatic dysfunction associated
             with prior use of azithromycin.

          -  Subject has a known alanine aminotransferase (ALT) value &gt;2 times upper limit of
             normal (ULN).

          -  Subject has a known bilirubin value &gt;1.5 times ULN (isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 times ULN
             is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin &lt;35%).

          -  Subject has a current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary
             abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones),
             including symptomatic viral hepatitis or moderate-to-severe liver insufficiency (Child
             Pugh class B or C).

          -  Subject has been previously enrolled in this study or has previously been treated with
             Gepotidacin.

          -  Subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within 30 days or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer.

          -  Subject has any of the following gonococcal infections that require a different dose
             or duration of treatment: suspected or confirmed pelvic inflammatory disease or
             suspected or confirmed gonococcal arthritis or suspected or confirmed gonococcal
             conjunctivitis or suspected or confirmed gonococcal endocarditis or other evidence of
             disseminated gonococcal infection.

          -  Subject has received any antibacterial therapy for the treatment of a gonococcal
             infection within 14 days before the Baseline Visit.

          -  Subject has received any systemic, topical, or intravaginal antibiotics or any
             systemic antifungals within 7 days before the Baseline Visit.

          -  Subject must not use St John's wort or ergot derivatives from within 14 days before
             the Baseline Visit through the TOC Visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0) 20 89904466</phone>
    <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90036</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter J Ruane</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>DeLand</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32720</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Godson Oguchi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32803</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Federico Hinestrosa</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Decatur</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anson K Wurapa</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Teresa Batteiger</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Springfield</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Claudia Martorell</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fayetteville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Connette McMahon</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann Avery</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gordon Crofoot</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Longview</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anita Scribner</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darlinghurst, Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Baker</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darlinghurst</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Bloch</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Darlinghurst</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2010</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Finlayson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carlton</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3053</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcus Chen</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prahran</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3181</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Norman Roth</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>10243</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christiane Cordes</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS2 8NG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>US GSK Clinical Trials Call Center</last_name>
      <phone>877-379-3718</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>EU GSK Clinical Trials Call Centre</last_name>
      <phone>+44 (0) 20 8990 4466</phone>
      <email>GSKClinicalSupportHD@gsk.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janet Wilson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Urogenital Gonorrhea, Gepotidacin, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Efficacy, Phase 3</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gonorrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Azithromycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ceftriaxone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD for this study will be made available via the Clinical Study Data Request site.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>IPD will be made available within 6 months of publishing the results of the primary endpoints of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access is provided after a research proposal is submitted and has received approval from the Independent Review Panel and after a Data Sharing Agreement is in place. Access is provided for an initial period of 12 months but an extension can be granted, when justified, for up to another 12 months.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>http://clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

