<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04013165</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VILLD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04013165</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Village-based Intervention for Late-life Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Village-based Intervention for Depression in Community-dwelling Older Adults: a Randomized Controlled Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Seoul National University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Seoul National University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigators aimed to examine the feasibility and effectiveness of a village-based
      multilevel intervention for late-life depression. Two small rural villages in rural South
      Korea were selected as the intervention group and active control. All older adults living in
      the two villages were included in the intervention program or received standard CMHS care,
      and the effectiveness of the program was examined using representative samples from both
      groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: To examine the feasibility and effectiveness of a village-based multilevel
      intervention for late-life depression, focusing on strengthening the autonomy of
      village-dwellers with help from the community mental health service (CMHS).

      DESIGN: A community-based randomized trial with participants (all village-dwellers) assigned
      to two parallel programs: intervention program or the CMHS's usual care.

      SETTING: Two small villages in a rural area of South Korea

      PARTICIPANTS: All older adults (aged ≥65 years) living in the two villages were included in
      the intervention or the CMHS's usual care, and the effectiveness of the program was examined
      using representative samples who were age- and sex-stratified randomly selected from both
      groups.

      INTERVENTION: A 12-week intervention was comprised of individual-based risk-stratified case
      management and group-based activities.

      MEASUREMENTS: The Korean version of Geriatric Depression Scale-Short form (SGDS-K) was used
      as the primary outcome while depressive episodes, suicidal ideation/plans/attempts, social
      network, functional status, and global cognitive function were measured as secondary
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A community-based randomized controlled pilot study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline Korean version of the short form of Geriatric Depression Scale (SGDS-K) after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The SGDS-K was developed for evaluating depressive symptoms of older adults; higher score means to have more depressive symptoms (lowest 0 - highest 15)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidental depressive episode after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Major or minor depressive episode was diagnosed based on the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, the fourth edition (DSM-IV) using a structured clinical interview, the Korean Version of the Composite International Diagnostic Interview (K-CIDI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidental suicidal ideation, plans, or attempts after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Multisite Intervention Study on Suicidal Behaviours (SUPRE-MISS) was used to assess of having suicidal ideation, plans, or attempts.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline Korean version of Lubben Social Network Scale (K-LSNS) after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>The Lubben Social Network Scale (LSNS) was developed for evaluating older adults' social interaction with their relatives and friends; higher score means to have stronger social network (lowest 0 - highest 50).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline Seoul-Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (S-IADL) after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Seoul-Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (S-IADL) was developed to assess elderly person's instrumental everyday activities; higher score means to have worse daily function (lowest 0 - highest 45).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline Korean version of the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE-KC) after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, after intervention (up to 24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Mini-Mental State Examination in the Korean version of the CERAD assessment packet (MMSE-KC) is a well-known screening tool for global cognitive function that measures orientation, language (repetition, naming, reading and writing), concentration, constructional praxis, and memory; higher score means to have better global cognitive function (lowest 0 - highest 30).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care of the Community Mental Health Service</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Village-based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individual-based case management + group-based program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Active control</intervention_name>
    <description>Control group received usual care of the Community Mental Health Service, consisted of case management for high-risk older adults and referral to psychiatric services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Village-based intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Individual-based case management was conducted both by healthy community dwellers (local committee) and Community Mental Health Service (CMHS) team based on risk-stratification for depression in older adults. Local committee-guided care was performed after matching a healthy dweller with 4-5 older neighbors included in risk groups. They visited the matched older individuals as often as possible at least once a week using a mood sticker. The CMHS team also conducted a separate case management for older adults with risk-stratified protocols; the higher the risk of suicide, the more intensive was the management, which could include frequent face-to-face visits. High-risk individuals were also referred to the psychiatric service, if deemed necessary.
Group-based program was comprised of weekly eight sessions, which were mainly consisted of programs enhancing interpersonal network and group cohesion, and were open to all community-dwelling older adults.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Village-based intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All community-dwelling older adults, aged 65 years and over

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who had significant sensory deficits or medical illnesses that would
             substantially restrict the delivery of the assessment were excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>110-744</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Old-aged</keyword>
  <keyword>Community-based intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Late-life depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Suicide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

