<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04014829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EPOCH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04014829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Central Sensitization, Fear-Avoidance, and Pain-Pressure Threshold With Chronic Pain After Hysterectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>EPOCH</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Central Sensitization, Fear-Avoidance, and Pain-Pressure Threshold With Chronic Pain in Post-Hysterectomy Patients: A Collaborative Cohort Study (EPOCH - Enhancing Post-operative Outcomes in Chronic Pain After Hysterectomy)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Central Sensitization Inventory (CSI), Fear-Avoidance Components Scale (FACS), pain-pressure
      threshold are factors associated with chronic post-hysterectomy pain (CPHP), but a complete
      understanding on the development of CPHP is lacking. The study aims to identify
      clinically-relevant factors for CPHP that can be reliably assessed preoperatively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic post-surgical pain is persistent pain after a surgical procedure that lasts for at
      least 3 months with other causes of pain excluded. It is a major socioeconomic and healthcare
      burden, and has impact on quality of life, physical function, emotional wellbeing and
      healthcare costs. In Singapore, hysterectomy for benign indications incurs 32% risk of
      developing chronic post-hysterectomy pain (CPHP). CPHP can occur around the surgical site,
      lower abdominal or pelvic region. Based on the pathophysiology underlying chronic pain, the
      investigators hypothesize that central sensitization, pain fear-avoidance and low
      pain-pressure threshold are plausible risk factors for CPHP. However, none of these three
      risk categories has been evaluated in patients with CPHP.

      The investigators hypothesize that preoperatively abnormal central sensitization, pain
      fear-avoidance and decreased pain-pressure threshold are associated with increased risk of
      developing CPHP. The investigators will evaluate these risk factors preoperatively, and
      follow-up study participants at 4- and 6-months after hysterectomy, to assess the
      associations between these risk factors and CPHP.

      The investigators will perform a prospective study of 236 patients undergoing
      abdominal/laparoscopic hysterectomy for benign indications, recruited at KK Hospital,
      Singapore. Central Sensitization Inventory (CSI), Fear-Avoidance Components Scale (FACS),
      pain-pressure threshold and other known factors associated with CPHP will be assessed and
      recorded. Participants will be followed up at 4- and 6-months postoperatively to assess CPHP.
      Logistical regression analysis will be used to evaluate the associations between these
      factors and CPHP.

      Knowledge of risk factors for CPHP will guide future studies to identify high-risk patients
      for implementation of individualized targeted therapies to optimize surgical outcomes of this
      patient group, and to confirm the hypothetical pathophysiological processes of chronic
      post-surgical pain similarly applicable to CPHP.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain at 4 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months after hysterectomy</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the development of chronic post-hysterectomy pain, which is defined as pain that lasts for at least 3 months around the surgical site, lower abdominal, or pelvic region. This will be determined by phone or online assessment at 4 months after surgery, based on the protocol used by Brandsborg et al and the investigators' previous study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Central Sensitization Inventory (CSI)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via the validated Central Sensitization Inventory (CSI) questionnaire prior to hysterectomy. Central sensitization is defined as an increased responsiveness of nociceptive neurons in the central nervous system to normal or sub-threshold afferent stimuli. The CSI a 25-item questionnaire, with each item rated 0 to 4. A higher value indicates greater central sensitization, and a threshold score of 40 was shown to be associated with increased risk of chronic pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fear Avoidance Components Scale (FACS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via the validated Fear Avoidance Components Scale (FACS) questionnaire prior to hysterectomy. Fear-avoidance is defined as the negative emotional perception of pain as terrorizing, which can generate catastrophic thoughts and vigilance. Pain fear-avoidance behavior can be assessed with the FACS, a 20-item questionnaire, with each item rated 0 to 5.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via the validated Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) questionnaire prior to hysterectomy. Anxiety and depression are known risk factors associated with CPHP. HADS is a combination test for both anxiety and depression, is a 14-item questionnaire, with each item rated 0 to 3. HADS &gt; 8 has been associated specifically with increased CPHP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via the validated Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS) questionnaire prior to hysterectomy. Pain catastrophizing refers to the negative thought processes patients have when they are exposed to pain or painful experiences. The PCS is a 13-item scale, with each item rated on a 5-point scale: 0 (Not at all) to 4 (all the time). It is broken into three subscales being magnification (0-12), rumination (0-16), and helplessness (0-24). A higher value in each subscale indicates a higher tendency to that subscale (worse outcome).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life via EQ-5D</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via the validated EQ-5D questionnaire prior to hysterectomy. Lower preoperative quality of life has been associated with CPHP. EQ-5D is a validated questionnaire to assess generic health-related quality of life, consisting of two components: health state description and evaluation.
The description component measures health status via five dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort, and anxiety/depression, with each dimension rated according to severity using a three-level scale.
The evaluation component assesses overall health status using the visual analogue scale (EQ-VAS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical Temporal Summation (MTS)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment via Mechanical Temporal Summation before hysterectomy. A 180 gram von Frey filament is applied on the subject's forearm. Patient will then be asked to rate the pinprick pain score on a verbal rating scale, 0-100. Following this, 10 consecutive touches at random locations are applied with a 1 second interstimulus interval and within a 1 cm diameter circle. The patient will then be asked to rate the 10th pain score (0-100). The Mechanical Temporal Summation Score is obtained by the difference between the 11th pain score and the 1st pain score. If the score is greater than zero, the patient is implied to have presence of Mechanical Temporal Summation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain-Pressure Threshold (PPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months (upon recruitment until before surgery)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Pain-pressure threshold (PPT) prior to hysterectomy. PPT is measured via an algometer in both groups. Pressure is applied 90 degree straight down force on the subject's right/left centre of the trapezius muscle using an algometer, with a speed of pressure ~ 1kgf/s. The above procedure is then repeated 3 times at each site (left/right) which is indicated on the pressure mark with each time having the reading recorded. When patient shows no response ≥ 6kgf, the threshold is recorded as 6kgf. The patient upon feeling pain will say stop or raise the hand to terminate the test. The mean value is obtained by averaging the readings and will then be recorded as the threshold estimate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after hysterectomy</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure is the development of chronic post-hysterectomy pain, which is defined as pain that lasts for at least 3 months around the surgical site, lower abdominal, or pelvic region. This will be determined by phone or online assessment at 6 months after surgery, based on the protocol used by Brandsborg et al and the investigators' previous study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">236</enrollment>
  <condition>Hysterectomy</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Central Sensitisation</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Preoperative assessment with questionnaires, Mechanical Temporal Summation, and Pain-Pressure Threshold. All patients will undergo elective abdominal or laparoscopic hysterectomy. Patients will be assigned to this group if no significant pain is noted during the follow up evaluations at 4 and 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Preoperative assessment with questionnaires, Mechanical Temporal Summation, and Pain-Pressure Threshold. All patients will undergo elective abdominal or laparoscopic hysterectomy. Patients will be assigned to this group if significant pain is noted during the follow up evaluations at 4 and 6 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain-Pressure Threshold</intervention_name>
    <description>Performed on bilateral trapezius muscles. Pressure will be applied at 90 degrees downward with an algometer, with the speed of pressure increase approximately 1kgf/s. Upon the sensation of pain, the patient will vocalize or raise her hand to terminate the test, and the highest reading will be recorded (up to maximum 6kgf). If two values are recorded within 0.2kgf of each other, the mean value will be recorded. If two values are greater than 0.2kgf of each other, a third test will be performed and the mean obtained.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PPT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mechanical Temporal Summation</intervention_name>
    <description>Pinprick hyperalgesia will be evoked using a Von Frey filament, applied to the volar aspect of the dominant forearm. Participants will report using the numerical rating scale the intensity of pain from the first stimulus. Subsequently, ten repetitive stimuli one second apart will be applied with the same filament within an area of 1cm diameter of the same forearm. Subjects will report the rate the pain intensity of the tenth stimulus. The magnitude of MTS is calculated as the difference between the last to the first pain scores. The investigators will classify the participants according to &quot;evoked MTS&quot; if the last stimulus is rated higher than the first, or &quot;no MTS&quot; if the last stimulus is rated equal or lower than the first. The research team administering the test will follow a set script.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MTS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized questionnaire to determine the level of anxiety and depression.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HADS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain Catastrophizing Scale</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized questionnaire to determine the level of pain catastrophizing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PCS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Central Sensitization Inventory</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized questionnaire to determine the level of central sensitization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CSI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fear-Avoidance Component Score</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized questionnaire to determine the level of fear and avoidance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FACS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EQ-5D</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized questionnaire to assess generic health-related quality of life.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Post-Hysterectomy Pain (CPHP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women scheduled for elective abdominal or laparoscopic hysterectomy at KK Women's and
        Children's Hospital, Singapore.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 21 to 80 years old

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists Physical Scale (ASA) I to III

          -  Benign gynaecological indications for hysterectomy

          -  Elective abdominal or laparoscopic hysterectomy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Vaginal hysterectomy

          -  Uterine prolapse, endometriosis, malignant disease, or pelvic pain as main indication
             for surgery

          -  History of drug dependence or recreational drug use

          -  History of chronic pain syndrome

          -  Current chronic daily treatment with corticosteroids, excluding inhaled steroids

          -  Allergy to study drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Hysterectomy is a surgical procedure that is performed only on women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Farida Ithnin, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ban Leong Sng, MBBS</last_name>
    <phone>+65 6394 1077</phone>
    <email>sng.ban.leong@singhealth.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hon Sen Tan, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+65 9365 7193</phone>
    <email>honsen.tan@mohh.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapman CR, Vierck CJ. The Transition of Acute Postoperative Pain to Chronic Pain: An Integrative Overview of Research on Mechanisms. J Pain. 2017 Apr;18(4):359.e1-359.e38. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2016.11.004. Epub 2016 Nov 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27908839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Han C, Ge Z, Jiang W, Zhao H, Ma T. Incidence and risk factors of chronic pain following hysterectomy among Southern Jiangsu Chinese Women. BMC Anesthesiol. 2017 Aug 11;17(1):103. doi: 10.1186/s12871-017-0394-3.</citation>
    <PMID>28800726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinto PR, McIntyre T, Nogueira-Silva C, Almeida A, Araújo-Soares V. Risk factors for persistent postsurgical pain in women undergoing hysterectomy due to benign causes: a prospective predictive study. J Pain. 2012 Nov;13(11):1045-57. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2012.07.014. Epub 2012 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23063345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sng BL, Ching YY, Han NR, Ithnin FB, Sultana R, Assam PN, Sia ATH. Incidence and association factors for the development of chronic post-hysterectomy pain at 4- and 6-month follow-up: a prospective cohort study. J Pain Res. 2018 Mar 27;11:629-636. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S149102. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29628772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fingleton C, Smart K, Moloney N, Fullen BM, Doody C. Pain sensitization in people with knee osteoarthritis: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Osteoarthritis Cartilage. 2015 Jul;23(7):1043-56. doi: 10.1016/j.joca.2015.02.163. Epub 2015 Mar 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25749012</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neblett R, Cohen H, Choi Y, Hartzell MM, Williams M, Mayer TG, Gatchel RJ. The Central Sensitization Inventory (CSI): establishing clinically significant values for identifying central sensitivity syndromes in an outpatient chronic pain sample. J Pain. 2013 May;14(5):438-45. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2012.11.012. Epub 2013 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23490634</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neblett R, Mayer TG, Hartzell MM, Williams MJ, Gatchel RJ. The Fear-avoidance Components Scale (FACS): Development and Psychometric Evaluation of a New Measure of Pain-related Fear Avoidance. Pain Pract. 2016 Apr;16(4):435-50. doi: 10.1111/papr.12333. Epub 2015 Jul 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26228238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brandsborg B, Dueholm M, Kehlet H, Jensen TS, Nikolajsen L. Mechanosensitivity before and after hysterectomy: a prospective study on the prediction of acute and chronic postoperative pain. Br J Anaesth. 2011 Dec;107(6):940-7. doi: 10.1093/bja/aer264. Epub 2011 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21890662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 29, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hysterectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Fear-Avoidance</keyword>
  <keyword>Central Sensitization</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain-Pressure Threshold</keyword>
  <keyword>Mechanical Temporal Summation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 29, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/29/NCT04014829/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

