<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04014673</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P071229</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04014673</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History Characterization in Symptomatic and Asymptomatic Progranuline Gene Mutation Carriers</brief_title>
  <acronym>Predict-PGRN</acronym>
  <official_title>Natural History Characterization in Symptomatic and Asymptomatic Progranuline Gene Mutation Carriers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate whether cognitive deficits, structural and
      functional changes can be detected before symptom onset in presymptomatic progranuline
      mutation carriers. The main objectives of the project are to identify novel cognitive, brain
      imaging markers and peripheral biomarkers for early diagnosis of FTLD, and to follow disease
      progression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The project focuses on the progranulin (PGRN) gene mutation, one of the most frequent genetic
      forms of frontotemporal dementias (FTD, or frontotemporal lobar degeneration, FTLD). FTD is
      the second commonest cause of degenerative dementia in presenium after Alzheimer's disease.
      Behavioral and cognitive impairments progressively lead to dementia. Two major pathological
      subtypes are now defined in FTD, FTD-TDP and FTD-TAU.

      FTD is difficult to detect at an early stage, and no clinical, biological or imaging features
      can predict the underlying pathology in living patients. Therapeutic perspectives have
      emerged against tau aggregation, PGRN deficit and C9orf72 expansion. Presymptomatic carriers
      of genetic FTD would benefit, before onset of symptoms, from these therapeutics that would
      delay or prevent the disease. At this step, it becomes crucial to develop markers to know how
      many years before symptoms, the pathological process begins, to treat the patients at the
      earliest stage of the disease. Markers are also needed to predict the pathology
      (FTD-TDP/FTD-tau) in patients that will be eligible for trials targeting specific
      pathological lesion. The main objectives of the project are to identify novel cognitive,
      brain imaging markers and peripheral biomarkers for early diagnosis of FTLD, and to follow
      disease progression. Ninety participants including 8 patients and 82 'at-risk' individuals
      will be recruited and evaluated by clinical partners of the project (Paris, Lille, Rouen,
      Toulouse, Saint-Etienne, Marseille, Nantes). 'At-risk individuals' are the first- degree
      relatives of PGRN patients, who have a high a risk (50%) to carry the mutation.

      Brain structural changes will be evaluated by voxel-based morphometry (SPM12 software) to
      assess global brain atrophy in one with the evaluation of atypical shape patterns such as
      cortical thickness (Freesurfer software) and the study of the cortical sulci
      (BrainVISA/Morphologist software).

      Fluoro Deoxy DGlucose-Positron Emission Tomography (FDG-PET) will allow the identification of
      brain metabolic markers. Then voxel-based methods using Statistical Parametric Mapping
      software will be applied to compare different groups or analyze correlations between brain
      metabolism and cognitive deficits.

      The identification of peripheral biomarkers of disease onset and disease progression will
      take advantage from RNA sequencing, in order to study gene expression and RNA splicing
      alterations in lymphocytes of patients and 'at risk individuals'.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 19, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Frontal Assessment Battery score (/18)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Executive functions changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Trail Making Test B-A time (seconds)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive flexibility changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Ekman's faces test score (/35)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Emotional assessment changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Faux-pas test score (/35)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Social cognition changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Digit span score</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Short-term memory changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Free and Cued Selective Reminding test, total recall score (/48)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Long-term memory changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Boston Naming test score (/34)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Language changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Gestural Praxis battery score (/168)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months, at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Gestural praxis changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological test)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Neuropsychiatric Inventory score (/144)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Behavioral changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological questionnaire)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of change of Apathy Evaluation Scale score (/42)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Apathy changes over time (rate of change in neuropsychological questionnaire)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in MRI morphological criteria (brain atrophy by voxel-based morphometry)</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cerebral metabolism by PET (metabolic markers by Fluoro-DeoxyDGlucose-Positron Emission Tomography (FDG-PET))</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlations between cognitive and behavioral scores, MRI morphological criteria, cerebral metabolism by FDG-PET and transcriptome analysis in presymptomatic subjects and in symptomatic patients at early disease stage</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Voxel-based methods using Statistical Parametric Mapping software will be applied to compare different groups or analyze correlations between brain atrophy/metabolism and cognitive deficits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in transcriptome analysis between symptomatic patients, asymptomatic carriers and controls.</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline 0 Months,at 42 Months,at 72 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Study gene expression and RNA splicing alterations in lymphocytes (RNA sequencing)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with a PGRN gene mutation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Symptomatic patients with a PGRN gene mutation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Presymptomatic individuals</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Asymptomatic 'At-risk' individuals with a PGRN gene mutation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>'At-risk' individuals without a PGRN gene mutation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral : Characterization</intervention_name>
    <description>Behavioral scales and neuropsychological tests; MRI, SPECT/PET</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with a PGRN gene mutation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Presymptomatic individuals</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>healthy volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for symptomatic patients:

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  Signed informed consent for genetic and clinical study

          -  To be carrier of a PGRN mutation - Diagnosis criteria of FTD

          -  To be affiliated to the social security scheme

        Inclusion criteria for 'at-risk' asymptomatic relatives:

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  To be first degree relative of a person carrying a PGRN mutation or first degree
             relative of FTD deceased patient whose PGRN mutation as been identified in the family

          -  Signed informed consent for genetic and clinical study

          -  To be affiliated to the social security scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria for symptomatic patients:

          -  Presence of one exclusion criteria from Diagnosis criteria of FTD. - Participation to
             another therapeutic trial. - Contra-indication to perform a brain MRI and/or PET-FDG

          -  Inability to lie one hour without moving

          -  Breastfeeding and pregnant women

          -  Presence of another intercurrent neurological pathology (vascular cerebral accident,
             tumor, etc.....)

        Exclusion criteria for 'at-risk' asymptomatic relatives :

          -  Presence of neurological or neurodegenerative disease

          -  Clinical proven signs of FTD, language disorder, praxis disorder, mnemic, of
             parkinson's syndrome or amyotrophic lateral sclerosis

          -  Contra-indication to perform a brain MRI and/or PET-FDG

          -  Inability to lie one hour without moving

          -  Breastfeeding and pregnant women

          -  Severe vascular lesion , tumor or infectious brain imaging if an MRI was done
             previously
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isabelle LE BER, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Isabelle LE BER, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1 57 27 46 79</phone>
    <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
    <email>isabelle.leber@upmc.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daisy RINALDI, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>1 57 27 45 52</phone>
    <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
    <email>daisy.rinaldi@aphp.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Pitié-Salpêtrière - Charles Foix</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isabelle LE BER, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>1 57 27 46 79</phone>
      <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
      <email>isabelle.leber@upmc.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Daisy RINALDI, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>1 57 27 45 52</phone>
      <phone_ext>0033</phone_ext>
      <email>daisy.rinaldi@aphp.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pitié Salpetriere Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Isabelle LE BER</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caroppo P, Habert MO, Durrleman S, Funkiewiez A, Perlbarg V, Hahn V, Bertin H, Gaubert M, Routier A, Hannequin D, Deramecourt V, Pasquier F, Rivaud-Pechoux S, Vercelletto M, Edouart G, Valabregue R, Lejeune P, Didic M, Corvol JC, Benali H, Lehericy S, Dubois B, Colliot O, Brice A, Le Ber I; Predict-PGRN study group. Lateral Temporal Lobe: An Early Imaging Marker of the Presymptomatic GRN Disease? J Alzheimers Dis. 2015;47(3):751-9. doi: 10.3233/JAD-150270.</citation>
    <PMID>26401709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Frontotemporal Dementia,</keyword>
  <keyword>biomarkers,</keyword>
  <keyword>brain Imaging PET</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

