<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04015544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-0092</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04015544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Markers of Atherosclerosis in Overweight, Postmenopausal Women Following Daily Watermelon Consumption</brief_title>
  <official_title>Expression of Systemic Markers of Atherosclerosis in Free-living, Overweight, Postmenopausal Women Following Daily Watermelon Consumption for Six Weeks: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Appalachian State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Watermelon Promotion Board; https://www.watermelon.org</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Appalachian State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to determine the effectiveness of six weeks of
      watermelon puree supplementation, compared to control (no treatment), on blood antioxidant
      capacity, inflammation markers in the blood, biomarkers of metabolism in the blood, and
      cardiovascular disease markers in the blood, and biomarkers in the blood related to
      watermelon ingestion in overweight post-menopausal women. The secondary purpose is to compare
      body composition and body mass between the watermelon supplement group and the control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ORIENTATION AND PRE-STUDY TESTING (1-2 hours):

        1. Come to the Lab in the morning in an overnight fasted state.

        2. Complete orientation to the study, and provide voluntary consent to join the study.

        3. Complete a medical health questionnaire to verify medical history and lifestyle habits,
           and provide a 3-day food record.

        4. Record symptoms on a questionnaire regarding how subjects have felt for the previous
           four weeks using a 12-point Likert scale. Symptoms relate to digestive health, hunger,
           energy, infection, pain, allergies, stress, mental focus, and overall wellbeing.

        5. All forms reviewed to determine eligibility to participate in this study.

        6. Subject height, body weight, and percent body fat measured.

        7. A blood sample taken by a trained phlebotomist; the sample not to exceed 40 mL. Blood
           tested for markers associated with inflammation and cardiovascular health, and
           nutritional compounds related to drinking watermelon puree.

        8. Subjects randomized to the Control or Watermelon group. If assigned to the Watermelon
           group subjects provided a six-week supply of watermelon puree.

        9. The morning of the study subjects consume the three bottles of watermelon puree (710 mL
           total, Watermelon group) each day thereafter for six weeks or maintain normal daily
           fluid intake (Control group).

       10. Six weeks after beginning the study subjects return to the Laboratory for the final
           measurements. Subjects to bring all beverage bottles.

      6-WEEK LAB VISIT (1-2 hours):

        1. Participants come to the Lab in the morning in an overnight fasted state.

        2. Subject body weight, and percent body fat are measured.

        3. Subjects record symptoms on a questionnaire regarding how they have felt for the
           previous six weeks.

        4. A final blood sample (40 mL) taken by a trained phlebotomist.

      BLOOD SAMPLE ANALYSES

        1. Blood borne cardiovascular disease markers: ADAM metallopeptidase with thrombospondin
           type 1 motif, 13 (ADAMTS13), soluble vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 (sVCAM-1),
           soluble P-selectin (sP-selectin), growth differentiation factor-15 (GDF-15), and soluble
           intercellular adhesion molecule-1 (sICAM-1) measured according to the manufacturer's
           specifications using the MAGPIX instrument and xPONENT analysis software (Luminex,
           Austin, TX).

        2. Fasting blood glucose, insulin, vitamin C, and high-sensitivity C-reactive (hs-CRP)
           protein were measured by LabCorp (Burlington, NC).

        3. Fasting plasma carotenoid concentrations measured commercially (Craft Technologies Inc.,
           Wilson, NC).

        4. Fasting plasma amino acid concentration determined by high-performance liquid
           chromatography.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in select plasma cardiovascular disease markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma concentrations of ADAMTS13, sVCAM-1, sP-selectin, GDF-15, hs-CRP, and sICAM-1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood glucose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood insulin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood carotenoids</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood carotenoids</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood amino acids</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood amino acids</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-study and study completion (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass index (kg/m2)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Postmenopausal</condition>
  <condition>Overweight and Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Watermelon</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Watermelon puree 710 mL per day for six weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Watermelon</intervention_name>
    <description>Pureed whole (100%) watermelon</description>
    <arm_group_label>Watermelon</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  50 to 75 years of age,

          -  have not menstruated for at least 1 year (menopause),

          -  have a BMI of ≥25 kg/m2,

          -  nonsmoker with

          -  no diagnosed history of chronic diseases including: coronary heart disease, stroke,
             cancer, type 1 or 2 diabetes mellitus, or rheumatoid arthritis;

          -  may not regularly consume large quantities of L-citrulline/L-arginine rich foods (red
             meat, tuna fish, cheese, nuts),

          -  may not regularly take L-citrulline/L-arginine supplements,

          -  may not use anti-hypertension medications (including diuretic medications),

          -  may not use exogenous ovarian hormones, or

          -  may not use medications known to influence inflammation within the two weeks of the
             study period (specifically non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; NSAIDS).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Male,

          -  younger than 50 or older than 75 years of age,

          -  menstruated within the last year,

          -  have a BMI of &lt;25 kg/m2, smoker,

          -  diagnosed history of chronic diseases including: coronary heart disease, stroke,
             cancer, type 1 or 2 diabetes mellitus, or rheumatoid arthritis;

          -  regularly consume large quantities of L-citrulline/L-arginine rich foods (red meat,
             tuna fish, cheese, nuts),

          -  regularly take L-citrulline/L-arginine supplements,

          -  use anti-hypertension medications (including diuretic medications),

          -  use exogenous ovarian hormones, or

          -  use medications known to influence inflammation within the two weeks of the study
             period (specifically non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; NSAIDS).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>R. Andrew Shanely, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Appalachian State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Appalachian State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boone</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Collins JK, Wu G, Perkins-Veazie P, Spears K, Claypool PL, Baker RA, Clevidence BA. Watermelon consumption increases plasma arginine concentrations in adults. Nutrition. 2007 Mar;23(3):261-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17352962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kannel WB, Hjortland MC, McNamara PM, Gordon T. Menopause and risk of cardiovascular disease: the Framingham study. Ann Intern Med. 1976 Oct;85(4):447-52.</citation>
    <PMID>970770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lum T, Connolly M, Marx A, Beidler J, Hooshmand S, Kern M, Liu C, Hong MY. Effects of Fresh Watermelon Consumption on the Acute Satiety Response and Cardiometabolic Risk Factors in Overweight and Obese Adults. Nutrients. 2019 Mar 12;11(3). pii: E595. doi: 10.3390/nu11030595.</citation>
    <PMID>30870970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards AJ, Vinyard BT, Wiley ER, Brown ED, Collins JK, Perkins-Veazie P, Baker RA, Clevidence BA. Consumption of watermelon juice increases plasma concentrations of lycopene and beta-carotene in humans. J Nutr. 2003 Apr;133(4):1043-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12672916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook-Mills JM, Marchese ME, Abdala-Valencia H. Vascular cell adhesion molecule-1 expression and signaling during disease: regulation by reactive oxygen species and antioxidants. Antioxid Redox Signal. 2011 Sep 15;15(6):1607-38. doi: 10.1089/ars.2010.3522. Epub 2011 May 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21050132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>glucose</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>watermelon</keyword>
  <keyword>L-citrulline</keyword>
  <keyword>L-arginine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

