<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04010461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUM00165239</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21MH120633-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04010461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Theta Burst Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation of Fronto-parietal Networks: Modulation by Mental State</brief_title>
  <acronym>TMScogMod</acronym>
  <official_title>Theta Burst Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation of Fronto-parietal Networks: Modulation by Mental State</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to improve understanding of the way transcranial magnetic
      stimulation (TMS), a form of non-invasive brain stimulation, affects the brain. The study
      hypothesis that when theta burst stimulation (TBS) is applied during a controlled mental
      state, network changes will be facilitated, compared to stimulation when mental state is
      uncontrolled. This study will focus on the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (dlPFC) and the
      associated frontoparietal network (FPN), which subserves cognitive control - the ability to
      flexibly adapt and regulate behavior, an ability known to be impaired in neuropsychiatric
      conditions such as depression and dementia.

      Healthy volunteers that qualify for this study will have psychological assessments and
      cognitive measures, as well as functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI) scans, completed
      after administration of TMS. Participants will be asked to come in for a total of five visits
      that include; a screening and assessment visit; a baseline functional magnetic resonance
      imaging (fMRI) scan, followed by TMS session; Visits 3, 4, and 5 will be the experimental TMS
      session, followed by fMRI scan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Please note the collaborator (NIMH) is requesting that an NCT number be obtained prior to
      receiving the award.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All participants will have 3 MRI sessions subsequent to the baseline visit and these will occur in a counterbalanced order.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>All subjects will receive all interventions in a cross-over design. The three intervention sessions (visits 3, 4 &amp; 5) will be given in counter-balanced order, stratified by gender. Subjects will be blind to the nature of the questions being asked; however, they will be told that different stimulation paradigms will be used, which will be evident to the subjects as they go through the procedures.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>3-back minus 1-back Blood Oxygen Level-Dependent (BOLD) activation, voxelwise in FPN</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Fronto-parietal network defined by BOLD change while subject performs the n-back working memory task, contrasting high (3-back) versus low (1-back) loads.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FPN connectivity to dlPFC TBS stimulation target</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Resting-state connectivity of low frequency BOLD fluctuations for a seed at the dlPFC</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>rCBF at stimulation target</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Regional cerebral blood flow measured at the site of TBS stimulation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy to 3-back</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Correct responses to letter stimuli, as a percentage of all responses</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3-back minus 1-back BOLD activation, voxelwise in whole brain</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Fronto-parietal network defined by BOLD change while subject performs the n-back working memory task, contrasting high (3-back) versus low (1-back) loads.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure cerebral blood flow (rCBF) in FPN</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Regional cerebral blood flow measured in the FPN</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Reaction Time (RT) to 3-back</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>Median reaction time for subjects responding in the n-back task, for correct responses</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>d-prime in 3-back</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after TMS during fMRI</time_frame>
    <description>d-prime measure, including all hits, misses, false alarms and 'correct rejections'</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, without a concurrent task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TMS (intermittent theta burst stimulation) will be applied to the dlPFC, when subjects are in a resting state</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to vertex, without concurrent task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TMS (intermittent theta burst stimulation) will be applied to the cerebral vertex, when subjects are in a resting state</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, during task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TMS (intermittent theta burst stimulation) will be applied to the dlPFC, when subjects are engaged in the n-back working memory task</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Intermittent theta burst stimulation TMS applied to the cortex to excite cerebral cortex</description>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, during task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, without a concurrent task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to vertex, without concurrent task</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>intermittent theta burst stimulation (iTBS)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>n-back working memory task</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects perform an executive function task, in which they view the serial presentation of letters and decide whether or not a letter matches a letter presented 'n' letters back (3 letters or 1 letter)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, during task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to dlPFC, without a concurrent task</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>TMS to vertex, without concurrent task</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women of child bearing age can not be pregnant or trying to become pregnant

          -  Ability to tolerate small, enclosed spaces without anxiety

          -  Size compatible with scanner gantry, e. g. men over 6 feet tall that weigh more than
             250 lbs, men under 6 feet tall that weigh over 220 lbs, women over 5'11&quot; tall that
             weigh more than 220 lbs, or women under 5'10&quot; tall that weigh more than 200 lbs.
             Subjects of these weights or greater typically have difficult fitting into the fMRI
             scanner properly

          -  Ability and willingness to give informed consent to participate

          -  Alcohol or drug dependence (if in remission for greater than 5 years)

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  History of past or current mental illness (except simple phobias)

          -  History of closed head injury, for example, loss of consciousness &gt; approximately 5
             minutes, hospitalization, neurological sequela;

          -  Metals, implants or metallic substances within or on the body that might cause adverse
             effects to the subject in a strong magnetic field, or interfere with image acquisition
             (for example; aneurysm clips, retained particles or metal workers with exposures,
             neurostimulators, foil-backed transdermal patches, carotid or cerebral stents,
             cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) shunts; magnetic dental implants, ferromagnetic ocular
             implants, pacemakers, and automatic implantable defibrillators).

          -  Prescription or non-prescription, with psychotropic effects (birth control medications
             allowed)

          -  First-degree family members with a history of epilepsy

          -  History of serious neurological illness or current medical condition that could
             compromise brain function, such as liver failure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephan Taylor, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pan Gu</last_name>
    <phone>734-936-4958</phone>
    <email>TMScogMod-study@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Laura Stchur, MSW</last_name>
    <phone>734-936-1323</phone>
    <email>lmarine@med.umich.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48170</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Stchur, MSW</last_name>
      <phone>734-936-1323</phone>
      <email>lmarine@med.umich.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stephan F. Taylor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>functional magnetic resonance imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>dorsolateral prefrontal cortex</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The PI will share information about this/these trial(s) via timely registration, updates, and results reporting in ClinicalTrials.gov in accordance with NIH policy.
The PI will also upload data gathered in this proposal to an National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)-designated central data, NIMH Data Archive (NDA), as prescribed by NOT-MH-15-012, working with NIMH program to determine the timing and extent of data sharing. This includes formulation of an enrollment strategy that will obtain the information necessary to generate a Global Unique Identifier (GUID) for each participant.
The consent form will include language indicating the intention to upload de-identified data into the central archive, and permission will be obtained from University of Michigan Institutional Review Board to do so. The budget includes a data manager to cover the costs of managing the data, building the data dictionary and harmonizing it with data structures.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>De-identified data will be entered into the NDA within 1 year of the conclusion of the study.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>No additional access restrictions will be placed on the de-identified data beyond those that are standard for the NDA.</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://nda.nih.gov</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

