<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04016155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FlashDKD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04016155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Flash Glucose Monitoring in Reduction of Hypoglycaemia in Diabetic Patients With Chronic Kidney Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Trial of Flash Glucose Monitoring in Reduction of Hypoglycaemia in Diabetes Patients With Chronic Kidney Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This will be a single centre study at the Prince of Wales Hospital, Hong Kong. Patients will
      be identified from an existing registry of diabetes patients with CKD. Potential subjects
      will be identified from patients attending diabetes, general medical and renal clinics.

      Following informed consent, patients will undergo screening where baseline HbA1c, renal
      function will be measured along withcomprehensive medical and drug history to confirm
      eligibility. All eligible patients will be fitted with a blinded CGM (Medtronic iPro2
      professional CGM) on week-1 for baseline glucose profiles for capturing baseline CGM profile.
      In case of blinded CGM sensor loss or malfunction, the sensor will be replaced once. Patients
      with at least 50% sensor data during the blinded wear period will proceed to randomization.

      At week 0, patients will be randomized to the flash glucose monitoring or SMBG. Both groups
      will receive standardised education on diabetes self-management, prevention and treatment of
      hypoglycaemia. This will be accordance with the usual practice at the study site. In the FGM
      group, patients will receive training on insertion, operation of the device with access to
      the device software for viewing of ambulatory glucose profiles. There is no protocol
      specified number of sensor scans per day as this study is designed to reflect real world use.
      Patients will be advised to confirm blood glucose readings with SMBG in the event of
      hypoglycaemic symptoms, if FGM displays glucose &lt;3.9mmol or in event of glucose instability.

      Patients randomized to the control group will perform SMBG using dedicated blood glucose
      meter at least twice daily.

      Blinded CGM will again be worn in both groups at week 16 for assessment of primary and
      secondary outcomes.

      Subjects will compete a hypoglycaemia diary for documenting symptomatic or asymptomatic
      hypoglycaemia during the study period.

      Questionnaires on hypoglycaemia unawarenesss, fear of hypoglycaemia and patient-reported
      outcomes will be completed at baseline, week 8 and week 16 in both groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in time in hypoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the difference in time in hypoglycaemia (&lt;3.9mmol/l) on blinded CGM between intervention and control groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CGM indices</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Time-in-range (4-10mmol/l), time-in-hyperglycaemia (&gt;10mmol), low blood glucose index, glycaemic variability (coefficient of variation). These CGM indices are defined in accordance with the latest International Consensus on Use of CGM</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycated haemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Change in HbA1c</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of hypoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Numbers of hypoglycaemic episode reported by study subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient compliance to Flash CGMS</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of sensor scans and time duration of sensor wear</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Diabetic treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Physician directed change in diabetes treatment (including insulin dosage)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient quality-of-life</measure>
    <time_frame>week 16</time_frame>
    <description>Measures by questionnaire: Diabetes Distress Scale (DDS; total score from 17-102), comprising 3 subscales namely emotional, physician, regimen / social support. A lower score indicates better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypoglycaemia awareness</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure by questionnaire: Gold Score Hypoglycaemia awareness (Total 7 grading, lowest score indicates better outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by questionnaire: IDTSQs (Total 8 questions with total score 0-48, highest score indicates better outcome)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fear of hypoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by questionnaire: Hypoglycemia Fear Survey II (comprising 2 subscales namely behaviour (15 items) and worry (18 items). Each item has 5 categorical selection from &quot;never&quot; to &quot;always&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes With Diabetic Chronic Kidney Disease (Diagnosis)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SMBG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients use their own glucometers as control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Flash CGMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abbott FreeStyle Libre</intervention_name>
    <description>Flash CGMS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Flash CGMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Own SMBG</intervention_name>
    <description>Market SMBG</description>
    <arm_group_label>SMBG</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Type I or II diabetes mellitus diagnosed for at least 6 months

          2. Male or female age ≥ 18 years old and ≤ 75 years old.

          3. Women who are not pregnant, lactating or planning a pregnancy during their
             participation in the clinical study.

          4. Patients with CKD stage 3b, 4 or 5 as defined by estimated glomerular filtration rate
             less than 45ml/min/m2 by the modified Chinese MDRD equation at screening

          5. History of at least 1 episode of mild or severe hypoglycaemia in the 12 months prior
             to screening

          6. Willingness, ability and commitment to comply with the testing, procedure and
             follow-up outlined in this protocol including (but not limited to) and use of
             pre-specified glucose monitoring devices.

          7. Willingness to perform SMBG during the study period

          8. In the opinion of the investigator, absence of any physical limitations, addictive
             diseases, or underlying medical conditions (including mental health) that may preclude
             the patient from being a suitable study candidate.

          9. Written informed consent to participate in the study provided by the patient.

         10. Willing and capable of use of a flash glucose monitor as judged by the investigator

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. HbA1C &gt;8.5% at screening

          2. Currently pregnant, as demonstrated by a positive pregnancy test at screening or
             planning pregnancy. Women of childbearing potential will also be asked to adopt
             adequate contraceptive measures throughout the study period, and to notify the study
             staff immediately if discovered pregnant. Participants who are unwilling to comply
             with these measures will be excluded.

          3. Any active acute or chronic disease or condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, might interfere with the performance of this study.

          4. Any active acute or chronic infectious disease that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would pose an excessive risk to study staff.

          5. Current use or recent exposure to any medication that in the opinion of the
             investigator could have an influence on the patient's ability to participate in this
             study or on the performance of the test device.

          6. Extensive skin changes/diseases that preclude wearing the FGM on normal skin at the
             proposed application sites (e.g., extensive psoriasis, recent burns or severe sunburn,
             extensive eczema, extensive scarring, extensive tattoos, dermatitis herpetiformis).

          7. Have a known allergy to medical-grade adhesives

          8. Known current or recent alcohol or drug abuse

          9. Diabetic ketoacidosis, hyperosmolar hyperglycaemic state or myocardial infarction in
             the six months prior to screening

         10. Patients on renal replacement therapy

         11. Currently participating in another investigational study protocol where the testing or
             results may interfere with study compliance, diagnostic results, or data collection.

         12. An identified protected vulnerable patient (including but not limited to those in
             detention, or a prisoner).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elaine Chow</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elaine Chow, MBChB PhD</last_name>
    <phone>852 3505 1549</phone>
    <email>e.chow@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Cherry Chiu</last_name>
    <email>cherrychiu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sha Tin</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elaine Chow, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>852 3505 3149</phone>
      <email>e.chow@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cherry Chiu</last_name>
      <phone>852 3505 3897</phone>
      <email>cherrychiu@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 29, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elaine Chow</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoglycemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

