<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04015817</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LPNE_02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04015817</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interdisciplinary Approach for Refractory Dyspnoea</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of an Interdisciplinary Approach in the Management of Refractory Dyspnoea on Patients' Quality of Life by a Respiratory Care Team Non-specialized in Palliative Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ligue Pulmonaire Neuchâteloise</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ligue Pulmonaire Neuchâteloise</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dyspnoea is a very common symptom in many diseases, not only cardiorespiratory, but also
      renal or neurological diseases. It can be defined as &quot; difficult, laboured and uncomfortable
      breathing […]. It is a subjective symptom. As pain, it involves both the patient's perception
      of the sensation and his reaction to it &quot;. It can occur during even moderate effort and
      sometimes also at rest and tends to increase as the disease causing it progresses. Dyspnoea
      has therefore a significant on the various aspects of the patient's daily life and those
      around him or her (travel, leisure, daily activities, etc.) leading to a decrease in quality
      of life and possibly to anxiety and/or depressive symptoms. Among a vulnerable, elderly
      population that benefits from home care, it affects more than 46 % of patients in north-west
      of Switzerland.

      Despite the handicap generated by daily dyspnoea, this complaint is often difficult to
      recognize by health professionals or family and friends, due in particular to a feeling of
      helplessness in the care provided. In addition, the treatment of the disease responsible for
      dyspnoea by the doctor does not always provide relief.

      In this context, it is essential that people with dyspnoea, families and friends are
      supported in their experiences and acquire techniques and alternatives that help them better
      manage dyspnoea on a daily basis.

      The first objective is to evaluate the feasibility of a dyspnoea support program led by a
      respiratory care team non-specialized in palliative care and its effect on quality of life
      and control of dyspnoea symptoms by patients .

      A second objective is to measure patient's satisfaction about the program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The dyspnoea support program will include 4 steps:

      Step 1: Initial interview Before the initial interview, the responsible physician will review
      or examine the medical records via the request sheet sent by the referring physician or
      pneumologist containing the patient's diagnoses, history and medications. These files will
      then be sent to the team coordinator.

      The team coordinator will meet the patient to obtain complete informations about his or her
      experiences with dyspnoea. Validated written questionnaires in French will be completed to
      complete the evaluation:

        -  Edmonton Symptom Assessment scale (ESAS):

        -  London Chest Activity of Daily Living (LCADL):

        -  Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale (HADS):

        -  Chronic Respiratory disease questionnaire (CRQ):

      Blood oxygen saturation (Sp02) without O2 will be measured for each patient. If deemed
      necessary by the responsible physician (Dr. Clark) to complete the evaluation, a spirometry
      and an Incremental Shuttle Walk Test (ISWT) test will be performed by a physiotherapist.

      Step 2: Specialized appointment:

      The coordinator will review the patient to present the measures and strategies that will be
      proposed according to his/her needs and with reference to the evaluation carried out. An
      anti-dyspnoea checklist providing advice, useful information and exercises to better manage
      dyspnoea in daily living will be provided, as well as a self-observation logbook to optimize
      self-energy and fatigue management.

      Step 3: Services:

      The measures proposed by the coordinator and accepted by the patient will be implemented, for
      example: work on positions, ventilatory education, use of a fan, pulmonary rehabilitation,
      stress management, mindfulness meditation, psychosocial services, possible support from the
      mobile palliative care team, etc. As the measures proposed depend on the evaluation carried
      out, this is an individualised program. Different measures can be combined in various ways
      and successions to meet the needs of the patient.

      Step 4: Assessment of progress:

      Once the program is completed, evolution of dyspnoea perception following the program will be
      evaluated. CRQ and HADS questionnaires will be completed and patient's satisfaction will be
      evaluated (look &quot;statistical consideration&quot;).

      After the program, a follow-up is planned: patients will be seen again at 3 and 6 months
      after the program. It will then be a matter of completing the CRQ and HADS questionnaires and
      monitoring the patients' progress.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change measured by the Chronic Respiratory Questionnaire (CRQ) between the initial interview (T0) and the progress report in patients with refractory dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of four month</time_frame>
    <description>Minimally important difference is reflected by a change in score of 0.5 on a 7 point scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure patient satisfaction with the program in the progress report : visual analogic scale</measure>
    <time_frame>an average of four month</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction assessment using a visual analogic scale (0-10)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspnea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Etude longitudinale</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Work on positions, ventilatory education, use of a fan, pulmonary rehabilitation, stress management, mindfulness meditation, psychosocial services, support from the mobile palliative care team</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>paramedical and non-pharmacological services</intervention_name>
    <description>Paramedical and non-pharmacological services (work on positions, ventilatory education, use of a fan, pulmonary rehabilitation, stress management, mindfulness meditation, psychosocial services, possible support from the mobile palliative care team)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Etude longitudinale</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  refractory breathlessness on exertion or rest (Medical Research Council (MRC) dyspnea
             scale score ≥2), despite optimum treatment of the underlying disease, as deemed by the
             responsible physician;

          -  advanced disease such as cancer, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic
             heart failure, interstitial lung disease or motor neuron disease;

          -  willing to engage with proposed therapy (physiotherapy);

          -  able to provide informed consent in French.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Breathlessness of unknown cause;

          -  A primary diagnosis of chronic hyperventilation syndrome;

          -  Completely house (or hospital or nursing home) bound
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Marc Fellrath, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hopital Neuchatelois</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gregory Clark, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>079 281 53 28</phone>
    <email>gclark@clarkpneumo.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marc Marechal</last_name>
    <phone>0327202050</phone>
    <email>marc.marechal@lpne.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Booth S, Burkin J, Moffat C, Spathis A. Managing Breathlessness in Clinical Practice. 1st ed. New York : Springer; 2013. 265 p.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Comroe, J. Some theories on the mechanism of dyspnea. In: Howell J, Campbell, E. Breathlessness: proceeding of an international symposium on breathlessness. Oxford: Blackwell; 1965.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higginson IJ, Bausewein C, Reilly CC, Gao W, Gysels M, Dzingina M, McCrone P, Booth S, Jolley CJ, Moxham J. An integrated palliative and respiratory care service for patients with advanced disease and refractory breathlessness: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet Respir Med. 2014 Dec;2(12):979-87. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(14)70226-7. Epub 2014 Oct 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25465642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark, G, Marechal, M. COPD knowledge in a swiss frail selected population. European respiratory Society Congress 2018</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pautex S, Vayne-Bossert P, Bernard M, Beauverd M, Cantin B, Mazzocato C, Thollet C, Bollondi-Pauly C, Ducloux D, Herrmann F, Escher M. Validation of the French Version of the Edmonton Symptom Assessment System. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2017 Nov;54(5):721-726.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2017.07.032. Epub 2017 Jul 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28751077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beaumont M, Couturaud F, Jego F, Pichon R, Le Ber C, Péran L, Rogé C, Renault D, Narayan S, Reychler G. Validation of the French version of the London Chest Activity of Daily Living scale and the Dyspnea-12 questionnaire. Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis. 2018 Apr 30;13:1399-1405. doi: 10.2147/COPD.S145048. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29750026</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bocéréan C, Dupret E. A validation study of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) in a large sample of French employees. BMC Psychiatry. 2014 Dec 16;14:354. doi: 10.1186/s12888-014-0354-0.</citation>
    <PMID>25511175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bourbeau J, Maltais F, Rouleau M, Guímont C. French-Canadian version of the Chronic Respiratory and St George's Respiratory questionnaires: an assessment of their psychometric properties in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. Can Respir J. 2004 Oct;11(7):480-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15505701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dyspnea</keyword>
  <keyword>Well being</keyword>
  <keyword>respiratory care team non-specialized in palliative care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There are no plans to share the data collected with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

