<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04016259</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC-SN-19-0452</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04016259</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self Cranial Electrical Stimulation (CES) for Pain in Older Adults With Knee Osteoarthritis (Self CES for Knee Pain)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Self Cranial Electrical Stimulation for Pain in Older Adults With Knee Osteoarthritis (Self CES for Knee Pain)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility, safety, and preliminary efficacy
      of a two-week self Cranial Electrical Stimulation(CES) on pain in older adults with knee
      osteoarthritis(OA)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 21, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 21, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in clinical pain as assessed by the numeric rating scale (NRS) for pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The NRS total score ranges from 0 (no pain) to 100 (most intense pain imaginable).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in clinical pain as assessed by the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The WOMAC ranges from 0 to 96, with higher scores indicating worse OA pain-related symptoms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychosocial symptoms as measured by the Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System(PROMIS) anxiety-short form</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The 7-item PROMIS Anxiety Short Form assesses the pure domain of anxiety in individuals age 18 and older, and each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 7 to 35 with higher scores indicating greater severity of anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychosocial symptoms as measured by the PROMIS depression-short form</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The 8-item PROMIS Depression Short Form assesses the pure domain of depression in individuals age 18 and older, and each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely; 3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychosocial symptoms as measured by the PROMIS sleep disturbance-short form scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The 8-item PROMIS Sleep Disturbance Short Form assesses the pure domain of sleep disturbance in individuals age 18 and older, and each item on the measure is rated on a 5-point scale (1=never; 2=rarely;3=sometimes; 4=often; and 5=always) with a range in score from 8 to 40 with higher scores indicating greater severity of sleep disturbance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Psychosocial symptoms as measured by the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS) consists of 13 items assessing three components of catastrophizing: rumination, magnification, and helplessness. It is measured using the 0 (not at all) to 4 (all the time) scale. Total score ranges from 0 to 52, with higher scores indicating greater pain catastrophizing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Experimental Pain Sensitivity as measured using a multimodal Quantitative Sensory Testing (QST) battery</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>In order to measure experimental pain sensitivity, a multimodal Quantitative Sensory Testing (QST) battery will be completed: heat pain sensitivity, pressure pain sensitivity, punctate mechanical pain, and Conditioned Pain Modulation (CPM).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain related cortical response using a continuous wave, multichannel Functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS) imaging system</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Pain-related cortical response will be measured using a continuous-wave, multichannel fNIRS imaging system (LIGHTNIRS, Shimadzu, Kyoto, Japan) with three semiconductor lasers at 780, 805, and 830 nm. Optical recordings will be collected during thermal pain stimulation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction with treatment using the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ-8)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The CSQ-8 comprises eight items that are summed to yield an overall score of 8-32, with higher scores indicating greater satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility as measured by the number of participants that completed the full CES protocol</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility as indicated by Participant's Cranial Electrical Stimulation (CES) experience</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2</time_frame>
    <description>CES experience will be measured on a 10-item scale, with each item rated 0-10 and 0 being strongly disagree and 10 being strongly agree. Total score ranges from 0 to 100, with higher scores indicating a better CES experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability as indicated by number of participants with possible side effects of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of presence and severity of possible side effects of treatment on a 0 (not at all) to 10 (highest degree) scale.If any side effects are reported, the degree of relatedness to the intervention will be assessed on a 5-point scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteo Arthritis Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self-CES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-CES</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cranial Electrical Stimulation (CES)</intervention_name>
    <description>CES will be applied for 60 minutes per session daily for 2 weeks (Monday to Friday) via the Alpha-Stim M Electromedical Products International, Inc., Mineral Wells, TX).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Self-CES</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alpha-Stim M</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham-CES</intervention_name>
    <description>For sham CES, the electrodes will be identical look and be placed in the same positions as for active stimulation, but the stimulator will not deliver electrical current.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham-CES</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alpha-Stim M</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  have self-reported unilateral or bilateral knee OA pain, according to American College
             of Rheumatology criteria

          -  have had knee OA pain in the past 3 months with an average of at least 30 on a 100
             Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) for pain

          -  can speak and read English

          -  have a device with internet access that can be used for secure video conferencing for
             real- time remote supervision

          -  have no plan to change medication regimens for pain throughout the trial

          -  are able to travel to the coordinating center

          -  are willing and able to provide written informed consent prior to enrollment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  history of brain surgery, brain tumor, seizure,stroke, or intracranial metal
             implantation

          -  serious medical illness, such as uncontrolled hypertension (i.e., systolic blood
             pressure/ diastolic blood pressure ≥ 150/95 mm Hg)heart failure, or history of acute
             myocardial infarction

          -  alcohol/substance abuse

          -  cognitive impairment

          -  pregnancy or lactation

          -  hospitalization within the preceding year for psychiatric illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hyochol Ahn, PhD, RN, MSN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hyochol Ahn</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

