<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04019145</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>28909092104862</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04019145</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Evaluation of Fiber Reinforced Resin Composite Base Versus Incremental Packing of Nanohybrid Resin Composite</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Evaluation of Fiber Reinforced Bulk Fill Resin Composite Versus Incremental Packing of Nanohybrid Resin Composite in Restoration of Deep Proximal Lesions of Permanent Posterior Molars: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A clinical trial, comparing two different incrementation techniques in the restoration of
      proximal caries in permanent posterior teeth . One utilizes a fiber reinforced bulk fill base
      material, followed by an occlusal nanohybrid capping layer. The other utilizes incremental
      packing of nanohybrid resin composite material to fill the whole cavity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to conduct an RCT to evaluate the clinical performance of the fiber
      reinforced bulk fill resin composite in comparison to incremental packing of nanohybrid resin
      composite.

      Examination and selection of all patients will be done according to inclusion and exclusion
      criteria. Diagnosis of patients' chief complaint and teeth that will be involved in this
      study will be done. Teeth are to be chosen according to standardized radiographic
      examination. Teeth should have proximal, primary deep carious lesions involving 2/3 of the
      entire dentin thickness with no continuity between the carious cavity and the pulp chamber.

      A Class II cavity will be prepared after local anesthesia has been given as required. The
      cavity will be prepared using a high-speed hand-piece with air and water coolant and diamond
      burs of different sizes. Sharp excavators will allow accessible removal of soft carious
      lesions will be used. Any tooth that will suffer from pulpal exposure will be excluded from
      the study. Finishing of the cavity walls will be done using a fine-grit, yellow coded,
      diamond bur.

      Rubber dam isolation will be done.

      Sectional matricing and wedging will be done. Followed by, placement of restorative material
      according to the randomization sequence.

      A closed centripetal technique will be utilized, where a proximal wall will be built using
      nanohyrbid resin composite first, followed by filling of cavity with bulk-fill fiber
      reinforced resin composite material in increments of 3-4mm, as required to end up with
      leaving an occlusal space on top of at least 2mm. Then, an occlusal increment of nanohybrid
      resin composite will be applied. Finally finishing and occlusal adjustment will be done under
      water spray by using superfine diamond burs. Polishing will be done using pre-impregnated
      rubber cups. Materials will be manipulated according to manufacturer instructions.

      A closed centripetal, oblique incrementation technique will be used to completely fill the
      whole cavity. Increments should be of 2mm thickness or less and should be placed obliquely
      from the cavity walls. Then finishing and occlusal adjustment will be done under water spray
      by using superfine diamond burs. Polishing will be done using pre-impregnated rubber cups.
      Materials will be manipulated according to manufacturer instructions

      Outcome Measuring Device: modified USPHS criteria .

      Primary Outcomes:

      Mechanical evaluation:

      Fracture and Retention Marginal integrity Marginal Discoloration Anatomic Form Surface
      Texture Proximal Contact Radiographic Examination

      Secondary Outcomes:

      Biological evaluation:

      Postoperative Sensitivity Recurrent Caries
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mechanical outcome according to USPHS criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>fracture or retention, marginal integrity, marginal discoloration, anatomic form, proximal contact, radiographic examination and surface texture</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biological outcome according to USPHS criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>postoperative sensitivity and recurrent caries</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Caries Class Ii</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fiber Reinforced bulk fill resin composite</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fiber reinforced bulk fill resin composite dentine substitute, capped occlusally and proximally (closed centripetal technique) by nanohybrid resin composite.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nanohybrid resin composite incrementation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nanohybrid resin composite layering to fill the whole cavity, using closed centripetal technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EverX Posterior</intervention_name>
    <description>fiber reinforced bulk fill resin composite</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fiber Reinforced bulk fill resin composite</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fiber reinforced bulk fill dentine substitute</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resins, Composite</intervention_name>
    <description>incremental packing of Nanohybrid Resin composite</description>
    <arm_group_label>nanohybrid resin composite incrementation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Universal Restorative Nanohybrid resin composite (Z250 XT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patient-related criteria:

          -  Patients consulting in one of the outpatient clinic listed above.

          -  Able to tolerate necessary restorative procedures.

          -  Provide informed consent.

          -  Accepts the one year follow-up period.

        Tooth related criteria:

          -  Teeth with primary deep carious lesions involving 2/3 of the entire dentin thickness
             with no continuity between the carious cavity and the pulp chamber.

          -  Teeth are vital according to pulp-sensitivity tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patient-related criteria:

          -  Medically compromised patients, as they will not be able to attend multiple
             appointments or may require special management.

          -  Pregnant women; as radiographs cannot be taken for them.

          -  Allergy to any of the restorative materials, including anesthetics.

          -  Uncooperative patients, will not abide by the instructions or attend the appointments.

        Tooth related criteria:

          -  Deciduous teeth; as the study is targeting only permanent teeth.

          -  Teeth with previous restorations, which may add another variable to the study (type of
             old restorative material, extent of recurrent caries).

          -  Spontaneous pain or prolonged pain after sensitivity tests (cold and electrical
             tests), which would indicate irreversible pulpal damage.

          -  Negative sensitivity tests, periapical radiolucencies and sensitivity to axial or
             lateral percussion, which would indicate pulp necrosis.

          -  Teeth presenting external or internal resorption, with adverse pulpal reactions which
             may affect the outcome of the study.

          -  Teeth with cervical caries; which can't be evaluated on periapical radiographs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olfat Hassanein, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cairo University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mennatallah Salem, Masters</last_name>
    <phone>00201007889167</phone>
    <email>mennatallah.salem@miuegypt.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dina ElKassas, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>00201221139772</phone>
    <email>dinaelkassas2000@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cairo University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mennatallah Salem</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Lecturer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

