<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04012151</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ARMFIN</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ANAESPRG19/012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04012151</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Arm and Finger Measurement for Blood Pressure Surveillance</brief_title>
  <acronym>ARMFIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Arm and Finger Measurement for Blood Pressure Surveillance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Accurate blood pressure (BP) measurement is critical in peripartum care. The cuff and bladder
      sizes affects the accuracy of BP measurement. Current international BP measurement
      recommendations are based on mid-arm circumference (MAC). However, evidence have shown the
      discrepancies between these sizes, leading to inaccuracy of BP measurement. This study will
      measure arm and finger size of 300 parturients in third trimester to determine whether the
      MAC, finger measurement or body mass index (BMI) is the best clinical predictor for
      non-standard cuff sizes for BP measurement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Accurate blood pressure (BP) measurement plays an important role in peripartum care as it is
      essential in detecting hypertensive disorders in pregnancy and medical decision making during
      the pregnancy. The cuff and bladder size have been highlighted as an important factor
      affecting the accuracy of BP measurement. Current international BP measurement
      recommendations are based on mid-arm circumference (MAC) assuming the arm is cylindrical in
      shape. However, evidence have shown a mismatch between these sizes, leading to BP
      overestimation or underestimation in obese patients. This is because the shape of the arm is
      a truncated cone instead of a cylinder, and the cuff will expand irregularly during inflation
      thus yielding inaccurate BP measurements. This is especially evident in Asian pregnant
      patients whereby no available guideline can recommend a suitable cuff for parturients with
      different MAC. Nexfin is a finger cuff device that can be a suitable alternative BP
      measurement device for such patients. In this study 300 parturients will be recruited in
      third trimester and undergoing nonemergent caesarean section in KKH. Patients' arm and finger
      sizes will be measured, and their user experience on current practices on BP measurement. The
      arm measurements will help to identify the proportion of women that may require non-standard
      cuff sizes for BP measurement. A conicity index will be determined whether the MAC, finger
      measurement or BMI is the best clinical predictor. The finger measurements will also help to
      determine the proportion of women that may require non-standard cuff sizes on the Nexfin
      device for BP measurement. The knowledge gathered in this pilot study will be used to design
      future studies in which the accuracy of Nexfin will be compared with standard BP measurement,
      which in turn will improve BP detection, subsequent patient monitoring and satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 10, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 11, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm length (Left, Right)</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>The distance (cm) between the tip of the acromion process to the tip of the olecranon process on the posterior aspect of the arm, with the elbow in the flexed position.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mid Arm circumference (MAC)(Left, Right)</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>The circumference (cm) of the arm at the mid-point of the arm length as measured above, with the arm hanging by the side.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proximal arm circumference (Left, Right)</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>Arm circumference (cm) of the arm measured at the axilla, with the arm hanging by the side.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distal arm circumference (Left, Right)</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>The circumference (cm) at the elbow above the elbow crease, with the arm hanging by the side.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Finger circumference (Left, Right)</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>The circumference (cm) of the mid-point of the middle phalanx of the middle finger will be measured with the hands placed flat on a table.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feedback on experiences of previous BP measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>During antenatal visit (1-2 hours). One visit only</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will also respond to a three-point rating scale (Never, sometimes, always) about their experience of the procedures for previous BP measurement during the current pregnancy, with questions such as the length of time taken to obtain a reading, the need to change a cuff when taking BP, the need to take BP on the leg and whether the arm felt uncomfortable when taking blood pressure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension, Pregnancy-Induced</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pregnant cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parturients of gestational age &gt;= 32 weeks will have measurements of arm length, MAC, proximal arm circumference, distal arm circumference, finger circumference to generate the conicity index.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical measurement</intervention_name>
    <description>Parturients of gestational week &gt;= 32 weeks will have their arms and fingers measured to generate the conicity index.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pregnant cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Measurement of fingers and arms</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cuff size fitting</intervention_name>
    <description>Fit on arm cuff and finger cuff as selected by investigators based on the measurement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pregnant cohort</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cuff fitting for arm and finger</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant women in Singapore
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anaesthesiologists physical status 1 or 2 (ASA 1 or 2) parturients
             at 32 or more weeks of gestation

          -  Multiparous or nulliparous;

          -  Age 21-50 years old;

          -  Undergoing Caesarean section in our institution.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Emergent Caesarean section such that consent and measurements cannot be taken.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant female in third trimester (&gt;=32 weeks gestation)</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Farida Ithnin, MMED (Anaes)</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>229899</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Brien E, Asmar R, Beilin L, Imai Y, Mallion JM, Mancia G, Mengden T, Myers M, Padfield P, Palatini P, Parati G, Pickering T, Redon J, Staessen J, Stergiou G, Verdecchia P; European Society of Hypertension Working Group on Blood Pressure Monitoring. European Society of Hypertension recommendations for conventional, ambulatory and home blood pressure measurement. J Hypertens. 2003 May;21(5):821-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12714851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickering TG, Hall JE, Appel LJ, Falkner BE, Graves J, Hill MN, Jones DW, Kurtz T, Sheps SG, Roccella EJ. Recommendations for blood pressure measurement in humans and experimental animals: part 1: blood pressure measurement in humans: a statement for professionals from the Subcommittee of Professional and Public Education of the American Heart Association Council on High Blood Pressure Research. Circulation. 2005 Feb 8;111(5):697-716.</citation>
    <PMID>15699287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perloff D, Grim C, Flack J, Frohlich ED, Hill M, McDonald M, Morgenstern BZ. Human blood pressure determination by sphygmomanometry. Circulation. 1993 Nov;88(5 Pt 1):2460-70.</citation>
    <PMID>8222141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown MA, Lindheimer MD, de Swiet M, Van Assche A, Moutquin JM. The classification and diagnosis of the hypertensive disorders of pregnancy: statement from the International Society for the Study of Hypertension in Pregnancy (ISSHP). Hypertens Pregnancy. 2001;20(1):IX-XIV. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12044323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Penáz J. Criteria for set point estimation in the volume clamp method of blood pressure measurement. Physiol Res. 1992;41(1):5-10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1610779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Palatini P, Parati G. Blood pressure measurement in very obese patients: a challenging problem. J Hypertens. 2011 Mar;29(3):425-9. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0b013e3283435b65.</citation>
    <PMID>21317721</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fonseca-Reyes S, de Alba-García JG, Parra-Carrillo JZ, Paczka-Zapata JA. Effect of standard cuff on blood pressure readings in patients with obese arms. How frequent are arms of a 'large circumference'? Blood Press Monit. 2003 Jun;8(3):101-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12900586</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bonso E, Saladini F, Zanier A, Benetti E, Dorigatti F, Palatini P. Accuracy of a single rigid conical cuff with standard-size bladder coupled to an automatic oscillometric device over a wide range of arm circumferences. Hypertens Res. 2010 Nov;33(11):1186-91. doi: 10.1038/hr.2010.146. Epub 2010 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>20686489</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Palatini P, Benetti E, Fania C, Malipiero G, Saladini F. Rectangular cuffs may overestimate blood pressure in individuals with large conical arms. J Hypertens. 2012 Mar;30(3):530-6. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0b013e32834f98a0.</citation>
    <PMID>22278143</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kho CL, Brown MA, Ong SL, Mangos GJ. Blood pressure measurement in pregnancy: the effect of arm circumference and sphygmomanometer cuff size. Obstet Med. 2009 Sep;2(3):116-20. doi: 10.1258/om.2009.090017. Epub 2009 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27582825</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eley VA, Roberts L, Rickards L, Pelecanos A, Blackie A, Zhang C, Christensen R, Barrett HL. Arm and finger measurements in the third trimester: Implications for blood pressure measurement. Pregnancy Hypertens. 2018 Oct;14:105-109. doi: 10.1016/j.preghy.2018.09.002. Epub 2018 Sep 5.</citation>
    <PMID>30527095</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wang J, Thornton JC, Russell M, Burastero S, Heymsfield S, Pierson RN Jr. Asians have lower body mass index (BMI) but higher percent body fat than do whites: comparisons of anthropometric measurements. Am J Clin Nutr. 1994 Jul;60(1):23-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8017333</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Blood pressure measurement</keyword>
  <keyword>Conicity index</keyword>
  <keyword>Mid arm circumference</keyword>
  <keyword>Cuff size</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pregnancy-Induced</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 10, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/51/NCT04012151/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

