<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04012853</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B3194-P</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04012853</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Remotely Supervised Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation for Persistent Post-traumatic Headache</brief_title>
  <acronym>tDCS for PTH</acronym>
  <official_title>Remotely Supervised tDCS for Persistent Post-traumatic Headache: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study is designed to provide preliminary data for a large scale, randomized
      clinical trial to evaluate the efficacy of remotely administrated at home transcranial Direct
      Current Stimulation (tDCS) with real-time monitoring via VA Tele-health for persistent post
      traumatic headache associated with mild traumatic brain injury (mTBI). Participants will
      receive total of 20 sessions of tDCS over four weeks. The investigators anticipate that the
      results generated from the study will directly translate into immediate meaningful clinical
      application: not only in management of chronic post traumatic headache, but also in reduction
      of acute pain medication use, and improving quality of life for our veterans with this
      debilitating neurological disorder.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of transcranial Direct
      Current Stimulation (tDCS) administered at home with real-time monitoring via VA Tele-health
      for persistent post traumatic headache (PTH) associated with mTBI, and the impact of this
      treatment on persistent PTH associated functional recovery. Total of 20 participants (10
      treatment group, 10 sham control) will be included in this study. The investigators will also
      evaluate recruitment strategies and participants clinical characteristics.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 4, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number of moderate to severe headache days per month</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the improvement in numbers of moderate to severe headache days per month from baseline period to end of treatment phase, and to the end of follow-up phase</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>total number of headache days per month</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate improvement in total number of headache days per month, acute pain mediation used based on number of doses of medication taken from baseline period to end of treatment phase, and to end of follow-up phase in the same cohort.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality of life based on change in Headache impact test-6 (HIT-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the impact of headaches on the quality of life measures (pain and disability) based on change in Headache impact test-6 (HIT-6) from baseline period to end of treatment phase, and to end of follow-up phase in persistent PTH. The six-item Headache Impact Test (HIT-6) provides a global measure of adverse headache impact and was developed to use in screening and monitoring patients with headaches in both clinical practice and clinical research. A total HIT-6 score ranges from 36 to 78: Little or no impact = HIT-6 score 49 or less; Some impact = HIT-6 score 50-55; Substantial impact = HIT-6 score 56-59; Severe impact = HIT-6 score 60.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>acute pain medication use</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>change in acute pain medication use based on number of doses of medication taken from baseline period to end of the treatment and follow up phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Persistent Post Traumatic Headache</condition>
  <condition>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>tDCS treatment group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham tDCS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial direct current stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment group will receive 20 minutes of tDCS stimulation at 2.0 mA administered daily for five days per week and a total of 4 weeks. During the 20minute treatment session, both treatment and sham groups will complete mindfulness meditation via VA health system approved program (Mindfulness Coach).</description>
    <arm_group_label>treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>tDCS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Verified history of mTBI

          2. Persistent PTH as defined by International Classification of Headache Disorders (ICHD)
             III diagnostic criteria(&quot;Headache Classification Committee of the International
             Headache Society (IHS) The ICHD, 3rd Edition 2018).

          3. Verification of headache frequency through prospectively collected baseline
             information during the 28-day screening/baseline phase.

          4. Not currently taking a migraine or headache preventive medication OR has been taking a
             stable dose of a preventive for at least 60 days prior to screening and agrees to not
             start, stop, or change medication and/or dosage during the study period.

          5. The investigators will include medication overuse headache as defined by ICHD III
             diagnostic criteria.

          6. Participants is either not of childbearing potential, or if they are of childbearing
             potential, they agree either to remain abstinent or use (or have their partner use) an
             acceptable method of birth control for the duration of the study.

          7. Male or female, age between 20-60 who demonstrates compliance with the electronic
             Daily Headache Diary during the 28-day baseline phase as defined by entry of headache
             data on a minimum of 22 to 28 days (80% diary compliance).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unable to complete headache diary as required by protocol.

          2. Any psychiatric condition with psychotic features, and/or any other psychiatric
             disorder not stable or well controlled, that would interfere in the ability to
             complete study activities

          3. Received onabotulinumtoxinA, cognitive behavior therapy, physical therapy or any other
             form of non-pharmacological therapy for headaches during the 4 months before
             screening.

          4. Has a planned military deployment within the 6 months post screening.

          5. Active substance abuse within last 4 months.

          6. History of seizure, stroke, multiple sclerosis or other unstable neurological
             condition or a significant abnormal neurological examination.

          7. Unable to tolerate tDCS stimulation.

          8. Have any other conditions that in the judgment of the Investigator would make the
             participants unsuitable for inclusion or interfere with participating or completing
             the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xiao M. Androulakis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wm. Jennings Bryan Dorn VA Medical Center, Columbia, SC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiao M Androulakis, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(803) 776-4000</phone>
    <phone_ext>4077</phone_ext>
    <email>Xiao.Androulakis@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathlyn S Haddock, PhD RN</last_name>
    <phone>(803) 776-4000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6670</phone_ext>
    <email>Kathlyn.Haddock@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wm. Jennings Bryan Dorn VA Medical Center, Columbia, SC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbia</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew E Barden</last_name>
      <phone>803-776-4000</phone>
      <phone_ext>6632</phone_ext>
      <email>Andrew.Barden@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xiao M. Androulakis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Concussion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Post-Traumatic Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tension-Type Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

