<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04011397</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UHuddersfield</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04011397</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of REHIT in NDH Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility of Procedures for a Pragmatic Randomized Controlled Trial of Reduced Exertion, High-intensity Interval Training (REHIT) With Non-diabetic Hyperglycaemia Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Huddersfield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Huddersfield</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this feasibility study was to describe and report data relevant to the
      acceptability of an exercise intervention (reduced-exertion, high-intensity interval
      training) in non-diabetic hyperglycaemia patients delivered in a National Health Service
      setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background Physical activity and exercise interventions to improve health frequently bring
      about intended effects under ideal circumstances but fail to demonstrate effectiveness when
      translated to demonstrable benefits in real-world contexts. The aim of this feasibility study
      was to describe and report data relevant to the acceptability of an exercise intervention
      (reduced-exertion, high-intensity interval training) in non-diabetic hyperglycaemia (NDH)
      patients delivered in a National Health Service (NHS) setting.

      Individuals with NDH are an intermediary group of patients whose blood glucose levels are
      higher than normal but not high enough to be diagnosed as diabetic. Such hyperglycaemic blood
      glucose excursions in 'pre-diabetic' states contribute to the development of macro- and
      micro-vascular disease risk and increases the risk of developing overt type 2 diabetes.
      Interventions - such as increased physical activity - for individuals who are diagnostically
      considered to have NDH are high priority, as they provide a substantial opportunity for
      preventing future burden of diabetes on patients, the NHS, and the economy.

      Evidence supporting the efficacy of exercise and physical activity as preventative or
      therapeutic treatments for a range of chronic diseases, including obesity and diabetes, is
      incontrovertible. However, exercise adherence is considered a significant issue. The most
      commonly cited barrier to undertaking physical activity is perceived 'lack of time'.
      Consequently, there has been a recent interest in high-intensity interval training (HIT)
      which is characterised by brief periods of repeated very high-intensity exercise interspersed
      with longer periods of recovery. More recently attempts have been made to modify HIT to make
      it more time-efficient and tolerable. This approach is known as reduced-exertion,
      high-intensity interval training (REHIT). In this study, issues of acceptability and
      feasibility were considered when implementing a REHIT intervention into usual care within an
      NHS setting.

      Methods The purpose was to assess whether it would be appropriate to progress to a
      larger-scale pragmatic trial, and to optimise the design and conduct of any such trial. The
      intention was to recruit 40 participants from a single centre (specialist diabesity centre).
      Patients were eligible to take part if they were diagnostically defined as non-diabetic
      hyperglycaemic based on a glycated haemoglobin value of 42-46 mmol·mol. Methodological issues
      were used to analyse problems that arose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Feasibility study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients screened and considered eligible to take part in the study</measure>
    <time_frame>4-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the number of patients who had contact with the recruitment team and who were assessed for eligibility using inclusion and exclusion criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>From first exposure to intervention to last (approx. 6-weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event was defined as any untoward occurrence that happened during the conduct of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intervention adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>From first exposure to intervention to last (approx. 6-weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention adherence was calculated by summing the total number of participants and the target number of REHIT sessions (15 per participant) and comparing this against the actual completed sessions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in affective valence (pleasure-displeasure)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from first exposure to intervention to last (approx. 6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-validated 'Feeling Scale' questionnaire which measure pleasure/displeasure responses during exercise. This is a single-item, 11-point, bipolar scale and ranges from - 5 'very bad' to + 5 'very good', with anchors designated for 0 (neutral) and all odd integers in-between. Lower scores are considered to be a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived exertion</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from first exposure to intervention to last (approx. 6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-validated 'Rating of Perceived Exertion' questionnaire which measures perceived effort during exercise. This is a 15-point scale and ranges from 6 'no exertion' to 20 'maximal exertion' with anchors designated for all the odd integers in-between. A higher score is considered a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in enjoyment</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from first exposure to intervention to last (approx. 6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-validated 'Exercise Enjoyment Scale' (ESS) which measures enjoyment associated with exercise. This is a single-item, 7-point scale. Anchors are given at every integer, ranging from 1 'not at all' to 7 'extremely'. A lower score is a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in peak oxygen uptake (fitness test)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline peak oxygen uptake at approx. 6-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Progressive cycle test to measure cardiovascular fitness (using gas analysis)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in HBA1c (blood test)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline HbA1c at approx. 6-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Widely used measure of blood glucose control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in body composition</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline body composition at approx. 6-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fat mass and fat-free mass estimated via bioelectrical impedance analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in systolic and diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline systolic and diastolic blood pressure at approx. 6-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measured via automated digital blood pressure monitor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Exercise intervention (reduced-exertion, high-intensity interval training) alongside normal treatment. [low recruitment prohibited control arm]</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise intervention (reduced-exertion, high-intensity interval training) delivered within an NHS setting. Consisted 10 min of cycle ergometry (inclusive of warm-up and cool down) including very brief maximal cycle sprints.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual care</intervention_name>
    <description>Members of a multi-disciplinary team including a consultant, diabetes specialist nurse, clinical psychologist, physiotherapist, and dietician worked together to promote patient self-management. Care was tailored to the specific circumstances of each patient after initial assessment and focussed on weight management, dietary education, behavioural therapy, and supported pharmacotherapy initiation as appropriate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Accessing the NHS Trust Weight Management Service (Specialist Diabesity Clinic)

          -  Aged between 18 and 65 years (inclusive)

          -  Diagnosed as NDH (using standard criteria)

          -  Male or female

          -  Any ethnicity

          -  Not currently partaking in a new structured exercise intervention

          -  Considered low or medium risk for exercise using standard risk stratification [37]

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 18 years and ≥ 66 years

          -  Currently partaking in a new structured exercise intervention

          -  Euglycaemic

          -  Diagnosed with type 1 or type 2 diabetes; taking insulin; history of end stage liver
             or kidney disease, neuropathy or retinopathy; has hypertension that cannot be
             controlled by standard medication; has cardiovascular disease, or another
             contraindication to exercise

          -  Considered high risk for exercise using standard risk stratification [37]

          -  Unable to adequately understand verbal explanations and written information given in
             English (there were no funds available for translation services)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Haines</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Huddersfield</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 8, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Huddersfield</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matthew Haines</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Feasibility</keyword>
  <keyword>HbA1c</keyword>
  <keyword>Interval training</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

