<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04013152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PROICM 2017-05 ROB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04013152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Database of Colorectal Robotic Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>ROBOT CR</acronym>
  <official_title>French Prospective Clinical Database of Colorectal Robotic Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut du Cancer de Montpellier - Val d'Aurelle</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut du Cancer de Montpellier - Val d'Aurelle</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Evaluation of robot Da Vinci Xi by determining its learning curve.The operating time will be
      defined by patient then the operating average will be calculated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since the emergence of minimally invasive technology twenty years ago, as a surgical concept
      and surgical technique for colorectal cancer surgery, its obvious advantages have been
      recognized.

      Laparoscopic technology, as one of the most important technology platform, has got a lot of
      evidence-based support for the oncological safety and effectiveness in colorectal cancer
      surgery Laparoscopic technique has advantages in terms of identification of anatomic plane
      and autonomic nerve, protection of pelvic structure, and fine dissection of vessels.

      But because of the limitation of laparoscopic technology there are still some deficiencies
      and shortcomings, including lack of touch and lack of stereo vision problems, in addition to
      the low rectal cancer, especially male, obese, narrow pelvis, larger tumors, it is difficult
      to get better view and manipulating triangle in laparoscopy. However, the emergence of a
      series of new minimally invasive technology platform is to make up for the defects and
      deficiencies. The robotic surgical system possesses advantages, such as stereo vision, higher
      magnification, manipulator wrist with high freedom degree, filtering of tremor and higher
      stability, but still has disadvantages, such as lack of haptic feedback, longer operation
      time, high operation cost and expensive price.

      3D system of laparoscopic surgery has similar visual experience and feelings as robotic
      surgery in the 3D view, the same operating skills as 2D laparoscopy and a short learning
      curve. Transanal total mesorectal excision (taTME) by changing the traditional laparoscopic
      pelvic surgery approach, may have certain advantages for male cases with narrow pelvic and
      patients with large tumor.

      No prospective study has compared these four surgical techniques. Furthermore, the learning
      curve still remains a crucial problem in term of data interpretation.

      We will collect synchronized videos and data on surgeon performance during colorectal
      surgeries using the Vinci Logger (dVLogger, Intuitive Surgical, Inc.), it is a personalized
      recording tool that captures synchronized video in the form of endoscope view at 30 frames
      per second. Kinematic data included characteristics of movement such as instrument travel
      time, path length and velocity. Events included frequency of master controller clutch use,
      camera movements, third arm swap and energy use.

      We will explore and validate objective surgeon performance metrics using novel recorder
      (&quot;dVLogger&quot;) to directly capture surgeon manipulations on the daVinci Surgical System.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Collection of clinical data following surgery with robotic assistance in colorectal pathologies</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of learning for each surgical technique by determining a learning curve for each of them</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The conversion rate of surgical technique</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operating time</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative complications rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>local relapse-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Digestive functionality assessment by using the Low Anterior Resection Syndrome score (LARS)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>This questionnaire assessed the bowel function of patient. The range is from 8 (low function) to 35 (high function)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Erectile Function of patient by using the II-EF-5 score (The International Index of Erectile Function)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The range is from 1 (low erectile function) to 27 (high erectile function)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The dysfunction of female Sexual Function by using the Index FSFI (The Female Sexual Function Index) score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The range is from 3 (low sexual function) to 55 (high sexual function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary functionality by using the questionnaire of urinary function</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The range is from 0 (low urinary function) to 40 (high urinary function).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective surgeon performance metrics using a novel recorder (dVLogger) to directly capture surgeon manipulations on the da Vinci Surgical System</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of lymph node resected</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of the mesorectum by using Quirke classification</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of the mesorectum resection is determined by the pathologist according to the aspect of mesorectum, the circumferential resection margin, cone effect .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1800</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn Disease</condition>
  <condition>Polyposis</condition>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <condition>Diverticulitis</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Rectal Prolapse</condition>
  <condition>Benign Colorectal Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>clinical database</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical database</intervention_name>
    <description>Constitution of a prospective, multicenter clinical database of surgery with robotic assistance in colorectal pathologies</description>
    <arm_group_label>clinical database</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female ≥ 18 years

          2. Colorectal pathologies (Crohn's disease, Polyposis, Ulcerative colitis,
             Diverticulitis, Colorectal tumor, Rectal prolapse, Benign and colorectal tumor)
             eligible for robotic surgery.

          3. Major techniques: right and left colectomy, rectal excision (low anterior resection,
             intersphincteric resection, abdominoperineal resection), Hartman reversal

          4. Or, Minor techniques: rectopexy, shaving for rectal endometriosis,

          5. Or, Complex techniques: extended rectal excision for T4 cancer, pelvectomy, redo
             surgery.

          6. Patient affiliated to a social security regimen

          7. Patient information for study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Legal incapacity or physical, psychological social or geographical status interfering
             with the patient's ability to agree to participate in the study

          2. Patient under tutelage, curatorship or safeguard of justice
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Rouanet, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Institut régional du cancer de Montpellier</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean-Pïerre Bleuse, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4 67 61 31 02</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>jean-pierre.bleuse@icm.unicancer.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <state>Gironde</state>
        <zip>33600</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Rullier, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut régional du cancer de Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <state>Hérault</state>
        <zip>34298</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Philippe Rouanet, MD</last_name>
      <phone>4 67 61 45 86</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>philippe.rouanet@icm.unicancer.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Clermont-Ferrand</name>
      <address>
        <city>Clermont-Ferrand</city>
        <state>Puy De Dôme</state>
        <zip>63103</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Dubois, MD</last_name>
      <phone>4 73 75 04 94</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>a_dubois@chu-clermontferrand.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Lyon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <state>Rhône</state>
        <zip>69310</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eddy Cotte, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6 07 67 86 09</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>eddy.cotte@chu-lyon.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colombo PE, Bertrand MM, Alline M, Boulay E, Mourregot A, Carrère S, Quénet F, Jarlier M, Rouanet P. Robotic Versus Laparoscopic Total Mesorectal Excision (TME) for Sphincter-Saving Surgery: Is There Any Difference in the Transanal TME Rectal Approach? : A Single-Center Series of 120 Consecutive Patients. Ann Surg Oncol. 2016 May;23(5):1594-600. doi: 10.1245/s10434-015-5048-4. Epub 2015 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26714950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bertrand MM, Colombo PE, Mourregot A, Traore D, Carrère S, Quénet F, Rouanet P. Standardized single docking, four arms and fully robotic proctectomy for rectal cancer: the key points are the ports and arms placement. J Robot Surg. 2016 Jun;10(2):171-4. doi: 10.1007/s11701-015-0551-y. Epub 2015 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26645073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagtegaal ID, van de Velde CJ, van der Worp E, Kapiteijn E, Quirke P, van Krieken JH; Cooperative Clinical Investigators of the Dutch Colorectal Cancer Group. Macroscopic evaluation of rectal cancer resection specimen: clinical significance of the pathologist in quality control. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Apr 1;20(7):1729-34.</citation>
    <PMID>11919228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen SL, Steele SR, Eberhardt J, Zhu K, Bilchik A, Stojadinovic A. Lymph node ratio as a quality and prognostic indicator in stage III colon cancer. Ann Surg. 2011 Jan;253(1):82-7. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181ffa780.</citation>
    <PMID>21135690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang X, Wei Z, Bie M, Peng X, Chen C. Robot-assisted versus laparoscopic-assisted surgery for colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis. Surg Endosc. 2016 Dec;30(12):5601-5614. Epub 2016 Jul 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27402096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parc Y, Reboul-Marty J, Lefevre JH, Shields C, Chafai N, Tiret E. Factors influencing mortality and morbidity following colorectal resection in France. Analysis of a national database (2009-2011). Colorectal Dis. 2016 Feb;18(2):205-13. doi: 10.1111/codi.13099.</citation>
    <PMID>26299627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bege T, Lelong B, Esterni B, Turrini O, Guiramand J, Francon D, Mokart D, Houvenaeghel G, Giovannini M, Delpero JR. The learning curve for the laparoscopic approach to conservative mesorectal excision for rectal cancer: lessons drawn from a single institution's experience. Ann Surg. 2010 Feb;251(2):249-53. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181b7fdb0.</citation>
    <PMID>20040854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poloniecki J, Valencia O, Littlejohns P. Cumulative risk adjusted mortality chart for detecting changes in death rate: observational study of heart surgery. BMJ. 1998 Jun 6;316(7146):1697-700. Erratum in: BMJ 1998 Jun 27;316(7149):1947.</citation>
    <PMID>9614015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guend H, Widmar M, Patel S, Nash GM, Paty PB, Guillem JG, Temple LK, Garcia-Aguilar J, Weiser MR. Developing a robotic colorectal cancer surgery program: understanding institutional and individual learning curves. Surg Endosc. 2017 Jul;31(7):2820-2828. doi: 10.1007/s00464-016-5292-0. Epub 2016 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>27815742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bokhari MB, Patel CB, Ramos-Valadez DI, Ragupathi M, Haas EM. Learning curve for robotic-assisted laparoscopic colorectal surgery. Surg Endosc. 2011 Mar;25(3):855-60. doi: 10.1007/s00464-010-1281-x. Epub 2010 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20734081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bolsin S, Colson M. The use of the Cusum technique in the assessment of trainee competence in new procedures. Int J Qual Health Care. 2000 Oct;12(5):433-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11079224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CROHN</keyword>
  <keyword>Diverticulitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Rectal</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal</keyword>
  <keyword>ulcerative</keyword>
  <keyword>colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>polyposis</keyword>
  <keyword>rectum</keyword>
  <keyword>prolapse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diverticulitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Prolapse</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prolapse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

