<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04013802</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-44843 TETRAVI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04013802</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TETRAVI Multivirus CTL for Treatment of EBV, CMV, Adenovirus, and BK Infections Post Allogeneic SCT.</brief_title>
  <acronym>TETRAVI</acronym>
  <official_title>Administration of Most Closely HLA-matched Multivirus-specific Cytotoxic T-Lymphocytes for the Treatment of EBV, CMV, Adenovirus, and BK Virus Infections Post Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to use VSTs (virus-specific T cells) from a donor that is a
      partial HLA (human leukocyte antigen) match with the patient to treat viral infections after
      an allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT).

      The patient must have had a myeloablative or non-myeloablative allogeneic HSCT using either
      bone marrow, single/double umbilical cord blood, or peripheral blood stem cells (PBSC). After
      a transplant, while the immune system grows back, the patient is at risk for infection. Some
      viruses can stay in the body for life and are normally controlled by a healthy immune system,
      but if the immune system is weakened, like after a transplant, they can cause life
      threatening infections. He/she must have had an infection with one or more of the following
      viruses -Epstein Barr virus (EBV), cytomegalovirus (CMV), adenovirus (AdV), Human
      polyomavirus type I (BKV), and human polyomavirus type II (JCV)- that has persisted or
      recurred despite standard therapy.

      In this study, the investigators want to use white blood cells that have been trained to
      treat viral infections. In an earlier study the investigators showed that treatment with such
      specially trained T cells has been successful when the cells are made from the transplant
      donor. However as it takes 1-2 months to make the cells, that approach is not practical for
      patients who already have an infection. In a subsequent study, the investigators were able to
      create multivirus-specific T cells (VSTs) from the blood of healthy donors and created a bank
      of these cells. The investigators then successfully used these banked cells to treat virus
      infections after a stem cell transplant. In this study the investigators have further
      modified their production method to decrease the potential side effects and the investigators
      want to find out if they can use these banked VSTs to fight infections caused by the viruses
      mentioned above.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The virus-specific T cells (VSTs) given to the patient will be thawed and injected into their
      intravenous line. To prevent an allergic reaction if the patient had a prior reaction to
      blood products like blood transfusions or platelets, prior to receiving the VSTs he/she may
      be given diphenhydramine (Benadryl) and acetaminophen (Tylenol). The patient will remain in
      the clinic for at least one hour after the infusion.

      All participants on this study will be infused with the same number (dose) of cells. If the
      patient has persistent infection after the first dose, the investigators would discuss this
      with the patient and allow them to receive up to four more treatments if there were no
      complications with prior infusions. These additional treatments might be with cells from the
      same donor, or if the investigators feel that there is another donor whose cells might be
      better for the patient, the investigators would use cells from a different donor. This second
      product will be administered at the same dose level 14 days after the patient's initial
      infusion, and any additional infusions should be at least 14 days apart. After each VST
      infusion, the patient will be monitored as described above.

      After the patient receives the cells the patient's transplant doctor will monitor the levels
      of the virus the subject is infected with in their blood.

      The patient will continue to be followed by their doctor(s) after the injection. They will be
      seen in the clinic by research staff for follow up every week for 6 weeks. To learn more
      about the way the VSTs are working in the patient's body, up to an extra 30-40 ml (6-8
      teaspoons) of blood may be taken before the infusion and then at 2, 4, and 6 weeks. Blood
      should come from the central intravenous line, and should not require extra needle sticks.

      Any leftover samples of blood may be used to help future research. The specimens may be kept
      for a long time. These specimens and information about the patient's circumstances may be
      shared with other cancer researchers. Although there will be a record identifying under what
      circumstances these specimens were obtained, under all circumstances the patient's identity
      will be kept confidential.

      Study Duration : The patient will be on the study for approximately 42 days after the
      patient's infusion. If the patient receives additional doses of the T cells as described
      above, the patient will be followed for 42 days after their last dose of T-cells.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Limiting toxicity: (DLT) rate by CTCAE v5</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety of HLA-matched VSTs: Safety including acute GVHD (Graft-versus-host disease) grades III-IV of the last dose of VSTs, secondary graft failure, or grades 3-5 non-hematological adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate: (The viral load of the virus (or viruses) by viral PRC (replication-competent retrovirus) within 42 days)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Antiviral Responses: Antiviral responses within 42 days after the first dose of VSTs.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Viral Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-matched VSTs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Partially HLA-matched VSTs will be thawed and given by intravenous injection. Patients will receive 2 x 107 partially HLA-matched VSTs/m2 as a single infusion. In the rare case where insufficient banked cell product is available, a lower number of cells may be infused with agreement of the principal investigator, patient and/or guardian and the treatment team
Additional doses may be from the same donor or a different donor based on available cell lines and patient/disease factors. Decision to switch to a different donor can be made by the principal investigator based on factors that include sequential treatment of different viral infections, concerns for immune escape of the targeted virus and/or availability of a better matched or otherwise superior VST line. Additional treatments will only be given following the agreement of the patient, treating physician, and investigator. This process can be repeated as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HLA-matched VSTs</intervention_name>
    <description>An alternative approach that bypasses the need to grow VSTs for individual patients is to bank closely HLA-matched allogeneic VSTs that could be available as an &quot;off the shelf&quot; product.
The HLA-matched VST product is to produce immune activity to CMV, Adv, BK virus and EBV in all recipients.
Most recently our group extended this &quot;off the shelf&quot; approach to five viruses using the T cell product manufactured in 10 days. The VSTs were administered to 38 patients with 45 infections in a phase II clinical trial. A single infusion produced a cumulative complete or partial response rate of 92% overall and the following rates by virus: 100% for BKV (n = 16), 94% for CMV (n = 17), 71% for AdV (n = 7), 100% for EBV (n = 2), and 67% for HHV-6 (human herpesvirus) (n = 3).</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-matched VSTs</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients has to have received a prior myeloablative or non-myeloablative allogeneic
             hematopoietic stem cell transplant using either bone marrow, single/double cord blood
             or PBSC

          2. Cells administered as:

               1. Treatment of relapsed or persistent reactivation or infection for EBV, CMV,
                  adenovirus, and/or BK virus despite standard therapy. Multiple infections are
                  eligible to enroll.

               2. Early treatment for single or multiple infections with EBV, CMV, adenovirus,
                  and/or BK virus following treatment failure or in patients who are unable to
                  tolerate standard therapy

               3. Treatment of JC virus infection

          3. Steroids less than or equal to 1.0 mg/kg/day methylprednisolone (or equivalent)

          4. Hgb ≥ 7.0 gm/dl

          5. Available VSTs must be partially HLA matched and verified

          6. Negative pregnancy test (if female of childbearing potential after reduced intensity
             conditioning)

          7. Patient or parent/guardian capable of providing informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Received ATG (anti-thymocyte globulin), Campath or other T cell immunosuppressive
             monoclonal antibodies in the last 28 days.

          2. Patients with other uncontrolled infections

          3. Patients who are less than 28 days removed from their allogeneic hematopoietic stem
             cell transplant or who have received donor lymphocyte infusions (DLI) within 28 days.

          4. Evidence of GVHD &gt;= grade 2

          5. Active and uncontrolled relapse of malignancy

          6. Requirement for FiO2 (fraction of inspired oxygen) &gt; 50% oxygen to maintain arterial
             oxygen saturation &gt; 90%.Note: patients requiring oxygen at FiO2&lt;=50% to maintain
             arterial oxygen saturation &gt;90% are eligible to receive VSTs if the reason for this
             oxygen requirement is believed attributable to the virus being treated
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Craddock, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>John Craddock, MD</last_name>
    <phone>832-824-1583</phone>
    <email>jacraddo@txch.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wendy Callejas</last_name>
    <phone>832-824-1583</phone>
    <email>wlcalle@texaschildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Craddock</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cytomegalovirus (CMV)</keyword>
  <keyword>BK virus</keyword>
  <keyword>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)</keyword>
  <keyword>adenovirus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenoviridae Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

