<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03973099</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KCMC07OT066</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03973099</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Double Blinded, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Clinical Study for Nelumbinis Semen</brief_title>
  <official_title>Double Blinded, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Clinical Study for Evaluating Anti-stress Effects of Nelumbinis Semen by 2 Week Administration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GMP BIO Co., LTD.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GMP BIO Co., LTD.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nelumbinis Semen, has been widely used as treatment of post-menopause symptoms in women for
      hundreds of years in many Asian countries. This study examines whether PM011, standardized
      herbal medicine made from Nelumbinis Semen, treats stress in above 5 of BDI score of human
      subjects and discusses its potential as treatment for depressed patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nelumbinis Semen, has been widely used as treatment of post-menopause symptoms in women for
      hundreds of years in many Asian countries. This study examines whether PM011, standardized
      herbal medicine made from Nelumbinis Semen, treats stress in above 5 of BDI score of human
      subjects and discusses its potential as treatment for depressed patients. Subjects were
      divided into three groups, the placebo-treated group (n = 10), the PM011-2.4 g treated group
      (n = 11) and PM011-4.8 g treated group (n = 11) per day. Alpha/Beta ratio of
      electroencephalogram (EGG), Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) and Stress Response Inventory
      (SRI) were conducted in order to measure changes in stress before and after 2 weeks of PM011
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 7, 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 30, 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Double blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical study for evaluating anti-stress effects of Nelumbinis Semen</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double-blind study : Participants and investigators do not know which treatment is placebo or treatment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory (BDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline BDI score at 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>BDI is a 21 item, self rated inventory with each item rated with a set of four possible answer choices of increasing intensity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress Response Inventory or Test (SRI or SRT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline SRI or SRT score at 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>SRI is highly reliable and valid, and that it is utilized as an effective measure of stress for research in stress-related fields in Korea. SRI is a total of 39 response items under the seven subscales. The seven subscales are divided into tension (A), aggression (B), somatization (C), anger (D), depression (E), fatigue (F), and frustration (G). When the test is scored, a value of 0 to 4 is assigned for each answer and then the total score is compared to a key to determine the stress's severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alpha/beta ratio of electroencephalogram (EEG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline Alpha/beta ratio of electroencephalogram (EEG) at 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Electroencephalogram (EEG) is used to measure the brain waves. Each wave pattern is associated with different mood state and state of consciousness. Alpha is one of four basic brain waves (delta, theta, alpha and beta) which make up the EEG. Alpha is seen in wakefulness where there is relaxed and effortless alertness. Beta is seen in highly stressful situations, and where there is difficult mental concentration and focus. Therefore, high alpha and less beta waves have been used as indices of relaxation, arousal, anti-stress, and better concentration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in the placebo group received the equivalent amount of starch and lactose mixture capsules and administered with the same schedule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PM011</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PM011 is a 400 mg hard gelatin capsule containing water extracts of Nelumbinis Semen. The sprayed-dry extract of the herbal medicine used was purchased from Sun Ten pharmaceutical company in Taiwan. Each participant received twelve capsules of PM011, which divided into 2.4 g treatment or 4.8 g treatment group or placebo daily for two weeks and was instructed to take six capsules after breakfast and six capsules after dinner.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PM011</intervention_name>
    <description>PM011 is a 400 mg hard gelatin capsule containing water extracts of Nelumbinis Semen. The sprayed-dry extract of the herbal medicine used was purchased from Sun Ten pharmaceutical company in Taiwan. Each participant received twelve capsules of PM011, which divided into 2.4 g treatment or 4.8 g treatment group or placebo daily for two weeks and was instructed to take six capsules after breakfast and six capsules after dinner. Subjects in the placebo group received the equivalent amount of starch and lactose mixture capsules and administered with the same schedule.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PM011</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nelumbinis Semen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        &lt;Inclusion Criteria&gt;

          -  Volunteers were selected based on following meet conditions;Men and women, who have
             willingness and capacity to comply with the study protocol, are included if they were
             aged 18 to 65 years.

          -  Volunteers, who can understand Korean and English alphabet are selected.

          -  Volunteers, who can communicate with clinical trial performer fully, comply with the
             all tests and medical examinations performed by study protocol.

          -  All volunteers or their protectors understand purpose of study fully and sign their
             names or seal.

          -  Volunteers, who do not come under exclusion criteria are selected.

          -  BDI score of Volunteers, who can be &gt;= 5.

        &lt;Exclusion Criteria&gt;

          -  Volunteers were excluded if they are applied to following meet conditions; Volunteers
             with fasting glucose level over 126 mg/dl.

          -  Volunteers with hypertension as having over 140 mmHg of systolic blood pressure or 90
             mmHg of diastolic blood pressure.

          -  Volunteers with blood thyroid stimulating hormone below 0.3 or over 4.0.

          -  Men with hemoglobin below 13.0 g/dl and women with hemoglobin below 12.0 g/dl.

          -  Volunteers with abnormality of liver function as having over 1.5 times of normal
             levels of ALT or AST.

          -  Patients with infections in upper airways or chronic diseases.

          -  Mental illness patients with such as alcoholism.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

