<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03974984</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SJ-704</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03974984</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anesthesia and Immunological and Oxidative Stress in Relation to Abdominal Cancer Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>ANIMOX</acronym>
  <official_title>Anesthesia and Immunological and Oxidative Stress in Relation to Abdominal Cancer Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Copenhagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Copenhagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer is a frequent type of cancer accounting for 600,000 deaths annually.
      Surgical resection remains the best treatment for long-term survival. However, studies
      suggest that events in the perioperative period can induce metastasis formation and tumor
      growth. Tumor cells are released into the blood stream during surgery and the surgical stress
      may create a favorable environment for dissemination of tumor cells into distant tissue. This
      is done by a cascade of pro-cancerous catecholamines, prostaglandins and cytokines combined
      with an impaired anti-cancerous cell mediated immune response.

      Until recently, focus on the anesthetic management of cancer patients has been limited.
      Relatively small alterations in the perioperative anesthetic management may play a tremendous
      role in tumor progression. Optimizing anesthesia to reduce the surgical stress response could
      improve recurrence rates and long-term outcomes for cancer patients by inhibiting
      perioperative metastasis formation. Regional anesthesia and amide local anesthetics are
      suspected to calm the immunologic storm of prostaglandins, catecholamines and cytokines when
      used in the perioperative phase. Furthermore, volatile inhalational anesthesia is thought to
      modulate the immune system in a pro-cancerous way, while propofol may have opposite effects.
      Many of these recent studies are statistically underpowered and susceptible to bias, and
      experts in cancer treatment and anesthesia have emphasized the need for further research
      within this specific field.

      In this study the investigators aim to characterize differences in the immunologic response
      to surgery between inhalational, total intravenous and epidural anesthesia. This will be done
      by analyzing blood samples obtained in the perioperative period in patients undergoing
      different modes of anesthesia. The Investigators will furthermore describe the quality of
      recovery for patients anesthetized with the different methods
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and Purpose Colorectal cancer is a frequent type of cancer accounting for 600,000
      deaths annually. Surgical resection remains the best treatment for long-term survival.
      However, studies suggest that events in the perioperative period can induce metastasis
      formation and tumor growth. Tumor cells are released into the blood stream during surgery and
      the surgical stress may create a favorable environment for dissemination of tumor cells into
      distant tissue. This is done by a cascade of pro-cancerous catecholamines, prostaglandins and
      cytokines combined with an impaired anti-cancerous cell mediated immune response.

      Until recently, focus on the anesthetic management of cancer patients has been limited.
      Relatively small alterations in the perioperative anesthetic management may play a tremendous
      role in tumor progression. Optimizing anesthesia to reduce the surgical stress response could
      improve recurrence rates and long-term outcomes for cancer patients by inhibiting
      perioperative metastasis formation. Regional anesthesia and amide local anesthetics are
      suspected to calm the immunologic storm of prostaglandins, catecholamines and cytokines when
      used in the perioperative phase. Furthermore, volatile inhalational anesthesia is thought to
      modulate the immune system in a pro-cancerous way, while propofol may have opposite effects.
      Many of these recent studies are statistically underpowered and susceptible to bias, and
      experts in cancer treatment and anesthesia have emphasized the need for further research
      within this specific field.

      In this study the investigators aim to characterize differences in the immunologic response
      to surgery between patients anesthetized with TIVA, epidural and NSAID and patients
      anesthetized with total intravenous anesthesia alone. This will be done by analyzing blood
      samples obtained in the perioperative period in patients undergoing different modes of
      anesthesia. The Investigators will furthermore describe the quality of recovery for patients
      anesthetized with the different methods Objectives The investigators hypothesize that the
      immunologic response to surgery and metastasis progression are influenced by the anesthetic
      technique.

      Methods The study is initiated by Center for Surgical Science, Department of Surgery, Zealand
      University Hospital.

      The study will take place at Hvidovre Hospital. This is a Danish university hospital. It
      supports 500,000 people and is one of four main emergency hospitals in Copenhagen Denmark.
      About 300 laparoscopic colon resections are performed at this facility every year.

      Intervention Participants will undergo laparoscopic colon resection for cancer. They will be
      anaesthetized according to the standard operating procedure at Hvidovre Hospital with the
      exception that no dexamethasone is administered as it could modulate the immune response.
      This includes anesthesia induction and maintenance with intravenous propofol and
      remifentanil. Patients will receive 4 mg ondansetron at the end of anesthesia.

      A thoracic epidural catheter will be installed preoperatively and kept for up to three days.
      After an initial bolus with bupivacaine, continuous infusion of bupivacaine and sufentanil
      will be used to maintain the epidural analgesic effect. Postoperatively the epidural will be
      paused or discontinued if it is displaced or if side effects occur. It will only be
      re-installed if there is still need of neuraxial analgesia.

      Patients will follow a standard Enhanced Recovery After Surgery (ERAS) protocol used at the
      facility.

      Blood samples will be obtained before surgery and at four time points postoperatively and
      patient files will be assessed for adverse events within 30 days from surgery.

      Withdrawal criteria:

      Patients can be withdrawn from the study for any of the following reasons:

        -  Failure to adhere to the anesthesia intervention described above- including failure to
           install effective continuous epidural anesthesia.

        -  Adverse events after surgery Any complication over grade 2 in Clavien-Dindo (26)
           classification Blood transfusion Deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism Anastomotic
           leak Acute renal failure Infection (wound infection or systemic infection) during the
           observation period.

        -  After consultation patients can be withdrawn due to withdrawal of informed consent to
           participate in the study at the patients' own request at any time for any reason.

      Population:

      Study group: The &quot;Hvidovre population&quot;:

      The investigators will include patients undergoing laparoscopic hemicolectomy for cancer
      scheduled for anesthesia with total intravenous anesthesia combined with epidural anesthesia
      on Hvidovre Hospital according to the intervention described above.

      Control group: The &quot;Zealand University Hospital population&quot; The immunological and oxidative
      stress in relation to abdominal surgery (IMOX) study is ongoing at Zealand University
      Hospital, Roskilde. It is a prospective explorative study cohort that consists of 60 patients
      undergoing laparoscopic colorectal cancer surgery. The aim of the study is to characterize
      the immunological and oxidative stress response to surgery. Outcomes similar to the primary
      and secondary outcomes of the ANIMOX-study are included in the IMOX-study. Patients are
      already included in the IMOX-study and blood samples are collected and kept in a bio bank.

      The investigators will retrieve data on our main outcomes from the IMOX study in our
      analysis. Only electronic data will be used and no biologic material will be transferred from
      the IMOX project to ANIMOX. The population will be stratified according to anesthetic
      technique, which, according to the standard operating procedure, is either total intravenous
      anesthesia with propofol and remifentanil or volatile anesthesia with sevoflurane combined
      with a fast acting opioid (remifentanil or sufentanil). Patients anaesthetized with other
      techniques including epidural or other regional blocks will be excluded from the analysis.

      Biological samples To characterize the immunological response to surgery the investigators
      obtain blood samples for analysis on postoperative day -1, 1, 2, 3 and 10 (or at the visit on
      day 10-14 where pathology results are given).

      Handling of blood samples Blood samples will be drawn by a trained professional and analyzed
      immediately at the standard lab facilities at Hvidovre Hospital and destroyed immediately
      hereafter. The results will be accessible in Sundhedsplatformen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 4, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio from preoperatively to day 1 postoperatively</measure>
    <time_frame>From preoperatively to day 1 postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in neutrophil to lymphocyte ratio from day 0 to day 1. The ratio will be estimated using absolute numbers from differential counts pre and postoperatively. A high neutrophil to lymfocyte ratio is related to poor outcome after cancer surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in quality of recovery-15 score from preoperatively to day 1 postoperatively.</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference from preoperatively to day 1 postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The QoR-15 questionnaire results in a score of 0-150 where a high score reflects good recovery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Anesthesia</condition>
  <condition>Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Hvidovre population&quot;:</arm_group_label>
    <description>We will include patients undergoing laparoscopic hemicolectomy for cancer scheduled for anesthesia with total intravenous anesthesia combined with epidural anesthesia and perioperative NSAID on Hvidovre Hospital.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Zealand University Hospital population&quot;</arm_group_label>
    <description>The immunological and oxidative stress in relation to abdominal surgery (IMOX) study is ongoing at Zealand University Hospital, Roskilde. It is a prospective explorative study cohort that consists of 60 patients undergoing laparoscopic colorectal cancer surgery.
The population has been anesthetized according to the standard operating procedure with either total intravenous anesthesia with propofol and remifentanil or volatile anesthesia with sevoflurane combined with a fast acting opioid (remifentanil or sufentanil). Patients anaesthetized with other techniques including epidural or other regional blocks will be excluded from the analysis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Colon Resection</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients undergo laparoscopic colon cancer resection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Hvidovre population&quot;:</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Zealand University Hospital population&quot;</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epidural anesthesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Epidural inserted preoperatively and kept for 1 day postoperatively</description>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Hvidovre population&quot;:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NSAID</intervention_name>
    <description>NSAID administered according to standard operating procedure postoperatively</description>
    <arm_group_label>The &quot;Hvidovre population&quot;:</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Standard blood samples analyzed immediately after sampling. These include Hgb, Leucocytes
      including a differential count, thrombocytes, ALAT, LDH, Alkaline phosphatase, bilirubin,
      INR, albumin, Na, K, Creatinine, CRP and Glucose.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We will include patients undergoing laparoscopic hemicolectomy for cancer scheduled for
        anesthesia with total intravenous anesthesia combined with epidural anesthesia on Hvidovre
        Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients over 18 years

          2. Patients diagnosed with colorectal cancer (UICC stadium I-III) and scheduled for
             laparoscopic hemicolectomy.

          3. ASA class I-III (Classification of the American Society of Anesthesiology)

          4. Patients scheduled for anesthesia with propofol, remifentanil and epidural anesthesia.

          5. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known immune-defects

          2. Patients undergoing neoadjuvant chemo or radiotherapy

          3. History of previous cancer

          4. Patients in immunomodulatory treatment within last 6 months

          5. Daily oral or intravenous steroid-use

          6. Patients that have undergone major surgery within one month before planned colon
             resection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rune Hasselager, MD</last_name>
    <phone>31104653</phone>
    <phone_ext>0045</phone_ext>
    <email>rubh@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ismail Gögenur, DMSc</last_name>
    <email>igo@regionsjaelland.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hvidovre University hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hvidovre</city>
        <state>Capital Region</state>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demicheli R, Fornili M, Ambrogi F, Higgins K, Boyd JA, Biganzoli E, Kelsey CR. Recurrence dynamics for non-small-cell lung cancer: effect of surgery on the development of metastases. J Thorac Oncol. 2012 Apr;7(4):723-30. doi: 10.1097/JTO.0b013e31824a9022.</citation>
    <PMID>22425921</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demicheli R, Biganzoli E, Boracchi P, Greco M, Retsky MW. Recurrence dynamics does not depend on the recurrence site. Breast Cancer Res. 2008;10(5):R83. doi: 10.1186/bcr2152. Epub 2008 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>18844974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ciechanowicz SJ, Ma D. Anaesthesia for oncological surgery - can it really influence cancer recurrence? Anaesthesia. 2016 Feb;71(2):127-31. doi: 10.1111/anae.13342. Epub 2015 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26669960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freeman J, Connolly C, Buggy D. Mechanisms of Metastasis of Solid Organ Tumors in the Perioperative Period. Int Anesthesiol Clin. 2016 Fall;54(4):29-47. doi: 10.1097/AIA.0000000000000124. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27648889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horowitz M, Neeman E, Sharon E, Ben-Eliyahu S. Exploiting the critical perioperative period to improve long-term cancer outcomes. Nat Rev Clin Oncol. 2015 Apr;12(4):213-26. doi: 10.1038/nrclinonc.2014.224. Epub 2015 Jan 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25601442</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamaguchi K, Takagi Y, Aoki S, Futamura M, Saji S. Significant detection of circulating cancer cells in the blood by reverse transcriptase-polymerase chain reaction during colorectal cancer resection. Ann Surg. 2000 Jul;232(1):58-65.</citation>
    <PMID>10862196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Demicheli R, Retsky MW, Hrushesky WJ, Baum M, Gukas ID. The effects of surgery on tumor growth: a century of investigations. Ann Oncol. 2008 Nov;19(11):1821-8. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdn386. Epub 2008 Jun 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18550576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coffey JC, Wang JH, Smith MJ, Bouchier-Hayes D, Cotter TG, Redmond HP. Excisional surgery for cancer cure: therapy at a cost. Lancet Oncol. 2003 Dec;4(12):760-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14662433</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duff S, Connolly C, Buggy DJ. Adrenergic, Inflammatory, and Immune Function in the Setting of Oncological Surgery: Their Effects on Cancer Progression and the Role of the Anesthetic Technique in their Modulation. Int Anesthesiol Clin. 2016 Fall;54(4):48-57. doi: 10.1097/AIA.0000000000000120. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27648890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartal I, Melamed R, Greenfeld K, Atzil S, Glasner A, Domankevich V, Naor R, Beilin B, Yardeni IZ, Ben-Eliyahu S. Immune perturbations in patients along the perioperative period: alterations in cell surface markers and leukocyte subtypes before and after surgery. Brain Behav Immun. 2010 Mar;24(3):376-86. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2009.02.010. Epub 2009 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>19254757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai LH, de Souza CT, Bélanger S, Ly L, Alkayyal AA, Zhang J, Rintoul JL, Ananth AA, Lam T, Breitbach CJ, Falls TJ, Kirn DH, Bell JC, Makrigiannis AP, Auer RA. Preventing postoperative metastatic disease by inhibiting surgery-induced dysfunction in natural killer cells. Cancer Res. 2013 Jan 1;73(1):97-107. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-1993. Epub 2012 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23090117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmitti G, Soliz J, Aloia TA, Gottumukkala V, Cata JP, Tzeng CW, Vauthey JN. Positive Impact of Epidural Analgesia on Oncologic Outcomes in Patients Undergoing Resection of Colorectal Liver Metastases. Ann Surg Oncol. 2016 Mar;23(3):1003-11. doi: 10.1245/s10434-015-4933-1. Epub 2015 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>26511261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hiller JG, Hacking MB, Link EK, Wessels KL, Riedel BJ. Perioperative epidural analgesia reduces cancer recurrence after gastro-oesophageal surgery. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2014 Mar;58(3):281-90. doi: 10.1111/aas.12255. Epub 2014 Jan 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24383612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottschalk A, Ford JG, Regelin CC, You J, Mascha EJ, Sessler DI, Durieux ME, Nemergut EC. Association between epidural analgesia and cancer recurrence after colorectal cancer surgery. Anesthesiology. 2010 Jul;113(1):27-34. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181de6d0d.</citation>
    <PMID>20508494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Exadaktylos AK, Buggy DJ, Moriarty DC, Mascha E, Sessler DI. Can anesthetic technique for primary breast cancer surgery affect recurrence or metastasis? Anesthesiology. 2006 Oct;105(4):660-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17006061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piegeler T, Schläpfer M, Dull RO, Schwartz DE, Borgeat A, Minshall RD, Beck-Schimmer B. Clinically relevant concentrations of lidocaine and ropivacaine inhibit TNFα-induced invasion of lung adenocarcinoma cells in vitro by blocking the activation of Akt and focal adhesion kinase. Br J Anaesth. 2015 Nov;115(5):784-91. doi: 10.1093/bja/aev341.</citation>
    <PMID>26475807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrne K, Levins KJ, Buggy DJ. Can anesthetic-analgesic technique during primary cancer surgery affect recurrence or metastasis? Can J Anaesth. 2016 Feb;63(2):184-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26497721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi QY, Zhang SJ, Liu L, Chen QS, Yu LN, Zhang FJ, Yan M. Sevoflurane promotes the expansion of glioma stem cells through activation of hypoxia-inducible factors in vitro. Br J Anaesth. 2015 May;114(5):825-30. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu402. Epub 2014 Dec 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25492570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luo X, Zhao H, Hennah L, Ning J, Liu J, Tu H, Ma D. Impact of isoflurane on malignant capability of ovarian cancer in vitro. Br J Anaesth. 2015 May;114(5):831-9. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu408. Epub 2014 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25501719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu YJ, Li SY, Cheng Q, Chen WK, Wang SL, Ren Y, Miao CH. Effects of anaesthesia on proliferation, invasion and apoptosis of LoVo colon cancer cells in vitro. Anaesthesia. 2016 Feb;71(2):147-54. doi: 10.1111/anae.13331. Epub 2015 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26669824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stollings LM, Jia LJ, Tang P, Dou H, Lu B, Xu Y. Immune Modulation by Volatile Anesthetics. Anesthesiology. 2016 Aug;125(2):399-411. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000001195. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27286478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wigmore TJ, Mohammed K, Jhanji S. Long-term Survival for Patients Undergoing Volatile versus IV Anesthesia for Cancer Surgery: A Retrospective Analysis. Anesthesiology. 2016 Jan;124(1):69-79. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000000936.</citation>
    <PMID>26556730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buggy DJ, Borgeat A, Cata J, Doherty DG, Doornebal CW, Forget P, Gottumukkala V, Gottschalk A, Gupta A, Gupta K, Hales TG, Hemmings HC, Hollmann MW, Kurz A, Ma D, Parat MO, Sessler DI, Shorten G, Singleton P. Consensus statement from the BJA Workshop on Cancer and Anaesthesia. Br J Anaesth. 2015 Jan;114(1):2-3. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeu262. Epub 2014 Aug 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25104229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Piegeler T, Beck-Schimmer B. Anesthesia and colorectal cancer - The perioperative period as a window of opportunity? Eur J Surg Oncol. 2016 Sep;42(9):1286-95. doi: 10.1016/j.ejso.2016.05.004. Epub 2016 May 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27265039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Copenhagen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rune Børch Hasselager</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>May 23, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/84/NCT03974984/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

