<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03974399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RI-Bacopa-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03974399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BDNF Levels After Bacopa</brief_title>
  <official_title>Longitudinal Assessment of BDNF Levels in Healthy Subjects Taking Bacopa Monnieri</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roskamp Institute Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Florida Department of Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roskamp Institute Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF) is a well-known neurotrophic factor important for
      learning, memory, and synaptogenesis. Healthy activities such as exercise are believed to
      raise BDNF, while stress is associated with lower BDNF. What is not well understood is if
      there are certain supplements that may raise BDNF over time. Bacopa monnieri is well
      characterized nutraceutical. Animal and pre-clinical data support multiple beneficial
      mechanisms, including raising BDNF and increasing synaptogenesis. Additionally, small studies
      have shown Bacopa enhances cognition and improves mood. We would like to investigate if BDNF
      level changes in people after starting Bacopa.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single site two-visit, 12-week, open label, trial to evaluate the safety,
      tolerability, and potential effects of Bacopa on BDNF, MoCA and GDS. Potentially eligible
      subjects will be invited to screening (Visit 1) at the study site. Subjects will sign an
      informed consent followed by collection of medical history and history of current
      medications, have their height, weight, vital signs (blood pressure, pulse, and temperature)
      measured, complete study assessments (MoCA , BDS and LEC) Routine clinical laboratory tests
      (hematology and chemistry) will be performed. Blood samples will be taken for analysis of
      BDNF and genetics (APOE, BDNF).

      Subjects will be instructed to orally self-administer the provided supplement (Bacopa)
      preferably with food with no dietary restrictions once a day in the morning.

      Subjects will be contacted by phone at 1 week (+/- 3 days) to be reminded to go to two pills
      per day, 1 month (+/-1 week) to check on compliance or any AE's and 2 months (+/- 1 week) to
      report any Adverse events for review by the Principal Investigator.

      Subjects will return to the study site for Visit 2 at the end of 12 weeks (+/- 1 week). Study
      staff will question subjects about any changes in the subject's health since the first visit.
      They will be asked about their exercise activity and if there have been any changes to their
      LEC-5. Subjects will have their weight and vital signs measured. Routine clinical laboratory
      tests (hematology and chemistry) will be performed, and blood samples will be saved for
      analysis of Bacopa and other biomarkers
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Brain Derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>a. Change in BDNF levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Brain Derived Neurotropic factor (BDNF) signaling pathway</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in BDNF signaling pathway</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montreal Cognitive Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA). Score range 0-30.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Geriatric Depression Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS). Score range 0-15.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Memory</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>study enrollment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>all participants will take dietary supplement, Bacopa Monnieri, daily for 3 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bacopa Monnieri</intervention_name>
    <description>subjects will take Bacopa Monnieri daily for 3 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>study enrollment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males or females of any ethnicity, at 60 to 78 on day of screening.

          2. Have a score of 25 or above on MoCA (Montreal Cognitive assessment).

          3. Have a score of 9 or below on GDS (Geriatric Depression Scale)

          4. Provide written informed consent.

          5. Be able and willing to follow instructions, participate in study assessments, and be
             present for the required study visits.

          6. Otherwise stable medical history and general health up to the discrepancy of the PI.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have contraindications, allergy, or sensitivity to the study product or their
             components.

          2. Have any significant illness or condition that could, in the Investigator's or
             sub-Investigator's opinion, be expected to interfere with the study parameters or
             study conduct or put the subject at significant risk. These may include but are not
             limited to: untreated chronic hypertension; receiving chemotherapy; depression
             requiring medical intervention on a daily basis; myocardial infarction within six
             months of screening; renal failure; and/or hepatic failure.

          3. Have a current unstable medical condition (e.g., symptomatic uncontrolled diabetes
             mellitus), or a condition that might affect their ability to participate (e.g., cancer
             requiring frequent medical visits for chemotherapy).

          4. Have values on standard clinical laboratory assessments that are deemed medically
             significant (show evidence of untreated significant medical illness or pose a risk of
             significant intercurrent illness during the study in the opinion of the investigator).

          5. Currently taking any medication classified by the FDA as an anti-depressant or have
             discontinued one of these types of medications within 30 days of screening.

          6. Currently abusing drugs or alcohol, and/or have a history of drug or alcohol
             dependence within six months of entering this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>78 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Keegan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Roskamp Institute Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lois Davis, RN, BSN, MA</last_name>
    <phone>9412568018</phone>
    <phone_ext>3056</phone_ext>
    <email>ldavis@roskampinstitute.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Patterson</last_name>
    <phone>9412568018</phone>
    <phone_ext>3008</phone_ext>
    <email>dpatterson@roskampclinic.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Roskamp Institute, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarasota</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34243</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lois Davis</last_name>
      <phone>941-256-8018</phone>
      <phone_ext>9412568018</phone_ext>
      <email>ldavis@roskampinstitute.net</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Adrienne Scott</last_name>
      <phone>9412568018</phone>
      <phone_ext>3007</phone_ext>
      <email>ascott@roskampclinic.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

