<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03974451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Finevision vs Symfony IOL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03974451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparison of FineVision Intraocular Lenses vs Symfony Intraocular Lenses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Visual Performance After Trifocal vs Extended Range of Vision Presbyopia-correcting Intraocular Lenses</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Physiol</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alexandria University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Physiol</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective randomised open-label study with the aim to compare the visual
      performance of the trifocal FineVision® IOL versus the extended range of vision Symfony® IOL
      after phaco-emulsification cataract surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With the advent of a new intraocular lens (IOL) materials, technologies and advanced optics,
      higher spectacle independence after surgery is now possible.

      Multifocal IOLs work by splitting light into different foci, which is known to generate
      photic effects. Trifocal optics, which have been available on the European market since 2010,
      offer spectacle independence in most cases. Typically, visual acuity is maintained throughout
      the whole range of vision from distance to near vision, and general patient satisfaction has
      proven that trifocal IOLs are well tolerated by patients.

      Patients having irregular corneal astigmatism, large pupils and weak zonules were considered
      unsuitable candidates for multifocal IOLs, while patients who aim for spectacle independence
      and with low pre-operative regular astigmatism were considered to be good candidates.

      The Fine Vision IOL (PhysIOL®; Liège, Belgium) is a diffractive trifocal IOL that provides an
      intermediate focus at 1.75 D and a near focus at 3.5 D (both at the IOL plane). This
      corresponds to a nominal intermediate add of approximately +1,15 D and near add of about 2,25
      D at the corneal plane, depending on the geometry of the patient's eye. This intermediate
      focal point is expected to improve patient satisfaction relative to bifocal IOLs, since
      bifocal IOLs have a greater drop off in visual acuity (VA) in the intermediate range. There
      is a concern that the addition of a third focal point may increase halos, However, a
      relatively small percentage of energy is dedicated to intermediate vision when compared to
      distance and near vision. The trifocal diffractive structure asymmetrically directs incident
      light to distant (50%) intermediate (20%) and near (30%) focal points, independent of pupil
      diameter (up to 4,5 mm).

      The FineVision is an aspheric trifocal IOL composed of 25% hydrophilic acrylic material with
      a blue light and ultraviolet light blocker. It has a total diameter of 10,75 mm and an optic
      body diameter of 6,15 mm.

      The Tecnis Symfony is an extended range of vision IOL based on diffractive achromatic
      technology. The IOL has an achromatic diffractive pattern that elongates the focus and
      compensates for the chromatic aberration of the cornea. According to the manufacturer, halos
      are not expected with this IOL, because it provides an elongated focal area rather than one
      or various focal points. The IOL has a biconvex wavefront-designed anterior aspheric surface
      and a posterior achromatic diffractive surface. The total diameter of the IOL is 13.0 mm, and
      the optic zone diameter is 6.0 mm. It is an ultraviolet-filtering hydrophobic acrylic
      material with a refractive index of 1,47 at 35° C.

      This is a prospective randomised open-label study with the aim to compare the visual
      performance of the trifocal FineVision® IOL versus the extended range of vision Symphony® IOL
      after phaco-emulsification cataract surgery.

      All patients will undergo and complete preoperative ophthalmologic examinations including
      refractive status, uncorrected and corrected near and distance visual acuities, biometry and
      keratometry.

      Postoperative, all patients will receive topical antibiotic treatment for 1 week and topical
      steroid tapered treatment for 4 weeks as well as NSAID topical treatment for 4 weeks. All
      patients will be followed up after 2 days, 1 week and 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Corrected Distance Visual Acuity at 6m (CDVA) - monocular</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>CDVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 6m distance with best aided corrective glasses according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected Distance Visual Acuity at 6m (UDVA) - monocular</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>UDVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 6m distance according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected Intermediate Visual Acuity at 65cm (UIVA) - monocular</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>UIVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 65cm distance. The examination is done without corrective glasses and according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance Corrected Intermediate Visual Acuity at 65cm (DCIVA) - monocular</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>DCIVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 65cm distance with corrective glasses for far distance according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uncorrected Near Visual Acuity at 35cm (UNVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>UNVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 35cm distance. The examination is done without corrective glasses and according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distance Corrected Near Visual Acuity at 35cm (DCNVA) - monocular</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>DCNVA is measured with ETDRS charts placed in 35cm distance with corrective glasses for far distance according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014. This assessment is done monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Defocus Curve</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the visual acuity for different distances, defocus curves under photopic light conditions are measured. This test is performed with best distance corrected refraction and spherical additions ranging from -4.0 D to 0.0 D. This examination is performed monocularly.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Contrast Sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>Contrast Sensitivity under photopic light conditions using the CSV-1000 contrast test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>National Eye Institute Visual Functioning Questionnaire - 25 (VFQ-25)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>For this study, the validated and verified questionnaire VFQ-25 (National Eye Institute) will be used. The VFQ-25 consists of a base set of 25 vision- targeted questions representing 11 vision-related constructs (General Health, General Vision, Ocular Pain,Near Activities, Distance Activities, Vision Specific (Social Functioning, Mental Health, Role Difficulties, Dependency), Driving, Color Vision, Peripheral Vision), plus an additional single-item general health rating question.
The minimum score is 0 and the maximum score is 100 for each construct. Higher values represent a better outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Manifest Refraction</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperative</time_frame>
    <description>The manifested refraction is measured by means of a phoropter. The data contains values for sphere, cylinder and axis of cylinder according to International Standards Organization (ISO) 11979-7:2014.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Lens Opacities</condition>
  <condition>Presbyopia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IOL implantation experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implantation of the PhysIOL FineVision POD F® IOL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IOL implantation active comparator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Implantation of the Abbott Medical Optics, Inc. Tecnis Symfony® IOL.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IOL implantation experimental</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of of PhysIOL trifocal FineVision® POD F IOL</description>
    <arm_group_label>IOL implantation experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IOL implantation active comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of the Abbott Medical Optics, Inc. Tecnis Symfony® IOL</description>
    <arm_group_label>IOL implantation active comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Cataract patients requesting independence from spectacles

          2. Potential visual acuity of 0.0 logMar

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unrealistic expectations (sharp clear vision is the main concern of the patient)

          2. Ocular pathology besides cataract (glaucoma, macular degeneration, retinopathies,
             corneal opacities, corneal guttata.. etc.)

          3. Previous refractive surgery

          4. Expected pathology after surgery (p.e. uveitis, diabetic retinopathy, PEX)

          5. Preoperative corneal astigmatism of &gt; 1.0 D

          6. Any intraocular or postoperative complication

          7. Dry eye disease

          8. History of ocular trauma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohammed H. F. Ghoneem, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Alexandria,</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Ophtalmology, Alexandria Main University Hospital (AMUH)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alexandria</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 11, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 2, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Physiol</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mohammed Ghoneem</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator and MD Alexandria University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intraocular Lens</keyword>
  <keyword>trifocal</keyword>
  <keyword>extended range of vision</keyword>
  <keyword>diffractive achromatic technology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Presbyopia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

