<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03972254</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2019:105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03972254</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Modified Interaction Guidance as an Intervention Tool for Caregivers and Their Child With Autism</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Modified Interaction Guidance as an Intervention Tool for Caregivers and Their Child With Autism</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Manitoba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manitoba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this mixed methods single subject study is to test the Modified Interaction
      Guidance (MIG) as an intervention to improve attachment for children with autism and their
      primary caregiver.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to answer the following research questions and hypotheses:

        1. Does the use of MIG with a child with autism, result in changes in attachment such as
           alterations in sensitivity and attunement, in a child-caregiver relationship? H1: A
           change in the rating on the GAS will demonstrate effectiveness of goal setting as a
           means of detecting changes in dyad relationship goals, as well as result in increased
           attunement and parental sensitivity as evidence by maintained or improved score in the
           AMBIANCE, PICCOLO and SAIAS following a 2-month period.

        2. Do caregivers feel more competent in their caregiving skills through the use of MIG? H2:
           Caregivers will demonstrate increased feelings of competency through the use of MIG as
           evidenced by scores on the Parenting Sense of Competency Scale.

        3. Do caregivers feel less stress in their role as a caregiver through the use of MIG? H3:
           Caregivers will demonstrate less feelings of stress through the use of the MIG as
           evidenced by scores on the Parent Stress Index.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is an explanatory sequential mixed methods study in which the quantitative complement (concurrent multiple baseline single case study) will be completed first, followed by qualitative interviews that build on and further explain the quantitative data.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parenting Interactions with Children Checklist of Observations Linked to Outcomes (PICCOLO)</measure>
    <time_frame>11 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Serves as an observational tool to determine parental abilities in four specific domains; Affection, Responsiveness, Encouragement and Teaching.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Atypical Maternal Behaviour Instrument for Assessment and Classification (AMBIANCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, week 7 and week 11.</time_frame>
    <description>It is an observational tool used to measure and ultimately assess the quality of parental interaction with their infant/child. It looks at atypical parental behaviours that are dysfunctional.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensoriaffective Interactional Attunement Scale (SAIAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 1, week 7 and week 11.</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses caregiver-child interactions and to target interventions to support . These items include, use of facial expressions, use of gesture, use of touch, use of position, use of movement, use of sound, use of language, use of pacing, and following a child's actions/intent. The items are scored on a 1-4 range. 1= rarely/very mild and a 4= always/severe on both underuse and overuse subsections.improvements in child, caregiver, and dyadic social-emotional functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers and their child will interact for 10 minutes while being observed and videotaped. Psychoeducation will be provided and goal setting will occur to ensure dyad specific relationship gains are made.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Modified Interaction Guidance</intervention_name>
    <description>The main steps in the procedure are to have the family identify the primary concern they are facing, highlight the strengths that the family already has in place and expand on those strengths, convey/impart caregiving and societal norms, and offer other perspectives (McDonough, 2004). The goal of this therapy is to engage the family to take an active role in the construction of their overall treatment. The individualized treatment approach focuses and builds on existing strengths.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of autism spectrum disorder

          2. Child between the ages of 24-60 months

          3. First born child

          4. No physical or medical conditions that affect the child's ability to participate in
             the activities that are part of the intervention process

          5. Ability to follow simple verbal directions in English

          6. No current plan to initiate any treatment alternatives during the study period

          7. Willingness to participate in a 11-week intervention with a frequency of once a week

          8. Adults are primary caregiver

          9. Under age of 35

         10. Speak English

         11. Minimum grade 5 schooling

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants (both child and adult) will be excluded from the present study if they
             were deemed low functioning

          -  child is not the first-born child

          -  child already receiving ABA treatment

          -  parents have a history of mental illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Megan Land McCarthy, Bsc OT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Megan Land McCarthy, Bsc OT</last_name>
    <phone>204-293-7043</phone>
    <email>mlandmccarthy@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leanne Leclair, PhD OT</last_name>
    <phone>204-977-5631</phone>
    <email>Leanne.Leclair@umanitoba.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 3, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Modified Interaction Guidance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

