<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03975465</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO32538</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03975465</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EMST and Swallowing in Long-Term Survivors of HNCA</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Expiratory Muscle Strength Training (EMST) on Long-Term Swallowing Dysfunction in Persons With Head and Neck Cancer (HNCA) Post Irradiation (RT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Froedtert Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomized trial examining the impact of expiratory muscle strength training
      (EMST) on oral intake, swallowing function, and swallow-related quality of life in persons
      treated for cancer of the head and neck (HNCA) with radiation therapy or chemoradiotherapy
      (RT/CRT) at least 5 years previously.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty (20) persons treated for cancer of the head and neck (HNCA) with radiation therapy or
      chemoradiotherapy (RT/CRT) at least 5 years previously will be randomized to an 8-week
      program of either EMST only and Standard Care only in order to examine the impact of EMST on
      swallowing function. The EMST program will consist of 5 sets of 5 breaths, 5 days per week
      for 8 weeks at 75% of maximum expiratory strength. Patients randomized to the EMST group will
      use the EMST150 (product name) expiratory muscle strength trainer according to package
      instructions. Standard Care will include swallowing exercises designed to strengthen muscles
      that contribute to pharyngeal phase motor events and increase structural range of motion.
      Subjects will be instructed to practice these exercises following a progressive protocol 5
      days per week for 8 weeks.

      All subjects will be evaluated at baseline and at the completion of their rehabilitation
      program. Assessment will include measurement of maximum expiratory pressure (MEP), a
      videofluoroscopic swallow study (VFSS) to objectively document swallow function,
      administration of swallow-related quality of life (QOL) questionnaires, and documentation of
      current diet using the International Dysphagia Diet Standardisation Initiative (IDDSI) Drink
      Levels and Food Levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Subjects will be randomized to an 8-week program of either Expiratory Muscle Strength Training (EMST) or Standard Care in order to examine the impact of EMST on swallowing function</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Researchers assessing the outcomes will not know the arm to which the subject was randomized.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of Oral Intake (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Food Level and Drink Level on International Dysphagia Diet Standardisation Initiative (IDDSI) scale will be calculated from baseline to post-treatment.
IDDSI scale rates the level of liquid or food that the person can eat. Scale values range from 0 to 7, with higher values indicating better outcome (greater ability to eat).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Expiratory Pressure (MEP) cm H20</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in maximum expiratory pressure level will be calculated from baseline to post-treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of hyoid movement (mm)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>From Videofluoroscopic Swallow Studies (VFSS), the change in extent of hyoid movement in mm will be determined from baseline to post-treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Upper esophageal sphincter (UES) opening width (mm)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>From Videofluoroscopic Swallow Studies (VFSS), the change in width of UES opening width in mm will be determined from baseline to post-treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of pharyngeal residue (dichotomous)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>From Videofluoroscopic Swallow Studies (VFSS), the presence of residue in the pharynx (yes or no) will be determined from baseline to post-treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Penetration-Aspiration Scale rating (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>From Videofluoroscopic Swallow Studies (VFSS), change in the Penetration-Aspiration Scale (PAS) score will be determined from baseline to post-treatment. Penetration-Aspiration Scale is an 8-point ordinal rating scale that rates the depth to which food or liquid invades the airway. Values range from a minimum of 1 to a maximum of 8; higher values represent worse outcome (i.e. greater depth of invasion into the airway)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Timing of Aspiration (category)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>From Videofluoroscopic Swallow Studies (VFSS), timing of aspiration will be determined from baseline to post-treatment. Timing is identified as a category, either before, during, or after.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Eating Assessment Tool (EAT-10) (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in score on the EAT-10 will be calculated from baseline to mid-treatment to post-treatment. EAT-10 is an ordinal rating scale with values that range from 0 to 40, with lower score reflecting better function.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>M.D. Anderson Dysphagia Inventory (MDADI) (number)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in scores on the M.D. Anderson Dysphagia Inventory (MDADI) will be calculated from baseline to post-treatment. MDADI consists of four ordinal rating scales with scores ranging from 0 to 100 with higher score reflecting better function.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Deglutition Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Expiratory Muscle Strength Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the EMST arm will use the EMST150 device as packaged, i.e. following package instructions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pharyngeal Muscle Strengthening Exercises</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to Standard Care will receive swallowing exercises designed to strengthen muscles that contribute to pharyngeal phase motor events and increase structural range of motion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Expiratory Muscle Strength Training</intervention_name>
    <description>8 weeks of EMST at 75% maximum expiratory pressure (MEP)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Expiratory Muscle Strength Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharyngeal Muscle Strengthening Exercises</intervention_name>
    <description>8 weeks of exercises designed to increase pharyngeal muscle strength for swallowing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pharyngeal Muscle Strengthening Exercises</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject was treated for cancer in the oral cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx, larynx, or
             for an unknown primary at least 5 years prior to enrollment. Subjects may have had
             surgery as long as a minimum dose of 50 Gy of radiation was part of the treatment;

          2. Subject must have a current swallow complaint or impairment; these include but are not
             limited to reduced oral intake, perceived difficulty with bolus transport (e.g.
             feeling of food sticking in throat); aspiration on various bolus consistencies;

          3. Ability to follow directions and engage in a program of rehabilitation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. the subject's swallowing problems are unrelated to treatment for HNCA (e.g. cognitive
             impairment, history of stroke);

          2. the subject presents with contraindications for EMST as specified in the EMST150
             package insert unless cleared for participation by the subject's physician. These
             conditions include untreated hypertension, untreated gastroesophageal reflux diseas,
             recent stroke, lung disease, and pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara Pauloski, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barbara Pauloski, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>4142296719</phone>
    <email>pauloski@uwm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stephanie Stevens, M.S.</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Milwaukee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Froedtert Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephanie Stevens, MS</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Barbara Pauloski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oropharyngeal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>laryngeal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>swallow</keyword>
  <keyword>chemoradiation</keyword>
  <keyword>expiratory muscle strength training</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term survivor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Deglutition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

