<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03977142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HgPCICU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03977142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validity of Radical 7 Masimo Monitor at Measuring Hemoglobin in Pediatric Cardiac Intensive Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Accuracy of the Noninvasive Radical-7 Pulse Co-oximeter at Detecting Hemoglobin Changes in Pediatric Cardiac Intensive Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Justine's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Justine's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fifty percent of children that survive a critical illness are anemic at discharge from the
      pediatric intensive care unit (PICU)(1). Given that there are approximately 9000 PICU
      admissions/year in Canada, this represents almost 4500 children per year. Anemia is
      associated with abnormal neurocognitive development in infants and young children. A
      contributor to PICU anemia is the excessive amount of blood testing and iatrogenic blood
      losses(2). Non-invasive continuous hemoglobin monitoring (Sp-Hb) have been developed in the
      medical setting in an attempt to minimize invasive blood testing and reduce blood losses. The
      Radical 7 Masimo device (Masimo corporation, Irvine, CA) is one of the popular devices used
      for non-invasive hemoglobin monitoring. Its accuracy has been previously investigated in
      various populations(3-6). The objective of this study is to investigate the validity of the
      Radical 7 Masimo device at measuring hemoglobin trends non-invasively in critically ill
      children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a prospective observational study. We will include 1) all patients that are
      admitted to the PICU of the CHUSJ after a cardiac surgery, 2) that are aged less than 6
      months on the day of admission and that 3) have an arterial line inserted.

      All children studied will have an arterial line inserted at the time of surgery that will
      allow for arterial-Hb measurements. As this study is strictly observational, all arterial-Hb
      measurements will be requested by the medical treating team as clinically indicated. We will
      install, on admission, the spectrophotometric adhesive sensor required for Sp-Hb measurements
      on each patient (Masimo Rainbow R1 20 for children over 30 kg and R1 20L for those under 30
      kg). The sensor will be applied on the hand or foot that does not have an arterial cannula.
      The sensor will be covered with an impermeable black shield to prevent optical interference.

      We will collect all the arterial-Hb measurements performed in the 48 hours after PICU
      admission as well as all the Sp-Hb readings performed at the time of the arterial samples.
      The blood samples drawn from the arterial catheter will be analyzed using a laboratory
      CO-oximeter (model ABL820; Radiometer, Copenhagen, Denmark). Simultaneous recording of Sp-Hb
      will performed within 10 seconds after the arterial blood sample is drawn. We will also
      collect demographic data and clinical data on each patient; age, weight, sex, ethnicity, type
      of cardiac surgery, blood transfusions. At the CHUSJ PICU, all clinical and demographic data
      is systematically recorded in our electronic database (Intellispace Critical Care and
      Anesthesia, Philips Medical Systems). Data on red cell transfusions are recorded through the
      TracelineTM database that is made available to our research group through Héma-Québec. Data
      will be extracted from our database by our research assistant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the precision of the Radical-7 pulse co-oximeter at detecting changes in Hb levels when comparted to arterial-Hb levels changes in children admitted to the PICU after a cardiac surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the precision of the Radical-7 pulse co-oximeter at measuring Hb values when compared to arterial-Hb in children admitted to the PICU after a cardiac surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Evaluate the Accuracy of the Masimo Radical 7 Hemoglobin Noninvasive Monitor</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radical 7 Masimo Hemoglobin pulse co-oximeter non invasive monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Measure hemoglobin levels non invasively by pulse co-oximeter</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Children admitted to the PICU after a cardiac surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1) patients that are admitted to the PICU of the CHUSJ after a cardiac surgery, 2)
             that are aged less than 6 months on the day of admission and that 3) have an arterial
             line inserted.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Geneviève Du Pont-Thibodeau, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>5143454931</phone>
    <phone_ext>5553</phone_ext>
    <email>genevievedpt@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Justine's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Genevieve Du Pont-Thibodeau</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Pediatric Intensivist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

