<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03973502</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201506041MINA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03973502</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Application of 18F-FDOPA PET and Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (MRS) With HCV and PD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Application of 18F-FDOPA PET and Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy (MRS) in Research of the Association Between HCV Infection and Parkinson's Disease.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to investigate the evidence of dopaminergic toxicity causing
      by HCV infection using 18F-FDOPA PET and MRS as imaging biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is the most common neurodegenerative disorder after Alzheimer's
      disease. It is characterized by degeneration of the dopaminergic neurons in substantia nigra
      and striatum, even before the clinical symptoms develop. Although the pathogenesis is still
      unclear, some viruses have been shown to be associated with acute or chronic parkinsonism.
      Recent studies have found that Hepatitis C virus (HCV) can replicate in the central nervous
      system, suggesting a possible link between PD and HCV. At the population and epidemiology
      level, the HCV infection and PD are strongly associated. At the molecular level, both HCV and
      PD have in common the overexpression of inflammatory biomarkers. Neuronal toxicity induced by
      HCV was also demonstrated. The positive association between HCV infection and PD has clinical
      implications for high endemic HCV areas, including Taiwan.

      18F-FDOPA, an analog to L-DOPA, has been used as a positron-emitting compound for PET
      examination of patients affected by PD. It has been shown that putamen 18F-FDOPA uptakes are
      reduced by at least 35% at onset of symptoms, making the 18F-FDOPA PET as an imaging
      biomarker for detecting subclinical and preclinical parkinsonism. Earlier imaging study using
      magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) to investigate cerebral effect of HCV also showed that
      chronic HCV infection had elevated choline/creatine ratios, a biomarker indicating
      inflammatory and infective conditions, in the basal ganglia and white matter.

      The objective of this study is to investigate the evidence of dopaminergic toxicity causing
      by HCV infection using 18F-FDOPA PET and MRS as imaging biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 12, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PET imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>in 3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Visual interpretation will be performed first by two independent readers to record if there is any abnormal 18F-FES accumulation. The presence, number, size, character, and location of suspected lesions will be filed for each patient in this study. The final results will be validated by tissue proof, correlation with other imaging, or follow-up results. Semi-quantitative analysis will be performed for each lesion suspected during visual interpretation. Standardized uptake values (SUV) will be obtained by placing regions of interest (ROIs) around the lesions that are identified on visual analysis. The maximum SUV (SUVmax) will be recorded.
Volumetric parameters will be performed by placing volume of interests (VOIs) around the suspected lesions. VOIs will be generated using defined fix SUV thresholds or algorithm-generated isocontours. Manual adjustment of VOIs is allowed when non-tumoral tissue is incorrectly included by automatic method.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">230</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis B</condition>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>18F-DOPA PET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PET/CT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>18F-DOPA PET</intervention_name>
    <description>One hour later all patient will be injected intravenously with 185 MBq (5mCi) 18F-FDOPA. PET emission data acquisition in 3-dimensional mode will be started at 60 minutes after tracer injection for 30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>18F-DOPA PET</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Test Group

               1. Age：above 20 years old with HBV or HCV subjects.

               2. Patient agrees to participate in the study and receive UPDRS, MMSE, BDI II, MRI
                  and PET imaging.

          -  Control Group

               1. Age：above 20 years old without carriers of Hepatitis B and C (ex. fatty liver),
                  and no known neurological (ex. stroke, Parkinson's disease and degenerative
                  neuropathy, etc.) and mental illness.

               2. Patient agrees to participate in the study and receive UPDRS, MMSE, BDI II, MRI
                  and PET imaging.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients could not receive PET and MRI studies, including panic mood to MRI study,
             allergy to contrast medium, hemodynamic instability.

          2. Patients with pregnancy or recently having a plan for pregnancy.

          3. Patient or family who does not agree to participate in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan Univeristy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yen Ruoh Fang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>886-2-23123456</phone>
      <phone_ext>65581</phone_ext>
      <email>rfyen@ntu.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Parkinson's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>18F-FDOPA PET, MRS</keyword>
  <keyword>MRS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

