<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03974477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>iMCSALT19-21</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03974477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study With an Innovative Equipment to Monitor and Control SALT During Cooking</brief_title>
  <acronym>iMC_SALT</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial With SALT CONTROL H - Impact on Individual Sodium and Sodium to Potassium Ratio Excretion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade do Porto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundação para a Ciência e a Tecnologia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Instituto Nacional de Saúde Doutor Ricardo Jorge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centro Hospitalar De São João, E.P.E.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade do Porto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, the researchers will evaluate the efficacy of an intervention using the SALT
      CONTROL H instrument (an innovative equipment to monitor and control salt) in workers at the
      University of Porto to reduce dietary salt intake. This is a randomized clinical trial with
      intervention conducted according to good clinical practice guidelines.

      The researchers will randomize 260 workers who meet the eligibility criteria and are enrolled
      in occupational health appointments. Prior to the intervention, the informed consent of the
      participants will be obtained and those who agree to participate will be allocated randomly
      in one of the two arms of the study (control or intervention), with balance of baseline
      characteristics (sex and hypertension).

      The intervention will last for 8 weeks, an individual session of presentation of SALT CONTROL
      H will be carried out, with explanation of how the equipment works in the culinary
      preparation with an adequate salt content, will be used an illustrative video and recipes
      with an adequate salt content; use of SALT CONTROL H at home by the participant to control
      the use of salt during the cooking process; supervision and enhancement of the use of
      equipment; daily occurrence log; and the application of a satisfaction questionnaire on the
      use of SALT CONTROL H. A leaflet will also be delivered about &quot;The new Food Wheel, a guide to
      the daily food choice!&quot;.

      Control Group: No intervention will be carried out except the provision of a leaflet on &quot;The
      new Food Wheel, a guide to the daily food choice!&quot; to the participants.

      Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention analysis
      will cover the following domains: urinary sodium excretion corresponding to a 24 hour urine
      collection as a proxy for salt intake; 24-hour urinary potassium excretion, sodium:potassium
      ratio, systolic and diastolic blood pressure, and anthropometric measurements. Urine samples
      will be collected according to standardized procedures and analyzed by a certified
      laboratory. Secondary data such as satisfaction questionnaire, daily use of equipment, iodine
      analysis of salt used and excreted in urine 24h, hydration status, analysis of quality of
      life and quality of diet will also be analyzed, as well as intestinal microbiota.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline 24h urinary sodium excretion at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Sodium excretion as a proxy of dietary salt intake</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline 24h urinary potassium excretion at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary potassium excretion as a proxy of dietary potassium intake</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Systolic Blood Pressure at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Systolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Diastolic Blood Pressure at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Diastolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Hydration Status at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>urinary osmolality (mOsm/kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Perception of quality of life at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8th intervention week, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire WHOQOL-BREF, results from 0 to 100, higher values represent better perception of quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Culinary competences at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at 8th intervention week, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire, questions scales from 1 to 6 according to culinary competences, higher values represent better culinary competences</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Intestinal Microbiota at after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 8th intervention week</time_frame>
    <description>OTU (operational taxonomy unit) analysis (%)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Diet Quality at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>HDI (Healthy Diet Indicator), HDI-2015 was calculated as the sum of 7 components (range 0-7) and was classified as follows: high adherence (met 6-7 components), moderate adherence (met 4-5 components), and low adherence (met 0-3 components)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Knowledges, attitudes and behaviours about salt at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire on Knowledge, Attitudes, Behavior toward Dietary Salt and Health from PAHO (n and %)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Weight at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Weight in kilograms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Height at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Height in meters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Fat Mass and Fat Free Mass at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Fat mass (in kg), Fat free mass (in kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Extra and intra cellular water at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Extra and intra cellular water, basal metabolic rate</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Extra and intra cellular water at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Extra and intra cellular water (in kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline Basal Metabolic Rate at during and after intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, at the 4th and 8th intervention weeks, and 6 months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Basal metabolic rate (in kcal)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Salt; Excess</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention will last for 8 weeks, an individual session of presentation of SALT CONTROL H will be carried out, with explanation of how the equipment works in the culinary preparation with an adequate salt content (will be used an illustrative video and recipes with an adequate salt content); use of SALT CONTROL H at home by the participant to control the use of salt during the cooking process; supervision and enhancement of the use of equipment; daily occurrence log; and the application of a satisfaction questionnaire on the use of SALT CONTROL H. A leaflet will also be delivered about &quot;The new Food Wheel, a guide to the daily food choice!&quot;.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No intervention will be carried out except the provision of a leaflet on &quot;The new Food Wheel, a guide to the daily food choice!&quot; to the participants.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SALT CONTROL H equipment to control and monitor salt during cooking process</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will use SALT CONTROL H at home during 8 weeks to cook meals with adequate salt content.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults (&gt; 18 years)

          -  Eat frequently cooked meals at home (&gt; 4 days a week, of which at least 3 Sundays /
             month)

          -  Have an occupational health appoitments at São João Hospital

          -  Reported motivation to control salt consumption

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant

          -  Subjects with kidney disease,

          -  Subjects with active infection with an impact on renal function,

          -  Subjects with urinary incontinence,

          -  Subjects with acute coronary syndrome,

          -  Subjects with severe liver disease;

          -  Subjects with heart failure;

          -  Subjects who do not use salt for cooking;

          -  Subjects with hypotension;

          -  Subjects that work at Faculty that are the Sponsor of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carla Gonçalves, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Researcher</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carla Gonçalves, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>225 074 320</phone>
    <phone_ext>+351</phone_ext>
    <email>carlagoncalves.pt@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carla Gonçalves, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>225 074 320</phone>
    <phone_ext>+351</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carla Gonçalves</name>
      <address>
        <city>Porto</city>
        <zip>4200-465</zip>
        <country>Portugal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carla Gonçalves, PhD</last_name>
      <email>carlagoncalves.pt@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carla Gonçalves, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Olívia Pinho, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Portugal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonçalves C, Abreu S, Padrão P, Pinho O, Graça P, Breda J, Santos R, Moreira P. Sodium and potassium urinary excretion and dietary intake: a cross-sectional analysis in adolescents. Food Nutr Res. 2016 Apr 11;60:29442. doi: 10.3402/fnr.v60.29442. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27072344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonçalves C, Monteiro S, Padrão P, Rocha A, Abreu S, Pinho O, Moreira P. Salt reduction in vegetable soup does not affect saltiness intensity and liking in the elderly and children. Food Nutr Res. 2014 Oct 6;58. doi: 10.3402/fnr.v58.24825. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25317121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreira P, Sousa AS, Guerra RS, Santos A, Borges N, Afonso C, Amaral TF, Padrão P. Sodium and potassium urinary excretion and their ratio in the elderly: results from the Nutrition UP 65 study. Food Nutr Res. 2018 Feb 27;62. doi: 10.29219/fnr.v62.1288. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29545733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dietary Salt</keyword>
  <keyword>Urinary sodium excretion</keyword>
  <keyword>Cooking</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Sodium</keyword>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Education</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>In order to promote the quality of the data, they will be introduced by an researcher with delegation of competences by the PI, a verification of double data entry and verification of outliers will be performed. The data will be used for publication of the results by the researchers of the project and for the accomplishment of master's and doctoral thesis.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

