<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03977025</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Saval 018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03977025</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Alzheimer Biomarkers on CSF of Elderly Patients Undergoing Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Alzheimer's Biomarkers in Cerebrospinal Fluid and Peripheral Blood of Elderly Patients Undergoing Surgery in the HCUCH.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chile</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chile</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dementia is a syndrome characterized by cognitive and behavioral impairment in older adults,
      which usually manifests as memory loss, communication difficulties or changes in mood.
      Dementias affect around 50 million people in the world, having an impact on their ability to
      carry out their daily activities, often requiring family and social support.

      The main cause of dementia in Chile and in the world is Alzheimer's disease (AD), which is
      characterized by affecting large areas of the cerebral cortex and hippocampus, manifesting
      mainly in alterations in selective memory. The pathogenesis of AD involves the neuronal
      accumulation of β-amyloid (Aβ) proteins in the form of extracellular plaques, and tau, which
      gives rise to neurofibrillary tangles. AD diagnosis is usually made based on clinical
      criteria, however, the accurate diagnosis of AD is clinical-neuropathological. Several
      studies have supported the neuropathological study based on the presence of Aβ and tau
      proteins in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), using them as biomarkers of the disease, which has
      allowed updating the definition of AD based on them. However, our country does not perform a
      study of dementia biomarkers in CSF, which is essential for the diagnosis of certainty of the
      pathology.

      The objective of this project is to evaluate a set of biomarkers of EA (tau, ptau, Aβ) in CSF
      and blood of elderly patients who will undergo surgery in the Clinical Hospital of the
      University of Chile (HCUCH) and in whom it is performed lumbar puncture (LP) by anesthesia,
      to detect those patients who have these CSF biomarkers and who show lower performance in
      cognitive evaluations. For this, it is intended to mount a biobank of CSF samples with
      samples of 30 subjects by conducting a clinical pilot study. Patients will be evaluated prior
      to surgery with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) to determine the presence of
      cognitive impairment, and CSF samples, obtained by LP, will be analyzed by immunodetection of
      Aβ40, Aβ42, tau and ptau with multiplex technology. In addition, tau will be detected in
      platelets by Western Blot of blood samples from patients, and the relationship between
      plateau tau levels and biomarkers in CSF will be evaluated. Finally, the correlation between
      performance in cognitive assessment and levels of biomarkers in blood and CSF will be
      evaluated, in order to assess the usefulness of these markers in the detection of the
      presence of cognitive impairment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal Cognitive Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Correlate the degree of cognitive deterioration obtained in the MOCA evaluation with the levels of biomarkers in CSF and blood.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lumbar punction</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated prior to surgery with the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) to determine the presence of cognitive impairment, and CSF samples, obtained by lumbar punction, will be analyzed by immunodetection of Aβ40, Aβ42, tau and ptau with multiplex technology</description>
    <other_name>Montreal Cognitive Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      CSF samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who will undergo surgery in the HCUCH, for any reason
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects older than 65 years who will undergo surgery in the HCUCH (for any reason)
             and who require lumbar puncture for anesthesia.

          -  Autovalent, with no history of dementia, with MoCA ≥ 20 points (score adapted to the
             Chilean population).

          -  The subjects will not be carriers of medical, neurological or psychiatric pathologies
             that could affect their participation in the study or its results. The presence of
             chronic pathologies will be admitted, as long as they are under stable treatment and
             without evidence of decompensation in the last 3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Antecedents of being carriers of dementia or symptomatic neurodegenerative disease.

          -  Medical or surgical decompensated pathology.

          -  Contraindication of lumbar puncture.

          -  Physical or mental inability to consent to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sergio Vera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chile</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sergio Vera, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+56977745935</phone>
    <email>sveran.med@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chile Clinical Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sergio Vera, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5), American Psychiatric Association. 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheltens P, Blennow K, Breteler MM, de Strooper B, Frisoni GB, Salloway S, Van der Flier WM. Alzheimer's disease. Lancet. 2016 Jul 30;388(10043):505-17. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01124-1. Epub 2016 Feb 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26921134</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang J, Gu BJ, Masters CL, Wang YJ. A systemic view of Alzheimer disease - insights from amyloid-β metabolism beyond the brain. Nat Rev Neurol. 2017 Sep 29;13(10):612-623. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2017.111. Review. Erratum in: Nat Rev Neurol. 2017 Oct 13;:.</citation>
    <PMID>28960209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Masters CL, Bateman R, Blennow K, Rowe CC, Sperling RA, Cummings JL. Alzheimer's disease. Nat Rev Dis Primers. 2015 Oct 15;1:15056. doi: 10.1038/nrdp.2015.56. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27188934</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alzheimer's Disease International publication team. From plan to impact. Progress towards targets of the Global action plan on dementia. Alzheimer's Disease International. 2018.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parra MA, Baez S, Allegri R, Nitrini R, Lopera F, Slachevsky A, Custodio N, Lira D, Piguet O, Kumfor F, Huepe D, Cogram P, Bak T, Manes F, Ibanez A. Dementia in Latin America: Assessing the present and envisioning the future. Neurology. 2018 Jan 30;90(5):222-231. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000004897. Epub 2018 Jan 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29305437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fuentes P, Albala C. An update on aging and dementia in Chile. Dement Neuropsychol. 2014 Oct-Dec;8(4):317-322. doi: 10.1590/S1980-57642014DN84000003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29213920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gremer L, Schölzel D, Schenk C, Reinartz E, Labahn J, Ravelli RBG, Tusche M, Lopez-Iglesias C, Hoyer W, Heise H, Willbold D, Schröder GF. Fibril structure of amyloid-β(1-42) by cryo-electron microscopy. Science. 2017 Oct 6;358(6359):116-119. doi: 10.1126/science.aao2825. Epub 2017 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>28882996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeVos SL, Miller RL, Schoch KM, Holmes BB, Kebodeaux CS, Wegener AJ, Chen G, Shen T, Tran H, Nichols B, Zanardi TA, Kordasiewicz HB, Swayze EE, Bennett CF, Diamond MI, Miller TM. Tau reduction prevents neuronal loss and reverses pathological tau deposition and seeding in mice with tauopathy. Sci Transl Med. 2017 Jan 25;9(374). pii: eaag0481. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.aag0481.</citation>
    <PMID>28123067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ittner A, Chua SW, Bertz J, Volkerling A, van der Hoven J, Gladbach A, Przybyla M, Bi M, van Hummel A, Stevens CH, Ippati S, Suh LS, Macmillan A, Sutherland G, Kril JJ, Silva AP, Mackay JP, Poljak A, Delerue F, Ke YD, Ittner LM. Site-specific phosphorylation of tau inhibits amyloid-β toxicity in Alzheimer's mice. Science. 2016 Nov 18;354(6314):904-908.</citation>
    <PMID>27856911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McKhann GM, Knopman DS, Chertkow H, Hyman BT, Jack CR Jr, Kawas CH, Klunk WE, Koroshetz WJ, Manly JJ, Mayeux R, Mohs RC, Morris JC, Rossor MN, Scheltens P, Carrillo MC, Thies B, Weintraub S, Phelps CH. The diagnosis of dementia due to Alzheimer's disease: recommendations from the National Institute on Aging-Alzheimer's Association workgroups on diagnostic guidelines for Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimers Dement. 2011 May;7(3):263-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2011.03.005. Epub 2011 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21514250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jack CR Jr, Bennett DA, Blennow K, Carrillo MC, Dunn B, Haeberlein SB, Holtzman DM, Jagust W, Jessen F, Karlawish J, Liu E, Molinuevo JL, Montine T, Phelps C, Rankin KP, Rowe CC, Scheltens P, Siemers E, Snyder HM, Sperling R; Contributors. NIA-AA Research Framework: Toward a biological definition of Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimers Dement. 2018 Apr;14(4):535-562. doi: 10.1016/j.jalz.2018.02.018. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29653606</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buerger K, Ewers M, Pirttilä T, Zinkowski R, Alafuzoff I, Teipel SJ, DeBernardis J, Kerkman D, McCulloch C, Soininen H, Hampel H. CSF phosphorylated tau protein correlates with neocortical neurofibrillary pathology in Alzheimer's disease. Brain. 2006 Nov;129(Pt 11):3035-41. Epub 2006 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>17012293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattsson N, Zetterberg H, Hansson O, Andreasen N, Parnetti L, Jonsson M, Herukka SK, van der Flier WM, Blankenstein MA, Ewers M, Rich K, Kaiser E, Verbeek M, Tsolaki M, Mulugeta E, Rosén E, Aarsland D, Visser PJ, Schröder J, Marcusson J, de Leon M, Hampel H, Scheltens P, Pirttilä T, Wallin A, Jönhagen ME, Minthon L, Winblad B, Blennow K. CSF biomarkers and incipient Alzheimer disease in patients with mild cognitive impairment. JAMA. 2009 Jul 22;302(4):385-93. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.1064.</citation>
    <PMID>19622817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark CM, Pontecorvo MJ, Beach TG, Bedell BJ, Coleman RE, Doraiswamy PM, Fleisher AS, Reiman EM, Sabbagh MN, Sadowsky CH, Schneider JA, Arora A, Carpenter AP, Flitter ML, Joshi AD, Krautkramer MJ, Lu M, Mintun MA, Skovronsky DM; AV-45-A16 Study Group. Cerebral PET with florbetapir compared with neuropathology at autopsy for detection of neuritic amyloid-β plaques: a prospective cohort study. Lancet Neurol. 2012 Aug;11(8):669-78. Epub 2012 Jun 28. Erratum in: Lancet Neurol. 2012 Aug;11(8):658.</citation>
    <PMID>22749065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark CM, Schneider JA, Bedell BJ, Beach TG, Bilker WB, Mintun MA, Pontecorvo MJ, Hefti F, Carpenter AP, Flitter ML, Krautkramer MJ, Kung HF, Coleman RE, Doraiswamy PM, Fleisher AS, Sabbagh MN, Sadowsky CH, Reiman EP, Zehntner SP, Skovronsky DM; AV45-A07 Study Group. Use of florbetapir-PET for imaging beta-amyloid pathology. JAMA. 2011 Jan 19;305(3):275-83. doi: 10.1001/jama.2010.2008. Erratum in: JAMA. 2011 Mar 16;305(11):1096. Reiman, P Eric M [corrected to Reiman, Eric M].</citation>
    <PMID>21245183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seo SW, Ayakta N, Grinberg LT, Villeneuve S, Lehmann M, Reed B, DeCarli C, Miller BL, Rosen HJ, Boxer AL, O'Neil JP, Jin LW, Seeley WW, Jagust WJ, Rabinovici GD. Regional correlations between [(11)C]PIB PET and post-mortem burden of amyloid-beta pathology in a diverse neuropathological cohort. Neuroimage Clin. 2016 Nov 11;13:130-137. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>27981028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blennow K, Zetterberg H. Biomarkers for Alzheimer's disease: current status and prospects for the future. J Intern Med. 2018 Dec;284(6):643-663. doi: 10.1111/joim.12816. Epub 2018 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30051512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slachevsky A, Guzmán-Martínez L, Delgado C, Reyes P, Farías GA, Muñoz-Neira C, Bravo E, Farías M, Flores P, Garrido C, Becker JT, López OL, Maccioni RB. Tau Platelets Correlate with Regional Brain Atrophy in Patients with Alzheimer's Disease. J Alzheimers Dis. 2017;55(4):1595-1603. doi: 10.3233/JAD-160652.</citation>
    <PMID>27911301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farías G, Pérez P, Slachevsky A, Maccioni RB. Platelet tau pattern correlates with cognitive status in Alzheimer's disease. J Alzheimers Dis. 2012;31(1):65-9. doi: 10.3233/JAD-2012-120304.</citation>
    <PMID>22495344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kern S, Zetterberg H, Kern J, Zettergren A, Waern M, Höglund K, Andreasson U, Wetterberg H, Börjesson-Hanson A, Blennow K, Skoog I. Prevalence of preclinical Alzheimer disease: Comparison of current classification systems. Neurology. 2018 May 8;90(19):e1682-e1691. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0000000000005476. Epub 2018 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>29653987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delgado C, Araneda A, Behrens MI. Validation of the Spanish-language version of the Montreal Cognitive Assessment test in adults older than 60 years. Neurologia. 2019 Jul - Aug;34(6):376-385. doi: 10.1016/j.nrl.2017.01.013. Epub 2017 Mar 30. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>28364958</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 6, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Chile</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sergio Vera</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

