<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03978572</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-F-55</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03978572</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dual-benefits of Aerobic and Resistance Training</brief_title>
  <acronym>DART</acronym>
  <official_title>The DART Study: Exercise Strategies to Improve Physical Function in Older Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Heart Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect of three different exercise strategies on physical function
      in older adults. Participants will be randomly assigned to one of three exercise groups:
      resistance training, moderate-intensity continuous cycling on a stationary bicycle, and
      high-intensity interval training on a stationary bicycle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project is confronting age-related physical disability by optimizing exercise strategies
      for older adults. Aerobic training is recommended to improve cardiorespiratory (heart and
      lung) function, while strength training is recommended for muscular function. These exercise
      effects are necessary for building healthier lives and reducing mortality and disability
      risk, but most older adults who do exercise typically only perform one type of exercise. In
      doing so they are missing a key component for healthy aging. This study will address whether
      stationary-cycling high-intensity interval training results in both cardiorespiratory and
      muscular improvements, and it will be the first controlled study comparing adaptations to
      high-intensity interval, aerobic, and strength training in sedentary older adults.

      It is unclear whether the lack of muscular adaptations to traditional aerobic training is due
      to the low intensity/high volume model that is currently prescribed, and thus the central
      hypothesize of the study is that stationary-cycling high-intensity interval training can
      improve both cardiorespiratory and muscular function. To test this hypothesis, the
      investigators will measure heart, lung, and muscle function, as well as physical performance
      in sedentary older adults, before and after 12 weeks of supervised training using one of
      three exercise strategies; stationary-cycling high-intensity interval training,
      stationary-cycling moderate-intensity continuous training, or strength training. By comparing
      the outcomes across these three groups, the investigators will be able to confirm if short
      intervals of high-intensity exercise can elicit both cardiorespiratory and muscular benefits.

      This work will demonstrate that older adults can improve their cardiovascular health and
      muscular strength with a single exercise strategy. Establishing in detail the cardiovascular
      and muscular benefits of this exercise can lead to the implementation of new and improved
      exercise guidelines for cardiovascular health and reduced physical disability in older
      adults. Incidentally, it will also provide a framework for future studies to investigate the
      importance of intensity in exercise. At the end of this study the investigators will be able
      to disseminate a new evidence-based exercise protocol that will address a significant barrier
      to healthy aging.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Temporarily paused due to COVID-19 and expected to resume. Not of IRB approval
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal Oxygen Consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is maximal oxygen consumption measured by both relative and absolute changes in maximal oxygen consumption obtained during a graded exercise test on a cycle ergometer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee extensor isokinetic power</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal muscle power (maximal torque in foot-pounds) of the quadriceps using an isokinetic dynamometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee extensor isometric force production</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal muscle strength of the quadriceps (in foot-pounds) as measured by an isometric dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee extensor isokinetic endurance</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline at 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Total power output (cumulative torque in foot-pounds) produced from 120 consecutive maximal knee extensions using an isokinetic dynamometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcopenia</condition>
  <condition>Aging</condition>
  <condition>Disability Physical</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Resistance Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 weeks of whole-body progressive resistance training, three days per week, lower-extremity focused (60% of exercises targeting lower extremities)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate-intensity continuous cycling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 weeks of progressive endurance cycling on a stationary bicycle at a target heart rate, three days per week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity interval cycling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 weeks of progressive high-intensity interval cycling on a stationary bicycle, three days per week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Resistance Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise intervention designed to improve muscular strength and power</description>
    <arm_group_label>Resistance Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moderate-Intensity Continuous Cycling</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise intervention designed to improve cardiorespiratory fitness and muscular endurance</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate-intensity continuous cycling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-Intensity Interval Cycling</intervention_name>
    <description>Exercise intervention designed to improve cardiorespiratory fitness, muscular endurance, and muscular strength and power</description>
    <arm_group_label>High-intensity interval cycling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 60-75 years with no significant health issues or conditions that, in the
             investigator's opinion, would limit the subject's ability to complete the study per
             protocol or that would impact the capability to get an accurate measurement of study
             endpoints.

          -  Body mass index between 18.0 and 35 kg/m2.

          -  Willingness to maintain current diet and adhere to the intervention programs described
             for the study and willing to undergo all testing procedures.

          -  Able to read, understand, and complete study-related questionnaires

          -  Able to read and understand, and willing to sign the informed consent form (ICF).

          -  6-minute walk distance of 450-725 meters for men and 400-675 meters for women.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Failure to provide informed consent.

          -  6-minute walk distance below 450 meters or above 725 meters for men, below 400 meters
             or above 675 meters for women

          -  Any activities of daily living (ADL) disability (difficulty feeding, dressing,
             continence, bathing, toileting, and transferring).

          -  Lives in a nursing home or assisted living facility

          -  Known neuromuscular or neurological conditions affecting somatosensory or motor
             function or control (e.g., hemiplegia, multiple sclerosis, peripheral neuropathy,
             Parkinsons disease, Myasthenia Gravis, Ataxia, Apraxia, post-polio syndrome,
             mitochondrial myopathy, etc.).

          -  Unable to communicate because of severe hearing loss or speech disorder.

          -  Severe visual impairment, which would preclude completion of the assessments.

          -  Cancer requiring treatment currently or in the past 2 years (except primary
             non-melanoma skin cancer or in situ cervical cancer)

          -  Hospitalization (medical confinement for 24 hours), or immobilization, or major
             surgical procedure requiring general anesthesia within 12 weeks prior to screening, or
             any planned surgical procedures during the study period.

          -  Chronic or relapsing/remitting gastrointestinal disorders such as inflammatory bowel
             disease and irritable bowel syndrome.

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibody at screening.

          -  Use of systemic glucocorticoids.

          -  Any history of angina pectoris

          -  Any history of heart failure

          -  Any history of myocardial infarction

          -  Any coronary artery bypass graft or percutaneous coronary intervention

          -  Heart disease that limits exercise (valvular, congenital, ischaemic and hypertrophic
             cardiomyopathy)

          -  Complex ventricular arrhythmias or heart block

          -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, cerebrovascular disease, or peripheral vascular
             disease

          -  Diabetes mellitus

          -  Severe neuropathy

          -  Mini-mental state exam score (MMSE) below 19

          -  Psychiatric conditions that warrant acute or chronic therapeutic intervention (e.g.,
             major depressive disorder, bipolar disorder, panic disorder, schizophrenia) that in
             the investigators opinion may interfere with the conduct of study procedures

          -  Unable to undergo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (e. g. body containing any metallic
             medical devices or equipment, including heart pacemakers, metal prostheses, implants
             or surgical clips, any prior injury from shrapnel or grinding metal, exposure to
             metallic dusts, metallic shavings or having tattoos containing metallic dyes).

          -  Unable to reliably undergo exercise or strength tests described for this study.

          -  Participation in progressive resistance exercise 2 or more days/week for most weeks
             over the 24 weeks prior to screening, OR 150+ minutes of accumulated aerobic exercise
             each week for most weeks over the 24 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Current self-reported activity level that, in the investigator's opinion, is
             considered highly active for older adults

          -  Participation in any clinical trial within 12 weeks prior to screening.

          -  Limb amputation (except for toes) and/or any fracture within 24 weeks.

          -  Any disorder that will not allow completion of the motions required for resistance or
             aerobic exercise

          -  Conditions (such as myasthenia gravis, myositis, muscular dystrophy or myopathy,
             including drug-induced myopathy) leading to muscle loss, muscle weakness, muscle
             cramps or myalgia.

          -  Acute viral or bacterial upper or lower respiratory infection at screening

          -  Abnormal or uncontrolled blood pressure (BP) at the screening visit defined as BP &gt;
             170/100 mmHg. If taking anti-hypertensive medication, have to be on stable doses of
             medication for more than 3 months.

          -  Current or recent history (within 1 year of screen) of heavy alcohol consumption or
             drug abuse that in the investigators opinion may interfere with the conduct of study
             procedures.

          -  Reports being pregnant, lactating, or that they anticipate becoming pregnant in the
             next 3-months. If a woman becomes pregnant while on study protocol they will be
             withdrawn from the study

        Prohibited Medications: Medications that, in the PIs opinion, would confound study
        integrity by interacting with study outcomes. For instance:

          -  Anti-obesity drugs, nutraceuticals, and dietary supplements that may affect body mass
             and body composition.

          -  Any drug or supplement known to influence muscle mass or performance including but not
             limited to anabolic steroids, insulin-like growth factor 1 (IGF-1), growth hormone
             (GH), replacement androgen therapy, anti-androgen therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian C Clark, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 7, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcopenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

