<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03973736</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>286/2018/OSS/AUSLRE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03973736</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Multidisciplinary and Radiologic Review on Outcome of Pancreatic Cancer Patients: an Observational Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>RevRadPAC</acronym>
  <official_title>Impatto Della Revisione Radiologica Con Valutazione Multidisciplinare Nella Gestione Terapeutica Dei Pazienti Affetti da Adenocarcinoma Pancreatico (PAC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Azienda Unità Sanitaria Locale Reggio Emilia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Azienda Unità Sanitaria Locale Reggio Emilia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators compared two different time periods respectively before and after the
      application of a dedicated diagnostic and therapeutic protocol for pancreatic ductal
      adenocarcinoma including multidisciplinary discussion and radiological review of cases, in
      order to evaluate the impact of the new protocol on surgical failures and overall survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Since 2012 in Reggio Emilia a new diagnostic and therapeutic protocol has been implemented
      including multidisciplinary team discussion of non-metastatic PDACs and radiological review
      of CT scans by an experienced radiologist.

      The aim of this study is to measure the impact of this new protocol on the occurrence of
      surgical failures, including incomplete resection or surgery in which resection resulted
      impossible at all. The investigators also describe the changes in overall survival and
      process indicators such as the proportion of patients referred to different therapeutic
      options (upfront surgery, neoadjuvant chemotherapy and no surgery) and the compliance with
      referral.

      Through a population-based cohort study, the investigators evaluated the impact of the new
      protocol on therapeutic management and surgical outcome of patients with non-metastatic PDAC
      by comparing two four-years periods, respectively 2008-2011 and 2013-2016, before and after
      the introduction of the protocol. Since 2012 was the transitional year when the protocol was
      introduced, patients diagnosed with PDAC in 2012 were excluded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of surgical failures on the total of eligible patients</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of patients with incomplete resection or who received surgery in which resection was not possible</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>overall survival (restricted to patients with at least 24 months follow-up)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of patients referred to different therapeutic options</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of patients referred to different therapeutic options (upfront surgery, neoadjuvant chemotherapy and no surgery)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">316</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDAC patients diagnosed in 2008-2011</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDAC patients diagnosed in 2013-2016</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>application of a diagnostic and therapeutic protocol (multidisciplinary discussion and radiological CT review)</intervention_name>
    <description>Since the introduction of the new protocol in 2012, a single central multidisciplinary team has been formalized, with weekly discussion of cases, including different specialists from all the provincial hospitals. CT scans of discussed cases are reviewed by one of two experienced radiologists based on pre-defined criteria.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDAC patients diagnosed in 2013-2016</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The Reggio Emilia Pancreatic Cancer Register registered 1157 PDAC cases from 2008 to 2016.
        After exclusion of cases diagnosed in 2012, patients aged &gt;85 years and cancer staged as IV
        or with unknown stage, a total of 132 and 184 patients were included in analysis
        respectively for 2008-2011 and 2013-2016 periods.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  all consecutive inhabitants of the Reggio Emilia province with incident PDACs in
             2008-2011 and 2013-2016 periods

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pancreatic cancers with cytohistological diagnosis different from PDAC,

          -  diagnosis in 2012,

          -  metastatic disease at diagnosis (stage IV) or unknown stage at diagnosis,

          -  patients aged &gt;85 years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda USL - IRCCS di Reggio Emilia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reggio Emilia</city>
        <zip>42123</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

