<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03973840</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLAR-18019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03973840</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Blood From Men Receiving Oral TU in Various Collection Tubes</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess Post-collection Conversion of Testosterone Undecanoate (TU) to Testosterone in Blood From Men Receiving Oral TU Collected Into Different Types of Sample Tubes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clarus Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celerion; Syneos Health; ARUP Laboratories</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clarus Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To describe the rate of post-collection TU to testosterone conversion, as manifested by
      increases in testosterone concentration, in Plain tubes held at room temperature and sodium
      fluoride (NaF)-ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) tubes held at room temperature or on
      ice prior to centrifugation
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was an open-label, non-randomized, single-sequence study in which men dosed with JATENZO
      had blood drawn into 3 different types of blood-collection tubes (ie, Plain, EDTA, and
      NaF-EDTA). These tubes were then processed in different ways (ie, different durations between
      phlebotomy and centrifugation, different holding temperatures [room temperature or on ice]
      between phlebotomy and centrifugation). After defined periods of incubation, the tubes were
      centrifuged and the serum/plasma transferred into vials and frozen. The testosterone and TU
      levels in the serum/plasma were then measured using validated liquid chromatography/tandem
      mass spectrometry assays.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>measure rate of post-collection TU-to-testosterone conversion in 3 types of collection tubes</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the rate of post-collection TU to testosterone conversion, as manifested by increases in testosterone concentration, in Plain tubes held at room temperature and sodium fluoride (NaF)-ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA) tubes held at room temperature or on ice prior to centrifugation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>rate of post-collection TU-to-testosterone conversion, as manifested by increases in testosterone concentration, in EDTA and NaF-EDTA collection tubes</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the rate of post-collection TU to testosterone conversion, as manifested by increases in testosterone concentration, in EDTA and NaF-EDTA tubes held at room temperature or on ice prior to centrifugation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>magnitude of overestimation of the true circulating testosterone concentration at 5 hours postdose</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the magnitude of overestimation of the true circulating testosterone concentration at 5 hours postdose, when blood was collected in various tubes and the tubes were held at room temperature or on ice.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>healthy men's testosterone levels in serum and plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>To compare healthy men's testosterone levels in serum and plasma from Plain and EDTA tubes, respectively</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the safety and tolerability of JATENZO</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypogonadism, Male</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy men treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects were given 15 doses over 8 days, and then blood was drawn into several types of collection tubes at different storage conditions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testosterone Undecanoate</intervention_name>
    <description>dose was given orally and allowed to reach steady state</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy men treatment arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects were required to meet all of the following criteria in order to be eligible for
        the study:

          1. Male (gender at birth) 18 to 65 years of age, inclusive, and legally able to give
             informed consent, as applicable by law. The percentage of non-Hispanic and Hispanic
             men was specified to be approximately ≥ 70% and ≤ 30%, respectively.

          2. Adequate venous access in the left or right arm to allow collection of a number of
             blood samples via a venous cannula or needle sticks

          3. Naïve to androgen-replacement therapy

          4. Willing to consume the entire protocol-specified breakfast and dinner meals

          5. Average screening systolic blood pressure &lt; 140 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure &lt;
             90 mmHg

          6. Voluntarily gave written informed consent to participate in this study -

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects who met any of the following criteria were not eligible for participation in this
        study:

          1. History of hypertension or taking anti-hypertensive medications

          2. Intercurrent disease deemed clinically significant, in the opinion of the
             Investigator, of any type; in particular, liver, kidney, uncontrolled or poorly
             controlled heart disease, including congestive heart failure, coronary heart disease,
             heart attack or cerebrovascular accident in prior 6 months, or psychiatric-illness,
             including severe depression

          3. Electrocardiogram which Principal Investigator, or designate, believed was clinically
             significantly abnormal

          4. Intercurrent process or disease which could have impacted the absorption of JATENZO,
             in particular vomiting, nausea, diarrhea, or inflammatory bowel disease

          5. Current use of the following groups of drugs that affect testosterone levels,
             testosterone metabolism, or levels of testosterone metabolites, namely antiandrogens,
             5 alpha reductase inhibitors (eg, dutasteride, finasteride), estrogens, long-acting
             opioid analgesics (eg, methadone hydrochloride, buprenorphine hydrochloride), or human
             growth hormone

          6. History of or was currently being evaluated for breast or prostate cancer

          7. Prostate specific antigen above the upper limit of normal

          8. Positive test for antibodies to human immunodeficiency virus type 1 or 2, hepatitis B
             surface antigen, or antibodies to hepatitis C virus at the Screening visit

          9. Positive urine drug test at the Screening visit

         10. Current treatment with oral lipase inhibitors (eg, orlistat [Xenical]), bile
             acid-binding resins (eg, cholestyramine [Questran], colestipol [Colestid]), fibric
             acid derivatives (eg, clofibrate [Atromid-X], gemfibrozil [Lopid]), and probucol
             (Lorelco).

         11. Smokers who were unable to refrain from smoking during the confinement period required
             in this study

         12. Current evidence of or history of abuse of alcohol or any drug substance within the
             previous 2 years

         13. Receipt of any drug as part of a research study within 30 days of initial dose
             administration in this study

         14. Blood donation (usually 550 mL) within the 12-week period before the initial study
             drug dose

         15. Hematocrit &lt; 35% or &gt; 50%

         16. Body mass index ≥ 31 kg/m2 -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clarus Therapeutics, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Northbrook</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60062</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypogonadism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eunuchism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methyltestosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone undecanoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone enanthate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Testosterone 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>November 2, 2019</submitted>
    <returned>November 20, 2019</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

