<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03973450</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Neuroendo-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03973450</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology of Pituitary Tumours: Prevalence of Associated Neoplasia</brief_title>
  <acronym>EpidemioPIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Epidemiology of Pituitary Tumours: Prevalence of Associated Endocrine and Non-endocrine Tumours and Potential Implications in the Management and Follow-up of Patients&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neuromed IRCCS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neuromed IRCCS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to update current knowledge about the epidemiology of pituitary tumours (PiT),
      based on the wide body of scientific literature on new familial and/or syndromic forms.
      Although inherited predisposition is increasingly recognized, its clinical relevance in
      unselected series of PiT patients has not been specifically addressed. In addition, it is
      likely that further recognition of peculiar associations between PiT and other endocrine
      and/or non-endocrine neoplasia will further increase the spectrum of syndromic forms. Since
      the identification of inherited forms of PiT may have significant clinical implications in
      terms of patients management and familial screening, we aim to collect any relevant
      information in order to estimate their prevalence in a large unselected series of PiT
      patients and provide new clues for a modern clinical approach to these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent epidemiological studies indicate that clinically relevant PiT have a prevalence around
      1%. The Neuromed Scientific Institute for Research and Cure (IRCCS) is a third referral
      center for the diagnosis and treatment of patients with hypothalamic-pituitary disorders, and
      PiT represent the most frequent condition.

      The best known syndromic of PiT is Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia type 1 (MEN1), others are
      rare conditions, such as MEN1-like syndromes, Carney complex, Mc Cune Albright syndrome, the
      pheochromocytoma/paraganglioma/Pit syndrome. Apparently isolated familial forms of PiT (FIPA)
      have also been well characterized in the last decade.The genetics of inherited PiT is
      involving a growing number of genes.At the moment, the most frequently reported gene
      abnormalities consist of inactivating mutations of the MEN1 and Aryl hydrocarbon receptor
      Interacting Protein (AIP) genes, which are mainly observed in syndromic and isolated familial
      forms of PiT, respectively.

      On the other hand, patients affected by growth-hormone (GH)-secreting PiT
      (acromegaly/gigantism) have an increased risk of associated neoplasia, which has been mainly
      attributed to the growth-promoting effects of GH and/or Insulin-like Growth Factor 1(IGF1).
      However, a variety of neoplasia have been recently observed in patients with non-functioning
      PiT, whereas patients affected by prolactinoma - the most common PiT phenotype - have been
      poorly studied. Associations between PiT and a variety of neoplasia may represent new forms
      of systemic forms of PiT.

      The aim of the study is to evaluate the prevalence of endocrine and non-endocrine neoplasia
      in a large series of PiTpatients and to identify potential familial and syndromic forms,
      including new forms of tumor associations, in order to provide new insights in the
      epidemiology and genetics of PiT and evaluate their clinical relevance in daily practice.

      Eligible patients will receive a detailed informative form about the aim, methods and
      potential implications of the study. They will be included upon written informed consent and
      be re-assured that they may refuse to participate or withdraw from the study at any time,
      without any prejudice in their clinical management.

      Data will be collected retrospectively in patients followed-up in the last 5 years, when an
      increased awareness of systemic conditions has lead, in the respect of good clinical
      practice, to a systematic registration of familiarity for PiT and/or for associated
      neoplasia. As clinically recommended, most patients have been screened at least once for
      primary hyperparathyroidism (pHPT), which is the most prevalent endocrine tumor in MEN1, and
      thyroid ultrasound, which is generally proposed as an extension of any endocrinological
      visit. Therefore, parathyroid and/or thyroid tumours should have been correctly identified in
      a large majority of patients. In contrast, except for systemic search for colonic polyps or
      tumours by coloscopy in acromegalic patients, and screening for breast and colon cancer
      performed by the patients in the setting of the Italian National Health System (NHS)
      programme since the age of 50 yr-old, no systematic search for additional tumours was
      performed and diagnoses were typically made by the general practitioner and other
      specialists.

      Any relevant clinical, biological or imaging data about PiT and extrapituitary tumours will
      be collected for each patients.

      All data will be collected anonymously in a dedicated Excel file.

      Statistical analysis will be performed with using a commercially available software - JMP
      version 11.0 distributed by Statistical Analysis Systems (SAS) (USA). The first part of the
      report will be descriptive, report all endocrine and non-endocrine neoplasia and potential
      familiarity for PiT and/or any other associated neoplasia. Then, a comparison will be made
      between groups and subgroups of PiT patients defined according to the PiT phenotype
      (functioning and nonfunctioning PiT subgroups, tumour volume and invasiveness), as well as
      gender, age and the presence of a familial setting. Based on public reports of the Italian
      registry of cancer (AIRTUM), an attempt will be made to compare the prevalence of the most
      frequent neoplasia in PiT patients with the general population. Attention will be paid to
      recognize syndromic forms of PiT, including known syndromes and new forms of associations
      between PiT and any endocrine or non-endocrine neoplasia.

      Genetic evaluation and counselling will be proposed in selected cases, based on evaluation of
      the clinical picture with the specialist in clinical genetics present in the study team. A
      specific additional consent will be necessary to proceed to the genetic step and DNA
      conservation for further studies where appropriate. Leukocyte DNA will be collected by blood
      sampling. Diagnostic genetic testing will be appropriately performed according to the
      clinical presentation. For unknown associations, this study is intended to be preliminary to
      further genetic studies aiming to identify new candidate genes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of hyperparathyroidism (HPT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of plasma Parathormone (PTH) in % of upper limit of normal values (ULN)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of hypercalcemia (hypercalcemic hyperparathyroidism)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of calcemia (mg/dl)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Search for secondary cause of hyperparathyroidism (1): vit D deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months (where indicated)</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of plasma 25(OH)D (ng/ml)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Search for secondary cause of hyperparathyroidism (2): renal failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of plasma creatinine (mg/dl)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of thyroid nodules</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Thyroid ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of other endocrine and non-endocrine neoplasia (1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report of any neoplasia before the diagnosis of PiT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of other endocrine and non-endocrine neoplasia (2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report of any neoplasia diagnosed during the follow-up of PiT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Familial setting (1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Report of any available information concerning familiarity for PiT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Familial setting (2)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Familiarity for any associated neoplasia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetics (1) familial forms of PiT</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>AIP gene sequencing upon genetic counselling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetics (2) familial PiT and/or association with HPT</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>MEN1 sequencing upon genetic counselling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetics (3) any other clinical suspicion for MEN1</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>MEN1 gene sequencing upon genetic counselling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetics (4) any other clinical suspicion of inherited neoplasia syndrome</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 15 months</time_frame>
    <description>genetic counselling for appropriate gene sequencing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Pituitary Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Endocrine Neoplasia</condition>
  <condition>Hyperparathyroidism</condition>
  <condition>Solid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Familial Tumor Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pituitary tumours</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients affected by pituitary tumours and followed-up at the Neuroendocrinology Unit over a 5 yrs period (2014-2018)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Registration of familial forms and associated neoplasia</intervention_name>
    <description>Retrospective registration of associated endocrine and non-endocrine neoplasia and potential familial setting</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pituitary tumours</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Genetic counselling where appropriate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We estimate that more than 500 patients followed at the Neuroendocrinology unit meet the
        eligibility criteria for the study period, and that a majority of them will accept to enter
        the study. Patients are affected prevalently by functional pituitary tumours (prolactinomas
        about 50%, followed by acromegaly about 20%, corticotroph tumours..), others have
        clinically non-functiong pituitary tumours (about 25%). The large majority of patients are
        adult (&gt; 90 %).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient affected by a documented endocrine pituitary tumour (PiT)

          -  At least one evaluation during the study period (2014-2018)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Uncertain diagnosis of endocrine pituitary tumour

          -  Any adult patient declining to enter the study

          -  For the (few) patients aged less than 18 years, parents or legal tutors declining to
             include the patient in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie-Lise Jaffrain-Rea, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neuromed IRCCS, Pozzilli (IS), Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marie-Lise Jaffrain-Rea, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+393487813716</phone>
    <email>marielise.jaffrain@univaq.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alba Di Pardo, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+393483631480</phone>
    <email>dipardoa@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daly AF, Rixhon M, Adam C, Dempegioti A, Tichomirowa MA, Beckers A. High prevalence of pituitary adenomas: a cross-sectional study in the province of Liege, Belgium. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2006 Dec;91(12):4769-75. Epub 2006 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>16968795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandez A, Karavitaki N, Wass JA. Prevalence of pituitary adenomas: a community-based, cross-sectional study in Banbury (Oxfordshire, UK). Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2010 Mar;72(3):377-82. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2009.03667.x. Epub 2009 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19650784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caimari F, Korbonits M. Novel Genetic Causes of Pituitary Adenomas. Clin Cancer Res. 2016 Oct 15;22(20):5030-5042. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27742789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbetta S, Pizzocaro A, Peracchi M, Beck-Peccoz P, Faglia G, Spada A. Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 in patients with recognized pituitary tumours of different types. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 1997 Nov;47(5):507-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9425388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alrezk R, Hannah-Shmouni F, Stratakis CA. MEN4 and CDKN1B mutations: the latest of the MEN syndromes. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2017 Oct;24(10):T195-T208. doi: 10.1530/ERC-17-0243. Epub 2017 Aug 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28824003</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thakker RV, Newey PJ, Walls GV, Bilezikian J, Dralle H, Ebeling PR, Melmed S, Sakurai A, Tonelli F, Brandi ML; Endocrine Society. Clinical practice guidelines for multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1). J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2012 Sep;97(9):2990-3011. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-1230. Epub 2012 Jun 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22723327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsson DS, Hammarstrand C, Bryngelsson IL, Nilsson AG, Andersson E, Johannsson G, Ragnarsson O. Incidence of malignant tumours in patients with a non-functioning pituitary adenoma. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2017 May;24(5):227-235. doi: 10.1530/ERC-16-0518. Epub 2017 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>28274953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Terzolo M, Reimondo G, Berchialla P, Ferrante E, Malchiodi E, De Marinis L, Pivonello R, Grottoli S, Losa M, Cannavo S, Ferone D, Montini M, Bondanelli M, De Menis E, Martini C, Puxeddu E, Velardo A, Peri A, Faustini-Fustini M, Tita P, Pigliaru F, Peraga G, Borretta G, Scaroni C, Bazzoni N, Bianchi A, Berton A, Serban AL, Baldelli R, Fatti LM, Colao A, Arosio M; Italian Study Group of Acromegaly. Acromegaly is associated with increased cancer risk: a survey in Italy. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2017 Sep;24(9):495-504. doi: 10.1530/ERC-16-0553. Epub 2017 Jul 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28710115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Toole SM, Dénes J, Robledo M, Stratakis CA, Korbonits M. 15 YEARS OF PARAGANGLIOMA: The association of pituitary adenomas and phaeochromocytomas or paragangliomas. Endocr Relat Cancer. 2015 Aug;22(4):T105-22. doi: 10.1530/ERC-15-0241. Epub 2015 Jun 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26113600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beckers A, Aaltonen LA, Daly AF, Karhu A. Familial isolated pituitary adenomas (FIPA) and the pituitary adenoma predisposition due to mutations in the aryl hydrocarbon receptor interacting protein (AIP) gene. Endocr Rev. 2013 Apr;34(2):239-77. doi: 10.1210/er.2012-1013. Epub 2013 Jan 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23371967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bilezikian JP, Bandeira L, Khan A, Cusano NE. Hyperparathyroidism. Lancet. 2018 Jan 13;391(10116):168-178. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(17)31430-7. Epub 2017 Sep 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28923463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jaffrain-Rea ML, Daly AF, Angelini M, Petrossians P, Bours V, Beckers A. Genetic susceptibility in pituitary adenomas: from pathogenesis to clinical implications. Expert Rev Endocrinol Metab. 2011 Mar;6(2):195-214. doi: 10.1586/eem.10.87.</citation>
    <PMID>30290451</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Daly AF, Vanbellinghen JF, Khoo SK, Jaffrain-Rea ML, Naves LA, Guitelman MA, Murat A, Emy P, Gimenez-Roqueplo AP, Tamburrano G, Raverot G, Barlier A, De Herder W, Penfornis A, Ciccarelli E, Estour B, Lecomte P, Gatta B, Chabre O, Sabaté MI, Bertagna X, Garcia Basavilbaso N, Stalldecker G, Colao A, Ferolla P, Wémeau JL, Caron P, Sadoul JL, Oneto A, Archambeaud F, Calender A, Sinilnikova O, Montañana CF, Cavagnini F, Hana V, Solano A, Delettieres D, Luccio-Camelo DC, Basso A, Rohmer V, Brue T, Bours V, Teh BT, Beckers A. Aryl hydrocarbon receptor-interacting protein gene mutations in familial isolated pituitary adenomas: analysis in 73 families. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2007 May;92(5):1891-6. Epub 2007 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17244780</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 31, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 4, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Neuromed IRCCS</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marie-Lise Jaffrain-Rea, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Endocrinology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endocrine Gland Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplastic Syndromes, Hereditary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperparathyroidism</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

