<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03624829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>273932</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03624829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Shared Care and Usual Health Care for Mental and Comorbid Health Problems</brief_title>
  <official_title>Shared Care and Usual Health Care for Mental and Comorbid Health Problems. A Cluster Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Akershus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Akershus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim is to study the impact on patients and health care by an adaption of the Hamilton
      Family Health Team model of shared care between general practitioners (GPs), mental health
      services and other primary or specialized services. The study is done at six GP centers with
      30 GPs in three boroughs in Oslo, Norway.

      At each GP center with shared care one clinical psychologist from a CMHC works two and a half
      day a week and a psychiatrist 1-2 hours a week. They are available for the GPs for
      discussions, and they give assessment and brief treatment as requested by the GPs. Other
      primary health and social care and other specialized mental health or substance addiction
      services are consulted according to needs of the patients.

      The study is a cluster randomized controlled study of GP patients and their health care in GP
      centers with shared care (experimental group) compared with usual health care in other GP
      centers (control group). In each of three boroughs one GP center is randomized to shared care
      for 18 months while another center continues with usual health care.

      Register data on patients and services are extracted for 12 months (T0) before implementation
      of shared care and for 12 months (T1) with shared care after 6 months implementation. The
      register data on patients and health care are extracted from the GP patient records, mental
      health and substance abuse services, and NAV (social/welfare services). The cohorts at T0 and
      T2 include all patients 16-65 years old seen by the GPs.

      Patient-reported mental health, functional impairment due to health problems, overall quality
      of life and satisfaction with health services are studied for a sub-sample of the register
      cohort at both T0 and T1.

      A qualitative sub-study of experiences with collaboration, the shared care model,
      implementation of the model, facilitators and barriers is done at the end of the 18 months
      period of shared care. The informants include patients, GPs and coworkers, and managers and
      professionals involved with shared care.

      The study protocol was approved by the regional and national committees on medical and health
      research, as well as by the data protection officer at health trust.

      Progress and status are described in Detailed description. Data analysis starts in September
      2018.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND

      There have been various forms of collaboration in Norway between community mental health
      centres (CMHCs), GPs and primary health and social care. But with a lack of research on such
      models, there is little knowledge on whether they contribute to better health care, outcome
      and satisfaction, e.g. for the large group of patients with moderately severe mental and
      comorbid health problems mostly seen by GPs. There is a great need for clearly defined
      collaboration models and for research-based knowledge of their feasibility and impact in the
      context of the Norwegian health services.

      Reviews of studies on collaboration show inconsistent results, including insufficient
      evidence to demonstrate significant benefits from shared care (Smith 2009), modest reductions
      in primary care consultations and mental health referrals (Harkness 2009), partly improved
      depression management (Butler 2011), and research primarily on simpler models of
      collaboration between two professionals (Hviding et al. 2008, Craven et al 2006).

      The Family Health Teams model developed in Hamilton, Canada, is a promising model of shared
      care (Kates 2011a, 2011b). It is built around GP practices. Each team include one or more
      GPs, nurses, mental health counsellors, a visiting consultant psychiatrist, and some other
      part-time staff (pharmacist, nutritionist, physiotherapist, occupational therapist). The
      model has increased access to care for persons with mental health and addiction problems,
      reduced waiting time, reduced referrals to outpatient mental health services, increased
      patient satisfaction, improved patient health, improved communication and co-ordination, and
      increased GPs' confidence and skills in treating mental health problems.

      CONTEXT

      The study is done in three Oslo boroughs (Alna, Grorud, Stovner) with a total population of
      108 000. They are served by a total of 85 GPs in GP centers, by the primary health and social
      care in the boroughs, and by a community mental health center (CMHC), child and adolescent
      mental health services (CAMHS) and other departments of the Division Mental Health Services
      at Akershus University Hospital.

      INTERVENTION

      The intervention is an adapted version of shared care with close collaboration by services
      and professional groups, mainly localized in three GP centers. At each GP center one clinical
      psychologist specialist from the community mental health center (CMHC) works two and a half
      day a week, and a psychiatrist from the CMHC work at each GP center 1-2 hours a week. The
      psychologist and the psychiatrist are available for the GPs for consultation and discussions,
      and they give assessment and brief treatment to patients as requested by the GPs. Other
      primary health and social care and other specialized mental health or substance addiction
      services are involved or consulted according to needs of the patients.

      The decisions on the adaption of the model were taken by the collaborating services
      themselves in October-December 2015 after a joint visit to Hamilton by 14 persons and with
      input from the research group. This secured that the services had ownership and commitment to
      the model and contributed to make it feasible and useful.

      The shared care in the three experimental GP centers was established during the winter of
      2016 and were operational for 18 months from the April/May 2016 to October/November 2017. The
      implementation was supported by discussions in monthly meetings at each GP center for the
      professionals collaborating on shared care there, and in monthly meetings at the CMHC between
      the psychologists and psychiatrists in shared care, managers at the CMHC and the principal
      investigator of the research study.

      AIMS

      The aim is to study the impact of a Norwegian adaption of the Hamilton Family Health Team
      model of shared care between general practitioners (GPs), mental health services and other
      primary or specialised services.

      RESEARCH QUESTIONS

        1. What are the characteristics of patients seen in the usual GP practices (ICPC-2 codes,
           mental health problems, comorbidity of mental and somatic health problems)?

        2. How is the total usual health care for the GP patients from GPs, primary health and
           social care, and mental health and substance addiction services?

        3. How is the patient-reported mental health, functioning and satisfaction with health
           services and collaboration in among patients seen in usual GP practices?

        4. Is shared care associated with changes in access to mental health care, referrals to
           specialized mental health care, use of health services and distribution of patients
           across services?

        5. What is the patient course and outcome (waiting time, sick leave, mental health,
           functioning, duration of treatment) with shared care compared to usual health care?

        6. Is there a more integrated care for comorbidity (concurrent mental/somatic/substance
           addiction problems) in shared care than in usual health care?

        7. How are the GP patients' experiences with shared care compared to usual health care?

        8. What do health professionals in shared care experience as main advantages and
           disadvantages of shared care?

        9. What do health professionals in shared care identify as facilitating factors or barriers
           for implementing shared care?

      METHODS

      CLUSTER RANDOMIZED CONTROLLED REGISTER STUDY ON IMPACT OF SHARED CARE

      The study is a cluster randomized controlled study of GP patients and their health care in
      shared care (experimental group) compared with usual health care (control group). In each of
      three boroughs one GP center is randomized to have shared care for 18 months while another GP
      center continues with usual health care. Register data on patients and health care are
      extracted for 12 months (T0) before the implementation of shared care and for 12 months (T1)
      with shared care (after 6 months with implementation of the shared care model).

      Retrospective register data on patients and use of services for the two 12 months periods (T0
      and T1) are extracted from the GP patient records, Akershus University Hospital (mental
      health and substance addiction services for adults and youth), and NAV (social/welfare
      services). Patient cohorts at T0 and T1 include all patients 16-65 years old seen by the 30
      GPs in 12 months. Based on earlier studies each cohort was expected to be 20-25 000 patients.
      In 2014 the 30 GPs referred 840 patients to outpatient mental health clinics and 190 to
      inpatient mental health wards. Based on this, significant changes in referrals to outpatient
      clinics (main primary outcome) are expected to be shown by comparing periods of 12 months.

      In the data analyses of the impact of shared care the experimental sites are compared with
      control sites at T1, as well as with all sites at T0, including a difference-in-difference
      analysis (research questions 4-6). Data analysis on usual health care at T0 will include
      descriptive analyses and analyses to identify and compare different patient subgroups or
      patterns of use of health care in this unique combined data set from the several services for
      a large group of GP patients (research questions 1-2).

      SUB-STUDY ON PATIENT-REPORTED HEALTH AND SATISFACTION

      Patient-reported mental health, functional impairment due to health problems, overall quality
      of life and satisfaction with health services are studied for a sub-sample of the register
      cohort at both T0 and T1. GP patient 16-65 years old are recruited during two weeks at each
      GP center with some assistance from research staff. Included patients give written consent
      and complete a brief questionnaire in Norwegian or English. Inclusion criteria and secondary
      outcome measures in the questionnaire are shown in the tables. The sample is a sub-sample of
      the register cohorts at T0 and T1. To identify a difference of 6 points on the mental health
      measure CORE-10 between T0 and T1 with 5% two-tailed significance and 90 % power 70 patients
      per arm is needed in a cluster randomized trial with ICC=0.03 and 12 GPs in each arm
      (Eldridge 2012, Schultz 2010, Moher 2010). Aiming to recruit 600-750 patients (20-25 per GP)
      will secure a more than large enough sub-sample for the main secondary outcome measure
      (CORE-10). Data analyses of patient-reported information will answer research question 3 and
      parts of research questions 4 and 5.

      QUALITATIVE SUB-STUDY ON EXPERIENCES WITH SHARED CARE

      A qualitative sub-study of experiences with collaboration in general, the shared care model,
      implementation of the model, facilitators and barriers is done at the end of the 18 months
      period of shared care. Focus groups are conducted with the GPs in each of the GP centers
      (experimental and control centers), and individual qualitative interviews are done with
      approximately 15 patients with experience of shared care, nurses and other co-workers at the
      GP centers, professionals involved with shared care in the primary health and social
      services, managers at the CMHC and the psychologists and psychiatrist from CMHC working in
      the shared care. This qualitative study is done in stead of a planned survey with a
      questionnaire to health personnel, as the number of potential informants would be too small
      for statistical analyses compared to what was expected when planning the study. Analyses of
      the qualitative data will answer the research questions 7-9.

      ETHICAL APPROVAL

      The study protocol was approved by the Regional Committee on Medical and Health Research
      Ethics Health Region South East 08 May 2014 (reg.no. 2014/435), by the National Committee on
      Medical and Health Research Ethics in Norway 10 November 2014 (reg.no. 2014/160) and by the
      Data Protection Officer at Akershus University Hospital (reg.no. 13/138). The National
      Committee on Medical and Health Research Ethics approved that the study fulfilled the
      necessary legal criteria to extract structured register data from the services without giving
      the patients information or asking for written consent. The approved protocol of 2014 is
      attached to this registration.

      PROGRESS AND STATUS OF THE STUDY

      Data extraction of the register cohorts was done from the GP electronic patient records in
      2015 and 2017, from the mental health services at Akershus University Hospital in 2017-2018
      and from the NAV (social/welfare services) in 2017-2018. Data collection from the two
      clinical cohorts at the GP centers was done in 2015 and 2017. Quality control and
      organization of data was done 2017-2018. Data analysis starts in September 2018.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 18, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Referrals from GPs to mental health outpatient clinics</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Referrals from GPs to mental health outpatient clinics during the period for data extraction</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Referrals from GPs to mental health inpatient wards</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Referrals from GPs to mental health inpatient wards during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waiting time from the referral to the first consultation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Days from the outpatient clinic has received a referral to the first consultation for a referral during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of GP consultations</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patient consultations at the GP center during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of outpatient consultations</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patient consultations at the outpatient clinic during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of inpatient days</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total number of inpatient days across all inpatient stays during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of an outpatient treatment episode</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Days from first consultation to last consultation of a series of outpatient consultations after a referral to the outpatient clinic during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of an inpatient stay</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Days from the inpatient admission to discharge after a referral to the inpatient ward during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of sick leave</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Days from first to last day of a period of sick leave clinic during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type of health problem</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>ICPC-2 codes in PG practices and/or ICD-10 diagnosis in mental health care during the period for data extraction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The severity of psychiatric symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Global Assessment of Functioning - subscale for symptoms (GAF-S), used in mental health services</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The severity of impairment in functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Global Assessment of Functioning - subscale for functional impairment (GAF-F), used in mental health services</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported mental health problems</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In the questionnaire to patients: Clinical Outcome in Routine Evaluation (CORE-10) with 10 items on mental health problems (Barkham 2013). Each item is answered on a 5-point scale of frequency from 0=&quot;not at all&quot; to 4=&quot;most of the time&quot;. The 10 items comprise the following: depression (2 items), anxiety (2 items), functioning (3 items, 1 each for 'general' 'social', and 'close'); trauma (1 item); physical (1 item); and suicidal risk (1 item). Two of the items are positively framed. The ten items are summed (reversing the two positive items) to a total score with a range from 0 to 40, where a higher total sum score means more severe mental health problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported impairment in functioning due to health problems</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In the questionnaire to patients: Work and Social Adjustment Scale (WSAS) with five items on impairment of functioning in various domains due to health problems (Mundt 2002). Each item is answered on a 5-point scale of degree of impairment from 0=&quot;not at all&quot; to 4=&quot;very much&quot; (adapted from the original 9-point scale from 0 to 8 to fit with the 5-point scales in the rest of the brief questionnaire). The five items comprise the following: Work/education, housework, social activities, activities alone, contact/relationship with family/others. The five items are summed to a total score with a range from 0 to 20, where a higher total sum score means more severe impairment of functioning due to health problems.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction with health services</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In the questionnaire to patients and developed for the study: Three items for a subscale on satisfaction with the GP (for access, met with respect, get help as needed), three items for a subscale on satisfaction with the mental health services (for access, met with respect, get help as needed) if such contact last 12 months, and three items for a subscale on satisfaction with the collaboration between the health services (their collaboration, their understanding of the situation, the usefulness of their total help). Each item is answered on a 5-point scale of degree of impairment from 1=&quot;very dissatisfied&quot; to 5=&quot;very satisfied&quot;. For each subscale the three items are summed to a total score with a range from 3 to 15, where a higher total sum score means a higher degree of satisfaction with the specific services.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall quality of life (MANSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In the questionnaire to patients: A single question on overall quality of life is taken from the Manchester Short Assessment of Quality of Life (MANSA), which is a questionnaire on quality of life used in many recent studies (Priebe 1999). The question is answered on a 5-point scale of degree of satisfaction with overall quality of life from 1=&quot;very dissatisfied&quot; to 5=&quot;very satisfied&quot; (adapted from the original 7-point scale in MANSA to fit with the 5-point scales in the rest of the brief questionnaire).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19000</enrollment>
  <condition>Mental Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exp: Patients of GPs with shared care</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients 16-65 years old who during 12 months have been in contact with a GP in any of the three GP centers that are randomized to shared care before the 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Con: Patients of GPs without shared care</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients 16-65 years old who during 12 months have been in contact with a GP in any of the three GP centers that are not randomized to shared care before the 12 months, and all patients 16-65 years old who during 12 months have been in contact with a GP in any of the six GP center before the randomization and implementation of shared care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shared care</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is an adapted version of shared care with close collaboration by services and professional groups, mainly localized in three GP centers. At each GP center one clinical psychologist specialist from the community mental health center (CMHC) works two and a half day a week, and a psychiatrist from the CMHC work at each GP center 1-2 hours a week. The psychologist and the psychiatrist are available for the GPs for consultation and discussions, and they give assessments and brief treatments to patients as requested by the GPs. Other primary health and social care and other specialized mental health or substance addiction services are involved or consulted according to needs of the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exp: Patients of GPs with shared care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The total sample of patients seen by any of the GPs at the six participating GP centers
        during the 12 months of retrospective data extraction from patient registers before
        randomization of GP centers to shared care, and patients seen by any of the GPs at the six
        participating GP centers during the 12 months of retrospective data extraction from patient
        registers during the period where three of the GP centers have shared care. The samples
        from the two time periods are different, but they may partly overlap as many patients are
        expected to se GPs during both periods.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Seen by a GP during the 12 months for extracted data on all contact

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No exclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tormod Fladby, Dr.Med.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Akershus</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Smith SM, Allwright S, O'Dowd T. Effectiveness of shared care across the interface between primary and specialty care in chronic disease management. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2007 Jul 18;(3):CD004910. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2017 Feb 23;2:CD004910.</citation>
    <PMID>17636778</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Harkness EF, Bower PJ. On-site mental health workers delivering psychological therapy and psychosocial interventions to patients in primary care: effects on the professional practice of primary care providers. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Jan 21;(1):CD000532. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD000532.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19160181</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Butler M, Kane RL, McAlpine D, Kathol R, Fu SS, Hagedorn H, Wilt T. Does integrated care improve treatment for depression? A systematic review. J Ambul Care Manage. 2011 Apr-Jun;34(2):113-25. doi: 10.1097/JAC.0b013e31820ef605. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21415610</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hviding K, Bugge P, Ekern P, Brelin P, Høifødt TS, Nessa J, Flottorp S (2006). Samhandling om pasienter med alvorlige psykiske problemer i allmennpraksis. [Collaboration regarding patients with severe mental problems in general practice]. Rapport Nr 1-2008. Oslo, Nasjonalt kunnskapssenter for helsetjenesten, 2008.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Craven MA, Bland R. Better practices in collaborative mental health care: an analysis of the evidence base. Can J Psychiatry. 2006 May;51(6 Suppl 1):7S-72S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16786824</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kates N, Mazowita G, Lemire F et al (2011a). The Evolution of Collaborative Mental Health Care in Canada; A shared vision for the future. Position paper. The Canadian Journal of Psychiatry 56(5).</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kates N, McPherson-Doe C, George L. Integrating mental health services within primary care settings: the Hamilton Family Health Team. J Ambul Care Manage. 2011 Apr-Jun;34(2):174-82. doi: 10.1097/JAC.0b013e31820f6435.</citation>
    <PMID>21415615</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Eldridge S, Kerry S. A practical guide to cluster randomised trials in health services research. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Chichester, UK, 2012</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schulz KF, Altman DG, Moher D; CONSORT Group. CONSORT 2010 Statement: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials. BMC Med. 2010 Mar 24;8:18. doi: 10.1186/1741-7015-8-18.</citation>
    <PMID>20334633</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moher D, Hopewell S, Schulz KF, Montori V, Gøtzsche PC, Devereaux PJ, Elbourne D, Egger M, Altman DG; Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials Group. CONSORT 2010 Explanation and Elaboration: Updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trials. J Clin Epidemiol. 2010 Aug;63(8):e1-37. doi: 10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.004. Epub 2010 Mar 25. Erratum in: J Clin Epidemiol. 2012 Mar;65(3):351.</citation>
    <PMID>20346624</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barkham M, Bewick B, Mullin T, Gilbody S, Connell J, Cahill J, Mellor-Clark J, Richards D, Unsworth G, Evans C. The CORE-10: A short measure of psychological distress for routine use in the psychological therapies, Counselling and Psychotherapy Research: Linking research with practice, 2013. 13(1):1-13,</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Mundt JC, Marks IM, Shear MK, Greist JH. The Work and Social Adjustment Scale: a simple measure of impairment in functioning. Br J Psychiatry. 2002 May;180:461-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11983645</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Priebe S, Huxley P, Knight S, Evans S. Application and results of the Manchester Short Assessment of Quality of Life (MANSA). Int J Soc Psychiatry. 1999 Spring;45(1):7-12.</citation>
    <PMID>10443245</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital, Akershus</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Torleif Ruud</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Researcher, Professor emeritus</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>February 12, 2014</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/29/NCT03624829/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

