<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03626077</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>205-S-37</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03626077</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biofeedback Training and Physical Therapy Program Improves Visual-motor Integration in Children With Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Augmented Biofeedback Training Combined With Physical Therapy Program Improves Visual-motor Integration, Visual Perception and Motor Coordination in Children With Spastic Hemiplegic Cerebral Palsy: a Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Princess Nourah Bint Abdulrahman University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Princess Nourah Bint Abdulrahman University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study was to investigate potential benefits of adding augmented biofeedback
      training to standard therapy in improving visual motor integration (VMI) visual perception
      (VP) and motor coordination (MC) in children with hemiplegic cerebral palsy .Participants
      were divided randomly into three equal groups. Group (A) received specially designed program
      of physical therapy intervention strategies to facilitate visual motor integration and visual
      perception over a period of three months. Group (B) received augmented biofeedback training
      only, and group (C) received augmented biofeedback training and same physical therapy program
      as group (A).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Children were assigned randomly into three groups of equal number (A, B and C). Children were
      selected randomly by collecting all names of children that matched the inclusion criteria of
      the study then upload the names and gender using an electronic program (SPSS) which divided
      the sample into three equal groups (A), (B) &amp; (C).

      Group A: this group included fifteen children with spastic hemiplegic CP. Children of this
      group received specially designed program of physical therapy exercises to facilitate
      eye-hand coordination and fine motor to improve VMI, VP and MC, which included: unbutton
      buttons, and button in all again; put the pellets in the bottle as fast as he/she can; place
      the shapes on its form board; build steps, wall, pyramid and a tower from cubes; cut out a
      line, square, triangle, and rectangular shapes on a paper by scissor; string squared cubes
      and lace the holes of strip. The tools used in training program were: button strip, lacing
      strip and its lace, mottle with screw- on cap, markers with different colors, beads and its
      lacing, square cubes, pellets, papers, blunt scissors, colored cubes, different types of form
      board and its shapes. Adjusted chair and table were used to accommodate differences in
      children's body built. Children were trained for 60 minutes per session, three times a week
      for three consecutive months.

      Group B: this group included fifteen children with spastic hemiplegic CP. Children of this
      group received training using the E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser for 60 minutes per session,
      three times a week for three consecutive months.

      Group C: this group included fifteen children with spastic hemiplegic CP. Children of this
      group received the same physical therapy program as conducted for group A, and training with
      E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser as conducted for group B. The training was for 60 minutes per
      session, three times a week for three consecutive months.

      The participated children were assessed by Beery-Buktenica Developmental Test before and
      after the three months of the treatment program. The average time required for evaluating
      each child was 40 min. The assessment and training methods were applied according to the
      instructions provided in the test and equipment manuals, no modifications were necessary.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 29, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 29, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Beery-Buktenica Developmental Test of Visual-Motor Integration (6th edition) &quot;change&quot; is being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>10-15 minutes total, it is taken at baseline and after 3 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>it evaluate the subject's ability to integrate visual and motor skills, through copying</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beery-Buktenica Developmental Test- Visual Perception test. &quot;change&quot; is being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes, it is taken at baseline and after 3 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>it evaluates subject visual perception (VP) and motor coordination matching shapes to stimulus form</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beery-Buktenica Developmental Test-Motor Coordination test. &quot;change&quot; is being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes, it is taken at baseline and after 3 months of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>it evaluates subject motor coordination through tracing within a confined space</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemiplegic Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group (A) physical therapy program for 60 minutes per session, three times a week for three consecutive months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group (B) E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser (augmented biofeedback training)for 60 minutes per session, three times a week for three consecutive months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>group (C) physical therapy program and E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>physical therapy program</intervention_name>
    <description>this group received specially designed physical therapy program to facilitate eye-hand coordination and fine motor to improve VMI, VP and MC, which included: unbutton buttons, and button in all again; put the pellets in the bottle as fast as he/she can; place the shapes on its form board; build steps, wall, pyramid and a tower from cubes; cut out a line, square, triangle, and rectangular shapes on a paper by scissor; string squared cubes and lace the holes of strip.Children were trained for 60 minutes per session, three times a week for three consecutive months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser</intervention_name>
    <description>The exercises in the E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser System are in the form of simple and exciting games such as soccer, hitting walls, space shooting, driving, arnd throwing balls into a bucket.Children were trained for 60 minutes per session, three times a week for three consecutive months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>physical therapy program and E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser</intervention_name>
    <description>physical therapy program and E-Link Upper Limb Exerciser. Children were trained for 60 minutes per session, three times a week for three months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>group C</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  grade of spasticity between 1 to 1+ according to Modified ashworth Scale, the ability
             to handle objects independently was between level (I) and (II) according to Manual
             Ability Classification System (MACS), no history of epilepsy; no botulinum toxin A
             treatment for the upper extremities in the previous 6 months, and able to understand
             and follow verbal commands and instructions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  presence of visual or auditory impairments, significant tightness or fixed deformities
             in the upper limbs, severe spasticity, autism, or severe cognitive impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>8 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Reem M Alwhaibi, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Princess Nourah Bint Abdulrahman University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Disabled Children's Association</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riyadh</city>
        <state>Alnakeel</state>
        <zip>11055</zip>
        <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Princess Nourah Bint Abdulrahman University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Reem M Alwhaibi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual-Motor Integration</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual Perception</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>data from participants will be made available</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>12 months after study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>data access requests will be reviewed by an external independent review panel. requestors will be required to sign a data access agreement.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

