<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03625427</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-2316</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03625427</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Palmitoleic Acid on C-reactive Protein</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Palmitoleic Acid on Circulating C-reactive Protein Levels in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Organic Technologies</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This clinical trial will test the effects of an n-7 monounsaturated fatty acid known as
      palmitoleic acid (POA) on a chronic inflammation marker in overweight subjects. The study
      will enroll male and female subjects from healthy populations with high levels of the
      inflammatory marker c-reactive protein (CRP). Investigators will then determine over time if
      palmitoleic acid supplementation can lower circulating levels of c-reactive protein.
      Investigators will administer palmitoleic acid at two doses in addition to a placebo and
      conduct a double-blind parallel arm study. Circulating CRP will be the primary endpoint and
      secondary endpoints are Interleukin 6 (IL-6), Tumor necrosis factor (TNF) alpha, ghrelin,
      peptide tyrosine tyrosine (peptide YY), cardio lipid markers, glucose, insulin, leptin,
      adiponectin, and red blood cell (RBC) and serum fatty acids.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Palmitoleic acid (POA) is a monounsaturated fatty acid that has recently been shown to
      function as a lipokine and is present in the human diet and in blood serum. While there is
      emerging evidence that POA can positively impact beta cell proliferation, reduce lipogenesis,
      support endothelial function, and suppress cytokine production, POA remains to be poorly
      studied for its beneficial anti-inflammatory potential. The latest studies suggest that POA
      could attenuate inflammation in metabolically active tissues. Therefore, the objective of
      this study is to determine if administration of POA in 2 varying doses to overweight
      participants with biomarkers of chronic inflammation will lower circulating c-reactive
      protein (CRP) and cytokine levels, as well as improve metabolism by lowering levels of
      circulating leptin and raising expression of adiponectin. The rationale for focusing on
      overweight individuals is that they routinely have elevated c-reactive protein levels and are
      highly prone to have chronic inflammation.

      Investigators propose a 12-week randomized, double blinded study to assess changes in select
      inflammatory markers, ghrelin, peptide YY, cardiovascular lipids, fatty acid levels, and
      glucose sensitivity markers in volunteers consuming either the test agent, 500 mg or 1,000 mg
      POA per day, or an olive oil containing fatty acid (placebo). There are three arms to study
      and 41 individuals per arm, thus, a total of 123 subjects. Approximately 30% loss of subjects
      is expected. Administration of the POA supplements and placebo (olive oil capsules) will be
      double blinded. The study sponsor will hold the code for the subjects and will randomize the
      capsules. Only the study sponsor will have the code. The identity of the capsules will be
      revealed after the completion of the study. Subjects will bring back their bottles at each of
      the concurrent visits and the end of the study to assess compliance and to account for any
      missed doses of POA. The rationale for selecting olive oil as a placebo is that olive oil is
      routinely consumed by the public. Additionally, oleic acid (the active ingredient of olive
      oil) is the most prevalent fatty acid in human circulation, and olive oil is a routine
      placebo for fatty acid intervention studies. The olive oil will not be extra virgin olive oil
      that has several bioactive components. POA is virtually tasteless, thus participants should
      not be able to self-identify their regimen of either placebo or active test agent. The
      rationale for the experimental dose follows what is commercially available in POA products,
      which average 700 mg per day and generally range from 450 - 1000 mg per day regimens. The
      rationale for the 12-week time frame is to ensure uptake of POA into the target cells.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>12-week randomized, double blinded study in volunteers consuming either the test agent, 500 mg or 1,000 mg POA per day, or an olive oil containing fatty acid (placebo). There are three arms to study and 41 individuals per arm, thus, a total of 123 subjects.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Administration of the POA supplements and placebo (olive oil capsules) will be via a simple randomized double-blinded allocation. The study sponsor will provide the Principal Investigator with bags, or boxes, of single serve packets containing two capsules for each daily dose per participant in accordance with the proper dosage for each of the three arms of the study. The study sponsor will hold the code for the subjects and will randomize the capsules. No site personnel will have access to the randomization allocation; only the study sponsor will have the code. The identity of the capsules will be revealed once all analyses are complete.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean c-reactive protein circulating level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating CRP level by high-sensitivity c-reactive protein laboratory blood analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating cytokine IL-6 level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating cytokine IL-6 level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating cytokine TNF alpha level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating cytokine TNF alpha level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating ghrelin level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating ghrelin level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating peptide YY level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating peptide YY level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating leptin level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating leptin level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean circulating adiponectin level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate circulating adiponectin level by ELISA (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean glucose/insulin ratio level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate glucose/insulin ratio level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean HbA1c level</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood draws will be used to evaluate HbA1c level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">123</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Inflammation</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The placebo is olive oil, stripped of polyphenols, 70% oleic acid, and will be administered at two 1 gram capsules per day for twelve weeks. The doses will be administered in single serve packets containing two capsules for each daily dose to be taken at breakfast.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palmitoleic acid, 500 mg (Dose 1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>POA Dose 1 is a 1 gram capsule containing 500 mg POA and one placebo capsule containing 500 mg olive oil per day for twelve weeks. The doses will be administered in single serve packets containing two capsules for each daily dose to be taken at breakfast.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Palmitoleic acid, 1,000 mg (Dose 2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>POA Dose 2 is two, 1 gram capsules containing 500 mg POA, totaling 1,000 mg POA per day for twelve weeks.The doses will be administered in single serve packets containing two capsules for each daily dose to be taken at breakfast.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo is olive oil, stripped of polyphenols, 70% oleic acid, administered as two 1-gram capsules per day. Packaged as single-serve packets containing 2 capsules for each daily dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Olive oil</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palmitoleic acid, 500 mg (Dose 1)</intervention_name>
    <description>Palmitoleic acid (POA) 1 gram capsules containing 500 mg POA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Palmitoleic acid, 500 mg (Dose 1)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>POA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palmitoleic acid, 1,000 mg (Dose 2)</intervention_name>
    <description>Palmitoleic acid (POA) taken as two 1 gram capsules each containing 500 mg POA</description>
    <arm_group_label>Palmitoleic acid, 1,000 mg (Dose 2)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>POA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject will be free-living, middle-aged to older men and women between ages 30-80
             years with BMIs between 25.0-40.0, and CRP greater than or equal to 2.0 mg/L

          2. Generally healthy adults

          3. Understand protocol and comply to take supplements during the trial

          4. Ability to understand English

          5. Be able to report to clinical research center, fasting, at least 3 times

          6. Women who are of childbearing potential should be on birth control (one method is
             acceptable)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. BMI higher than 40.0

          2. Taking anti-hyperlipidemia medications (including statins)

          3. Taking anti-diabetic medications

          4. Auto-immune disease

          5. Documented cognitive impairment

          6. Unable to draw blood from veins

          7. Alcohol or other drug dependency

          8. Are currently breastfeeding, or pregnant, or plan to become pregnant

          9. Have experienced a significant weight change of 10%, or more, of body weight in
             previous 3 months

         10. If on hormone therapy, no change during study

         11. Chronic use of NSAIDs

         12. Decreased QOL due to pathology, such as cancer, genetic diseases, Rx side effects, or
             injury

         13. Taking fish oil, within 8 weeks of enrollment

         14. Taking Seabuckthorn supplements

         15. Taking sterols or fat blockers

         16. Fish allergies
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Saame R Shaikh, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tondra S Blevins</last_name>
    <phone>(704) 305-5709</phone>
    <email>tondra_blevins@unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Traci Davis, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 843-5145</phone>
    <email>traci_davis@unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina Nutrition Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kannapolis</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28081</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jomari Torres, MD</last_name>
      <phone>704-250-5062</phone>
      <email>jomari_torres@unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frigolet ME, Gutiérrez-Aguilar R. The Role of the Novel Lipokine Palmitoleic Acid in Health and Disease. Adv Nutr. 2017 Jan 17;8(1):173S-181S. doi: 10.3945/an.115.011130. Print 2017 Jan. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28096141</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yadav A, Kataria MA, Saini V, Yadav A. Role of leptin and adiponectin in insulin resistance. Clin Chim Acta. 2013 Feb 18;417:80-4. doi: 10.1016/j.cca.2012.12.007. Epub 2012 Dec 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23266767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schirmer M, Smeekens SP, Vlamakis H, Jaeger M, Oosting M, Franzosa EA, Ter Horst R, Jansen T, Jacobs L, Bonder MJ, Kurilshikov A, Fu J, Joosten LAB, Zhernakova A, Huttenhower C, Wijmenga C, Netea MG, Xavier RJ. Linking the Human Gut Microbiome to Inflammatory Cytokine Production Capacity. Cell. 2016 Nov 3;167(4):1125-1136.e8. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2016.10.020. Erratum in: Cell. 2016 Dec 15;167(7):1897. Cell. 2016 Dec 15;167(7):1897.</citation>
    <PMID>27814509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Souza CO, Vannice GK, Rosa Neto JC, Calder PC. Is Palmitoleic Acid a Plausible Nonpharmacological Strategy to Prevent or Control Chronic Metabolic and Inflammatory Disorders? Mol Nutr Food Res. 2018 Jan;62(1). doi: 10.1002/mnfr.201700504. Epub 2017 Dec 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28980402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bernstein AM, Roizen MF, Martinez L. Purified palmitoleic acid for the reduction of high-sensitivity C-reactive protein and serum lipids: a double-blinded, randomized, placebo controlled study. J Clin Lipidol. 2014 Nov-Dec;8(6):612-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jacl.2014.08.001. Epub 2014 Aug 19.</citation>
    <PMID>25499944</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 10, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 11, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 11, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 13, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>palmitoleic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>monounsaturated fatty acid</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Deidentified individual data that supports the results will be shared beginning 9 to 36 months following publication provided the investigator who proposes to use the data has approval from an Institutional Review Board (IRB), Independent Ethics Committee (IEC), or Research Ethics Board (REB), as applicable, and executes a data use/sharing agreement with the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>9 to 36 months following publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>A Data Use Agreement (DUA) specifying the uses of such data to be shared must be in place before any data is shared. The requestor should contact the Principal Investigator for further instruction.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

