<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03620994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20188517</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03620994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Predictive Value of Alarm Symptoms in Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome Based on Rome IV</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Predictive Value of Alarm Symptoms in Patients With Irritable Bowel Syndrome Based on Rome IV</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is one of the most commonly diagnosed functional bowel
      disorders (FBD). IBS is diagnosed by symptom-based criteria，while the available literature
      suggests that symptom-based diagnostic algorithms, which often used for clinical and research
      studies, have poor sensitivity. Although diagnostic algorithms can discriminate IBS from
      health or upper gastrointestinal tract conditions, studies do not provide convincing evidence
      that the criteria can discriminate IBS from organic disease of the colon. Rectal bleeding,
      anemia, weight loss, fever, family history of colon cancer, and age above 50 years are
      considered the warning signs of severe gastrointestinal disease. Colonoscopy is the most
      direct way to rule out organic colonic diseases. There is no consensus so far on whether
      patients with suspected IBS lacking warning signs need colonoscopy or not. In 2016, the Rome
      IV criteria was updated and published. However, there are few studies on the clinical
      practice based on Rome IV. The value of alarm symptoms in discriminating organic disease from
      functional disorders remains uncertain and further research is needed. To evaluate the
      predictive value of alarm symptoms of IBS patients based on Roman IV, the investigators
      designed this cross-sectional study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Functional bowel disorders (FBD) are a spectrum of chronic gastrointestinal (GI) disorders
      characterized by predominant symptoms or signs of abdominal pain bloating, distention, and/or
      bowel habit abnormalities, and the absence of obvious anatomic or physiologic abnormalities
      identiﬁed by routine diagnostic examinations, as deemed clinically appropriate. Irritable
      bowel syndrome (IBS) is one of the most commonly diagnosed functional bowel disorders (FBD).
      characterized by abdominal pain and bowel dysfunction, presenting as constipation, diarrhea,
      or alternating periods of both. Incidence rates of IBS are seldom calculated, and prevalence
      estimates fluctuate both between and within countries. A literature review by Sperber and
      colleagues suggests that a global prevalence rate could not be estimated owing to the
      heterogeneity of the studies. The pooled prevalence rate that the investigators cited for
      North America, Europe, Australia, and New Zealand was 8.1%. While IBS is not associated with
      increased mortality rates, it represents a significant burden on affected patients and
      society as a result of direct medical costs, lost productivity, and reduced health-related
      quality of life.

      The development and persistence of IBS symptoms are understood to be multifactorial.
      Consequently, diagnosis and treatment are complicated clinical endeavors. IBS is diagnosed by
      symptom-based criteria, initially proposed by Manning and subsequently modified and
      quantified in the Rome I, II, and III criteria. However, the available literature suggests
      that symptom based diagnostic algorithms, although often used for clinical and research
      studies, have poor sensitivity. Although diagnostic algorithms can discriminate IBS from
      health or upper gastrointestinal tract conditions, studies do not provide convincing evidence
      that the criteria can discriminate IBS from organic disease of the colon. Therefore, in
      clinical practice, medical history should include evidence of organic disease (alarm
      symptoms) in addition to the main symptoms. Rectal bleeding, anemia, weight loss, fever,
      family history of colon cancer, and age above 50 years are considered the warning signs of
      severe gastrointestinal disease. Colonoscopy is the most direct way to rule out organic
      colonic diseases. It is an agreement that patients who meet Rome criteria on IBS with warning
      signs are strongly advised to perform colonoscopy to rule out severe colonic diseases such as
      inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) and colorectal cancer . The diagnostic sensitivity of
      symptom criteria on irritable bowel syndrome without colonoscopy is not more than 69.7% in
      patients with suspected irritable bowel syndrome lacking warning signs. There is no consensus
      so far on whether patients with suspected IBS lacking warning signs need colonoscopy or not.
      However, the value of alarm symptoms in discriminating organic disease from functional
      disorders remains uncertain and further research is needed, especially as alarm features are
      common.

      In 2016, the Rome IV criteria was updated and published, in which IBS involved several
      changes. And there are currently few clinical studies based on Roman IV. This cross-sectional
      study was designed to evaluate the predictive value of alarm symptoms for IBS and organic
      bowel diseases and the difference in predictive value between different subtypes based on
      Roman IV.

      Data collection：Basic information: name, gender, race, age, BMI index (height, weight),
      marital status ；Gastrointestinal symptoms: IBS-related symptoms，change in form of
      stool，duration and incidence of symptoms； Alarm Symptoms: Rectal bleeding (black stool, blood
      on toilet paper), anemia, weight loss, fever, nocturnal symptoms； Lifestyle habits: eating
      habits (spicy stimulation, dietary fiber), smoking, drinking, sleep quality, daily exercise
      time; Family history: colorectal cancer, inflammatory bowel disease, celiac disease, etc;
      Personal history: history of gastrointestinal infections, life emergency events; Test
      results: laboratory test results，colonoscopy results. The investigators obtained relevant
      information through consultation, telephone follow-up, questionnaire follow-up.Through
      endoscopy results to determine organic or functional diseases, benign or malignant, through
      contacts with the basic data, to determine the alarm symptoms. Further more, this study was
      proved by the ethical committee of second hospital of Xi'an jiaotong university.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of organic bowel diseases</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To collect the results of colonoscopy in patients who meet inclusion criteria, and to calculate the incidence of organic bowel diseases to analyze the predictive value of alarm symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of organic bowel diseases in different subtypes of IBS</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To collect the results of colonoscopy in patients who meet subtypes criteria, and to calculate the incidence of organic bowel diseases to compare the difference in predictive value of alarm symptoms for different subtypes of IBS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients who were satisfied with the inclusion criteria and exclusion criteria in the department of the second affiliated hospital of Xi'an JiaoTong University, Xijing Hospital ,Tangdu Hospital or affiliated hospital of Northwest University received investigation. Patients who participate in the study are determined on their own initiative, with full understanding and informedness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        From August 2018 to March 2019, patients went to the Gastroenterology clinics of the second
        affiliated hospital of Xi'an JiaoTong University, Xijing Hospital ,Tangdu Hospital or
        affiliated hospital of Northwest University who met the inclusion criteria were followed
        up.Subjects are voluntarily involved in the study, provided that they are fully understood
        and informed. The patients included in this study are all patients who underwent
        colonoscopy and signed an informed consent form for colonoscopy.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of Irritable bowel syndrome symptoms，that is，recurrent abdominal pain, on
             average, at least 1 day per week in the last 3 months, associated with 2 or more of
             the following criteria:

             Related to defecation;

             Associated with a change in frequency of stool;

             Associated with a change in form (appearance) of stool.

             （Criteria fulﬁlled for the last 3 months with symptom onset at least 6 months before
             diagnosis.）

          2. Aged 18 years and older;

          3. August 2018 to March 2019, patients went to the Gastroenterology clinics of the second
             affiliated hospital of Xi'an JiaoTong University, Xijing Hospital ,Tangdu Hospital or
             affiliated hospital of Northwest University , and received Colonoscopy;

          4. Blood routine examination, fecal routine examination, and fecal occult blood test were
             conducted within 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previously diagnosed with diseases that better explain the participant's IBS symptoms
             (e.g. celiac disease, colorectal cancer, inflammatory bowel disease, microscopic
             colitis, lactose intolerance, bile acid malabsorption, intestinal tuberculosis,
             diverticulosis, ischemic enteritis, etc.);

          2. Metabolic disease: uncontrolled thyroid disease and diabetes;

          3. Severe neurological and psychiatric disorders, which may impede conduct of the
             clinical trial. These disorders include but are not limited to major depression with a
             high risk of suicidal behavior (i.e. intent or plan), alcohol or substance
             abuse/dependence, a lifetime history of psychosis;

          4. Participant has an unstable severe extraintestinal medical condition (such as heart,
             liver, kidney and respiratory failure) with immediate or foreseeable treatment needs;

          5. Previous major abdominal surgery that would have resulted in significant changes in
             the anatomy or physiology of the gastrointestinal tract, which can fully explain GI
             symptoms. Note: appendectomy, cholecystectomy, endoscopic polypectomy, endoscopic
             mucosal resection and endoscopic submucosal resection are not excluded criteria;

          6. Were pregnant, might become pregnant, or were lactating;

          7. Colonoscopy for structural evaluation of the GI tract in the past 6 months due to
             their IBS symptoms;

          8. Taking anti-anxiety, anti-depressant drugs or intestinal sensitive antibiotics
             recently;

          9. A current infection or infection of any type within the 2 weeks prior to evaluation
             that would obscure the presentation of IBS symptoms, in which case the assessment can
             be delayed until 2 weeks after full recovery;

         10. Currently diagnosed malignancy, with exception of localized basal or squamous cell
             carcinomas of the skin which is completely removed. The so-called &quot;current&quot; means that
             the diagnosis of any malignancy (except basal cells or squamous cell carcinoma) that
             is active occurs within the first 12 months of enrollment;

         11. Refusal to participate in this study or who cannot follow the research requirements
             for various reasons.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>The Second Affiliated Hospital of Xi'an Jiaotong University,Xi'an, Shanxi, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-29-18700932477</phone>
    <email>jinhaiwang@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yang Qian</last_name>
    <phone>+86-29-15091893818</phone>
    <email>1565952553@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The second affiliated hospital of xi'an jiaotong university</name>
      <address>
        <city>Xi'an</city>
        <state>Shanxi</state>
        <zip>710004</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jinhai Wang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86-29-18700932477</phone>
      <email>jinhaiwang@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yang Qian</last_name>
      <phone>+86-29-15091893818</phone>
      <email>1565952553@qq.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 5, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>alarm symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Roman IV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

