<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03628417</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>032104/2016/OTIG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03628417</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Confirmatory Trial in the Evaluation of Ca Electroporation for the Treatment of Cutaneous Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fázis II, randomizált, kettős Vak vizsgálat a bőr metasztázisok kezelésére kálcium elektroporációval</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Szeged University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Szeged University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Electroporation is a method that can facilitate transport of molecules across the cell
      membrane and into the cell by means of electrical pulses. The method can be used with
      molecules that normally have difficulty passing the cell membrane such as chemotherapy
      (electrochemotherapy). Electrochemotherapy (ECT) is used in cancer therapy, where
      chemotherapy is administered intratumoral or intravenous, then followed by electrical pulses
      applied directly on the tumor. The chemotherapy accumulates in the cancer cells which results
      in an increased cytotoxic effect. The most used chemotherapeutic drug used in
      electrochemotherapy is bleomycin. Electrochemotherapy is a well-documented local treatment
      form for especially cutaneous tumors. Today, the treatment is used mostly in palliative care
      in more than 140 centres around Europe.

      In vitro and in vivo studies have shown that the combination of calcium and electroporation
      is an effective method in killing cancer cells without serious side effects.This new
      combination opens the possibility of replacing bleomycin with calcium in treatments with
      electroporation.

      Calcium electroporation is a local treatment where calcium is administered intratumoral and
      followed by electrical pulses applied on the tumor.

      The preclinical studies have shown that there is a difference in sensitivity in tumor cells
      and normal cells, as normal cells tolerate the treatment better than tumor cells (own data
      manuscript in preparation). The studies have also shown that there is no cell injury by
      calcium injection without electroporation, the investigators therefore expect that the
      treatment only will cause minor side effects.

      Calcium electroporation would be possible to use on patients for whom chemotherapy is
      contradicted e.g. severe lung functions impairment, pregnant woman etc. Calcium
      electroporation is a simple and unexpensive cancer treatment that does not involve any
      administration of cytotoxic chemotherapy, and can be performed by surgeons, radiologists as
      well as oncologists. Both electroporation equipment and calcium are already being used in the
      clinic, so the treatment can easily be implemented.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Trial Design for Treatment of Cutaneous Metastases:

      The current study is a randomized double blinded phase II study comparing the effect of
      calcium electroporation with ECT with bleomycin on patients with cutaneous metastases of any
      histology. As calcium and bleomycin are administered intratumoral, only small metastases from
      0.5-3 cm will be treated. The treatments will be compared in tumor response and adverse
      events. Treatment will be done in a palliative purpose.

      Cancer patients with cutaneous involvement have often several metastases. A maximum of ten
      metastases will be included per patient. One to six metastases (depending on the patient's
      number of metastases) will be numbered 1-6 and randomized into one of two treatment arms

        1. Intratumoral calcium followed by electroporation

        2. Intratumoral bleomycin followed by electroporation Randomization will be performed
           separately on each metastasis, so the patient may receive both treatments. Calcium and
           bleomycin will be mixed into syringes labeled with numbers according to the metastases
           and both treating doctor and patient will be blinded to the content of the syringes.

      If the patient has more than six metastases, then one to four metastases will be used for
      biopsy. The treatment of these metastases will be known, and biopsies will be performed
      before and after treatment.

      Biopsies will only be performed if the patient has more than six metastases. The metastases
      used for biopsy will not be evaluated on response.

      The treatment will be performed in local or general anesthesia depending on location and
      number of metastases. Bleomycin/calcium will be administered intratumorally and immediately
      after the electrode will be placed on the metastasis. The electric pulses are generated using
      a cliniporator according to ESOPE (European Standard Operating Procedure of
      Electrochemotherapy). The therapy is a once only treatment and the patients will be followed
      up with regular clinical controls for six months. At follow up six months after treatment,
      the randomization code for the one patient will be revealed. If the patient agrees, biopsies
      will then be taken from an area treated with calcium and an area treated with bleomycin. Last
      visit will be one year after treatment.

      To identify the metastases at follow up visits, the metastases will be marked with a pen,
      numbered and documented with clinical photos at baseline.

      Randomization The metastases are randomized by block randomization and are done separately in
      each patient. The randomization is performed by an extern unit, using the computer program
      nQuery Adviser 7.0. The bleomycin and calcium are mixed and labeled by an extern unit, and
      since both calcium and bleomycin are transparent and identical in volume, it is possible to
      label the syringes in a manner to blind the treating doctor. The syringes are labeled with
      numbers according to the metastases so syringe number &quot;1&quot; goes to metastasis number &quot;1&quot; and
      so on. The randomization code is kept behind locked doors, and is not accessible to the
      treating doctor. The randomization code is revealed for each patient after follow up, 6
      months after treatment.

      The randomization code can be revealed before completion of the investigation, if the
      investigator believes that the treatment causes so serious unexpected events or reactions,
      that a continuation of treatment is unacceptable.

      As the randomization is done separately in each patient, code-break is possible for the
      individual patient, without breaking the code of the other participants.

      Dose In the preclinical study, the tumors were treated with isotonic calcium chloride
      solution 168 mmol/L and with a volume equivalent to 0.5 x tumor volume, and this with good
      effect. In another preclinical study the investigators have tested the effect of this dose in
      different tumor types and saw variable results of the response rate. Some tumor types showed
      slightly lower response at this dose (own data, manuscript in preparation). Because of this
      experience the investigators have decided to increase the dose of calcium chloride, in this
      trial, to 220 mmol/L.

      Volume of calcium chloride is dependent on tumor volume. Smaller tumors should have bigger
      volume per cm³, as smaller tumors are expected to have a bigger loss of injected medicine
      into the surrounding tissue. The dose volume is calculated according to the &quot;European
      Standard Operating Procedure of the Electrochemotherapy (ESOPE)&quot;.

      Calcium

      Calcium chloride 220 mmol/L (9 mg/ml):

        -  Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ - 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume

        -  Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ - 0.5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab2π/6 (a = longest diameter, b
           = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)

      Bleomycin Both dose and volume of bleomycin is standard according to ESOPE

      Bleomycin 1000 IU/ml:

        -  Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ - 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume

        -  Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ - 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter,
           b= longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)

      Maximum of injected bleomycin per tumor will be 1500 IU and total dose per treatment 7500 IU.
      Normal maximum limit for bleomycin is 15.000 IU/m² body surface area.

      Bleomycin and calcium chloride are mixed and labeled according to current guidelines. The
      mixtures will be used in a maximum of 6 hours after mixing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 20, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 4, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 4, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This randomized double blinded phase II study is comparing the effect of calcium electroporation with ECT with bleomycin on patients with cutaneous metastases of any histology where the metastases are randomized by block randomization and are done separately in each patient.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate (RECIST1.1) of Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy on Cutaneous Metastases at Day 180.</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Documentation was done with digital color photography, including a ruler to estimate tumor size. Primary evaluation of the response was based on criteria similar RECIST 1.1 guidelines and defined as complete response (CR) - disappearance of the lesion, partial response (PR) - at least 30% decrease in the largest diameter of the lesion, progressive disease - at least 20% increase in the largest diameter of the lesion and stable disease - neither 30% decrease nor 20% increase of the largest diameter of the lesion.
Change in the largest diameter:</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events for Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy. The Adverse Reactions Are Classified According to CTCAE Version 4.0 (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events).</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Event, AE: Any adverse events in a patient that occur or worsen during the trial and does not necessarily have a causal relationship to study treatment
Adverse Reaction, AR: All noxious and unintended reactions to a trial drug at any dose (possible relation between the study drug and the adverse reaction cannot be excluded)
Unexpected Adverse Reaction, UAR: An adverse reaction with a nature or severity that is not in accordance with the current product information (Investigator's Brochure)
Serious Adverse Event, SAE: an event or side effect that at any dose:
Results in death
Is life threatening
Leads to hospitalization or prolongation of hospital stay
Results in persistent or significant disability or incapacity
Leads to a congenital anomaly or birth defect
Is a major medical event
Suspected Unexpected Serious Adverse Reactions, SUSARs: adverse reactions that are not described in the product information for the experimental drug</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The Tertiary Outcome is to Register if Calcium Affects the Current Strength in Electroporation Treatments.</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 - During Ca-electroporation and bleomycin based electrochemotherapy interventions</time_frame>
    <description>We measured the maximum electric current which was given to the metastases. The measurement was needed because the current is unknown during Ca-electroporation, and also we would like to determine wether there is a difference between bleomycin based electrochemotherapy and calcium electroporation in current.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Cutaneous Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium Electroporation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Calcium
Calcium chloride 220 mmol/L (9 mg/ml):
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ - 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ - 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bleomycin based electrochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bleomycin
Bleomycin 1000 IU/ml:
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ - 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ - 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)
Maximum of injected bleomycin per tumor will be 1500 IU and total dose per treatment 7500 IU. Normal maximum limit for bleomycin is 15.000 IU/m² body surface area.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcium Electroporation</intervention_name>
    <description>If the patient agrees biopsies will be performed from the tumor area before and after electroporation during local anaesthesia. Maximum of 8 biopsies will be done, depending on the patient's number of metastases.
All patient's regardless of the number of metastases will have one biopsy from area treated with calcium and one from area treated with bleomycin, after the randomization code is revealed at day 180.
Patients with more than 6 metastases: One to two biopsies before treatment, one to two biopsies one week after treatment from metastases treated with calcium and bleomycin respectively.
All biopsies will be handled according to current guidelines and analyzed by a pathologist for amount of tumor tissue, inflammation, fibrosis and necrosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium Electroporation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bleomycin based electrochemotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>If the patient agrees biopsies will be performed from the tumor area before and after electroporation during local anaesthesia. Maximum of 8 biopsies will be done, depending on the patient's number of metastases.
All patient's regardless of the number of metastases will have one biopsy from area treated with calcium and one from area treated with bleomycin, after the randomization code is revealed at day 180.
Patients with more than 6 metastases: One to two biopsies before treatment, one to two biopsies one week after treatment from metastases treated with calcium and bleomycin respectively.
All biopsies will be handled according to current guidelines and analyzed by a pathologist for amount of tumor tissue, inflammation, fibrosis and necrosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bleomycin based electrochemotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years.

          -  Verified cutaneous metastases of any histology.

          -  At least one cutaneous metastases between 0.5 to 3 cm and accessible to
             electroporation.

          -  The patient should have been offered current standard treatment. If there is no
             further standard treatment to offer, or if the patient does not want to receive this,
             the patient may be included in the trial.

          -  Treatment free interval of more than two weeks. However, patients treated with
             Navelbine (Vinorelbine) Capecitabine (Xeloda) or weekly paclitaxel (Taxol) can
             continue these treatments, if there is no regression of cutaneous metastases. Other
             medical cancer treatments such as endocrine treatment, targeted treatment and
             radiotherapy to another area may also continue.

          -  Performance status World Health Organization (WHO) ≤ 2.

          -  Expected survival of &gt; 3 months.

          -  Platelets ≥ 50 billion/L, international normalized ratio (INR) &lt; 1.5. Medical
             correction is allowed, e.g. correction of a high INR using vitamin K.

          -  Sexually active men and women who can become pregnant should use adequate
             contraception during this trial (pill, spiral, injection of prolonged progestin,
             subdermal implantation, hormone-containing vaginal devices, transdermal patches).

          -  The patient should be able to understand the information.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous bleomycin treatment with more than 200,000 U/m² .

          -  History of severe allergic reactions associated with bleomycin.

          -  Coagulation disorder which cannot be corrected.

          -  Pregnancy and lactation.

          -  Participating in other clinical trials involving experimental drugs or involved in a
             trial within 4 weeks prior to study drug administration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <link>
    <url>http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/0284186X.2017.1355109</url>
    <description>Calcium electroporation for treatment of cutaneous metastases; a randomized double-blinded phase II study, comparing the effect of calcium electroporation with electrochemotherapy</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Falk H, Forde PF, Bay ML, Mangalanathan UM, Hojman P, Soden DM, Gehl J. Calcium electroporation induces tumor eradication, long-lasting immunity and cytokine responses in the CT26 colon cancer mouse model. Oncoimmunology. 2017 Mar 17;6(5):e1301332. doi: 10.1080/2162402X.2017.1301332. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28638724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>September 24, 2019</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>December 31, 2019</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 31, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 31, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Szeged University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Erika Kis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator, Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cutaneous metastases</keyword>
  <keyword>calcium electroporation</keyword>
  <keyword>bleomycin electroporation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bleomycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>September 24, 2019</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/17/NCT03628417/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Participants with cutan metastases of melanoma malignum and breast cancer were followed-up at one of the academic medical center in Hungary between September 2016 and June 2019 based on oncologist refferal.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Enrolled participants were not excluded from the study before assignment to groups. Block randomization was performed separately on each metastasis, so the patients received both treatments.
The bleomycin and calcium syringes were mixed and labeled with numbers according to the metastases.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Calcium Electroporation</title>
          <description>Volume of calcium chloride (220 mmol/L) was dependent on tumor volume. Smaller tumors should have bigger volume per cm³, as smaller tumors were expected to have a bigger loss of injected medicine into the surrounding tissue.The dose volume was calculated according to the 'European Standard Operating Procedure of the Electrochemotherapy'.
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ – 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ – 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;) Biopsies were performed from the tumor area before and after electroporation. Maximum of 8 biopsies were done, depending on the patient’s number of metastases. All patient’s regardless of the number of metastases had one biopsy from area treated with calcium and one from area treated with bleomycin, after the randomization code was revealed at day 180.
All biopsies were handled and analyzed by a pathologist for amount of tumor tissue, inflammation, fibrosis and necrosis.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy</title>
          <description>Both dose and volume of bleomycin (1000 IU/ml) was standard according to ESOPE.
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ – 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ – 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;) Maximum of injected bleomycin per tumor was 1500 IU and total dose per treatment was 7500 IU.
Biopsies were performed from the tumor area before and after electroporation. Maximum of 8 biopsies were done, depending on the patient’s number of metastases. All patient’s regardless of the number of metastases had one biopsy from area treated with bleomycin and one from area treated with calcium, after the randomization code was revealed at day 180.
All biopsies will be handled according to current guidelines and analyzed by a pathologist.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 0</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 7</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 15</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 30</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 60</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 90</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Day 180</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6">One patient died and 3 more Ca electroporated lesions were removed before the one-year closing visit</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6">One patient died before the one-year closing visit,this is why decreased the number of metastases</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Death</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>All Study Participants</title>
          <description>All participants receiving Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Age</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="70" lower_limit="49" upper_limit="83"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex/Gender, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Caucasian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Patients with cutaneous metastases</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Patients with MM cutaneous metastases</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Patients with breast cc. cutaneous metastases</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Response Rate (RECIST1.1) of Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy on Cutaneous Metastases at Day 180.</title>
        <description>Documentation was done with digital color photography, including a ruler to estimate tumor size. Primary evaluation of the response was based on criteria similar RECIST 1.1 guidelines and defined as complete response (CR) - disappearance of the lesion, partial response (PR) - at least 30% decrease in the largest diameter of the lesion, progressive disease - at least 20% increase in the largest diameter of the lesion and stable disease - neither 30% decrease nor 20% increase of the largest diameter of the lesion.
Change in the largest diameter:</description>
        <time_frame>180 days after treatment</time_frame>
        <population>There were 7 patients with a total of 44 cutaneous metastases which were randomized. We chose up to 10 tumours on each patient. At the first 6 tumours we examined the clinical response rate, and (if they had more) the rest 4 were used for biopsy. 33 from the 44 lesions were evaluated in clinical response, the rest were used for biopsy.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Calcium Electroporation</title>
            <description>Volume of calcium chloride (220 mmol/L) was dependent on the tumor volume. Smaller tumors should have bigger volume per cm3, as smaller tumors were expected to have a bigger loss of injected medicine into the surrounding tissue. The dose volume was calculated according to the 'European Standard Operating Procedure of the Electrochemotherapi (ESOPE)'.
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ – 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ – 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)
All patient’s regardless of the number of metastases have had one biopsy from area treated with calcium and one from area treated with bleomycin, after the randomization code is revealed at day 180.
All biopsies were handled according to current guidelines and analyzed by a pathologist for amount of tumor tissue, inflammation, fibrosis and necrosis.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy</title>
            <description>Both dose and volume of bleomycin (1000 IU/ml) is standard according to ESOPE.
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ – 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ – 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)
Maximum of injected bleomycin per tumor was1500 IU and total dose per treatment 7500 IU. Normal maximum limit for bleomycin was 15.000 IU/m² body surface area.
All patient’s regardless of the number of metastases have had one biopsy from area treated with calcium and one from area treated with bleomycin, after the randomization code is revealed at day 180.
All biopsies were handled according to current guidelines and analyzed by a pathologist for amount of tumor tissue, inflammation, fibrosis and necrosis.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Response Rate (RECIST1.1) of Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy on Cutaneous Metastases at Day 180.</title>
          <description>Documentation was done with digital color photography, including a ruler to estimate tumor size. Primary evaluation of the response was based on criteria similar RECIST 1.1 guidelines and defined as complete response (CR) - disappearance of the lesion, partial response (PR) - at least 30% decrease in the largest diameter of the lesion, progressive disease - at least 20% increase in the largest diameter of the lesion and stable disease - neither 30% decrease nor 20% increase of the largest diameter of the lesion.
Change in the largest diameter:</description>
          <population>There were 7 patients with a total of 44 cutaneous metastases which were randomized. We chose up to 10 tumours on each patient. At the first 6 tumours we examined the clinical response rate, and (if they had more) the rest 4 were used for biopsy. 33 from the 44 lesions were evaluated in clinical response, the rest were used for biopsy.</population>
          <units>cutaneous metastases</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <units_analyzed>cutaneous metastases</units_analyzed>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
            <analyzed>
              <units>cutaneous metastases</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="18"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="15"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>CR</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>PR</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>SD</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>PD</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <groups_desc>After reviewing existing data from electrochemotherapy with intratumoral bleomycin on small cutaneous metastases ≤3cm , we estimated the expected response rate for electrochemotherapy to 85%. We have no clinical results for the treatment of calcium electroporation, but on the basis of preclinical studies, we decided to accept a difference in response of 20%. All statistical analysis were done using IBM SPSS v24.</groups_desc>
            <non_inferiority_type>Non-Inferiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <non_inferiority_desc>Examined the objective response rate (ORR) that there was 20% difference between the 2 treatment arms at day 180. With a significance level of 0,05 and a power of 80% the study required 28 evaluable metastases.</non_inferiority_desc>
            <p_value>0.30</p_value>
            <method>Fisher Exact</method>
            <param_type>Odds Ratio (OR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.4489629</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>-13.30</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>53.30</ci_upper_limit>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Adverse Events for Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy. The Adverse Reactions Are Classified According to CTCAE Version 4.0 (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events).</title>
        <description>Adverse Event, AE: Any adverse events in a patient that occur or worsen during the trial and does not necessarily have a causal relationship to study treatment
Adverse Reaction, AR: All noxious and unintended reactions to a trial drug at any dose (possible relation between the study drug and the adverse reaction cannot be excluded)
Unexpected Adverse Reaction, UAR: An adverse reaction with a nature or severity that is not in accordance with the current product information (Investigator's Brochure)
Serious Adverse Event, SAE: an event or side effect that at any dose:
Results in death
Is life threatening
Leads to hospitalization or prolongation of hospital stay
Results in persistent or significant disability or incapacity
Leads to a congenital anomaly or birth defect
Is a major medical event
Suspected Unexpected Serious Adverse Reactions, SUSARs: adverse reactions that are not described in the product information for the experimental drug</description>
        <time_frame>180 days after treatment</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Calcium Electroporation</title>
            <description>Experiences from treating small tumors with electrochemotherapy, show that the treated area initially can become erythmatose and swollen, but this fades quickly. The area can then become necrotic which heals within 6-10 weeks. In a few cases, infection may occur in the treatment area. With calcium electroporation we expect to see the same response to treatment.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy</title>
            <description>At electrochemotherapy the most reported adverse events are pain after the procedure and flu-like symptoms. The latter is a reaction to bleomycin and is therefore not expected by calcium electroporation.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Adverse Events for Calcium Electroporation and Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy. The Adverse Reactions Are Classified According to CTCAE Version 4.0 (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events).</title>
          <description>Adverse Event, AE: Any adverse events in a patient that occur or worsen during the trial and does not necessarily have a causal relationship to study treatment
Adverse Reaction, AR: All noxious and unintended reactions to a trial drug at any dose (possible relation between the study drug and the adverse reaction cannot be excluded)
Unexpected Adverse Reaction, UAR: An adverse reaction with a nature or severity that is not in accordance with the current product information (Investigator's Brochure)
Serious Adverse Event, SAE: an event or side effect that at any dose:
Results in death
Is life threatening
Leads to hospitalization or prolongation of hospital stay
Results in persistent or significant disability or incapacity
Leads to a congenital anomaly or birth defect
Is a major medical event
Suspected Unexpected Serious Adverse Reactions, SUSARs: adverse reactions that are not described in the product information for the experimental drug</description>
          <units>cutaneous metastases</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <units_analyzed>cutaneous metastases</units_analyzed>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
            <analyzed>
              <units>cutaneous metastases</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="18"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="15"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Ulceration</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Hyperpigmentation</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Flu-like symptoms</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Itch</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Other Pre-specified</type>
        <title>The Tertiary Outcome is to Register if Calcium Affects the Current Strength in Electroporation Treatments.</title>
        <description>We measured the maximum electric current which was given to the metastases. The measurement was needed because the current is unknown during Ca-electroporation, and also we would like to determine wether there is a difference between bleomycin based electrochemotherapy and calcium electroporation in current.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 0 - During Ca-electroporation and bleomycin based electrochemotherapy interventions</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Calcium Electroporation</title>
            <description>Calcium electroporation is a local treatment where calcium is administered intratumoral and followed by electrical pulses applied on the tumor. Volume of calcium chloride (220 mmol/L) was dependent on tumor volume which was calculated according to the 'European Standard Operating Procedure of the Electrochemotherapy' (ESOPE).
Calcium chloride 220 mmol/L (9 mg/ml):
Tumor &lt; 0,5 cm3 – 1 ml / cm3 tumor volume
Tumor &gt;0,5 cm3 – 0,5 ml/ cm3 tumor volume Tumor volume = ab2π/6 (a=longest diameter, b= longest diameter perpendicular to a)</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy</title>
            <description>Electroporation is a method that can facilitate transport of molecules across the cell membrane and into the cell by means of electrical pulses. The method can be used with molecules that normally have difficulty passing the cell membrane such as chemotherapy (electrochemotherapy).The most used chemotherapeutic drug used in electrochemotherapy is bleomycin (1000 IU/ml). Both dose and volume of bleomycin is standard according to ESOPE.
Bleomycin 1000 IU/ml:
Tumor &lt; 0.5 cm³ – 1 ml/cm³ tumor volume
Tumor &gt; 0.5 cm³ – 0,5 ml/cm³ tumor volume Tumor volume = ab²π/6 (a = longest diameter, b = longest diameter perpendicular to &quot;a&quot;)
Maximum of injected bleomycin per tumor was 1500 IU and total dose per treatment was 7500 IU.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>The Tertiary Outcome is to Register if Calcium Affects the Current Strength in Electroporation Treatments.</title>
          <description>We measured the maximum electric current which was given to the metastases. The measurement was needed because the current is unknown during Ca-electroporation, and also we would like to determine wether there is a difference between bleomycin based electrochemotherapy and calcium electroporation in current.</description>
          <units>Amper</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <units_analyzed>cutaneous metastases</units_analyzed>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
            <analyzed>
              <units>cutaneous metastases</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="18"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="15"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3.850" lower_limit="1.400" upper_limit="9.000"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="4.000" lower_limit="1.400" upper_limit="6.500"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>180 days after treatment</time_frame>
      <desc>Any adverse events in a patient that occur or worsen during the trial and does not necessarily have a causal relationship to study treatment</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Calcium Electroporation</title>
          <description>Experiences from treating small tumors with electrochemotherapy, show that the treated area initially can become erythmatose and swollen, but this fades quickly. The area can then become necrotic which heals within 6-10 weeks. In a few cases, infection may occur in the treatment area. With calcium electroporation we expect to see the same response to treatment.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Bleomycin Based Electrochemotherapy</title>
          <description>At electrochemotherapy the most reported adverse events are pain after the procedure and flu-like symptoms. The latter is a reaction to bleomycin and is therefore not expected by calcium electroporation.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTCAE version 4.0</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Other primary tumor</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>The study has certain limitations, like the small number of enrolled metastases, and the use of different electrodes.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Principal Investigator, Assistant Professor</name_or_title>
      <organization>Szeged University</organization>
      <phone>+36-62-545-259</phone>
      <email>kis.erika.gabriella@med.u-szeged.hu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

