<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03621865</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018_A01390-55</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03621865</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Comparative Pharmacokinetic Study to Evaluate the Ability of a New Formulation to Enhance Curcuminoids Bioavailability</brief_title>
  <acronym>TURBIO</acronym>
  <official_title>A Comparative Pharmacokinetic Study in Healthy Volunteers to Evaluate the Ability of TURMIPURE GOLD Formulation to Enhance the Bioavailability of Curcuminoids</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Naturex SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biofortis Mérieux NutriSciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Naturex SA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rhizome of Curcuma longa (turmeric) is commonly used as a spice and for its medicinal
      properties traditionally in Asian countries. Turmeric extract usually contains 95%
      curcuminoids with a specific ratio (approximately 75-80% curcumin, 15-20% demethoxycurcumin
      (DMC), and 0-10% bisdemethoxycurcumin (BDMC)).

      Curcuminoids have higher solubility in organic solvents than in water. As a consequence,
      curcuminoids have low aqueous solubility and poor gastrointestinal absorption. They also
      exhibit rapid metabolism and systemic elimination and are therefore known to have limited
      bioavailability, which limits the use of turmeric extract in general health care and as an
      adjunct in managing various diseases. In order to improve the bioavailability of curcumin,
      several approaches have been undertaken. The use of adjuvant like piperine that interferes
      with glucuronidation; liposomal curcumin, nanoparticles, phospholipid complex; and structural
      analogues of curcumin.

      Recently, Naturex has developed a dried emulsion formulation using a turmeric extract mixed
      together with a quillaja extract, sunflower oil and arabic gum. This formulation is highly
      dispersible in water and should therefore improve the bioavailability of curcuminoids. The
      aim of this study is to assess the bioavailability of curcuminoids and their metabolites
      after oral intake of 4 turmeric extract-based formulations in comparison to a standard
      unformulated turmeric extract.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rhizome of Curcuma longa (turmeric) is commonly used as a spice and for its medicinal
      proprieties traditionally in Asian countries. Turmeric has been studying in different
      therapeutic areas. Antioxidant, anti-inflammatory (respiratory system, joints and digestive),
      antimutagenic, antimicrobial, neurological disease, hepatoprotective and anticancer
      properties are supported by in vitro and in vivo data.

      Curcumin has been studied as the main bioactive component of turmeric associated to its
      potential health effect. However, besides curcumin, others components have been identified
      (demethoxycurcumin DMC and bisdemethoxycurcumin BDMC); this group of coumpounds are named
      together &quot;curcuminoids&quot;. Curcuminoids are natural yellow-orange pigments and hydrophobic
      polyphenols derived from the rhizome of the herb Curcuma longa. They are commonly isolated
      from the spice and food-coloring agent turmeric. Extracts of turmeric generally contain
      75-80% curcumin, 15-20% DMC, and 0-10% BDMC. Regarding the intrinsic property, curcuminoids
      have higher solubility in organic solvents than in water. As a consequence, curcuminoids have
      low aqueous solubility and poor gastrointestinal absorption. They also exhibit rapid
      metabolism and systemic elimination.

      This leads to the conclusion that curcuminoids from turmeric extract have low
      bioavailability, which limits its use in general health care and as an adjunct in managing
      various diseases. In order to improve the bioavailability of curcumin, several approaches
      have been undertaken. The use of adjuvant like piperine that interferes with glucuronidation;
      liposomal curcumin, nanoparticles, phospholipid complex; and structural analogues of
      curcumin.

      Recently, Naturex has developed a dried emulsion formulation using a turmeric extract mixed
      together with a quillaja extract, sunflower oil and arabic gum. This formulation is highly
      dispersible in water and should therefore improve the bioavailability of curcuminoids. The
      aim of this study is to assess the bioavailability of curcuminoids and their metabolites
      after oral intake of 4 turmeric extract-based formulations in comparison to a standard
      unformulated turmeric extract.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 26, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 26, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 26, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This pharmacokinectic study is designed as a monocentric, randomized, cross-over, pilot and open clinical trial</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-normalized AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint is the dose-normalized AUC of total curcuminoids (sum of curcumin, DMC, BDMC and their metabolites) plasmatic concentration from 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24h/dose) (expressed in µg.h/mL/mg). The dose-normalized AUC is the AUC normalized to curcuminoids intake by dividing the observed AUC by the corresponding curcuminoids dosage of each administration The following time-points are considered: T0, T15, T30, T45, T60, T90, T120, T240, T60, T480, T24H. T-10 will be considered as baseline value (T0) for AUC calculation. The primary comparison is Turmipure Gold 300 mg vs Standard turmeric 1500 mg powder extract.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration from 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24h, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations from 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24h, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations from 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24h, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration normalized to curcuminoids intake</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 8 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration from 0 to 8 hours normalized to curcuminoids intake (AUC0-8h/dose, expressed in µg.h/mL/mg);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 8 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration from 0 to 8 hours (AUC0-8h) (expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 8 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations from 0 to 8 hours (AUC0-8h, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 8 hours</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations from 0 to 8 hours (AUC0-8h, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration normalized to curcuminoids intake</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to infinity</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration from 0 to infinity normalized to curcuminoids intake (AUC0-infinity/dose, expressed in µg.h/mL/mg);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to infinity</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration from 0 to infinity (AUC0-infinity, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to infinity</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations from 0 to infinity (AUC0-infinity, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to infinity</time_frame>
    <description>AUC of curcuminoidsmetabolites plasmatic concentrations from 0 to infinity (AUC0-infinity, expressed in µg.h/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration normalized to curcuminoids intake</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration normalized to curcuminoids intake (Cmax/dose, expressed in µg/mL/mg);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration (Cmax, expressed in µg/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak of curcuminoids separately plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak of curcuminoids separately plasmatic concentrations (Cmax, expressed in µg/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Peak of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations (Cmax, expressed in µg/mL);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Half-life of total curcuminoids in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Half-life of total curcuminoids in plasma (t1/2, expressed in minutes);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Half-life of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Half-life of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) in plasma (t1/2, expressed in minutes);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Half-life of curcuminoids metabolites in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Half-life of curcuminoids metabolites in plasma (t1/2, expressed in minutes);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination rate constant of total curcuminoids in plasma (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal elimination rate constant of total curcuminoids in plasma (λz);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination rate constant curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) in plasma (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal elimination rate constant curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) in plasma (λz);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal elimination rate constant curcuminoids metabolites in plasma (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal elimination rate constant curcuminoids metabolites in plasma (λz);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak of total curcuminoids plasmatic concentration in plasma (Tmax, expressed in minutes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to peak of curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak of plasmatic concentrations curcuminoids separately (curcumin, DMC, BDMC) in plasma (Tmax, expressed in minutes);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to peak of curcuminoids metabolites plasmatic concentrations</measure>
    <time_frame>24hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time to peak of plasmatic concentrations curcuminoids metabolites in plasma (Tmax, expressed in minutes);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative bioavailability</measure>
    <time_frame>from 0 to 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability from 0 to 24 hours defined as the ratio of dose-normalized AUC0-24h of total curcuminoids for the different tested formulation to the dose-normalized AUC0-24h obtained for the reference product (turmeric extract 95% curcuminoids).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>10</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 1. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 2. IIntervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 3. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 4. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 5. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 6. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 7. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 8. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 9. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subject allocation sequence 10. Intervention: The subject will receive the five products (TG, STE, NOV, PHYT or TEP) in a certain order.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TG</intervention_name>
    <description>Turmipure GOLD™ 30% curcuminoids (300 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Turmipure GOLD™</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>STE</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard turmeric powder extract 95% curcuminoids (1500 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Standard turmeric powder extract</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NOV</intervention_name>
    <description>Novasol® Liquid micellar formulation 6% curcuminoids (1000 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PHYT</intervention_name>
    <description>Meriva® Turmeric Phytosome formulation 20% curcuminoids (1000 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TEP</intervention_name>
    <description>Turmeric extract C3 complex® 95% curcuminoids (1500mg) + BioPerine® 95% piperine (15 mg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 7</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>subject sequence 9</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 18 and 45 years (limits included),

          -  BMI between 19 and 25 kg/m² (limits included),

          -  Weight stable within ±3kg in the last three months,

          -  With routine blood chemistry values within the normal range

          -  For women: Non menopausal with the same reliable contraception since at least 3 cycles
             before the beginning of the study and agreeing to keep it during the entire duration
             of the study (condom with spermicidal gel and estrogen/progestin combination
             contraception accepted) or menopausal without or with hormone replacement therapy
             (estrogenic replacement therapy begun from less than 3 months excluded),

          -  Non smoking or with tobacco consumption ≤ 5 cigarettes / day and agreeing not to smoke
             during all experimental sessions (V1 to V5),

          -  Agreeing not to consume food, drink and condiment containing curcumin, turmeric
             (curcuma longa Linn.) or curry for 1 week prior to and throughout the entire study,

          -  Good general and mental health with in the opinion of the investigator: no clinically
             significant and relevant abnormalities of medical history or physical examination,

          -  Able and willing to participate to the study by complying with the protocol procedures
             as evidenced by his dated and signed informed consent form,

          -  Affiliated with a social security scheme,

          -  Agreeing to be registered on the volunteers in biomedical research file

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Suffering from a metabolic or endocrine disorder such as diabetes, uncontrolled or
             controlled thyroidal trouble or other metabolic disorder,

          -  Suffering from a severe chronic disease (e.g. cancer, HIV, renal failure, ongoing
             hepatic or biliary disorders, chronic inflammatory digestive disease, arthritis or
             other chronic respiratory trouble, etc.) or gastrointestinal disorders found to be
             inconsistent with the conduct of the study by the investigator (e.g. celiac disease),

          -  Suffering from liver diseases

          -  Current disease states that are contraindicated to subjects with dietary
             supplementation: chronic diarrhea, constipation or abdominal pain, Inflammatory bowel
             diseases (Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis), Cirrhosis, chronic laxatives use…,

          -  Suffering from Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS) diagnosed by a medical doctor and
             treated with chronic medication,

          -  Having medical history of current pathology which could affect the study results or
             expose the subject to an additional risk according to the investigator,

          -  Recent gastroenteritis or food borne illness such as confirmed food poisoning (less
             than 1 month),

          -  Who made a blood donation in the 3 months before the V0 visit or intending to make it
             within 3 months ahead,

          -  With a low venous capital not allowing to perform kinetic of blood samples according
             to the investigator's opinion,

          -  With a known or suspected food allergy or intolerance or hypersensitivity to any of
             the study products' ingredient and/or of the standard meals (gluten intolerance,
             celiac disease, etc….)

          -  Pregnant or lactating women or intending to become pregnant within 3 months ahead,

          -  Exhibiting alcohol or drug dependence

          -  On any chronic drug treatment (for example anticoagulant, antihypertensive treatment,
             treatment thyroid, asthma treatment, anxiolytic, antidepressant, lipid-lowering
             treatment, corticosteroids, phlebotonic, veino-tonic, drug with impact on blood
             circulation …) excepting oral and local contraceptives,

          -  Currently taking (and during the past 3 months) any supplementation from botanical
             origins

          -  Having consumed curcumin-containing food supplements (curcumin, turmeric and curry) or
             foods (curcumin, turmeric, E100, and curry) defined as at least 3 times per week and
             for 2 weeks prior to testing

          -  Currently taking (and during the past 3 months) any prebiotics or probiotics
             supplementation from food or from dietary supplements

          -  With significant change in food habits or in physical activity in the 3 months before
             the V0 visit or not agreeing to keep them unchanged throughout the study,

          -  Trying to lose weight with a current or planned in the next 3 months specific diet
             (hyper or hypocaloric, vegan, vegetarian…) or exercice regimen

          -  With a personal history of anorexia nervosa, bulimia or significant eating disorders
             according to the investigator,

          -  Consuming more than 3 standard drinks of alcoholic beverage daily for men or 2 daily
             for women or not agreeing to keep his alcohol consumption habits unchanged throughout
             the study,

          -  Having a lifestyle deemed incompatible with the study according to the investigator
             including high level physical activity (defined as more than 10 hours of significant
             physical activity a week, walking excluded),

          -  Taking part in another clinical trial or being in the exclusion period of a previous
             clinical trial,

          -  Having received, during the last 12 months, indemnities for clinical trial higher or
             equal to 4500 Euros,

          -  Under legal protection (guardianship, wardship) or deprived from his rights following
             administrative or judicial decision,

          -  Presenting a psychological or linguistic incapability to sign the informed consent,

          -  Impossible to contact in case of emergency.

        After V0 biological analyses the subject will be considered as non-eligible to the study on
        the following criteria:

        - Control record (Glycaemia, GGT, ASAT, ALAT, Urea, Creatinine and Complete blood count)
        with clinically significant abnormality according to the investigator
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pascale Fança-Berthon, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Naturex</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Biofortis Mérieux NutriSciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Herblain</city>
        <zip>44800</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bioavailability</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetic study</keyword>
  <keyword>curcuminoids</keyword>
  <keyword>curcumin</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

