<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03621202</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PVP004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03621202</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Accuracy of the Saranas EBBMS for the Detection of Endovascular Procedure Related Bleeding Events</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Study to Evaluate the Safety and Accuracy of the Saranas Early Bird Bleed Monitoring System for the Detection of Endovascular Procedure Related Bleeding Events</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saranas, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Proxima Clinical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Metrics Diagnostics, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saranas, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the safety and accuracy of the Saranas EBBMS for the detection of access site
      related internal bleeding events during large-bore endovascular procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy in bleeding detection of the Saranas EBBMS as assessed by post-procedural computerized tomography.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy in bleeding detection of the Saranas EBBMS as determined by either clinical assessment or post-procedural computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device sensitivity in bleeding detection of the Saranas EBBMS as compared to post-procedural computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device specificity in bleeding detection of the Saranas EBBMS as compared to post-procedural computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device sensitivity in bleeding detection between Saranas EBBMS and either clinical assessment or post-procedural computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Device specificity in bleeding detection between Saranas EBBMS and either clinical assessment or post-procedural computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between level (severity) of bleed detected by the Saranas EBBMS and the severity of bleeding as assessed by computerized tomography</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between level (severity) of bleed detected by the Saranas EBBMS and the severity of bleeding as assessed by the absolute drop in hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between level (severity) of bleed detected by the Saranas EBBMS and the number of transfusions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between level (severity) of bleed detected by the Saranas EBBMS and the severity of bleeding as assessed by VARC-2 criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relationship between level (severity) of bleed detected by the Saranas EBBMS and the occurrence of post-procedural acute kidney injury</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 hours post procedure</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Endovascular Procedures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saranas Early Bird Bleed Monitoring System (EBBMS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saranas Early Bird Bleed Monitoring System (EBBMS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will undergo their planned endovascular procedure with monitoring for internal bleeding using the Saranas EBBMS.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saranas Early Bird Bleed Monitoring System (EBBMS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥18 years of age

          -  Willing and capable to sign an Informed Consent form

          -  Planned endovascular procedure such as trans-femoral transcatheter aortic valve
             replacement (TAVR), balloon aortic valvuloplasty, percutaneous coronary intervention,
             complex or high-risk percutaneous coronary intervention requiring hemodynamic support
             device (Impella 2.5, Impella CP, and ECMO), endovascular aortic repair (EVAR), any
             other endovascular procedures requiring arterial or venous access or surgical
             insertion of hemodynamic support

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is participating, or planning to participate in a clinical trial or study of
             an investigational product that may influence the data collected for this
             investigation

          -  Inability to access artery or vein for the endovascular procedure

          -  Current active bleeding

          -  Pre-procedural conditions precluding the realization of a post-procedural CT scan

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Mental disability or any other lack of fitness, in the Investigator's opinion, to
             preclude subject's participation in or ability to complete the study as planned
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Genereux, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gagnon Cardiovascular Institute, Morristown Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North Florida Regional Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Morristown Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morristown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07960</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nguyen CT, Lee E, Luo H, Siegel RJ. Echocardiographic guidance for diagnostic and therapeutic percutaneous procedures. Cardiovasc Diagn Ther. 2011 Dec;1(1):11-36. doi: 10.3978/j.issn.2223-3652.2011.09.02. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24282682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roger VL, Go AS, Lloyd-Jones DM, Adams RJ, Berry JD, Brown TM, Carnethon MR, Dai S, de Simone G, Ford ES, Fox CS, Fullerton HJ, Gillespie C, Greenlund KJ, Hailpern SM, Heit JA, Ho PM, Howard VJ, Kissela BM, Kittner SJ, Lackland DT, Lichtman JH, Lisabeth LD, Makuc DM, Marcus GM, Marelli A, Matchar DB, McDermott MM, Meigs JB, Moy CS, Mozaffarian D, Mussolino ME, Nichol G, Paynter NP, Rosamond WD, Sorlie PD, Stafford RS, Turan TN, Turner MB, Wong ND, Wylie-Rosett J; American Heart Association Statistics Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Heart disease and stroke statistics--2011 update: a report from the American Heart Association. Circulation. 2011 Feb 1;123(4):e18-e209. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0b013e3182009701. Epub 2010 Dec 15. Erratum in: Circulation. 2011 Feb 15;123(6):e240. Circulation. 2011 Oct 18;124(16):e426.</citation>
    <PMID>21160056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>SELDINGER SI. Catheter replacement of the needle in percutaneous arteriography; a new technique. Acta radiol. 1953 May;39(5):368-76.</citation>
    <PMID>13057644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Babu SC, Piccorelli GO, Shah PM, Stein JH, Clauss RH. Incidence and results of arterial complications among 16,350 patients undergoing cardiac catheterization. J Vasc Surg. 1989 Aug;10(2):113-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2788227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandrasekar B, Doucet S, Bilodeau L, Crepeau J, deGuise P, Gregoire J, Gallo R, Cote G, Bonan R, Joyal M, Gosselin G, Tanguay JF, Dyrda I, Bois M, Pasternac A. Complications of cardiac catheterization in the current era: a single-center experience. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2001 Mar;52(3):289-95.</citation>
    <PMID>11246238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kinnaird TD, Stabile E, Mintz GS, Lee CW, Canos DA, Gevorkian N, Pinnow EE, Kent KM, Pichard AD, Satler LF, Weissman NJ, Lindsay J, Fuchs S. Incidence, predictors, and prognostic implications of bleeding and blood transfusion following percutaneous coronary interventions. Am J Cardiol. 2003 Oct 15;92(8):930-5.</citation>
    <PMID>14556868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yatskar L, Selzer F, Feit F, Cohen HA, Jacobs AK, Williams DO, Slater J. Access site hematoma requiring blood transfusion predicts mortality in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention: data from the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute Dynamic Registry. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2007 Jun 1;69(7):961-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17421023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moscucci M, Fox KA, Cannon CP, Klein W, López-Sendón J, Montalescot G, White K, Goldberg RJ. Predictors of major bleeding in acute coronary syndromes: the Global Registry of Acute Coronary Events (GRACE). Eur Heart J. 2003 Oct;24(20):1815-23.</citation>
    <PMID>14563340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crudu V, Blankenship J, Berger P, Scott T, Skelding K. Complications related to access site after percutaneous coronary interventions: are the adverse events underreported? Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Apr 1;77(5):643-7. doi: 10.1002/ccd.22759. Epub 2011 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20824761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherev DA, Shaw RE, Brent BN. Angiographic predictors of femoral access site complications: implication for planned percutaneous coronary intervention. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2005 Jun;65(2):196-202.</citation>
    <PMID>15895402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kent KC, Moscucci M, Mansour KA, DiMattia S, Gallagher S, Kuntz R, Skillman JJ. Retroperitoneal hematoma after cardiac catheterization: prevalence, risk factors, and optimal management. J Vasc Surg. 1994 Dec;20(6):905-10; discussion 910-3.</citation>
    <PMID>7990185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fruhwirth J, Pascher O, Hauser H, Amann W. [Local vascular complications after iatrogenic femoral artery puncture]. Wien Klin Wochenschr. 1996;108(7):196-200. German.</citation>
    <PMID>8677663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berry C, Kelly J, Cobbe SM, Eteiba H. Comparison of femoral bleeding complications after coronary angiography versus percutaneous coronary intervention. Am J Cardiol. 2004 Aug 1;94(3):361-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15276106</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khoury M, Batra S, Berg R, Rama K, Kozul V. Influence of arterial access sites and interventional procedures on vascular complications after cardiac catheterizations. Am J Surg. 1992 Sep;164(3):205-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1415915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>large bore</keyword>
  <keyword>femoral access</keyword>
  <keyword>internal bleeding</keyword>
  <keyword>retroperitoneal hematoma</keyword>
  <keyword>bleeding complications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

