<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03621982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADCT-301-103</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2019-003132-23</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03621982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of ADCT-301 in Patients With Selected Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b, Open-Label, Dose-Escalation and Dose-Expansion Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Antitumor Activity of Camidanlumab Tesirine (ADCT-301) in Patients With Selected Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ADC Therapeutics S.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ADC Therapeutics S.A.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates ADCT-301 in patients with Selected Advanced Solid Tumors. Patients will
      participate in a Treatment Period with 3-week cycles and a Follow-up Period every 12 weeks
      for up to 1 year after treatment discontinuation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1b, multi-center, open-label study with a dose-escalation part and a dose
      expansion part.

      The duration of the study participation for each patient is defined as the time from the date
      of signed written informed consent to the completion of the follow-up period, withdrawal of
      consent, loss to follow-up, or death, whichever occurs first.

      The study will include a Screening Period (of up to 21 days), a Treatment Period (with cycles
      of 3 weeks for a Q3W dosing regimen), and a Follow-up Period (approximately every 12 week
      visits) for up to 1 year after treatment discontinuation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Dose Limiting Toxicities in Determination of the Maximum Tolerated Dose Dose Limiting toxicities as defined per protocol, as related to ADCT-301</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a participant or clinical investigation subject administered a pharmaceutical product, which does not necessarily have to have a casual relationship with this treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events of Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Grade 3 or Above</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be graded according to CTAE v4.0 (or more recent). For events not included in the CTCAE criteria, the severity of the AE will be graded on a scale of 1 to 5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Serious Adverse Events (SAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>A SAE is defined as any AE that results in death, is life threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization of prolongation of existing hospitalization (hospitalization for elective procedures or for protocol compliance is not considered an SAE), results in persistent or significant disability/incapacity, is a congenital anomaly/birth defect or important medical events that do not meet the preceding criteria but based on appropriate medical judgement may jeopardize the patient or may require medical or surgical intervention to prevent any of the outcomes listed above.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of SAEs of Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Grade 3 or Above</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>AEs will be graded according to CTCAE v.4.0 (or more recent). For events not included in the CTCAE criteria, the severity of the AE will be graded on a scale of 1 to 5.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Dose Interruptions and/or Dose Reductions</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Dose Limiting Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Experience a Clinically Significant Change in Baseline in Laboratory Values</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Experience a Clinically Significant Change in Baseline in Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Experience a Clinically Significant Change in Baseline in Electrocardiogram (ECG) Results</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Particpants who Experience a Clinically Significant Change in Baseline in Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the preliminary anti-tumor activity of camidanlumab tesirine</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease assessments will occur 6 weeks and 12 weeks after Cycle 1 Day 1, then every 12 weeks (cycle = 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) according to the Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) v1.1 and iRECIST</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the preliminary anti-tumor activity of camidanlumab tesirine</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease assessments will occur 6 weeks and 12 weeks after Cycle 1 Day 1, then every 12 weeks (cycle = 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of response (DOR) defined as the time from the first documentation of tumor response to disease progression or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the preliminary anti-tumor activity of camidanlumab tesirine</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease assessments will occur 6 weeks and 12 weeks after Cycle 1 Day 1, then every 12 weeks (cycle = 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival (PFS) defined as the time between start of treatment and the first documentation of recurrence, progression, or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the preliminary anti-tumor activity of camidanlumab tesirine</measure>
    <time_frame>Disease assessments will occur 6 weeks and 12 weeks after Cycle 1 Day 1, then every 12 weeks (cycle = 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) defined as the time between the start of treatment and death from any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine total antibody, PBD-conjugated antibody, and unconjugated warhead SG3199 in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the maximum concentration (Cmax)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the time to maximum concentration (Tmax)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the area under the concentration-time curve from time zero to the last quantifiable concentration (AUC0 last)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the area under the concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity (AUC0-∞)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the area under the concentration-time curve from time zero to the end of the dosing interval (AUC0-τ)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of the accumulation index (AI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of clearance (CL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetics and Pharmacodynamics assessment- camidanlumab tesirine in serum</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1, 3, 5, 8, and 15 for Cycles 1 and 2; Day 1 for Cycles 3 and 4; Day 1 for every subsequent cycle (cycle=21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Noncompartmental analysis of volume of distribution (Vd)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of confirmed positive anti-drug antibody (ADA) responses</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood sample collection on Day 1 and Day 15 for Cycle 1 and Day 1 only for Cycle 2,Cycle 3,Cycle 4 and then Day 1 of every other cycle (cycle = 21 days)</time_frame>
    <description>ADA titers if applicable, neutralizing activity to camidanlumab tesirine after treatment with camidanlumab tesirine.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">62</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumors With Literature Evidence of CD25(+) Treg Content</condition>
  <condition>Head and Neck Cancer Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Pancreas Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <condition>Triple-negative Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colo-rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ADCT-301</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In Part 1 (dose-escalation), patients will receive a 1-hour intravenous infusion of ADCT-301 on Day 1 every 3 weeks (21-day cycle) at escalating doses. Part 1 will continue until the maximum tolerated dose or the recommended dose(s) and schedule(s) for expansion are determined.
In Part 2 (expansion), patients will be assigned to receive the recommended dose(s) of ADCT-301 as determined by the Dose Escalation Steering Committee (DESC).
This study will investigate dose levels between 20 μg/kg and 300 μg/kg Q3W.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ADCT-301</intervention_name>
    <description>intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>ADCT-301</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Camidanlumab tesirine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent must be obtained prior to any procedures.

          2. Male or female patient aged 18 years or older.

          3. Pathologic diagnosis of solid tumor malignancy that is locally advanced or metastatic
             at time of Screening:

             Part 1 (Dose-Escalation):

             Selected advanced solid tumors: colorectal, head and neck, NSCLC, gastric and
             esophageal cancers, pancreas, bladder, renal cell carcinoma, melanoma, TNBC, and
             ovarian cancers

             Part 2 (Dose-Expansion):

               -  Group 1: One of the indications identified in Part 1, for which at least 1
                  response (PR or CR) was seen.

               -  Group 2: Any indication allowed in Part 1, except for the one selected for Group
                  1.

          4. Patients who are refractory to or intolerant of existing therapy(ies) known to provide
             clinical benefit for their condition.

          5. Patients with advanced/metastatic cancer, with measurable disease as determined by
             RECIST v1.1 or irRC/irRECIST/iRECIST.

          6. Patient must have a site of disease amenable to biopsy and be willing to undergo fresh
             biopsy procedures (minimum 3 passes each) prior to first dose, according to the
             treating institution's guidelines.

             Patients included in the paired-biopsy cohort must in addition be willing to undergo
             fresh biopsy procedures (minimum 3 passes each) after receiving at least one dose of
             study drug.

          7. ECOG performance status 0-1.

          8. Adequate organ function as defined by screening laboratory values within the following
             parameters:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 × 10^3/μL (off growth factors at least 72
                  h).

               2. Platelet count ≥100 × 10^3/μL without transfusion in the past 10 days.

               3. Hemoglobin ≥9 g/dL (5.6 mmol/L) (prior transfusion allowed).

               4. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), or gamma
                  glutamyl transferase (GGT) ≤2.5 × the upper limit of normal (ULN) if there is no
                  liver involvement; ALT or AST ≤5 × ULN if there is liver involvement.

               5. Total bilirubin ≤1.5 × ULN (patients with known Gilbert's syndrome may have a
                  total bilirubin up to ≤3 × ULN with direct bilirubin ≤1.5 × ULN).

               6. Blood creatinine ≤1.5 × ULN or calculated creatinine clearance ≥60 mL/min by the
                  Cockcroft-Gault equation.

          9. Negative beta-human chorionic gonadotropin (β-HCG) pregnancy test within 7 days prior
             to start of study drug for women of childbearing potential.

         10. Women of childbearing potential* must agree to use a highly effective** method of
             contraception from the time of giving informed consent until at least 16 weeks after
             the last dose of camidanlumab tesirine. Men with female partners who are of
             childbearing potential must agree to use a condom when sexually active or practice
             total abstinence from the time of giving informed consent until at least 16 weeks
             after the patient receives his last dose of camidanlumab tesirine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Participation in another investigational interventional study.

          2. Prior therapy with a CD25 (IL-2R) antibody within the last 4 months.

          3. Known history of ≥Grade 3 hypersensitivity to a therapeutic antibody.

          4. Patients with prior solid organ or allogeneic bone marrow transplant.

          5. History of symptomatic autoimmune disease (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic
             progressive sclerosis [scleroderma], systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjögren's syndrome,
             autoimmune vasculitis [e.g., Wegener's granulomatosis]) (subjects with vitiligo, type
             I diabetes mellitus, residual hypothyroidism, hypophysitis due to autoimmune condition
             only requiring hormone replacement may be enrolled).

          6. History of neuropathy considered of autoimmune origin (e.g., polyradiculopathy
             including Guillain-Barré syndrome and myasthenia gravis) or other central nervous
             system (CNS) autoimmune disease (e.g., poliomyelitis, multiple sclerosis).

          7. History of recent infection (within 4 weeks of C1D1) considered to be caused by one of
             the following pathogens: herpes simplex virus 1/2 (HSV1, HSV2), varicella zoster
             (VZV), Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), cytomegalovirus (CMV), measles, Influenza A, Zika
             virus, Chikungunya virus, mycoplasma pneumonia, Campylobacter jejuni, or enterovirus
             D68.

          8. Known seropositive and requiring anti-viral therapy for human immunodeficiency (HIV)
             virus, hepatitis B virus (HBV), or hepatitis C virus (HCV). Note: Testing is not
             mandatory to be eligible but should be considered in patients with high risk for these
             infections.

          9. History of Stevens-Johnson syndrome or toxic epidermal necrolysis.

         10. Failure to recover to ≤Grade 1 (Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version
             4.0 [CTCAE v4.0]) from acute nonhematologic toxicity (to ≤Grade 2 for neuropathy or
             alopecia), due to previous therapy, prior to screening.

         11. Symptomatic CNS metastases or evidence of leptomeningeal disease (brain MRI or
             previously documented cerebrospinal fluid [CSF] cytology). Previously treated
             asymptomatic CNS metastases are permitted provided that the last treatment (systemic
             anticancer therapy and/or local radiotherapy) was completed ≥8 weeks prior to Day 1
             except usage of low dose of steroids on a taper (i.e., up to 10 mg prednisone or
             equivalent on Day 1 and consecutive days is permissible if being tapered down).
             Patients with discrete dural metastases are eligible.

         12. Clinically significant third space fluid accumulation (i.e., ascites requiring
             drainage or pleural effusion that is either requiring drainage or associated with
             shortness of breath).

         13. Active diarrhea CTCAE Grade 2 or a medical condition associated with chronic diarrhea
             (such as irritable bowel syndrome, inflammatory bowel disease).

         14. Active infection requiring systemic antibiotic therapy.

         15. Active bleeding diathesis or significant anticoagulation (international normalized
             ratio [INR] ≥2.0).

         16. Breastfeeding or pregnant.

         17. Significant medical comorbidities, including uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure
             [BP] ≥160 mmHg systolic and/or ≥110 mmHg diastolic repeatedly with or without anti
             hypertensive medication), unstable angina, congestive heart failure (greater than New
             York Heart Association class II), electrocardiographic evidence of acute ischemia,
             coronary angioplasty or myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to screening,
             severe uncontrolled atrial or ventricular cardiac arrhythmia, poorly controlled
             diabetes, active ulceration of the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract or GI bleeding,
             or severe chronic pulmonary disease.

         18. Major surgery, radiotherapy, chemotherapy or other anti-neoplastic therapy within 14
             days prior to start of study drug (C1D1), except shorter if approved by the Sponsor.
             For cytotoxic agents that have major delayed toxicity, e.g., mitomycin C and
             nitrosoureas, 4 weeks is indicated as washout period. For patients receiving systemic
             anticancer immunotherapies (as opposed to intralesional) that lead to activation of
             Teffs and/or increase the Teff/Treg ratio, such as anti-PD-1 antibodies, 4 weeks are
             indicated as the washout period.

         19. Use of any other experimental medication within 14 days prior to start of study drug
             (C1D1).

         20. Patients requiring concomitant immunosuppressive agents or chronic treatment with
             corticosteroids except:

               -  replacement dose steroids in the setting of adrenal insufficiency

               -  topical, inhaled, nasal, and ophthalmic steroids are allowed

         21. Planned live vaccine administration after starting study drug (C1D1).

         22. Congenital long QT syndrome, or a corrected QTcF interval of ≥ 480 ms, at screening
             (unless secondary to pacemaker or bundle branch block).

         23. Active second primary malignancy other than non-melanoma skin cancers, non-metastatic
             prostate cancer, in situ cervical cancer, ductal or lobular carcinoma in situ of the
             breast, or other malignancy that the Sponsor's medical monitor and Investigator agree
             and document should not be exclusionary.

         24. Any other significant medical illness, abnormality, or condition that would, in the
             Investigator's judgment, make the patient inappropriate for study participation or put
             the patient at risk
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>ADC Therapeutics</last_name>
    <phone>954-903-7994</phone>
    <email>clinical.trials@adctherapeutics.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shivanni Kummar, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Smilow Cancer Hospital Phase 1 Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06511</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Patricia LoRusso, DO</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Igor Puzanov, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johanna C Bendell, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Texas Accelerated Research Therapeutics, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kyriakos P Papadopoulos, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Camidanlumab tesirine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

