<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03627325</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHR-14-OR-0094</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03627325</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Difference in Preoperative Evaluation That is Given by a Senior Physician, a Specialist, and a Computer Program</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACS</acronym>
  <official_title>Differences in Surgical Risk Evaluation by Surgical Risk Calculator, Residents and Senior Anesthesiologists</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Western Galilee Hospital-Nahariya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western Galilee Hospital-Nahariya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is an increasing need and interest in being able to empirically estimate customized,
      patient-specific risks for virtually all surgical operations in a user-friendly format.

      The ACS (American College of Surgeons) surgical risk calculator is a decision-support tool
      based on reliable multi institutional clinical data, which can be used to estimate the risks
      of most operations.1 The aim of this study is to compare the assessment provided by the The
      ACS Surgical Risk Calculator with the assessment provided by a senior and a resident
      anesthesiologist, and by that comparison to establish the need for the ACS calculator
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Understanding the risks of surgery is clearly important for both patients and surgeons in the
      shared decision making process. Informed consent requires that patients have a thorough
      understanding of the potential risks of surgery. Moreover, clinicians and patients also need
      information regarding surgical risks in order to make decisions on the type of operation or
      whether surgery should be performed at all.

      Therefore, there is a need to discuss the risks derived empirically with a specific patient
      before any action to guide both surgical decision-making and informed consent.

      However, predicting postoperative risks and identifying patients at a higher risk of adverse
      events have traditionally been based on individual surgeon experience and augmented by
      published rates in the literature, either from single institution studies or clinical trials.
      Unfortunately, these estimates are typically not specific to an individual Patient's risk
      factors. The ACS (American College of Surgeons) Surgical Risk Calculator estimates the chance
      of an unfavorable outcome (such as a complication or death) after surgery. The risk is
      estimated based upon information the patient gives to the healthcare provider about prior
      health history. The estimates are calculated using data from a large number of patients who
      had a surgical procedure similar to the one the patient may have.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 15, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 15, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity for each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient is assessed within a week by both physicians and the ACS web-based computer. The trial is scheduled for a whole year.</time_frame>
    <description>Anesthesiologists give their estimation of overall mortality that is compared to that given by the ACS web-based calculator</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity for each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Each patient is assessed within a week by both physicians and the ACS web-based computer. The trial is scheduled for a whole year.</time_frame>
    <description>Anesthesiologists give their estimation of different morbidities and that is compared to that given by the ACS web-based calculator</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patients who are scheduled for any surgical procedure</intervention_name>
    <description>looking for correlation for estimating the complications between the anesthesiologists and the computerized method.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who are scheduled for any surgical procedure will be recruited for the study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients candidates for surgery

          -  Signed informed consent by patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>August 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 13, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western Galilee Hospital-Nahariya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ronen Ohad</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director Head and Neck Surgery Unit</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>there is no plan to make individual participant data available to other researchers</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

