<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03629093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GENIUS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03629093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurodevelopment of Infants Exposed to General Anesthesia: a Multi-center Investigation</brief_title>
  <acronym>GENIUS</acronym>
  <official_title>General Anesthesia Exposed Infants Neurodevelopment Investigation: a Multi-center Prospective Cohort Study United in Shanghai</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Huashan Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Children's Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Fudan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Shanghai Ninth People's Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai Jiao Tong University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Huashan Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Numerous preclinical evidence has confirmed that most commonly-used general anesthetics can
      affect neurodevelopment of young animals adversely, causing both structural defect of brain
      and cognitive impairment. However, it is unclear at present whether such effect would also
      occur to children exposed to general anesthesia in their early life. Several observational
      clinical studies and one interventional clinical trial indicated that short-time general
      anesthesia less than 80 minutes might be safe to cognitive development. Concerning long-time
      and/or multiple anesthesia exposure, some studies supported its association with long-term
      cognitive defects, while other studies did not. These studies are mainly retrospective or
      ambirectional researches. We have designed a prospective, multicenter cohort study to examine
      the neurodevelopment of infants exposed to anesthesia before age 2 in the first year after
      surgery, and compare the neurodevelopment status of infants exposed to anesthesia less than 3
      hours and those more than 3 hours. The Gesell Developmental Inventory (GDI) and several
      neuropsychological testing batteries will be used. The anticipated outcome of the study will
      add reliable evidence from Asians to elucidate the relationship of anesthesia and long-term
      neurodevelopment of infants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the developmental quotient of the Gesell Developmental Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline before anesthesia to 1 year after anesthesia</time_frame>
    <description>The Gesell Developmental Inventory has been translated into Chinese and standardized by the Beijing Children's Health Care Institute and the performance results are expressed as a developmental quotient (DQ).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the standardized score of the five domains of the Gesell Developmental Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline before anesthesia to 1 year after anesthesia</time_frame>
    <description>The five behavioral domains are gross motor, fine motor, language, adaptive, and personal-social behaviors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of the standardized score of the Social Maturity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline before anesthesia to 1 year after anesthesia</time_frame>
    <description>The Social Maturity Scale includes six domains and 132 questions designed to be completed by the parents.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>General Anesthetics Toxicity</condition>
  <condition>Neurodevelopment</condition>
  <condition>Infant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Long-time anesthesia exposure</arm_group_label>
    <description>Infants receive general anesthetics longer than 3 hours in total.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Short-time anesthesia exposure</arm_group_label>
    <description>Infants receive general anesthetics shorter than 3 hours in total.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General Anesthetics</intervention_name>
    <description>General anesthesia required for surgery procedures or diagnostic interventions using either intravenous or inhalation anesthetics, or both.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Long-time anesthesia exposure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Short-time anesthesia exposure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>General anesthesia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible infants scheduled for elective surgeries under general anesthesia will be
        recruited in six medical centers in Shanghai, China. The medical centers include Huashan
        Hospital Fudan University, Shanghai Children's Medical Center, Children's Hospital of Fudan
        University, Children's Hospital of Shanghai, Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital, and Shanghai
        Ninth People's Hospital Affiliated to Shanghai Jiao Tong University.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Apgar score ≥ 8 at birth

          -  ASA level Ⅰ~Ⅲ

          -  Obtained written consent form from the infants' parents or guardians

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Postmenstrual age ≤ 44 weeks, or postmenstrual age ≥ 144 weeks

          -  Severe cardiac, pulmonary, or neurologic disease

          -  Severe obstructive sleep apnea hypopnea syndrome

          -  History of dystocia and/or hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy

          -  Gestational age at birth ≤32 weeks

          -  Any known or suspected chromosomal abnormalities, abnormal development of vision or
             hearing, neurodevelopment retardation, or other known acquired or congenital
             abnormalities that might affect neurodevelopment

          -  Significant cardiovascular surgery, significant ENT surgery, or neurosurgery

          -  Malignant diseases that may reduce survival

          -  Taking part in other clinical trials in the last 3 months or at present
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>2 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ying-Wei Wang, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Huashan Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiao-Yu Yang, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>52889999</phone>
    <phone_ext>7693</phone_ext>
    <email>yangxiaoyu@huashan.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Meng-Qiang Luo, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>52889999</phone>
    <phone_ext>7693</phone_ext>
    <email>viteroman@sina.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davidson AJ, Disma N, de Graaff JC, Withington DE, Dorris L, Bell G, Stargatt R, Bellinger DC, Schuster T, Arnup SJ, Hardy P, Hunt RW, Takagi MJ, Giribaldi G, Hartmann PL, Salvo I, Morton NS, von Ungern Sternberg BS, Locatelli BG, Wilton N, Lynn A, Thomas JJ, Polaner D, Bagshaw O, Szmuk P, Absalom AR, Frawley G, Berde C, Ormond GD, Marmor J, McCann ME; GAS consortium. Neurodevelopmental outcome at 2 years of age after general anaesthesia and awake-regional anaesthesia in infancy (GAS): an international multicentre, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2016 Jan 16;387(10015):239-50. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)00608-X. Epub 2015 Nov 4. Erratum in: Lancet. 2016 Jan 16;387(10015):228.</citation>
    <PMID>26507180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham MR. Clinical update regarding general anesthesia-associated neurotoxicity in infants and children. Curr Opin Anaesthesiol. 2017 Dec;30(6):682-687. doi: 10.1097/ACO.0000000000000520. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28915132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun LS, Li G, Miller TL, Salorio C, Byrne MW, Bellinger DC, Ing C, Park R, Radcliffe J, Hays SR, DiMaggio CJ, Cooper TJ, Rauh V, Maxwell LG, Youn A, McGowan FX. Association Between a Single General Anesthesia Exposure Before Age 36 Months and Neurocognitive Outcomes in Later Childhood. JAMA. 2016 Jun 7;315(21):2312-20. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.6967.</citation>
    <PMID>27272582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warner DO, Zaccariello MJ, Katusic SK, Schroeder DR, Hanson AC, Schulte PJ, Buenvenida SL, Gleich SJ, Wilder RT, Sprung J, Hu D, Voigt RG, Paule MG, Chelonis JJ, Flick RP. Neuropsychological and Behavioral Outcomes after Exposure of Young Children to Procedures Requiring General Anesthesia: The Mayo Anesthesia Safety in Kids (MASK) Study. Anesthesiology. 2018 Jul;129(1):89-105. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000002232.</citation>
    <PMID>29672337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Huashan Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Xiao-Yu Yang, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>General anesthesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodevelopment</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative</keyword>
  <keyword>the Gesell Developmental Inventory</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, General</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

