<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01188993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I09003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01188993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transpulmonary Thermodilution and Transesophageal Echocardiography in Early Septic Shock</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEMOSEPSIS</acronym>
  <official_title>Hemodynamic Assessment With Transpulmonary Thermodilution and Transesophageal Echocardiography in Patients With Early Septic Shock</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Limoges</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Limoges</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the concordance of therapeutic changes proposed after
      an early hemodynamic evaluation (hemodynamic profile) in septic shock patients using jointly
      the transpulmonary thermodilution technique and transesophageal echocardiography (TEE).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each patient will be assessed by both the transpulmonary thermodilution technique and TEE
      (H0). The two assessments will be performed in random order (central randomization stratified
      by participating center), but within 30 minutes (no change of ongoing treatment during the
      assessment period). Two investigators not involved in patient care and blinded to the results
      of the alternative technique will performed independently the hemodynamic assessment using
      one of the two modalities for hemodynamic assessment tested in the study. They will interpret
      the results at bedside and propose a therapeutic change to the attending physician, according
      to the hemodynamic profile. The latter will finally: precisely identify the clinical problem
      to be solved (e.g., therapeutic target of the Surviving Sepsis Campaign not reached, tissue
      hypoperfusion), choose a therapy adapted while taking into account the clinical scenario and
      the results of both the transpulmonary thermodilution and TEE, evaluate the efficacy of this
      treatment (problem solved or not) and its tolerance (potential side-effect attributable to
      the treatment). In addition, the presence or resolution of signs of tissue hypoperfusion will
      systematically be assessed at H6, H12 and H24. Primary and secondary outcomes will be
      assessed by an independent committee of experts.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>therapeutic procedure following the hemodynamic assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in therapy proposed after the hemodynamic assessment (hemodynamic profile) by each of the two tested methods: blood volume expansion (preload responsiveness), positive inotrope (cardiac dysfunction), vasopressor (vasoplegia), no change in ongoing therapy or dose tapering (inotropes or vasopressor).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy and safety of therapeutic intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy (clinical problem solved) and tolerance (potential side-effects) of the therapeutic change.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">153</enrollment>
  <condition>Septic Shock</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>septic shock TPT then TEE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1: Each patient will be assessed by both the transpulmonary thermodilution technique and transesophageal echocardiography (TEE)..</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>septic shock TEE then TPT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Goup 2: Each patient will be assessed by both transesophageal echocardiography (TEE) and the transpulmonary thermodilution technique.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>early septic shock</intervention_name>
    <description>Each patient will be assessed by both the transpulmonary thermodilution and Transesophageal Echocardiography.</description>
    <arm_group_label>septic shock TEE then TPT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>septic shock TPT then TEE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ventilated patient in sinus rhythm with septic shock requiring a hemodynamic
             assessment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 18 yr-old

          -  pregnancy

          -  contra-indication for TEE, non sinus rhythm, aplasia, prior participation to the
             study, hemodynamic assessment using any other technique than those tested in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bordeaux UH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33 076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toulouse UH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31 059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vignon P, Begot E, Mari A, Silva S, Chimot L, Delour P, Vargas F, Filloux B, Vandroux D, Jabot J, François B, Pichon N, Clavel M, Levy B, Slama M, Riu-Poulenc B. Hemodynamic Assessment of Patients With Septic Shock Using Transpulmonary Thermodilution and Critical Care Echocardiography: A Comparative Study. Chest. 2018 Jan;153(1):55-64. doi: 10.1016/j.chest.2017.08.022. Epub 2017 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28866112</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2010</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 25, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Shock, Septic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shock</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

