<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04376918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0172-20-HMO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04376918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bag-Valve-Guedel Adaptor vs Common Face Mask for the Ventilation of Anesthetized Bearded Men</brief_title>
  <acronym>BVGA02</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Safety and Efficacy of the Bag-Valve-Guedel Adaptor in Anesthetized Bearded Men in Comparison to the Standard Face Mask - A Prospective, Randomized Cross-over Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ventilation of a bearded patient with the commonly used face mask has low efficiency because
      of difficulties to achieve a tight seal around the mouth and nose. The purpose of this study
      is to evaluate the efficacy of a novel bag valve Guedel adaptor (BVGA) that enables the
      direct connection of a bag valve device to a Guedel - eliminating the need for a face mask in
      anesthetized bearded men.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ventilating a patient using a bag valve and a face mask is not easy to perform, especially
      for a long period of time, and mandates experience and strength by the care giver. The need
      for a tight seal around the mouth and nose is a major challenge especially if the patient has
      a beard. Nevertheless, the face mask is the only approved respiratory support that medics and
      other basic care givers are allowed to use in the out-of-the-hospital setting, and only
      physicians and paramedics are allowed to use more advanced techniques, providing a definite
      airway. Thus, despite its lower effectiveness, the bag valve mask technique is the most
      commonly used in the field. We have shown previously that the BVGA provides significantly
      more efficient (less leak) ventilation compared to a facemask, in a randomized, cross-over
      (BVGA vs mask) controlled clinical trial (NCT02768246) with healthy bearded volunteers that
      were awake and breathed spontaneously.

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the BVGA compared to a
      classic facemask in anesthetized bearded volunteers.

      Study Design:

      Prospective, randomized (sequence randomization), controlled (cross over). The study
      population will include ASA 1 or 2patients that are planned to undergo elective surgery under
      general anesthesia with non-depolarizing muscle relaxants. These will include 45 men with
      beards, and 14 men without beards or women

      All subjects will sign an informed consent before participation and will be randomized by
      sequence (BVGA followed by Mask or Mask followed by BVGA). The physician will initiate
      anesthesia induction with a face mask according to normal procedures. Experimental phase:
      According to the sequence of devices determined in the randomization, the physician will then
      place the first device for 2 minutes, and then replace it with the second device for 2
      minutes. The devices will be connected to the operating ventilation machines and
      physiological and respiratory parameters will be monitored continuously. During the
      experimental phase, a study assistant will note if the physician used 1 or 2 hands during the
      ventilation with the experimental devices (BVGA/mask).

      The physician will then continue the anesthesia procedures as planned. The physician will
      complete a questionnaire related to the use of the BVGA in comparison to the standard mask.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, randomized (sequence randomization), controlled (cross over)</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tidal Volume</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Tidal volume will be monitored while the volunteer breathes through the BVGA or the face mask. The second minute of each of the interventions will be used for the data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>End tidal CO2 levels (EtCO2)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>EtCO2 will be monitored while the volunteer breathes through the BVGA or the face mask. The second minute of each of the interventions will be used for the data analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of use</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The number of hands (1 or 2) the physician had to use during the ventilation procedure while using each device (mask or BVGA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventilation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Begin with BVGA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After initial anesthesia induction, anesthetized volunteers will be ventilated through through the BVGA for 2 minutes and then through the face-mask for 2 minutes. The normal anesthesia procedures will then be resumed.
The BVGA enables the direct connection of a bag valve device to a Guedel, eliminating the need for a face mask during ventilation The Mask is a classic face mask</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Begin with Face-mask</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>After initial anesthesia induction, anesthetized volunteers will be ventilated through the face mask for 2 minutes and then through the BVGA for 2 minutes. The normal anesthesia procedures will then be resumed
The BVGA enables the direct connection of a bag valve device to a Guedel, eliminating the need for a face mask during ventilation The Mask is a classic face mask</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Begin with BVGA</intervention_name>
    <description>Device: BVGA The BVGA enables the direct connection of a bag valve device to a Guedel, eliminating the need for a face mask during ventilation
Other Names:
• Bag Valve Guedel Adaptor Device: Face Mask Classic face mask</description>
    <arm_group_label>Begin with BVGA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Begin with Face-mask</intervention_name>
    <description>Device: BVGA The BVGA enables the direct connection of a bag valve device to a Guedel, eliminating the need for a face mask during ventilation
Other Names:
• Bag Valve Guedel Adaptor Device: Face Mask Classic face mask</description>
    <arm_group_label>Begin with Face-mask</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Beards men with different levels of beard fullness, men without beards, or women

          2. planned to undergo elective surgery with endotracheal intubation using
             non-depolarizing neuromuscular blocking agents

          3. ASA 1 or 2

          4. BMI ≤30

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant women

          2. ASA&gt;2

          3. Presence of facial fractures or injuries.

          4. Expected to suffer from aspiration and requiring rapid sequence induction

          5. Edentulous or unstable teeth

          6. Morbid obesity

          7. Suspected difficult intubation

          8. Suspected difficult ventilation (except of the presence of beard)

          9. If an unexpected difficulty in ventilation will arise during induction, patient will
             be excluded from study.

         10. Worker from Hadassah Medical Center
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Most volunteers are required to have a beard, therefore most volunteers will be men.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shimon Firman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lilach Gavish, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lilach Gavish, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+97226758623</phone>
    <email>lilachg@ekmd.huji.ac.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haddasah Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gavish L, Rittblat M, Gertz SD, Shaylor R, Weissman C, Eisenkraft A. Ventilating the Bearded: A Randomized Crossover Trial Comparing a Novel Bag-Valve-Guedel Adaptor to a Standard Mask. September 2019 accepted for publication in Military Medicine. Usz378, https://doi.org/10.1093/milmed/usz378</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lilach Gavish</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Study Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>airway management</keyword>
  <keyword>intubation</keyword>
  <keyword>emergency responders</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

