<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04376931</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ISINFULA 37-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04376931</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Dose Finding Study of Iscador Infusion</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Dose Finding Study of Iscador Infusion: Phase Ib Study With Prolonged Observation (ISINFULA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>HaEmek Medical Center, Israel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>HaEmek Medical Center, Israel</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prospective, dose-escalating mono-center open label dose-finding study without control group
      (3+3 design), including a follow-up on-treatment observation. In this study will be recruited
      15 patients with a histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of an advanced
      malignant disease during a therapy-free interval.Investigational drug:Iscador®P: fermented
      aqueous extract of mistletoe grown on pine tree (Viscum album L. subspecies austriacum
      (Wiesb.) Vollmann), licensed for subcutaneous (SC) application in Switzerland, Germany,
      Austria, Sweden, and South Korea in dosages up to 20 mg.

      The initial dose group of the study is set to 40 mg Iscador®P.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective open label dose finding study (phase I) of Iscador®P in patients with
      histological or cytological confirmed diagnosis of an advanced malignant disease during a
      therapy-free interval. Primary objective : To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of
      Iscador®P as intravenous infusion in the aforementioned patient population, based on the
      incidence of dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs). Secondary objective :To investigate safety and
      tolerability of long-term intravenous infusion of Iscador®P based on incidence and severity
      of adverse drug reactions.

      All patients are receiving best supportive care and may receive, if necessary, specified
      concomitant therapies, which should not interfere with the safety parameters chosen for this
      study.

      Investigational therapy will be administered in six Dose Groups (DG): 10 mg, 20 mg, 40 mg, 90
      mg, 140 mg and 200 mg Iscador®P. The initial dose group of the study is set to 40 mg
      Iscador®P.

      The two lower dose groups (20 or 10 mg) will only be used in case of intolerance at 40 mg
      Iscador®P. Once per week patients receive intravenous infusions of Iscador®P dissolved in 250
      ml of sodium chloride solution (0.9 %). After the 4-week period of the MTD estimation phase
      each subject will immediately be included into a follow up observation in which he/she
      receives the last well tolerated dosage they had or the next lower dosage than the currently
      investigated DG in the running phase Ib study depending on the current estimate of the MTD at
      that time.

      Study entry of individual patients will be set apart by one week. Dosages of subsequent dose
      groups depend on the incidence of DLTs in former groups.

      For safety reasons the values of endotoxin content in Iscador®P, measured by the limulus
      test, are considered as the real content of endotoxins although the mistletoe lectins are
      cross reacting in this test. This leads to a maximum dose of 200 mg representing the upper
      limit of this dose finding study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, dose-escalating mono-center open label dose-finding study without control group (3+3 design), including a follow-up on-treatment observation.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of dose-limiting toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be in this study for up to 58 weeks ( 4 weeks of treatment and follow-up for a maximum of 52 weeks if subjects are deemed to have continuous clinical benefit from the Iscador®P infusions.</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Iscador®P infusions, i.e. the dose eliciting dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) in a maximum of 1 out of 6 patients treated at that dose.treated at that dose.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life as Assessed Using Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - General (FACIT-G)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and prior to each infusion in phase I and monthly in the follow-up period.4 weeks and follow up period for a maximum of 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The FACIT-F evaluates quality of life using 5 categories: physical well-being (PWB), social/family well-being (SWB), emotional well-being (EWB), functional well-being (FWB), and fatigue (FS). Participants answer each item on a 5-point scale from 0 to 4. The total score is the sum of individual responses across all 5 categories and may range from 0 to 160. The FACIT-General (FACIT-G; range 0 to 108) is the sum of scores for PWB, SWB, EWB, and FWB; the FACIT-Fatigue (FACIT-F) trial outcome index (TOI; range 0 to 108) is the sum of scores for PWB, FWB, and FS; and the FACIT-F fatigue (range 0 to 52) is the sum of scores for the FS only. For derivations of the FACIT-F reported here, higher scores indicate better quality of life. The mean score at each timepoint was determined by averaging scores among all participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse drug reactions (ADRs).</measure>
    <time_frame>Subjects will be in this study for up to 58 weeks ( 4 weeks of treatment and follow-up for a maximum of 52 weeks if subjects are deemed to have continuous clinical benefit from the Iscador®P infusions.</time_frame>
    <description>frequency of ADRs to intravenous mistletoe treatment will be measured during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and follow up period for a maximum of 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of tumor response will be according to the RECIST criteria V1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and follow up period for a maximum of 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time to disease progression will be defined as the time from first infusion of Iscador®P to the date of documentation of disease progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks and follow up period for a maximum of 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival will be measured from the date of first infusion of Iscador®P until the date of the last follow-up or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iscador®P as intravenous infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigational therapy will be administered in six Dose Groups (DG):
10 mg, 20 mg, 40 mg, 90 mg, 140 mg and 200 mg Iscador®P. The initial dose group of the study is set to 40 mg Iscador®P. The two lower dose groups (20 or 10 mg) will only be used in case of intolerance at 40 mg Iscador®P. Once per week patients receive intravenous infusions of Iscador®P dissolved in 250 ml of sodium chloride solution (0.9 %). After the 4-week period of the MTD estimation phase each subject will immediately be included into a follow up observation in which he/she receives the last well tolerated dosage they had or the next lower dosage than the currently investigated DG in the running phase Ib study depending on the current estimate of the MTD at that time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravenous Solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Iscador®P: fermented aqueous extract of mistletoe grown on pine tree (Viscum album L. subspecies austriacum (Wiesb.) Vollmann), licensed for subcutaneous (SC) application in Switzerland, Germany, Austria, Sweden, and South Korea in dosages up to 20 mg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iscador®P as intravenous infusion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ISINFULA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Voluntarily given written informed consent.

          -  ≥18 years of age.

          -  Metastatic or locally advanced solid tumor, histologically or cytologically confirmed,
             no standard therapy available or standard therapy has failed.

          -  Adequate organ function

          -  Life expectancy ≥ 3 months, ECOG ≤ 2.

          -  No ongoing or preceding therapy with mistletoe products.

          -  Women of childbearing potential: negative serum pregnancy test at screening, use of
             two adequate barrier methods

          -  Compliance with protocol, legal competence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  - Systemic cytotoxic chemotherapy, biological therapy, radiation therapy, OR major
             surgery prior trial treatment.

          -  Persisting toxicity of NCI-CTCAE Grade &gt;1 related to prior therapy (Sensory neuropathy
             of Grade ≤2 is acceptable).

          -  Expected to require any other form of systemic or localized antineoplastic therapy
             while on trial

          -  Systemic corticosteroid therapy received ≤ 3 days prior to trial treatment or other
             forms of systemic immunosuppressive medication (except corticosteroids against
             immune-related AEs and /or premedication for IV contrast allergies/reactions;
             corticosteroid replacement therapy)

          -  Tumor and/or metastases of the CNS and/or carcinomatous meningitis

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous systemic therapy, HIV, severe allergic illness
             (including asthma), active tuberculosis, inflammatory diseases with body temperature &gt;
             38° C.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to mistletoe products.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gil Bar Sela, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Haemek MC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gil Bar Sela, Prof</last_name>
    <phone>+97250-206-1207</phone>
    <email>gil_ba@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ela Lutwak, M.SC</last_name>
    <phone>+972546459510</phone>
    <email>ella_lu@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haemek MC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Afula</city>
        <state>North</state>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ela Lutwak, MSC</last_name>
      <phone>+972546459510</phone>
      <email>ella_lu@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gil Bar Sela, Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>advanced malignant disease</keyword>
  <keyword>mistletoe</keyword>
  <keyword>Iscador</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

