<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04377009</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CNRM-02-9662</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04377009</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Internet-guided Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia in Military Service Members With History of Traumatic Brain Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled, Double-blinded Study of Internet-guided Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia in Military Service Members With History of Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Henry M. Jackson Foundation for the Advancement of Military Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Neuroscience and Regenerative Medicine (CNRM)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Henry M. Jackson Foundation for the Advancement of Military Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to validate an established internet-guided cognitive behavioral therapy for
      insomnia (CBT-I) as an alternative program to traditional in-person therapy that may increase
      treatment availability and utilization within the military health system. The version of the
      internet-guided CBT-I program being studied has been customized specifically for military
      service members.

      The study will assess if the customized internet-guided CBT-I program will positively improve
      clinical measures of insomnia and quality of life outcomes in active or retired service
      members with primary insomnia and associated mild traumatic brain injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Traumatic brain injury (TBI) represents a major health problem in United States military
      service members. Mild traumatic brain injury, also called &quot;concussion&quot;, accounts for
      approximately 90% of the overall cases of TBI. Mild TBI (mTBI) is associated with various
      debilitating symptoms, such as headache, mood disorders, and sleep alterations. A high
      percentage of service members and veterans with suspected or confirmed mTBI are also
      diagnosed with insomnia or other sleep disorders.

      In-person cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) has been documented as an
      effective therapy for treating insomnia. However, implementation within the Military
      Healthcare System (MHS) has been lacking due to lack of appropriately trained practitioners.
      Additionally, patients may overlook in-person therapy due to significant time commitment.

      This study is a double-blind, randomized, controlled clinical trial to assess internet-guided
      CBT-I in military service members with insomnia and mTBI. The primary outcome measure for
      efficacy is the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) with secondary cross-validation using the
      Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI). Approximately 200 participants will be randomized to
      treatment or control groups. Participants receiving active CBT-I will follow a 9-week
      internet-guided program requiring daily follow-up through an online portal that may be
      accessed via computer or phone. Participants in the control group will also receive access to
      an online portal for 9 weeks.

      Primary analysis is percent improvement in severity symptoms assessed pre- and
      post-treatment. Secondary analysis is percent retained improvement in severity of symptoms
      assessed post-treatment and long-term follow-up at 6 months.

      Secondary outcome measures will capture a variety of known and suspected insomnia precursors,
      predictors, or correlates and functional outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 7, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in ISI scores from baseline to post-intervention. A clinically meaningful change will be defined as &gt;=25% reduction in total symptom score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in ISI scores from baseline to post-intervention. A clinically meaningful change will be defined as &gt;=25% reduction in total symptom score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PHQ-9 scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire 9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PHQ-9 scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PCL-5 scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PCL-5 scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Migraine Disability Assessment (MIDAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in MIDAS scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Migraine Disability Assessment (MIDAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in MIDAS scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PSQI scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PSQI scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) with Addendum for PTSD (PSQI-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PSQI-A scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) with Addendum for PTSD (PSQI-A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in PSQI-A scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue (FACIT-F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in FACIT-F scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue (FACIT-F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of changes in FACIT-F scores from baseline to post-intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess changes in sleep outcomes and calculated sleep efficiency: bed time, sleep onset latency, number of awakenings, total duration of awakenings, wake time, arising time, daytime naps, soundness of sleep, sleep quality, sleep medication and alcohol use</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Blinding efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess investigator blinding efficacy as reflected by mid-intervention and post-intervention questionnaires</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concurrent Medications</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess concurrent medications and correlation with intervention efficacy</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Expectations</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 9 weeks; 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess participant expectation of benefit and blinding efficacy as reflected by pre-intervention and post-intervention questionnaires</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess participant satisfaction and help-seeking behavior as reflected by a 3-month follow-up questionnaire</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Insomnia Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active CBT-I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Internet-guided cognitive behavioral therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Education control program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sleep Healthy Using the Internet (SHUT-I)</intervention_name>
    <description>Cognitive behavioral therapy delivered via internet-guided program customized for military service members</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active CBT-I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Education Control Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Online portal designed to inform participants about healthy lifestyle activities and general insomnia information</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-64

          -  Service member or veteran

          -  Ability to provide electronic informed consent and follow study-related instructions

          -  Presence of clinical insomnia for a period of at least 1 month prior to consent as
             confirmed by self-reported Insomnia Severity Index (ISI) score ≥15 and Pittsburgh
             Sleep Quality Index ≥5

          -  History of mild traumatic brain injury ≥6 months prior to consent, including
             blast-related, as confirmed by a telephone administered traumatic brain injury
             screener

          -  Reliable access to a telephone and the Internet via their computer or smartphone

          -  Stable regimen of medications for sleep or potentially affecting sleep over prior 1
             month as confirmed by clinical history review

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or previous cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (CBT-I) or electronic
             CBT- I intervention; participants may still receive other approved therapies provided
             via standard of care

          -  Life expectancy of &lt;6 months

          -  Rapidly progressive illnesses (i.e., late-stage cancer, neurodegenerative conditions,
             major organ failure, etc.)

          -  Self-reported history of moderate to severe substance use disorders with the exception
             of nicotine

          -  Active bipolar disorder or psychosis that could be worsened by mild sleep restriction
             as part of electronic CBT-I

          -  Routine irregular work schedules or sleep patterns defined as shift work greater than
             1 day per week

          -  Any other considerations that in the view of the principal investigator may adversely
             affect patient safety, participation, or scientific validity of the data being
             collected
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David L Brody, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Molly Malarkey</last_name>
    <phone>301-456-5474</phone>
    <email>cnrm-ecbti@usuhs.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uniformed Services University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Molly Malarkey</last_name>
      <email>cnrm-ecbti@usuhs.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 13, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Insomnia</keyword>
  <keyword>Concussion</keyword>
  <keyword>Mild Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Initiation and Maintenance Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Concussion</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Identifier-free participant data sets will be shared with the Uniformed Services University Center for Neuroscience and Regenerative Medicine Data Repository. Identifier-free data sets may also be shared with the Federal Interagency Traumatic Brain Injury Research (FITBIR) Data Repository.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_time_frame>After study completion, data sets will be de-identified and shared with the repositories. De-identified data sets will be stored in the repositories indefinitely.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Access to the CNRM Data Repository will be determined b the CNRM Data Quality, Access, and Publication Committee. Investigators requesting access to the data will provide a list of investigators and collaborators who will have access to the data, documentation of Ethical Conduct of Research and Human Participants Protection Training, and documentation of Institutional Review Board Approval of the research project.
Access to FITBIR will follow FITBIR Access Criteria</ipd_access_criteria>
    <ipd_url>https://fitbir.nih.gov/content/access-data</ipd_url>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

