<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04377633</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2020-042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04377633</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anesthesia-handover Checklist and Perioperative Outcomes in Elderly</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of an Anesthesia-handover Checklist on Perioperative Outcomes of Elderly Patients Undergoing Major Noncardiac Surgery: A Prospective Before-and-after Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University First Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University First Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the increasing number of surgical cases, intraoperative handover of anesthesia care is
      common and inevitable. Verbal handover from one anesthesiologist to another during surgery
      are being used in many hospitals. However, verbal handover is often an informal, unstructured
      process during which omissions and errors can occur. It is possible that an improved
      anesthesia handover may reduce the related adverse events. This study aims to test the
      hypothesis that use of a well-designed, structured handover-checklist to improve handover
      quality may decrease the occurrence of postoperative complications in elderly patients
      undergoing major noncardiac surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It was estimated that more than 9 million patients undergo surgery with a complete anesthesia
      handover each year worldwide. Verbal handover from one anesthesiologist to another during
      surgery are being used in many hospitals; and there is no unified patient handover guideline
      at present.

      It is well recognized that the transfer-of-care is a point of vulnerability where valuable
      patient information can be distorted and omitted. A previous study of the investigators
      showed that handover of anesthesia care was associated with a higher risk of delirium in
      elderly patients after major noncardiac surgery. The World Health Organization has included
      communication during patient care handovers among its top 5 patient safety initiatives.

      It is possible that an improved anesthesia-handover protocol may reduce the related adverse
      events. Many efforts have performed to optimize handover processes. However, handover quality
      between anesthesiologists has rarely been investigated. The investigators hypothesize that a
      well-designed, structured handover-checklist will improve handover quality and reduce the
      occurrence of postoperative complications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 16, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>A composite incidence of all complications within 30 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Include organ injury (delirium, acute kidney injury, and myocardial injury) within 3 days and other major complications (class II or higher on Clavien-Dindo classification) within 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intensive care unit admission after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Intensive care unit admission after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in the intensive care unit after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in the intensive care unit after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of organ injury (delirium, acute kidney injury, and acute myocardial injury) within 3 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Delirium is diagnosed with the Confusion Assessment Method. Acute kidney injury is diagnosed according to the KDIGO (Kidney Disease: Improving Global Outcomes) Criteria. Acute myocardial injury is diagnosed according to the serum cardiac tropinin I level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of major complications within 30 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Major complications are defined as newly occurred conditions that are harmful to patients' recovery and required medical therapy, i.e., class II or higher on the Clavien-Dindo classification.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Length of hospital stay after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-cause mortality within 30 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause mortality within 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity within 3 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity is assessed with the Numeric Rating Scale, an 11-point scale where 0=no pain and 10=the worst pain.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective sleep quality within 3 days after surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days after surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective sleep quality is assessed with the Numeric Rating Scale, an 11-point scale where 0=the best sleep and 10=the worst sleep.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1440</enrollment>
  <condition>Elderly Patients</condition>
  <condition>Major Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Anesthesia; Adverse Effect</condition>
  <condition>Prevention</condition>
  <condition>Postoperative Complications</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anesthesia handover during surgery will be performed as usual, i.e., a verbal exchange of pertinent clinical information.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Anesthesia handover during surgery will be performed according to a structured checklist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral handover</intervention_name>
    <description>Anesthesia handover during surgery will be performed as usual, i.e., oral exchange of pertinent clinical information.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Checklist handover</intervention_name>
    <description>Anesthesia handover during surgery will be performed according to a structured handover checklist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Elderly patients (aged 65 years and over);

          2. Scheduled to undergo major non-cardiac surgery with an expected duration of at least 2
             hours;

          3. Requirement of complete handover between anesthesiologists during surgery (initial
             anesthesiologist no longer returns).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Preoperative history of schizophrenia, epilepsy, Parkinsonism or myasthenia gravis;

          2. Inability to communicate before surgery (coma, profound dementia or language barrier);

          3. Craniocerebral injury or neurosurgery;

          4. Severe liver dysfunction (Child-Pugh grade C), severe renal dysfunction (requiring
             dialysis), or expected survival of &lt;24 hours.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>86(10) 83572784</phone>
    <email>wangdongxin@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Xiao-Ling Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>86(10) 83575138</phone>
    <email>lani-zxl@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peking University First Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100034</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dong-Xin Wang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>86(10) 83572784</phone>
      <email>wangdongxin@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Xiao-Ling Zhang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>86(10) 83575138</phone>
      <email>lani-zxl@163.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choromanski D, Frederick J, McKelvey GM, Wang H. Intraoperative patient information handover between anesthesia providers. J Biomed Res. 2014 Sep;28(5):383-7. doi: 10.7555/JBR.28.20140001. Epub 2014 Jun 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25332710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siddiqui N, Arzola C, Iqbal M, Sritharan K, Guerina L, Chung F, Friedman Z. Deficits in information transfer between anaesthesiologist and postanaesthesia care unit staff: an analysis of patient handover. Eur J Anaesthesiol. 2012 Sep;29(9):438-45. doi: 10.1097/EJA.0b013e3283543e43.</citation>
    <PMID>22569028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh H, Thomas EJ, Petersen LA, Studdert DM. Medical errors involving trainees: a study of closed malpractice claims from 5 insurers. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Oct 22;167(19):2030-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17954795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arora V, Johnson J, Lovinger D, Humphrey HJ, Meltzer DO. Communication failures in patient sign-out and suggestions for improvement: a critical incident analysis. Qual Saf Health Care. 2005 Dec;14(6):401-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16326783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horwitz LI, Moin T, Krumholz HM, Wang L, Bradley EH. Consequences of inadequate sign-out for patient care. Arch Intern Med. 2008 Sep 8;168(16):1755-60. doi: 10.1001/archinte.168.16.1755.</citation>
    <PMID>18779462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudson CC, McDonald B, Hudson JK, Tran D, Boodhwani M. Impact of anesthetic handover on mortality and morbidity in cardiac surgery: a cohort study. J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth. 2015 Feb;29(1):11-6. doi: 10.1053/j.jvca.2014.05.018. Epub 2014 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25440620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones PM, Cherry RA, Allen BN, Jenkyn KMB, Shariff SZ, Flier S, Vogt KN, Wijeysundera DN. Association Between Handover of Anesthesia Care and Adverse Postoperative Outcomes Among Patients Undergoing Major Surgery. JAMA. 2018 Jan 9;319(2):143-153. doi: 10.1001/jama.2017.20040.</citation>
    <PMID>29318277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu GY, Su X, Meng ZT, Cui F, Li HL, Zhu SN, Wang DX. Handover of anesthesia care is associated with an increased risk of delirium in elderly after major noncardiac surgery: results of a secondary analysis. J Anesth. 2019 Apr;33(2):295-303. doi: 10.1007/s00540-019-02627-3. Epub 2019 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>30820749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hyder JA, Bohman JK, Kor DJ, Subramanian A, Bittner EA, Narr BJ, Cima RR, Montori VM. Anesthesia Care Transitions and Risk of Postoperative Complications. Anesth Analg. 2016 Jan;122(1):134-44. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000692.</citation>
    <PMID>25794111</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kraman SS, Hamm G. Risk management: extreme honesty may be the best policy. Ann Intern Med. 1999 Dec 21;131(12):963-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10610649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berkenstadt H, Haviv Y, Tuval A, Shemesh Y, Megrill A, Perry A, Rubin O, Ziv A. Improving handoff communications in critical care: utilizing simulation-based training toward process improvement in managing patient risk. Chest. 2008 Jul;134(1):158-62. doi: 10.1378/chest.08-0914.</citation>
    <PMID>18628218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wayne JD, Tyagi R, Reinhardt G, Rooney D, Makoul G, Chopra S, Darosa DA. Simple standardized patient handoff system that increases accuracy and completeness. J Surg Educ. 2008 Nov-Dec;65(6):476-85. doi: 10.1016/j.jsurg.2008.06.011.</citation>
    <PMID>19059181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Joint Commission releases Improving America's Hospitals: The Joint Commission's Annual Report on Quality and Safety, 2008. Jt Comm Perspect. 2009 Jan;29(1):3, 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19368073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferran NA, Metcalfe AJ, O'Doherty D. Standardised proformas improve patient handover: Audit of trauma handover practice. Patient Saf Surg. 2008 Sep 25;2:24. doi: 10.1186/1754-9493-2-24.</citation>
    <PMID>18817559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riesenberg LA, Leitzsch J, Little BW. Systematic review of handoff mnemonics literature. Am J Med Qual. 2009 May-Jun;24(3):196-204. doi: 10.1177/1062860609332512. Epub 2009 Mar 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19269930</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haynes AB, Weiser TG, Berry WR, Lipsitz SR, Breizat AH, Dellinger EP, Herbosa T, Joseph S, Kibatala PL, Lapitan MC, Merry AF, Moorthy K, Reznick RK, Taylor B, Gawande AA; Safe Surgery Saves Lives Study Group. A surgical safety checklist to reduce morbidity and mortality in a global population. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jan 29;360(5):491-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMsa0810119. Epub 2009 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19144931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah AC, Oh DC, Xue AH, Lang JD, Nair BG. An electronic handoff tool to facilitate transfer of care from anesthesia to nursing in intensive care units. Health Informatics J. 2019 Mar;25(1):3-16. doi: 10.1177/1460458216681180. Epub 2016 Dec 1.</citation>
    <PMID>29231091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hall M, Robertson J, Merkel M, Aziz M, Hutchens M. A Structured Transfer of Care Process Reduces Perioperative Complications in Cardiac Surgery Patients. Anesth Analg. 2017 Aug;125(2):477-482. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000002020.</citation>
    <PMID>28504990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalkman CJ. Handover in the perioperative care process. Curr Opin Anaesthesiol. 2010 Dec;23(6):749-53. doi: 10.1097/ACO.0b013e3283405ac8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21037475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Catchpole KR, de Leval MR, McEwan A, Pigott N, Elliott MJ, McQuillan A, MacDonald C, Goldman AJ. Patient handover from surgery to intensive care: using Formula 1 pit-stop and aviation models to improve safety and quality. Paediatr Anaesth. 2007 May;17(5):470-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17474955</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Philibert I, Barach P. The European HANDOVER Project: a multi-nation program to improve transitions at the primary care--inpatient interface. BMJ Qual Saf. 2012 Dec;21 Suppl 1:i1-6. doi: 10.1136/bmjqs-2012-001598.</citation>
    <PMID>23173180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wohlauer MV, Arora VM, Horwitz LI, Bass EJ, Mahar SE, Philibert I; Handoff Education and Assessment for Residents (HEAR) Computer Supported Cooperative Workgroup. The patient handoff: a comprehensive curricular blueprint for resident education to improve continuity of care. Acad Med. 2012 Apr;87(4):411-8. doi: 10.1097/ACM.0b013e318248e766.</citation>
    <PMID>22361791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arriaga AF, Elbardissi AW, Regenbogen SE, Greenberg CC, Berry WR, Lipsitz S, Moorman D, Kasser J, Warshaw AL, Zinner MJ, Gawande AA. A policy-based intervention for the reduction of communication breakdowns in inpatient surgical care: results from a Harvard surgical safety collaborative. Ann Surg. 2011 May;253(5):849-54. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e3181f4dfc8.</citation>
    <PMID>21173696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petrovic MA, Martinez EA, Aboumatar H. Implementing a perioperative handoff tool to improve postprocedural patient transfers. Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf. 2012 Mar;38(3):135-42.</citation>
    <PMID>22435231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pugel AE, Simianu VV, Flum DR, Patchen Dellinger E. Use of the surgical safety checklist to improve communication and reduce complications. J Infect Public Health. 2015 May-Jun;8(3):219-25. doi: 10.1016/j.jiph.2015.01.001. Epub 2015 Feb 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25731674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaba DM. Anaesthesiology as a model for patient safety in health care. BMJ. 2000 Mar 18;320(7237):785-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10720368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dindo D, Demartines N, Clavien PA. Classification of surgical complications: a new proposal with evaluation in a cohort of 6336 patients and results of a survey. Ann Surg. 2004 Aug;240(2):205-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15273542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University First Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dong-Xin Wang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Department of Anaesthesiology and Critical Care Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Elderly patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Major surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Anesthesia handover</keyword>
  <keyword>Handover checklist</keyword>
  <keyword>Postoperative complications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Complications</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

