<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04370444</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H19-00294</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04370444</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathways for Patient-centered Diagnosis and Management of Endometriosis-associated Deep Dyspareunia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pathways for Patient-centered Diagnosis and Management of Endometriosis-associated Deep Dyspareunia: A Pilot Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>BC Women's Hospital &amp; Health Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>BC Women's Hospital &amp; Health Centre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the acceptability and effectiveness of two tools
      that may help address the management of deep dyspareunia: 1) A phallus length reducer (PLR,
      brand name: Ohnut), consisting of 4 interconnected silicone rings worn externally over the
      penetrating object to reduce pain with deep penetration by allowing adjustable limitation of
      penetration depth, and 2) A vaginal insert for at home self-assessment of the extent and
      severity of deep dyspareunia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Endometriosis is a gynecological condition characterized by the abnormal growth
      of endometrial like tissue outside of the uterus. The condition affects approximately 10% of
      reproductive-age females and can cause various types of pain, including chronic pelvic pain
      and deep dyspareunia (pelvic pain with deep sexual intercourse). Research has shown that
      individuals with endometriosis and dyspareunia have significantly reduced sexual quality of
      life, lower self-esteem, and impaired sexual function. Qualitative research has also
      demonstrated that many individuals with dyspareunia feel guilty about their pain, and often
      continue to engage in intercourse even when the pain is severe.

      Aims and Hypotheses:

        1. To assess the acceptability of the phallus length reducer (PLR) for participants with
           endometriosis and their partners. The investigators hypothesize that both partners will
           indicate the PLR is acceptable on the self-reported questionnaire.

        2. To measure the reduction in deep dyspareunia observed among people using the PLR with
           their partner. The investigators hypothesize that the PLR will be associated with a
           reduction in self-reported deep dyspareunia scores among participants randomized to the
           PLR intervention, compared to participants randomized to the waitlist control group. The
           measured reduction in deep dyspareunia will be used to power a future definitive trial.

        3. To explore whether an at-home assessment of dyspareunia is an acceptable and valid
           alternative to clinical measures. The investigators hypothesize that the at-home
           assessments of dyspareunia will be acceptable to participants and will yield results
           that are highly correlated with questionnaire-based and clinical assessments of this
           pain.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of the phallus length reducer (PLR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks of using the PLR</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the PLR as measured via questionnaire using a 7 point likert scale (1 = most positive/ best/ strongly agree, 7 = most negative/ worst/ strongly disagree)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of dyspareunia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks of using the PLR</time_frame>
    <description>Self reported on an 11-point numeric rating scale (0 being no pain, 10 being worst pain imaginable)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sexual function</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and after 6 weeks of using the PLR</time_frame>
    <description>Change in sexual function as measured by Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI). This a brief, self-administered questionnaire to assess key dimensions of sexual function in women. The scale consists of 19 items that assess sexual function over the past four weeks and are scored from 1 to 5 (with 1 being the lowest report of desire and 5 being the highest).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sexual distress</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and after 6 weeks of using the PLR</time_frame>
    <description>Change in sexual distress as measured in Female Sexual Distress Scale - Revised (FSDS-R) This is a self-administered measure of female personal distress associated with sexual dysfunction. There are 13 questions. The range for each question is 0 (Never) to 4 (Always).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of self-measurement of dyspareunia</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment and questionnaire administered 2 times, each one week apart, during the first 4 weeks of the study (to be assessed at week 2 and 3 of participant's menstrual cycle, which may vary)</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of self-measurement of dyspareunia will be measured via questionnaire using 7 point likert scale (1 = most positive/ best/ strongly agree, 7 = most negative/ worst/ strongly disagree)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Validity of self-measurement of dyspareunia</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessment and questionnaire administered 2 times, each one week apart, during the first 4 weeks of the study (to be assessed at week 2 and 3 of participant's menstrual cycle, which may vary)</time_frame>
    <description>Dyspareunia score from the self-measurement will be compared to records of dyspareunia scores from physician performed pelvic exams. (11 point scale, 0 being no pain, 10 being worst pain imaginable)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometriosis-related Pain</condition>
  <condition>Dyspareunia Deep</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental (PLR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be given the OhNut Phallus Length Reducer (PLR) for use during the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Waitlist)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will not have a PLR during the study period. They will be placed on a waitlist to receive the PLR at the end of the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phallus Length Reducer</intervention_name>
    <description>Phallus Length Reducer</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental (PLR)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OhNut</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-assessment of dyspareunia</intervention_name>
    <description>Use of a vaginal insert to self assess dyspareunia</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Waitlist)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental (PLR)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patient

          -  19 to 49 years of age

          -  Monogamous partnership

          -  Sexually active or not sexually active due to deep dyspareunia

          -  Self-reported deep dyspareunia score ≥ 4/10

          -  Sexual partner who is willing to participate

          -  Willing to engage in penetrative sex at least once during the duration of the study
             Partner

          -  19 years of age or older

          -  Sexually active with a patient participant who has consented to participate in this
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patient

          -  Superficial dyspareunia score ≥ 4/10 (This is a potentially confounding variable; the
             PLR is not expected to affect introital pain)

          -  Current use of a PLR

          -  Inability to complete English-language questionnaires

          -  GAD-7 score ≥ 15

          -  Intense fear/anxiety in anticipation of, during, or as a result of vaginal intercourse
             Partner

          -  Current use of a PLR

          -  Inability to complete English-language questionnaires
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participants with endometriosis by definition are female. We are also recruiting their sexual partners, who may be any gender.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 10, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>BC Women's Hospital &amp; Health Centre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Yong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endometriosis</keyword>
  <keyword>dyspareunia</keyword>
  <keyword>sexual distress</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyspareunia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

