<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04372836</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2018-0732</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04372836</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vasopressin Injection Technique to Preserve Ovarian Reserve in Surgery for Unilateral Ovarian Endometriomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Vasopressin Injection Technique in Laparoscopic Excision of Unilateral Ovarian Endometriomas on Ovarian Reserve: Prospective Randomized Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Endometriosis is a common disease with an incidence rate of 15% in women of childbearing age,
      and is a chronic disease that significantly affects women's quality of life by causing two
      problems: pain and infertility. The usual treatment for ovarian endometrioma is surgery, and
      the most common surgical method is laparoscopy, however, Surgery has the disadvantage of
      deteriorating ovarian function. Previous studies reported that local injection of vasopressin
      may minimize damage to the ovarian tissue during the surgical procedure. Currently, the best
      way to evaluate ovarian function is to measure AMH (anti-mullerian hormone). However,
      previous studies has not evaluated ovarian function by AMH. Aim of this study is to compare
      the anti-mullarian hormone (AMH) change in vasopressin-administered patients after unilateral
      endometrioma surgery. In this study, antimullerian hormone (AMH) will be used as an indicator
      of ovarian function evaluation, and will be evaluated before surgery, 6 and 12 months after
      surgery. Subjects were allocated randomly with stratification of AMH level 3.0mg / ml.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Endometriosis is a common disease with an incidence rate of 15% in women of childbearing age,
      and is a chronic disease that significantly affects women's quality of life by causing two
      problems: pain and infertility. The usual treatment for ovarian endometrioma is surgery, and
      the most common surgical method is laparoscopy. Surgery has the advantage of reducing the
      pain of ovarian endometrioma and lower recurrence rate compared to other treatment methods,
      but it also has the disadvantage of deteriorating ovarian function. This is because healthy
      ovarian tissue adjacent to the ovarian tumor are damaged at the time of surgery, and damage
      to the ovarian tissue while using an electric cauterizer for hemostasis when removing the
      ovarian tumor. Therefore, various surgical methods have been studied to minimize damage to
      the ovarian tissue during the surgical procedure including local vasopressin injection into
      the surgical site.

      Vasopressin is a peptide hormone secreted by the posterior lobe of the pituitary gland, which
      promotes reabsorption of water in the kidney when administered systemically, but when
      administered locally, it constricts blood vessels and prevents bleeding such as in esophageal
      variceal therapy or myomectomy. There are previous studies that demonstrated, vasopressin
      injection prior to endometrioma resection, the interface between the endometrioma and normal
      ovarian tissue is dissected, and the amount of deterioration in ovarian function after
      surgery is reduced compared to the group without vasopressin by reducing the amount of
      bleeding through vasoconstriction.

      Endometriosis is the most common disease that interferes with pregnancy, and is known to have
      a significant decrease in ovarian function after surgery compared to other benign ovarian
      tumors. Currently, the best way to evaluate ovarian function is to measure AMH
      (anti-mullerian hormone). In a paper published in JMIG in 2014, the degradation of ovarian
      function was not evaluated as AMH. The purpose of this study is to investigate the effect of
      vasopressin on ovarian function in endometrioma surgery.

      Patients who have obtained consent in advance are divided into a test group that injects
      vasopressin and a control that excises it without injection. In the test group, everything
      except the administration of vasopressin at the surgical site immediately before the
      endometriosis was performed is the same as that of the control group. In this study,
      antimullerian hormone (AMH) will be used as an indicator of ovarian function evaluation, and
      will be evaluated before surgery, 6 and 12 months after surgery Aim of this study is to
      compare the anti-mullarian hormone (AMH) change in vasopressin-administered patients after
      unilateral endometrioma surgery. In this study, subjects were allocated randomly with
      stratification of AMH level 3.0mg / ml. When α (type 1 error) = 0.05
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Primary and secondary outcomes are compared between study group and control group 6 months and 12 months after intervention during surgery for unilateral endometrioma.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>anti-mullerian hormone(AMH)</measure>
    <time_frame>before surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-mullerian hormone is the most reliable marker to assess ovarian reserve to date.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>anti-mullerian hormone(AMH)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-mullerian hormone is the most reliable marker to assess ovarian reserve to date.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>anti-mullerian hormone(AMH)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-mullerian hormone is the most reliable marker to assess ovarian reserve to date.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Coagulation time during surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Coagulation time has a relationship with decrease of ovarian function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">76</enrollment>
  <condition>Unilateral Ovarian Endometrioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>During laparoscopic enucleation of unilateral endometrial cyst, no intervention is added to subjects allocated to control arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm (with vasopressin injection)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>During laparoscopic enucleation of unilateral endometrial cyst, diluted vasopressin is injected into the interface between endometrioma and ovarian parenchyma of patients allocated to study arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vasopressin injection</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention consists of five steps: rupture the ovarian endometrial cyst and remove the ''chocolate fluid;'' inject diluted vasopressin solution into the interface between endometrioma and ovarian parenchyma; stop injecting until the solution overflow; separate the endometrioma away from the ovarian parenchyma; and coagulate bleeding spots and suture the ovary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study arm (with vasopressin injection)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects undergoing laparoscopic ovarian cyst enucleation for unilateral endometrioma.

          -  25≤Age≤45

          -  0.5≤AMH≤7

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with major medical conditions such as uncontrolled infection, diabetes,
             severe renal or hepatic disease.

          -  History of hormonal medication use within 2months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Objective of this study is to assess decrease in ovarian reserve after ovarian endometrioma surgery.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sang-Wun Kim, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-2228-2230</phone>
    <email>san1@yuhs.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Yonsei University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sang-Wun Kim, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-2230</phone>
      <email>san1@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saeki A, Matsumoto T, Ikuma K, Tanase Y, Inaba F, Oku H, Kuno A. The vasopressin injection technique for laparoscopic excision of ovarian endometrioma: a technique to reduce the use of coagulation. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2010 Mar-Apr;17(2):176-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2009.11.004.</citation>
    <PMID>20226404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qiong-Zhen R, Ge Y, Deng Y, Qian ZH, Zhu WP. Effect of vasopressin injection technique in laparoscopic excision of bilateral ovarian endometriomas on ovarian reserve: prospective randomized study. J Minim Invasive Gynecol. 2014 Mar-Apr;21(2):266-71. doi: 10.1016/j.jmig.2013.07.024. Epub 2013 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24075865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang NN, Sun TS, Yang Q. An effective &quot;water injection&quot;-assisted method for excision of ovarian endometrioma by laparoscopy. Fertil Steril. 2019 Sep;112(3):608-609. doi: 10.1016/j.fertnstert.2019.05.014. Epub 2019 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>31280960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endometriosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Vasopressins</keyword>
  <keyword>Anti-mullerian Hormone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vasopressins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arginine Vasopressin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Raw data of basic dermographic informations and outcomes of interventions (AMH, coagulation time, recurrence of endometriosis cyst) can be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

