<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04375722</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>36878</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04375722</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transcranial Alternating Current Stimulation (tACS) in Subacute Aphasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exogenous Tuning of Neural Oscillations as a Mode of Treatment in Post-stroke Sub-acute Aphasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical College of Wisconsin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical College of Wisconsin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the effects of transcranial alternating current stimulation (tACS) on
      language recovery after stroke as well as healthy language functions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aphasia is a debilitating disorder, typically resulting from damage to the left hemisphere,
      that can impair a range of communication abilities, including language production and
      comprehension, reading, and writing. Approximately 180,000 new cases of aphasia are
      identified per year, and approximately 1 million or 1 in 250 are living with aphasia in the
      United States (NIH-NIDCD, 2015). Treatments are limited and provide modest benefits at best.
      The current emphasis in aphasia rehabilitation is to formulate intensive speech and language
      therapies and augment therapeutic benefits by providing brain stimulation concurrent with
      therapies. Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) is one of the most widely used such
      technique. While tDCS has had relative success in chronic aphasia (&gt;6 months after stroke),
      it has not been efficacious during subacute stages (&lt;3 months after stroke). But enhancing
      language recovery early after stroke is desirable because of its potential impact on
      long-term language outcomes and quality-of-life.

      The current study will investigate the efficacy of high-definition tACS (HD-tACS) to help
      restore neural oscillatory activity in subacute aphasia. TACS differs from tDCS in that
      sinusoidal, alternating currents are delivered rather than constant currents. TACS can
      manipulate the ongoing oscillatory neuronal activity and potentially increase functional
      synchronization (or connectivity) between targeted areas. This feature of tACS is quite
      attractive, given the new body of evidence suggesting that language impairments stem from
      diminished functional connectivity and disruptions in the language network due to stroke. The
      selection of tACS frequencies in this study is guided by our preliminary work examining
      pathological neural oscillations found near stroke-lesioned areas (or perilesional) in
      aphasia. By exogenously tuning the perilesional oscillations with tACS, the investigators
      hope to up-regulate communication across these areas and other connected areas to improve
      language outcome. If successful, tACS will be a powerful and novel treatment approach with
      reverberating positive impact on long-term recovery.

      The study will employ HD-tACS in a within-subject and sham-controlled design, using two
      frequencies (alpha/10 Hz and low-gamma/40 Hz) combined with language tasks and
      electroencephalography (EEG) to evaluate subsequent behavioral and neurophysiological
      changes. Investigators plan to recruit 50 participants: 25 stroke survivors with aphasia
      within 2-3 months after stroke, and 25 healthy controls.

      Participants will complete language testing that covers a broad range of language functions,
      medical history, and MRI. Eligible participants will undergo active tACS at 10 Hz or 40 Hz,
      or sham-tACS. All participants will receive all three stimulation types during separate
      visits. The tACS administrator and participants will be blinded to the stimulation type. The
      order of stimulation type will be counterbalanced across participants. Washout period between
      visits will be at least 48 hours to minimize potential carryover effects. EEG will be
      acquired before and after tACS during periods of rest (resting-state) and during language
      tasks. Participants will complete a questionnaire at the end of stimulation visits to assess
      potential side effects of tACS. Total time enrolled in the study is expected to be 2-3 weeks,
      which may be longer depending on participant's availability.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In the within-subject design healthy participants and stroke survivors will receive tACS stimulation at 10 Hz, 40 Hz, and sham settings in a randomized order with &gt;48 hours washout period in between stimulation sessions.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participant, care provider, investigator and outcomes assessor are all blinded. One study team member will be designated as unblinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>tACS frequency-dependent changes in language performance on object and action naming tasks</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate changes monitored after 20 minutes of tACS of each type</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement on noun and verb retrieval performance as determined by increases in accuracy and decreases in reaction time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>tACS frequency-dependent neurophysiological changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediate changes monitored after 20 minutes of tACS of each type</time_frame>
    <description>Concomitant frequency-specific EEG changes in spectral power and phase synchronization are expected.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Individual differences in tACS responsiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>Based on immediate changes monitored after 20 minutes of tACS of each type</time_frame>
    <description>tACS responsiveness depending on language impairment types, stroke lesion and language lateralization characteristics will be explored.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Aphasia</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tACS 10 Hz low frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-Definition-tACS will be delivered via a battery operated alternating current stimulator (Soterix) using two 3x1 center-surround montages. Targets of stimulation will be localized based on the 10-10 International EEG system with center electrodes placed at a frontal and a temporoparietal site. The current is turned on and increased in a ramplike fashion over approximately 30 seconds. Participants will undergo tACS with 10-Hz stimulation for 20-minutes with 1 milliampere (mA) peak-to-peak intensity. Stimulation will be maintained no longer than 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tACS 40 Hz high frequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-Definition-tACS will be delivered via a battery operated alternating current stimulator (Soterix) using two 3x1 center-surround montages. Targets of stimulation will be localized based on the 10-10 International EEG system with center electrodes placed at a frontal and a temporoparietal site. The current is turned on and increased in a ramplike fashion over approximately 30 seconds. Participants will undergo tACS with 40-Hz stimulation for 20-minutes with 1 milliampere (mA) peak-to-peak intensity. Stimulation will be maintained no longer than 20 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tACS sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>High-Definition-tACS will be delivered via a battery operated alternating current stimulator (Soterix) using two 3x1 center-surround montages. Targets of stimulation will be localized based on the 10-10 International EEG system with center electrodes placed at a frontal and a temporoparietal site. The current is turned on and increased in a ramplike fashion for 10 to 30 seconds and then ramped down. In this way, the participants experience the same initial sensations (mild tingling) as the active tACS groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tACS 10-Hz</intervention_name>
    <description>Low frequency alternating current will be applied.</description>
    <arm_group_label>tACS 10 Hz low frequency</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tACS 40-Hz</intervention_name>
    <description>High frequency alternating current will be applied.</description>
    <arm_group_label>tACS 40 Hz high frequency</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tACS sham</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham stimulation setting will be applied.</description>
    <arm_group_label>tACS sham</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Healthy Controls

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Fluent in English

          -  No history of neurological or psychiatric disorders

        Stroke Patients

          -  Diagnosed with post-stroke aphasia by referring physician/neuropsychologist

          -  Consent date &lt;=3 months after stroke onset

          -  Right-handed

          -  Fluent in English

          -  18 years of age or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe cognitive, auditory or visual impairments that would preclude cognitive and
             language testing

          -  Presence of major untreated or unstable psychiatric disease

          -  A chronic medical condition that is not treated or is unstable

          -  The presence of cardiac stimulators or pacemakers

          -  Any metal implants in the skull

          -  Contraindications to MRI or tACS

          -  History of seizures

          -  History of dyslexia or other developmental learning disabilities
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Priyanka Shah-Basak, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Samantha Drane, MS</last_name>
    <phone>414-955-5891</phone>
    <phone_ext>4149555894</phone_ext>
    <email>sdrane@mcw.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Samantha Drane, MS</last_name>
      <phone>414-955-5891</phone>
      <email>sdrane@mcw.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antal A, Alekseichuk I, Bikson M, Brockmöller J, Brunoni AR, Chen R, Cohen LG, Dowthwaite G, Ellrich J, Flöel A, Fregni F, George MS, Hamilton R, Haueisen J, Herrmann CS, Hummel FC, Lefaucheur JP, Liebetanz D, Loo CK, McCaig CD, Miniussi C, Miranda PC, Moliadze V, Nitsche MA, Nowak R, Padberg F, Pascual-Leone A, Poppendieck W, Priori A, Rossi S, Rossini PM, Rothwell J, Rueger MA, Ruffini G, Schellhorn K, Siebner HR, Ugawa Y, Wexler A, Ziemann U, Hallett M, Paulus W. Low intensity transcranial electric stimulation: Safety, ethical, legal regulatory and application guidelines. Clin Neurophysiol. 2017 Sep;128(9):1774-1809. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2017.06.001. Epub 2017 Jun 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28709880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bucur M, Papagno C. Are transcranial brain stimulation effects long-lasting in post-stroke aphasia? A comparative systematic review and meta-analysis on naming performance. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2019 Jul;102:264-289. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2019.04.019. Epub 2019 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>31077693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buzsaki, G. (2006). Rhythms of the brain. New York: Oxford.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chu RK, Braun AR, Meltzer JA. MEG-based detection and localization of perilesional dysfunction in chronic stroke. Neuroimage Clin. 2015 Apr 8;8:157-69. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2015.03.019. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26106540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dubovik S, Ptak R, Aboulafia T, Magnin C, Gillabert N, Allet L, Pignat JM, Schnider A, Guggisberg AG. EEG alpha band synchrony predicts cognitive and motor performance in patients with ischemic stroke. Behav Neurol. 2013;26(3):187-9. doi: 10.3233/BEN-2012-129007.</citation>
    <PMID>22713421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finnigan S, van Putten MJ. EEG in ischaemic stroke: quantitative EEG can uniquely inform (sub-)acute prognoses and clinical management. Clin Neurophysiol. 2013 Jan;124(1):10-9. doi: 10.1016/j.clinph.2012.07.003. Epub 2012 Aug 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22858178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finnigan SP, Walsh M, Rose SE, Chalk JB. Quantitative EEG indices of sub-acute ischaemic stroke correlate with clinical outcomes. Clin Neurophysiol. 2007 Nov;118(11):2525-32. Epub 2007 Sep 21.</citation>
    <PMID>17889600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fridriksson J, Rorden C, Elm J, Sen S, George MS, Bonilha L. Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation vs Sham Stimulation to Treat Aphasia After Stroke: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Neurol. 2018 Dec 1;75(12):1470-1476. doi: 10.1001/jamaneurol.2018.2287.</citation>
    <PMID>30128538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fries P. Rhythms for Cognition: Communication through Coherence. Neuron. 2015 Oct 7;88(1):220-35. doi: 10.1016/j.neuron.2015.09.034. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26447583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grefkes C, Fink GR. Reorganization of cerebral networks after stroke: new insights from neuroimaging with connectivity approaches. Brain. 2011 May;134(Pt 5):1264-76. doi: 10.1093/brain/awr033. Epub 2011 Mar 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21414995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Helfrich RF, Schneider TR, Rach S, Trautmann-Lengsfeld SA, Engel AK, Herrmann CS. Entrainment of brain oscillations by transcranial alternating current stimulation. Curr Biol. 2014 Feb 3;24(3):333-9. doi: 10.1016/j.cub.2013.12.041. Epub 2014 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24461998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herrmann CS, Rach S, Neuling T, Strüber D. Transcranial alternating current stimulation: a review of the underlying mechanisms and modulation of cognitive processes. Front Hum Neurosci. 2013 Jun 14;7:279. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2013.00279. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23785325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kielar A, Deschamps T, Chu RK, Jokel R, Khatamian YB, Chen JJ, Meltzer JA. Identifying Dysfunctional Cortex: Dissociable Effects of Stroke and Aging on Resting State Dynamics in MEG and fMRI. Front Aging Neurosci. 2016 Mar 3;8:40. doi: 10.3389/fnagi.2016.00040. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26973515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah-Basak PP, Wurzman R, Purcell JB, Gervits F, Hamilton R. Fields or flows? A comparative metaanalysis of transcranial magnetic and direct current stimulation to treat post-stroke aphasia. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2016 May 2;34(4):537-58. doi: 10.3233/RNN-150616. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27163249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah-Basak PP, Kielar A, Deschamps T, Verhoeff NP, Jokel R, Meltzer J. Spontaneous oscillatory markers of cognitive status in two forms of dementia. Hum Brain Mapp. 2019 Apr 1;40(5):1594-1607. doi: 10.1002/hbm.24470. Epub 2018 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>30421472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah-Basak PP, Norise C, Garcia G, Torres J, Faseyitan O, Hamilton RH. Individualized treatment with transcranial direct current stimulation in patients with chronic non-fluent aphasia due to stroke. Front Hum Neurosci. 2015 Apr 21;9:201. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2015.00201. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25954178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical College of Wisconsin</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Priyanka Shah-Basak, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Priyanka Shah-Basak, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>language</keyword>
  <keyword>language impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>transcranial alternating current stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>tACS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aphasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

