<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04370990</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Ethic committee H-17040114</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04370990</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Automated Oxygen Administration -Rethinking Interventions Alleviating Dyspnea in Patients With COPD</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Robot-administered Oxygen Have Effect on the Perception of Dyspnea in Patients Admitted With COPD and Hypoxemia?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is associated with high morbidity and mortality.
      The Danish Lung Association estimates that 320,000 Danes live with COPD, of which
      approximately 50,000 with severe COPD. In 2017, records showed that 23,979 admissions in
      Denmark were related to COPD; of these patients, about 20% were readmitted 2-30 days after
      discharge. The main symptom is dyspnea, which is often accompanied by anxiety. Primary
      treatment is; oxygen, bronchiolitis, prednisolone, morfica, NIV, and anxiolytics.

      Researchers at Hvidovre Hospital have developed an oxygen robot that continuously monitors
      the patient's SaO2 (oxygen saturation) and automatically administrates the oxygen depending
      on it. The preliminary results show that patients with robot-administrated oxygen were within
      defined SaO2 range in 85.7% of the time versus 46.6% when oxygen was nurse-administrated. The
      research was conducted as a multicentre Randomized Controlled Trial focusing on physiological
      end-points.

      There is a lack of knowledge about the patient perspective of treatment with the oxygen
      robot.

      The purpose of this study is:

      1. To examine the effect of robot-administered oxygen on patients' perception of dyspnoea,
      including the emotional response in the form of anxiety and depression

      The perspective is to be able to provide a holistic response to whether robot-administered
      oxygen can be a better method of treating and alleviating dyspnoea.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is a high prevalence disease and is associated
      with high morbidity and mortality worldwide. In 2017, there were 23.979 COPD related
      admissions in Denmark, approximately 10% died during hospitalization, while 20% of survivors
      were readmitted between day 2-30 after discharge.

      Patients with COPD often experience long disease trajectories characterized by a substantial
      burden of symptoms, impaired functional status, multiple admissions and thereby reduced
      quality of life.

      The cardinal symptom dyspnea is associated with hypoxemia, anxiety and depression. Evidence
      shows that depression is a significant risk factor for disabling dyspnea, while risk of
      anxiety increases with the severity of Dyspnea. The prevalence of anxiety and depression is
      indicated to lie between 10%-55% and 10%-86% in patients hospitalized with COPD in
      exacerbation . Patients with COPD have an 85% increased risk of developing anxiety compared
      to a matching control group without COPD. The prevalence of anxiety is 10 times higher among
      patients with COPD than in the background population and are strongly associated with the
      risk of hospitalization, long admissions, readmissions and death. Anxiety and depression are
      often treated with benzodiazepines which have a respiratory suppressive effect. Consumption
      of benzodiazepines increases disease progression, and studies have shown that 31.7% of
      patients with COPD have a benzodiazepine consumption and that 9% initiate a new
      benzodiazepine ordination in conjunction with an exacerbation.

      The evidence that oxygen prevents disease progression and mortality is consistent, but there
      is a lack of knowledge about whether oxygen, can reduce the intensity of dyspnea in patients
      with COPD.

      In the acute phase of an exacerbation the oxygen flow is titrated to achieve a SaO2 between
      88-92%. Keeping patients with COPD within the given SaO2 range is essential because too low
      SaO2 can induce tissue damage, heart overload and difficulty concentrating, while
      hyperoxaemia can inhibit respiration and increase the risk of hypercapnia, acidosis and the
      need for ventilatory support in the form of Non-invasive Ventilation (NIV).

      In clinical practice, oxygen flow is administered and titrated, via aggregates, by nurses
      based on point observations, with the risk of patients being outside optimal SaO2 range,
      between observations.

      To improve practice, a group of researchers at Hvidovre Hospital has developed an oxygen
      robot, called O2matic, which continuously monitors the patient's SaO2 and automatically
      administrates oxygenflow according to it.

      O2Matic has been tested in a randomized controlled trial in 2018. Patients admitted with an
      exacerbation of COPD and hypoxemia (SaO2 ≤ 88%) was included (N = 19). The design was
      crossover and patients were allocated to either 4 hours of manual oxygen administration via
      nurse followed by 4 hours of oxygen administration via O2Matic, or vice versa. The study
      showed that patients with O2matic controlled oxygen administration were within defined SaO2
      range in 85.7% of the time versus 46,6% of the time when the oxygen was controlled and
      administrated by a nurse . These results are in consensus with a former Canadian study
      testing an alternative oxygen robot (FreeO2). The two RCT Studies provide evidence to
      investigate robot-administered oxygen therapy for inpatient patients with exacerbation of
      COPD in a larger multicenter RCT.

      Dyspnea is defined as; &quot;A subjective experience of breathing discomfort that consist of
      qualitatively distinct sensations that vary in intensity&quot;. The experience of dyspnea is a
      product of a physical perception based on signals from the body to the brain followed by the
      cognitive processing of these into an emotional experience. Dyspnea is thus an emotional and
      sensational experience based on perceptual afferent feedback from various respiratory
      receptors. Up to 16 possible mechanisms are involved in the process . Given the above,
      dyspnea is a complex symptom, mainly induced by the body's attempts to obtain homeostasis,
      when subjected to hypoxemia. Despite this dyspnea is not the same as hypoxemia, as it has not
      been clearly demonstrated that reduced hypoxemia, by oxygen therapy also reduces Dyspnea.
      However, there are indications in the literature that oxygen therapy can reduce the
      experience of dyspnea. A significant barrier to the use of oxygen therapy as an intervention
      on fragmentary dyspnea in patients with COPD is the risk of hypercapnia and acidosis. Oxygen
      therapy administrated according to saturation in a closed-loop-feedback-system by a robot,
      could potentially be an intervention to relieve fragmentary dyspnea in patients with COPD.
      International guidelines show that dyspnea is not treated consistently nor effectively in the
      advanced stages of the disease.

      Opioids are one of the most widely used agents in the treatments of dyspnea. Opioids
      suppress' respiration and treatment should be balanced to avoid respiratory depression.

      Guidelines points out the importance of identifying and graduate the intensity of dyspnea in
      clinical practice, without indicating any superior instruments to achieve this. Majority of
      instruments developed, describe dyspnea in relation to activity. As COPD progress, dyspnea
      intensifies and patients will become more inactive and often live a sedentary life.

      Few questionnaires measure the sensory and emotional domains of dyspnea independently of
      activity and diagnose. One is the multidimensional Dyspnoea profile (MDP) that has currently
      been translated into Danish.

      In order to reduce symptom burden, length of hospital stay, number of re-admissions and
      mortality, new knowledge and more effective methods for treating and alleviating dyspnea and
      the associated anxiety and depression are needed in patients with COPD.

      Studies investigating the effect of oxygen therapy, including time with and degree of
      hypoxemia, in hypoxemic patients experiencing dyspnea, anxiety or depression during
      hospitalization with acute exacerbation, could not be identified.

      Because O2matic provides a new and unique opportunity to reduce and illuminate time with
      hypoxemia during hospitalization and patient's subjective experience of the sensory and
      emotional aspects of dyspnea can be reported on a validated questionnaire via MDP, the
      investigators now have an option to investigate if a robot intervention, that reduces time
      with hypoxemia, has an effect on dyspnea in patients admitted with a exacerbation of COPD.
      Furthermore, investigators want to examine whether this intervention alters the consumption
      of opioids and benzodiazepines.

      Primary hypothesis. Robot-administered oxygen reduces the perception of dyspnea measured at
      scale A1 on the multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP), in patients with COPD and hypoxemia.

      Primary objective. To investigate if oxygen administration by O2matic has an effect on the
      perception of dyspnea in patients admitted with an exacerbation of COPD and hypoxemia, versus
      conventional oxygen administration by oxygen aggregate and a nurse Primary end points.

        -  Global dyspnea measured on scale A1 on multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) Secondary
           hypothesis. Oxygen administration by O2matic reduces the sensory and emotional dimension
           of dyspnea, respiratory symptoms, anxiety and depression, as well as consumption of
           anxiolytics in patients admitted with hypoxemia and exacerbation of COPD versus
           conventional Oxygen management by aggregate and nurse Secondary aim. To investigate if
           oxygen administration by O2matic has an effect on the sensory and emotional dimension of
           dyspnea, respiratory symptoms, anxiety and depression, as well as the consumption of
           anxiolytics in patients admitted with hypoxemia and exacerbation in COPD versus
           Conventional oxygen management by aggregate and nurse Secondary end-points.

        -  Sensory and emotional dimension of dyspnea described by The Sensory Quality scale (SQ)
           and the A2 scale of the MDP

        -  Current dyspnea measured on visual Analog scale (VAS)

        -  Accumulated dyspnea over 3 days measured on VAS

        -  Respiratory symptoms described by COPD Assessment Test

        -  Anxiety described by HADS A score

        -  Depression described by HADS D scores

        -  Consumption of anxiolytics reported in Mg and in number of administrations

      Following variables will be tested for confounding:

      Age, gender, BMI, smoking status, package year, Long-term Oxygen Therapy (LOT), FEV1, GOLD
      classification A-D and Prednisolone reported in Mg
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Open label randomized controlled parallel study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Global dyspnea measured on scale A1 on multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) is validated for patients with COPD (40) The schedule is an instrument consisting of 11 rating scales that describe both the sensory and emotional dimension of dyspnea in a user-specified focus period.Patients perception of unpleasantness or discomfort in breathing sensations described as global dyspnea measured on an intensity scale from 0 (anchored by term; neutral) -10(anchored by term; unbearable )</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The sensory dimension of dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>The SQ-scale of the Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) is validated for patients with COPD. The schedule is an instrument consisting of 11 rating scales that describe both the sensory and emotional dimension of dyspnea in a user-specified focus period. The sensory dimension of dyspnea is described by 5 categorical variables. The intensity of the symptoms described by the variables is indicated by numerical scales from 0-10, called Sensory Questions (SQ) (range 0-50).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The emotional dimension of dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>The A2-Scale of the Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile (MDP) is validated for patients with COPD. The schedule is an instrument consisting of 11 rating scales that describe both the sensory and emotional dimension of dyspnea in a user-specified focus period.The emotional dimension of dyspnea is also accessed with five variables measuring the intensity by numerical scales from 0-10, the scale is called the emotional response A2 (range 0-50).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Current dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Current dyspnea measured on a Visual analog scale (VASD). Sensation of dyspnea expressed in subject's feelings of breathlessness measured by Visual Analogue Scale for Dyspnea (VASD).
Patients subjective sensation of dyspnea expressed as feelings of breathlessness is measured on a vertical line length equal to 100mm. VAS-scale consist of one construction and no subscales are provided.
Each end of the line showing words that anchors the scale and describes the extreme e.g. &quot;No breathlessness at all&quot; or &quot;Worst possible breathlessness&quot; complimented by a describing smiley looking happy or sad, but no words describing intermediate positions (VAS-scale).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accumulated dyspnea</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>accumulated dyspnea over past 3 days measured on Visual analog scale (VASD). Sensation of dyspnea expressed in subject's feelings of breathlessness measured by Visual Analogue Scale for Dyspnea (VASD).
Patients subjective sensation of dyspnea expressed as feelings of breathlessness is measured on a vertical line length equal to 100mm. VAS-scale consist of one construction and no subscales are provided.
Each end of the line showing words that anchors the scale and describes the extreme e.g. &quot;No breathlessness at all&quot; or &quot;Worst possible breathlessness&quot; complimented by a describing smiley looking happy or sad, but no words describing intermediate positions (VAS-scale).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Respiratory symptom intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>COPD assessment test (CAT). The COPD Assessment Test (CAT) is a symptom screening tool which was developed to illustrate the effect of COPD on the patient's health status . The questionnaire consists of 8 questions, each of which uncovers a symptom. The intensity of the symptom is assessed on a rating scale from 0-5, where 5 is the highest intensity. CAT has a scoring range of 0-40. A difference in scores of 2 units is proposed as minimal clinically significant change A CAT score: 0-10 = Low impact, 11-20 = Medium impact, 21-30 = high impact and 31-40 = Very high impact .</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients sensation of anxiety is assessed by the Hospital and Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) (HADS Zigmond and Snaith, 1983). HADS is a quality of Life instrument containing two constructs; &quot;anxiety&quot; and &quot;Depression&quot;. HADS consists of 14 items, with seven items/questions relating to anxiety and seven items/questions relating to depression. The questionnaire has a simple theoretical structure making item/question 1,3,5,7,9,11 and 11 measuring different aspects of anxiety and item/question 2,4,6,8,10,12 and 14 measuring different aspects of depression.
Ratings by subjects are made on a four-point ordinal scale, which represents the degree of distress:
0=not at all; 1=occasionally; 2= a lot of the time; 3= most of the time Items are summed on each of the seven-item-subscales reflecting the constructs anxiety or depression. Range of each subscale is between 0-21 with high scoring indicating presence of anxiety or depression</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients sensation of depressive symptoms is assessed by the Hospital and Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) (HADS Zigmond and Snaith, 1983). HADS is a quality of Life instrument containing two constructs; &quot;anxiety&quot; and &quot;Depression&quot;. HADS consists of 14 items, with seven items/questions relating to anxiety and seven items/questions relating to depression. The questionnaire has a simple theoretical structure making item/question 1,3,5,7,9,11 and 11 measuring different aspects of anxiety and item/question 2,4,6,8,10,12 and 14 measuring different aspects of depression.
Ratings by subjects are made on a four-point ordinal scale, which represents the degree of distress:
0=not at all; 1=occasionally; 2= a lot of the time; 3= most of the time Items are summed on each of the seven-item-subscales reflecting the constructs anxiety or depression. Range of each subscale is between 0-21 with high scoring indicating presence of anxiety or depression</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>consumption of anxiolytics</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Reprted by; name of drug, mg and number of administrations</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <condition>Hypoxia</condition>
  <condition>Closed-Loop Communication</condition>
  <condition>Dyspnea</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care plus O2matic controlled oxygen therapy for a maximum of 3 days or until weaning from oxygen supplementation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>controle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care plus manual controlled oxygen therapy by nursing staff. O2matic used in monitoring mode to measure SpO2 continuously</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>O2matic</intervention_name>
    <description>O2matic is a closed-loop-system that controls oxygenadministration according to SpO2. The aim is to maintain SpO2 within a predefined target interval, E.G. 88-92% with the lowest possible supplementation of oxygen by nasal cannula</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  COPD veryfied by Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 sec (Fev1) divided by forced Vital
             Capacity (FVC)&lt; 0,70

          -  Admission due to exercabation in COPD

          -  COPD exacerbation and pneumonia can be included

          -  Expeted duration of admission &gt;48 hours

          -  Need for oxygen supplementation (SpO2&lt;= 88% in room air) Cognitive able to participate
             in the study

          -  Willing to participate and give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Need or anticipated need for mechanical ventilation ( Intermittent continuous Positive
             Airway Pressure (CPAP) is allowed)

          -  Major comorbidities causing hypoxemia (cancer, heart disease, pulmonary embolia)

          -  Asthma or other respiratory conditions requiring higher SpO2 than normal for COPD
             Pregnancy

          -  Cognitive barrierers for participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>35 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>charlotte Sandau Bech, RN, MScHS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hvidovre University Hospital, Kettegaard alle</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Jørgen Ringbæk, PhD, associated professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hvidovre University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>charlotte Sandau Bech, MScHS</last_name>
    <phone>+45 21277711</phone>
    <email>charlotte.sandau.bech.01@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ejvind Frausing Hansen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 38623233</phone>
    <email>ejvind.frausing.hansen@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bispebjerg University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2400</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lars Pedersen, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 38636177</phone>
      <email>lars.pedersen.03@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hvidovre University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2650</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Charlotte Sandau Bech, MScHS</last_name>
      <phone>+45 21277711</phone>
      <email>charlotte.sandau.bech.01@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ejvind Frausing Hansen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+ 45 38623233</phone>
      <email>ejvind.frausing.hansen@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herlev University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2730</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Lange, DMSc</last_name>
      <email>peter.lange@ku.sund.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gentofte University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2900</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jens-Ulrik Jensen, PhD</last_name>
      <email>jens.ulrik.jensen@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nordsjællands Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frederikssund</city>
        <zip>3600</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisette Snedker, RN</last_name>
      <phone>+45 48295263</phone>
      <email>lisette.hedegaard.snedker@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Copenhagen University Hospital, Hvidovre</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Charlotte Sandau Bech</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Nursing Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>O2matic</keyword>
  <keyword>Multidimensional Dyspnea Profile</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

