<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04379830</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8246</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04379830</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Preoperative Very Low Energy Diet for Obese Rectal Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Preoperative Very Low Energy Diet on Mesorectal Volume in Rectal Cancer Patients: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study will aim to determine the feasibility, safety, and cost associated with a
      preoperative VLED for obese rectal cancer patients. Ultimately, the investigators seek to
      provide evidence that may inform the development of a standardized preoperative weight loss
      protocol in obese rectal cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single center, single-arm prospective cohort pilot study with a primary aim
      of determining the feasibility, safety, and cost associated with a preoperative VLED for
      obese rectal cancer patients. Efficacy of preoperative VLED in this study population will be
      assessed through measures of mesolectal fat volume with MRI at two separate time points,
      prior to commencing a pre-operative VLED diet and immediately prior to patients undergoing
      laparoscopic low anterior resection for rectal cancer, to objectively quantify the proportion
      of mesorectal fat loss in response to VLED. Secondary aims include an assessment of whether
      preoperative weight loss contributes to improved intraoperative outcomes including operative
      time, blood loss, and rate of conversion to open procedure. Furthermore, postoperative
      outcomes including rates of 30-day complication rate, hospital stay, among others will be
      evaluated.

      Optifast 900 will be administered to enrolled patients over a 3-week period immediately prior
      to their scheduled elective operation date. Compliance will be measured with a food diary.
      Two MRIs of the rectum will be obtained: one prior to the commencement of VLED and one
      following the completion of the VLED before the scheduled operation date. The first MRI will
      be a clinically indicated preoperative staging investigation, while the second MRI will be
      used purely for research purposes. Patients will be enrolled in an enhanced recovery after
      surgery (ERAS) for colorectal surgery program. All patients will be followed by their surgeon
      as per that individual surgeon's postoperative surveillance schedule. At the routine
      one-month follow-up visit, patients will see the surgeon as well as a study investigator who
      will complete a standardized follow up questionnaire, focusing on adverse events and
      functional independence. Research personnel and study investigators will follow patients
      throughout their postoperative course in hospital and note any secondary outcomes including
      laboratory tests or adverse events through the electronic patient chart.

      Ultimately, the investigators seek to provide evidence that may inform the development of a
      standardized preoperative weight loss protocol in obese rectal cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study is a single center, single-arm prospective cohort pilot study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Target (trial feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>20 patients over 6 months (3.33 patients per month)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication Compliance Rate (trial feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants adhering to prescribed Optifast 900 dosages and percentage of Optifast 900 dosages missed by study participants</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Follow-Up Rate (trial feasibility)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participants completing follow up appointments, questionnaires, and investigations</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (safety and tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in functional independence from the preoperative, pre-VLED period to 1-month postoperatively using the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Mesorectal Fat Volume (efficacy)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Change in mesolectal fat volume on MRI from prior to 3 weeks of preoperative VLED to immediately following completion of preoperative VLED</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the cost (in Canadian dollars) of a 3-week course of Optifast 900 to the cost associated with length of hospital stay and additional treatments during index hospitalization (e.g. reoperation, packed red blood cell transfusion)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Length of Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay (LOS) in hospital postoperatively in days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events attributable to the index surgery for up to 30 days following hospital discharge, including: surgical site infection (SSI), urinary tract infection (UTI), venous thromboembolism (VTE), pneumonia, acute kidney injury (AKI), postoperative ileus, anastomotic leak, wound dehiscence, erectile dysfunction, and readmission</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative Time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Operative time during index surgery for rectal cancer in minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Blood Loss</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Blood loss during index surgery for rectal cancer in millilitres</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Review of surgical dictation for any deviation from expected intraoperative processes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Very Low Energy Diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>VLED in its entirety is composed of the following for 3-weeks preoperatively: Optifast 900 with a single piece of fruit for breakfast, Optifast 900 with one cup of vegetables for lunch, and Optifast 900 with one cup of vegetables for dinner. Patients will be provided written information on fruits and vegetables permitted for consumption with Optifast 900 to provide a total energy intake between 450 and 800 kilocalories (kcal) per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Very Low Energy Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Optifast 900 is an FDA approved commercial nutritionally complete meal replacement product manufactured and marketed in the United States. Optifast 900 will be employed as part of the VLED in the present study in the following manner: Optifast 900 with a single piece of fruit for breakfast, Optifast 900 with one cup of vegetables for lunch, and Optifast 900 with one cup of vegetables for dinner. Patients will be provided written information on fruits and vegetables permitted for consumption with Optifast 900 to provide a total energy intake between 450 and 800 kilocalories (kcal) per day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Very Low Energy Diet</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Optifast 900</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  BMI greater than or equal to 30kg/m2 and less than or equal to 55kg/m2

          -  Patients undergoing elective surgery

          -  Documented pathological diagnosis of rectal adenocarcinoma

          -  Preoperative staging investigations consistent with stage I, II, and III disease

          -  Laparoscopic surgery occurring at St. Joseph's Healthcare Hamilton

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI less than 30kg/m2

          -  Contraindications to magnetic resonance imaging, general anesthesia, or major
             colorectal surgery

          -  Patient undergoing open surgery

          -  Patients undergoing emergency or palliative surgery

          -  Preoperative staging investigations consistent with metastatic disease

          -  Allergy or contraindication to the use of Optifast

          -  Prior pelvic colorectal surgery or bariatric surgery

          -  Enrolled in any other clinical trials or prospective studies where similar outcomes
             are measured

          -  Severe, chronic cardiovascular disease (i.e. recent myocardial infarction, unstable
             angina), renal disease, or hepatic dysfunction

          -  Patients with pharmacologically managed diabetes mellitus

          -  Pregnant and/or breastfeeding patients

          -  Inability to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cagla Eskicioglu, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(905) 522-1155</phone>
    <phone_ext>35921</phone_ext>
    <email>eskicio@mcmaster.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tyler McKechnie, BSc</last_name>
    <email>tyler.mckechnie@medportal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 4A6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cagla Eskicioglu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(905) 522-1155</phone>
      <phone_ext>35921</phone_ext>
      <email>eskicio@mcmaster.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Very Low Energy Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Anterior Resection</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

