<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04370860</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>202002122RINC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04370860</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal EGFR TKIs Treatment Strategies for Lung Adenocarcinoma Harboring EGFR Exon 19 Deletion Variants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determine the Optimal EGFR TKIs Treatment Strategies for Lung Adenocarcinoma Harboring EGFR Exon 19 Deletion Variants : the Clinical Analysis and Cell Lines Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine the optimal EGFR TKIs treatment strategies for lung adenocarcinoma harboring
      EGFR exon 19 deletion variants
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RNA extraction: The investigators will extract total RNA from cell lysates by using
      Tri-reagent (Molecular Research Center, Inc., Cincinnati, Ohio) and an RNA Mini Kit (Qiagen,
      Hilden, Germany) according to the manufacturer's instruction. RNA obtained from the Mini Kit
      column will be eluted. The quantity and quality of the purified RNA will be evaluated using a
      NanoDrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer will be stored at -80 °C for further mutational analyses.

      Data acquisition: The investigators will record and follow participants' clinical
      information, including ethnicity, age, gender, smoking status, histological types, lung
      cancer stage (the TNM status), metastatic sites, ECOG score, CT/CXR imaging, chemotherapy or
      radiation treatment at the time of diagnosis of lung cancer and through the entire clinical
      courses. Specific marker such as TTF1, is used to ensure the diagnosis of primary lung tumor.
      Clinicopathologic stage assigns according to the seventh tumor-node-metastasis
      classification. The investigators assess the treatment responses according to the Response
      Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) using the unidimension method, and record the
      best response achieved per treatment. Treatment response, progression-free survival, and
      overall survival are recorded prospectively for further analysis.

      Statistical analysis: All categorical variables will be analyzed with Pearson's χ² test,
      except where a small size required the use of Fisher's exact test. The progression-free
      survival curve and overall survival will be plotted by the Kaplan-Meier method and compared
      by the log-rank test. Multivariate analysis for overall survival will be performed using the
      Cox's proportional hazards model. Two-sided p-values of less than 0.05 is considered
      significant. All analyses will be performed using SPSS software (version 16.0 for Windows;
      SPSS Inc.).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor size measurement for evaluating tumor progression</measure>
    <time_frame>&quot;up to 5 years,&quot; &quot;from date of treatment (EGFR TKIs) until the date of first documented progression</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor size is recorded using CT scan before the first day of of treatment and routine CT scan image is captured at each cycle of treatment to evaluate the growth of tumor.
According to RECIST (The Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors), tumor progression will be assigned based on (1) a sum measurement of original target lesions that has increased more than 20%, (2) the reappearance of the original target lesions, (3) appearance of new lesions, and (4) a new lymph node metastatic lesion which is more than 10mm in diameter. Statistically, patients will be divided into several groups according to Exon 19 deletion variants, which is detected before the first day of treatment. The clinicopathologic characteristics (sex, age, smoking history) will be enrolled in multivariate analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>EGFR Exon 19 Mutation</condition>
  <condition>Tumor Progression</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Biopsy tissue, DNA, RNA
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        only citizens of Taiwan will be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients have signed the informed consent (201103013RC and 201111039RIC) before
             2019/12/31 and authorized the Institutional Review Board of Nation Taiwan University
             Hospital to review the new study for approving the usage of residual specimens.

          -  The residual samples from various sources, including surgical tissues, computed
             tomography (CT)-guided needle aspiration and/or biopsy, echo-guided needle aspiration
             and /or biopsy, bronchoscopic biopsy or brushing, bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL),
             endobronchial ultrasound guided needle aspiration, and lymph node aspiration, and
             pleural effusion specimens. The samples will be collected at the time of diagnostic
             procedure performed. All patients should sign an informed consent for purpose of using
             samples for molecular genetic testing.

          -  1000 residual specimens will be used for the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients didn't sign the informed consent (201103013RC, 201111039RIC)

          -  The residual specimens are not qualified.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JIN-YUAN SHIH, PhD,MD</last_name>
    <phone>+886-2-23123456</phone>
    <phone_ext>62910</phone_ext>
    <email>jyshih@ntu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Taiwan University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <zip>100</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>lung adenocarcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma of Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

