<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04376671</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Mansoura University 15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04376671</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Quantitative EEG Markers in Mild Cognitive Impairment in Epilepsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Quantitative EEG Markers in Mild Cognitive Impairment in Epilepsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Epileptic patients are plighted with limited daily activities, social dysfunction, family
      conflicts and cognitive impairment. Most of the studies had showed that cognitive disorders
      were frequent in patients with epilepsy.The cognitive impairment has been reported in around
      25% of epileptic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive consequences in epilepsy are often described in the following domains: verbal
      memory, language, executive functions, and attention. However, most of the studies focus on
      one or two domains in a relatively small sample.

      Few studies have investigated the influential factors for the epilepsy-related cognitive
      impairment . However, most of these studies merely focused on one or a few potential factors
      and failed to consider possible distractions from other influential factors. Therefore, it is
      crucial to include more potential factors in the analysis and to rule out possible
      confounding interactions between factors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mini-mental state examination (MMSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>This is a rapid screening tool to estimate the cognitive functions that evaluates orientation, basic attention, working memory, learning, naming, construction, comprehension, and repetition. The maximum score is 30 and scores below 24 indicating cognitive impairment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal cognitive assessment (MoCA)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Montreal cognitive assessment is a rapid sensitive screening tool for assessment of impaired cognitive function (Nasreddine et al., 2005). The main domains of MoCA scale include attention, executive functions, memory, language, attention, naming, orientation, and visual-spatial ability. The total score is 30 points. A score of 25 points or less indicated impaired cognitive function. For patients with less than12 years of education, one point was added to the total score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>temporal lobe epilepsy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group of patients with temporal lobe epilepsy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extra-temporal lobe epilepsy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group of patients with extra-temporal lobe epilepsy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electroencephalography</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients underwent EEG recordings according to previously published methods (Bonanni et al., 2008). . EEG recordings were analyzed with methods described in our previous work (Bonanni et al., 2008) by 2 experimenters unaware of the clinical conditions of the subjects. Briefly, quantitative EEGs (QEEGs) were recorded from 21 scalp derivations. Ag/AgCl disk scalp electrodes (19) were placed according to the international 10-20 system, EEG was recorded from Fp1, Fp2, Fz, F3, F4, F7, F8, Cz, C3, C4, Pz, P3, P4, T3, T 4, T5, T6, O1, and O2. Two additional electrodes were placed on A1 and A2. EEG activity was analyzed from single or multiple leads grouped to define the following scalp regions: anterior (Fz, Fp2, F7, Fp1, F3, F4, and F8), central (Cz, C3, and C4), posterior (Pz, P3, P4, O1, and O2), and temporal (T3, T4, T5, and T6).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extra-temporal lobe epilepsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>temporal lobe epilepsy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A total of 90 adult epileptic patients (according to the diagnosis of epilepsy in 2017,
        Fisher et al., 2017), 50 males and 40 females. With average age 24.5 ±5 .63.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with clinically confirmed epilepsy in adult patients.

          -  Non-symptomatic epilepsy.

          -  Normal CT or MRI brain, and

          -  Education level of primary school at least to respond to the scales correctly were
             included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psycho-neurological illnesses,

          -  History of alcoholism or drug abuse, or

          -  Recently on medications that may affect cognitive functions (like antidepressants and
             antipsychotic drugs).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Esmael M Ahmed, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistant Prof of Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mansoura University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansoura</city>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>England MJ, Liverman CT, Schultz AM, Strawbridge LM. Epilepsy across the spectrum: promoting health and understanding. A summary of the Institute of Medicine report. Epilepsy Behav. 2012 Oct;25(2):266-76. doi: 10.1016/j.yebeh.2012.06.016. Epub 2012 Oct 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23041175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Matonda-Ma-Nzuzi T, Mampunza Ma Miezi S, Mpembi MN, Mvumbi DM, Aloni MN, Malendakana F, Mpaka Mbeya D, Lelo GM, Charlier-Mikolajczak D. Factors associated with behavioral problems and cognitive impairment in children with epilepsy of Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of the Congo. Epilepsy Behav. 2018 Jan;78:78-83. doi: 10.1016/j.yebeh.2017.08.030. Epub 2017 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>29179103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bora E, Meletti S. Social cognition in temporal lobe epilepsy: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Epilepsy Behav. 2016 Jul;60:50-57. doi: 10.1016/j.yebeh.2016.04.024. Epub 2016 May 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27179192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Black LC, Schefft BK, Howe SR, Szaflarski JP, Yeh HS, Privitera MD. The effect of seizures on working memory and executive functioning performance. Epilepsy Behav. 2010 Mar;17(3):412-9. doi: 10.1016/j.yebeh.2010.01.006. Epub 2010 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20153981</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cassel A, Morris R, Koutroumanidis M, Kopelman M. Forgetting in temporal lobe epilepsy: When does it become accelerated? Cortex. 2016 May;78:70-84. doi: 10.1016/j.cortex.2016.02.005. Epub 2016 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27010834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonanni L, Thomas A, Tiraboschi P, Perfetti B, Varanese S, Onofrj M. EEG comparisons in early Alzheimer's disease, dementia with Lewy bodies and Parkinson's disease with dementia patients with a 2-year follow-up. Brain. 2008 Mar;131(Pt 3):690-705. doi: 10.1093/brain/awm322. Epub 2008 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>18202105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mansoura University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ahmed Esmael</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Prof of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Epilepsy, Mini Mental State Examination</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

