<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04370093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU-2019-0907</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04370093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pathogenesis of Uric Acid Nephrolithiasis: Role of Pioglitazone/Weight Loss</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pathogenesis of Uric Acid Nephrolithiasis: Role of Pioglitazone/Weight Loss</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will randomize overweight and obese iuan patients to Pio (45 mg/day,
      highest approved dose or placebo), WL (10% of body weight, following the established program
      used in the Diabetes Prevention Program), or Pio+WL. Participants will be evaluated at
      baseline and after 24 weeks of intervention while on a fixed metabolic diet to exclude the
      confounding effects of diet and perspiration. The primary endpoint will be change in upH, and
      multiple additional endpoints (serum, urine, imaging) will be assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In IUAN patients, the investigator will compare 1. PPAR activation; 2. weight loss; or 3.
      combination; on urine acid-base parameters relevant to UA stone risk. The investigator will
      assess the effect of these interventions on fat distribution, insulin sensitivity, and serum
      adiponectin, and correlate these changes with urine chemistry.

      Hypothesis: Weight loss + TZD independently result in durable changes in urine chemistry.

      Significance: Epidemiology of uric acid nephrolithiasis: Nephrolithiasis is an increasingly
      prevalent condition that leads to significant pain1, work productivity loss2, reduced quality
      of life3, urinary tract infection4, chronic kidney disease5,6 and end-stage renal disease7.
      In the U.S., nephrolithiasis prevalence doubled in the past 30 years to a level similar to
      diabetes, and is the most expensive non-malignant urologic condition (2006 U.S. annual cost:
      $10 billion)8. Compared with other stone types, uric acid stones recur at a higher rate9,
      lead to more CKD10, and comprise a rising fraction of stones11,12 , in part due to the
      growing prevalence of obesity and diabetes13-18. The single most important pathogenic factor
      in human IUAN is an overly acidic urine, promoting protonation of urate to the insoluble
      UA16,19. In previously completed NIH-supported studies, the Investigator identified increased
      net acid excretion and blunted ammoniagenesis to be the principal metabolic defects
      underlying aciduria in humans IUAN and in rodent models of IUAN risk16,18,20-23. Treatment
      has been empirical urinary alkalinization24 which is efficacious but has not changed since
      1986. Limitations include frequent dosing25, need for high dose in obese patients26,
      medication intolerance27, and need for periodic urine collections disliked by patients.
      Therapy that targets the underlying pathophysiologic defect rather than urinary chemistry is
      directly needed. The Investigator showed that the thiazolidinedione (TZD) pioglitazone that
      activates PPAR, improves systemic and urinary abnormalities in IUAN including impaired
      excessive acid excretion and ammoniagenesis, and results in a rise in UpH. TZD treatment of
      rodent IUAN model shows similar improvements28. The Investigator may have a therapy targeting
      the underlying pathobiology.

      The translational potential of our regimen is extremely high and immediate. If combined TZD
      and weight loss (Aim) are efficacious in reducing stone risk, one can move straight to a
      clinical trial using hard outcomes such as stone events, and stone count by imaging to test
      this regimen. None of these maneuvers requires FDA approval to initiate. Patients will then
      have instant control of urinary chemistry with empiric alkali therapy (existing therapy), but
      also a chance to achieve more lasting improvement with TZD and weight loss, which reverses
      the pathophysiology. Separately, adiponectin (APN) receptor agonists are being developed as
      potential pharmacological agents for the management of metabolic syndrome complications
      including diabetes and dyslipidemia29,30. If approved, such agents could be tested as therapy
      for aciduria in the metabolic syndrome if adiponectin mediates the impact of TZD on renal
      ammoniagenesis.

      UA nephrolithiasis is the clinically palpable sentinel of some complex underlying systemic
      pathophysiology; hence the impact of these studies extends beyond UA stones. The Investigator
      is examining a novel multi-organ paradigm of increased acid production from the gut that
      escapes hepatic metabolism, and ending up as an acid load imposed on the kidney. When
      compounded with renal ammoniagenesis defect, this leads to aciduria and UA lithogenesis. The
      Investigator will address some fundamental pathobiologic mechanisms of the metabolic
      syndrome. Due to the time and budget limits, the Investigator will concentrate our efforts to
      yield informative data; hence the renal focus. Our long-term goal is to use this as a portal
      to study multiple aspects of the gut, hepatic, and adipose pathophysiology of the metabolic
      syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 17, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine pH</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>24-hour urine pH is the main determinant of uric acid stone formation and recurrence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Ammonium/Net Acid Excretion</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The ratio of urine ammonium to net acid excretion (NH4+/NAE) is a key pathophysiologic risk factor to uric acid stone formation. This is calculated from 24 hr urine ammonium and 24 hr urine net acid excretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine Net Acid Excretion/Sulphate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Urine Net Acid Excretion to Sulphate ratio represents the diet-independent fraction of acid excreted. This is calculated from 24 hr urine net acid excretion and 24 hr urine sulphate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Supersaturation Index of Uric Acid</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Supersaturation Index of Uric Acid is a calculated parameters that indicates the degree of urinary saturation with respect to uric acid.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Nephrolithiasis, Uric Acid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone Drug (including Placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>45 mg/day- one pioglitazone tablet once daily throughout the 24 weeks of the study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Weight Loss, Behavioral</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weight loss following the Group Lifestyle Balance Program based on the Diabetes Prevention Program that utilizes cognitive behavioral strategies (goal setting, problem solving, self-monitoring, stimulus control),and provides written education materials to support health and nutrition behavior changes for weight management and disease prevention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone + Weight Loss</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pioglitazone 45 mg/day + Weight Loss following the Group Lifestyle Balance Program based on the Diabetes Prevention Program that utilizes cognitive behavioral strategies (goal setting, problem solving, self-monitoring, stimulus control),and provides written education materials to support health and nutrition behavior changes for weight management and disease prevention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pioglitazone 45 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>45 mg/day- one pioglitazone tablet once daily throughout the 24 weeks of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone Drug (including Placebo)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Weight Loss</intervention_name>
    <description>Weight loss following the Group Lifestyle Balance Program based on the Diabetes Prevention Program that utilizes cognitive behavioral strategies (goal setting, problem solving, self-monitoring, stimulus control),and provides written education materials to support health and nutrition behavior changes for weight management and disease prevention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Weight Loss, Behavioral</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pioglitazone + Weight Loss</intervention_name>
    <description>Pioglitazone + Weight loss following the Group Lifestyle Balance Program based on the Diabetes Prevention Program that utilizes cognitive behavioral strategies (goal setting, problem solving, self-monitoring, stimulus control),and provides written education materials to support health and nutrition behavior changes for weight management and disease prevention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pioglitazone + Weight Loss</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Idiopathic uric acid nephrolithiasis, with last stone analysis showing that stone has &gt;90%
        uric acid in composition Age &gt;21 years Any gender, race/ethnicity (from weight loss), but
        weight &lt;165 Kg (to fit into MR instrument); eGFR&gt;60ml/min/1.73 m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Bariatric surgery, chronic diarrhea, recurrent UTIs current insulin use use of a
        thiazolidinedione in past 2 years contraindication to thiazolidinedione use (liver dz,
        pedal edema, CHF NYHA class III/IV, no contraception)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Khashayar Sakhaee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UTSW</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390-9107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biomedical Sciences</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nephrolithiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pioglitazone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

