<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04372524</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H19-02032</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04372524</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biomarker Verification in Pediatric Chronic GvHD: ABLE 2.0 / PBMTC 1901 Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biomarker Verification in Pediatric Chronic Graft-Versus-Host Disease: Applied Biomarkers to Minimize Long Term Effects of Childhood/Adolescent Cancer Treatment (ABLE) / Pediatric Blood and Marrow Transplant Consortium (PBMTC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will validate a previously developed pediatric prognostic biomarker algorithm
      aimed at improving prediction of risk for the later development of chronic graft-versus-host
      disease (cGvHD) in children and young adults undergoing allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplant.

      By developing an early risk stratification of patients into low-, intermediate-, and
      high-risk for future cGvHD development (based upon their biomarker profile, before the onset
      of cGvHD), pre-emptive therapies aimed at preventing the onset of cGvHD can be developed
      based upon an individual's biological risk profile.

      This study will also continue research into diagnostic biomarkers of cGvHD, and begin work
      into biomarker models that predict clinical response to cGvHD therapies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic graft-versus-host disease (cGvHD) occurs when the new donor immune system &quot;attacks&quot;
      tissues in the recipient following allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT),
      leading to chronic inflammation, scarring and fibrosis, impaired immunity (including immune
      deficiency and immune dysregulation), and altered organ system functioning. Almost any organ
      or system has the potential to be affected by cGvHD, although eight organ systems are
      classically involved, including the skin, eyes, mouth, lungs, liver, gastrointestinal tract,
      genitourinary tract, and the musculoskeletal system.

      The investigators will be enrolling allogeneic HSCT recipients before conditioning, following
      these patients prospectively until 12-months (+/- 1 month) post-transplant for the
      development of all forms of GvHD (classical acute, late acute and chronic GvHD), collecting
      blood samples at day +60 (+/- 7 days), day +100 (+/- 14 days), and at the onset of either
      late acute or chronic GvHD. In addition, clinical data will be collected at different time
      points.

      Case report forms of standard transplant related data will be completed and entered into a
      REDCap database.

      Blood samples will be drawn and shipped to the Central Laboratory in Vancouver, BC, Canada,
      processed, analyzed, with the final biomarker risk algorithm being sent back to the treating
      clinician along with a short survey asking about their perception of the feasibility of
      altering their approach to cGvHD management based upon these results.

      If chronic GvHD develops at any time after transplant (day 0 to 1 year), or if any form of
      GvHD occurs at or after day +100 (whether late acute, chronic GvHD, or overlap syndrome), a
      blood sample will be drawn before escalating immune suppression, and the onset GvHD case
      report form will be completed following the protocol. If chronic GvHD is confirmed, an
      additional CRF will be submitted at 24-months (+/- 3 months) post-transplant to document new
      chronic GvHD manifestations, severity, and response to therapy.

      Study participants will have between 1 and 3 blood samples drawn over the course of 1-year
      post-transplant, depending upon their event and GvHD status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Day 60 blood sample collection</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 60 (+/- 7 days) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Validation of prognostic and diagnostic power of cGvHD biomarkers and testing of the biomarker assay performance of Day 60 post-transplant blood sample. Using this algorithm-based assay the investigators will attempt to develop risk assignment for cGvHD and L-aGvHD at Day 60 and determine whether this time point has a similar (or improved) predictive value to the day +100 (+/-14 days). Flow Cytometry and ELISA assays will be used for biomarker measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Day 100 blood sample collection</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100 (+/- 14 days) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Validation of prognostic and diagnostic power of cGvHD biomarkers and testing of the biomarker assay performance of Day 100 post-transplant blood sample (diagnostic biomarkers). Using this algorithm-based assay the investigators will attempt to develop risk assignment for cGvHD and L-aGvHD at Day 100. Flow Cytometry and ELISA assays will be used for biomarker measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Onset CvHD blood sample collection</measure>
    <time_frame>The day of initial diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Validation of prognostic and diagnostic power of cGvHD biomarkers and testing of the biomarker assay performance of the GvHD onset blood sample. The investigators will attempt to determine whether biomarkers present at the onset of new late-acte GvHD developing after day +100 (diagnostic biomarkers) or are similar to or different than at the onset of chronic GvHD. Flow Cytometry and ELISA assays will be used for biomarker measurement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline transplant clinical data collection at Day 0</measure>
    <time_frame>Between day 0 (day of transplant) and day +21</time_frame>
    <description>Baseline Transplant Data Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at Day 60</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 60 (+/- 7 days) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Day 60 Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at Day 100</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100 (+/- 14 days) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months (+/- 1 month) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months (+/- 1 month) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Months (+/- 1 month) post-transplant</time_frame>
    <description>Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical data collection at onset of GvHD</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Case Report Form to be completed. Clinical data will be used in data analysis.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Demonstration of identifiable and reproducible differences in diagnostics of cGvHD and L-aGvHD</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the study by year 2025</time_frame>
    <description>Metrics to measure this outcome will employ the difference in biomarkers (in combination with clinical manifestation) that can be used to discriminate between cGvHD and L-aGvHD and aid clinicians in establishing a more accurate diagnosis. Laboratory procedure and statistical data analysis will be used to achieve this.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of patient's risk profile and prediction of treatment responses</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the study by year 2025</time_frame>
    <description>Utilizing cGvHD specific biomarkers, clinicians will be able to predict patient's treatment responses and chose the more accurate and effective treatment options.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">500</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Graft-versus-Host-Disease</condition>
  <condition>Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Blood Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Non-Malignant Hematologic and Lymphocytic Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Allogeneic HSC Transplant recipients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Five possible patient scenarios are anticipated to occur in those who underwent allogeneic HSCT:
Early event (e.g. death, non-engraftment) occurring before day 100.
No late-acute or chronic GvHD ever develops at any time point in the first year post-transplant (regardless of whether or not classical acute GvHD develops in the first 100 days after transplant).
Early-onset chronic GvHD (including overlap syndrome) occurred before day 60.
Early-onset chronic GvHD (including overlap syndrome) occurred between day 60 and day 100.
Chronic GvHD after Day 100, Late-acute GvHD (de-novo or recurrent) after day 100, or cases of overlap syndrome occurred after day 100.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pediatric and adult (under age of 25 y.o.) patients undergoing allogeneic HSCT
        (hematopoietic stem cell transplantation) before the start of the conditioning regimen.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Any indication for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplant (malignant or
             non-malignant)

          2. Age 0 - 24.99 years at the time of transplant (on day 0)

          3. Any conditioning regimen (including myeloablative or
             reduced-toxicity/reduced-intensity)

          4. Any graft source (bone marrow, peripheral blood, cord blood)

          5. Any graft-versus-host disease prophylaxis strategy, including serotherapy such as ATG
             or alemtuzumab

          6. Haploidentical transplants, including post-transplant cyclophosphamide and alpha-beta
             TCR depletion, are allowed

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Second or greater allogeneic transplant

          2. Weight 7 kg or less

          3. Pure CD34+ selected haploidentical stem cell transplant (not including CD34 enrichment
             used in alpha-beta TCR depleted haploidentical transplants, which is allowed)

          4. Inability of a center to follow a patient for the development of late-acute and
             chronic GVHD until 1-year post-transplant (referral sites who transplant patients from
             outside institutions should not enroll participants if sending back to the referring
             site early, such that long-term follow up, blood, and data collection cannot be
             assured).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>24 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirk R Schultz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia / BC Children's Hospital Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Geoffrey DE Cuvelier, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manitoba / CancerCare Manitoba</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elena Ostroumov, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>604-875-2000</phone>
    <phone_ext>6648</phone_ext>
    <email>Elena.Ostroumov@bcchr.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sayeh Abdossamadi, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>604-875-2454</phone>
    <email>sabdossamadi@bcchr.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>BC Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6H 3N1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rupinder Aulakh, BSc</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kirk R. Schultz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jacob Rozmus, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amanda Li, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz KR, Kariminia A, Ng B, Abdossamadi S, Lauener M, Nemecek ER, Wahlstrom JT, Kitko CL, Lewis VA, Schechter T, Jacobsohn DA, Harris AC, Pulsipher MA, Bittencourt H, Choi SW, Caywood EH, Kasow KA, Bhatia M, Oshrine BR, Flower A, Chaudhury S, Coulter D, Chewning JH, Joyce M, Savasan S, Pawlowska AB, Megason GC, Mitchell D, Cheerva AC, Lawitschka A, Azadpour S, Ostroumov E, Subrt P, Halevy A, Mostafavi S, Cuvelier GDE. Immune profile differences between chronic GVHD and late acute GVHD: results of the ABLE/PBMTC 1202 studies. Blood. 2020 Apr 9;135(15):1287-1298. doi: 10.1182/blood.2019003186.</citation>
    <PMID>32047896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cuvelier GDE, Nemecek ER, Wahlstrom JT, Kitko CL, Lewis VA, Schechter T, Jacobsohn DA, Harris AC, Pulsipher MA, Bittencourt H, Choi SW, Caywood EH, Kasow KA, Bhatia M, Oshrine BR, Flower A, Chaudhury S, Coulter D, Chewning JH, Joyce M, Savaşan S, Pawlowska AB, Megason GC, Mitchell D, Cheerva AC, Lawitschka A, West LJ, Pan B, Al Hamarneh YN, Halevy A, Schultz KR. Benefits and challenges with diagnosing chronic and late acute GVHD in children using the NIH consensus criteria. Blood. 2019 Jul 18;134(3):304-316. doi: 10.1182/blood.2019000216. Epub 2019 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>31043425</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 29, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kirk Schultz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cGvHD</keyword>
  <keyword>HSCT</keyword>
  <keyword>L-aGvHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Graft-versus-Host-Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Late acute Graft-versus-Host Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

