<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04360681</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AS170014-A6</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04360681</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lofexidine Combined With Buprenorphine for Reducing Symptoms of PTSD and OU Relapse in Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lofexidine Combined With Buprenorphine for Reducing Symptoms of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD) and Opioid Use Relapse in Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pharmacotherapies for Alcohol and Substance Abuse Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RTI International</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michael Debakey Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>US WorldMeds LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pharmacotherapies for Alcohol and Substance Abuse Consortium</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of the proposed study is to determine if lofexidine (LFX) as an adjunct
      to buprenorphine (BUP) treatment improves symptoms of both opioid use disorder (OUD) and
      Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Other study objectives are to compare the safety,
      tolerability, and efficacy of BUP treatment alone, to BUP treatment with adjunct LFX, on
      measures of OUD and PTSD in Veterans with both disorders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this clinical trial is to evaluate the efficacy of Lucemyra™ (lofexidine; LFX), an
      alpha-2-adrenergic receptor (α2-AR) agonist, as a medication for the prevention of opiate
      relapse and the alleviation of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) symptoms in
      opiate-dependent veterans.

      Primary Endpoints :

      For OUD:

      Drug-Taking Behavior (% abstinent from illicit opioid use from Week 5 to Week 12 of the
      active treatment phase) is the primary efficacy endpoint for monitoring the effects of
      treatment on OUD, which is measured by both urine drug screen (UDS; opioids are detectable
      for 1-4 days) and timeline follow-back (TLFB) interviews of drug/alcohol use.

      For PTSD:

      The primary efficacy endpoint for monitoring the effects of treatment on PTSD symptoms is
      mean change scores on the PTSD Checklist for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental
      Disorders (DSM-5) (PCL-5), which is recommended by the Department of Veterans Affairs and the
      Department of Defense (VA/DoD) Clinical Practice Guideline as a quantitative measure of a
      patient's PTSD symptoms and response to treatment over time.

      Secondary Endpoints:

      For OUD:

      Drug-Taking Behavior (≥ 80% abstinent between Week 5 to Week 12), treatment duration (days in
      treatment), and scores on the Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS), the Clinical Opiate
      Withdrawal Scale (COWS), and the Opioid Craving Visual Analog Scale (OC-VAS) are secondary
      efficacy endpoints for monitoring the effects of treatment on symptoms on OUD.

      For PTSD:

      The secondary efficacy endpoints for monitoring the effects of treatment on core symptoms of
      PTSD are CAPS-5 change score (between screening and Week 12) and extinction of Fear
      Potentiated Startle (FPS) responses.

      Population:

      120 veteran participants will be recruited from within the Michael E. DeBakey Veterans
      Affairs Medical Center (in Houston, Texas) (MEDVAMC). The study population will consist of
      veterans diagnosed with OUD and PTSD who are seeking treatment.

      Phase:

      This is a Phase 2 randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-site, parallel groups,
      12-week treatment study

      Duration:

      Enrollment period of 24 months. Participant duration is 18 weeks (consisting of 4 weeks
      screening, a 12-week treatment period, and a 2-week follow-up).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 28, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a Phase 2 randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, single-site, parallel groups, 12-week treatment study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>To minimize bias, all participants will be screened for assurance that they meet study eligibility criteria. A placebo drug will be employed as the comparison group to active study drug and the study will be conducted in a double-blinded fashion in that both the participants and the site investigators and staff interacting with participants and assessing study outcomes will be blinded to treatment assignment. The only individuals at the site with assess to treatment assignment information will be the research pharmacists.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Use</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Drug-Taking Behavior (% abstinent from illicit opioid use from Week 5 to Week 12 of the active treatment phase) is the primary efficacy endpoint for monitoring the effects of treatment on OUD, which is measured by both urine drug screen (UDS; opioids are detectable for 1-4 days) and timeline follow-back (TLFB) interviews of drug/alcohol use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Symptoms (Checklist)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary efficacy endpoint for monitoring the effects of treatment on PTSD symptoms is mean change scores on the PTSD Checklist for DSM-5 (PCL-5), which is recommended by the Department of Veterans Affairs and the Department of Defense (VA/DoD) Clinical Practice Guideline as a quantitative measure of a patient's PTSD symptoms and response to treatment over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Withdrawal</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Scores on opiate withdrawal scales, including the Subjective Opiate Withdrawal Scale (SOWS) and the Clinical Opiate Withdrawal Scale (COWS), are secondary efficacy endpoints. A lower total SOWS score (range: 0-64) indicates a more favorable clinical outcome. A COWS score of 5 to 12 is considered mild, 13 to 24 is moderate, 25 to 36 is moderately severe, and a score exceeding 36 is considered severe withdrawal. These scales are completed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PTSD Symptoms (Fear-Potentiated Startle Testing)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Fear-Potentiated Startle (FPS) is another he secondary efficacy endpoint for monitoring the effects of treatment on core symptoms of PTSD is extinction of FPS responses. Several groups have shown that Veterans and Marines with PTSD symptoms exhibit increased conditioned fear responding (i.e., FPS responses), reduced extinction learning and reduced safety signal learning in FPS tasks. Hence, veterans will complete FPS acquisition and extinction on day 1, acquisition and extinction again on day 80, and recall on day 81.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Opioid-use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lofexidine (LFX)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LFX starting dosage is two 0.2 mg LFX tablet taken orally 2 times daily (i.e., 0.8 mg/day). At study visit 2 (Day 3), the dosage is increased to 1.2mg/day (3 tablets, BID). At visit 3 (Day 5), the dose is increased to the target dose of 1.6mg/day (4 tablets, BID). Participants enter the flexible dosing period at visit 4, at which point the LFX dose can be maintained at 1.6 mg/day or decreased to 1.2 mg/day based on symptoms and the clinical judgement of the investigator. The flexible dosing period extends through to visit 6, however, doses will be adjusted during the study as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (PLB)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A placebo drug will be employed as the comparison group to active study drug.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lofexidine</intervention_name>
    <description>BID dosing, and a max daily dose of 1.6 mg/day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lofexidine (LFX)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LFX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo (PLB)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLB</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female, 18 to 65 years of age, capable of reading and understanding English,
             and able to provide written informed consent (i.e. no persons who are imprisoned, of
             minor age, diagnosed with dementia, diagnosed with a terminal illness, or who
             otherwise require a surrogate to provide informed consent)

          -  Be on a stable dose of BUP maintenance therapy for at least 7 days at the same
             maintenance dose.

          -  Veterans who are not currently on a stable dose of BUP maintenance therapy will be
             referred to the Substance Dependence treatment Program at the MEDVAMC and invited to
             screen for this study once BUP treatment is stable.

          -  Have a positive urine toxicology screen for BUP.

          -  Meet criteria for current PTSD as assessed by the Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale
             for DSM-5 (CAPS-5).

          -  Have hematology and chemistry laboratory tests that are within normal (plus or minus
             10 percent) limits, except liver function test results, which can be 5 times (5x) the
             upper limit of normal.

          -  Have a medical history and physical examination demonstrating no clinically
             significant contraindications for study participation.

          -  Be able to detect 500-2000 Hz tones at 40 decibel (dB) or less (i.e., a hearing test),
             which is to ensure reliability of the FPS data.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        -DSM-5 criteria for substance use disorders (SUDs) other than OUD, nicotine, or cannabis
        (assessed by UDS and the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI)).

        Note that because the MINI assesses for SUDs over the past 12 months, potential
        participants will only be excluded if they both meet DSM-5 criteria for a SUD and have a
        positive UDS for that substance on study day 1. If a participant both meets DSM-5 criteria
        for a SUD and has a positive UDS at the screening visit, they will be informed that to be
        enrolled in the study they must have a negative UDS at their first study visit (i.e., prior
        to being enrolled).

          -  Self-reported use of methadone in the last 14 days.

          -  Be undergoing significant opioid withdrawal, as assessed by the COWS (defined as
             greater than 12 on the COWS).

          -  Increased risk of suicide that necessitates inpatient treatment or warrants therapy
             excluded by the protocol, and/or current suicidal plan, per investigator clinical
             judgement, based on interview and defined on the Columbia Suicidality Severity Rating
             Scale (C-SSRS).

          -  Females of child-bearing potential must be using medically acceptable birth control
             (e.g. oral, implantable, injectable, or transdermal contraceptives; intrauterine
             device; double-barrier method) and not be pregnant OR have plans for pregnancy or
             breastfeeding during the study.

          -  Use of any of the following medications within 30 days prior to enrollment
             (self-report on Prior/Concomitant Medications form):

        Inducers or inhibitors of cytochrome P-450 3A4 (CYP3A4), the main metabolic enzyme of BUP:

        Antiretrovirals or other strong CYP3A4 inhibitors: boceprevir, cobicistat, conivaptan,
        danoprevir and ritonavir, elvitegravir and ritonavir, grapefruit juice, indinavir and
        ritonavir, itraconazole, ketoconazole, lopinavir and ritonavir, paritaprevir and ritonavir
        and ombitasvir and/or dasabuvir, posaconazole, ritonavir, saquinavir and ritonavir,
        telaprevir, tipranavir and ritonavir, troleandomycin, voriconazole, clarithromycin,
        diltiazem, idelalisib, nefazodone, nelfinavir, etc.

        Moderate CYP3A4 inhibitors: aprepitant, cimetidine, ciprofloxacin, clotrimazole,
        crizotinib, cyclosporine, dronedarone, erythromycin, fluconazole, fluvoxamine, imatinib,
        tofisopam, verapamil, etc.

        Anticonvulsants or other strong CYP3A4 inducers: carbamazepine, enzalutamide, mitotane,
        phenytoin, rifampin, St. John's wort, etc.

        Benzodiazepines, barbiturates, or other central nervous system (CNS) depressants

        Adrenergic antihypertensives

        Methadone or any other prescription analgesics, except BUP or BUP/naloxone

        Opioid antagonists such as naltrexone, except naloxone in combination with BUP

        Tricyclic antidepressants, which may reduce the efficacy of imidazoline derivatives

        Drugs that have been associated with QT prolongation, including antiarrhythmics
        (amiodarone, ajmaline, quinidine, disopyramide, procainamide, sotalol, ibutilide,
        dofetilide, etc.)

        Antimicrobials:

        Fluoroquinolones: ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, gatifloxacin, moxifloxacin, etc. Macrolides:
        erythromycin, roxithromycin, azithromycin, clarithromycin, etc. Antifungals: ketoconazole,
        itraconazole, etc.

        Antipsychotics: haloperidol, thioridazine, ziprasidone, clozapine, quetiapine, risperidone,
        olanzapine, etc.

        Drugs that affect the metabolism of LFX:

        Statins: lovastatin, atorvastatin, simvastatin, fluvastatin, pravastatin, rosuvastatin,
        etc.

        Any other medications that might seriously and adversely interact with either LFX or BUP or
        have contraindication(s) to these medications

          -  Clinically significant abnormal ECG (such as second or third-degree heart block,
             corrected QT interval (QTc) greater than or equal to 500 msec, uncontrolled
             arrhythmia), and/or history of a myocardial infarction,

          -  Heart rate less than 55 bpm or symptomatic bradycardia

          -  Systolic blood pressure less than 90 mmHg, and/or diastolic blood pressure less than
             60 mmHg, and/or symptomatic hypotension

          -  Have a history of seizure disorder or severe traumatic brain injury (TBI); per the
             Ohio State TBI assessment.

          -  Self-reported HIV/AIDS, active tuberculosis, and/or active syphilis.

          -  Have significant hepatic, pancreatic (e.g., Type I diabetes), gastrointestinal or
             renal (that would affect absorption, metabolism or excretion of the study drug),
             endocrine, cardiac, neurological, psychiatric, pulmonary, hematologic, or other
             disorders (self-reported during Medical History assessment) that a study clinician
             believes would make study participation unsafe, treatment compliance difficult, or
             otherwise be determined by the PI to not be a good study candidate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher D. Verrico, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas R Kosten, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Adetola Vaughan</last_name>
    <phone>713-794-8912</phone>
    <email>adetola.vaughan@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher D Verrico, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>713-791-1414</phone>
    <phone_ext>26020</phone_ext>
    <email>verrico@bcm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael E. DeBakey Veterans Affairs Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christopher D. Verrico, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>713-791-1414</phone>
      <phone_ext>26020</phone_ext>
      <email>verrico@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Thomas R. Kosten, MD</last_name>
      <phone>713-794-7032</phone>
      <email>kosten@bcm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher D. Verrico, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Opioid Use Disorder (OUD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid Use</keyword>
  <keyword>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Veteran</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lofexidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Congressionally Directed Medical Research Programs (CDMRP) has a policy to share and make available to the public the results and accomplishments of the activities that it funds. The Pharmacotherapies for Alcohol and Substance Abuse (PASA) Consortium plans to share de-identified data after final publication in a government-supported data repository</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

