<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04362280</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00001135</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04362280</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Teens Committed to Health Through Activity, Relationships, and Good Eating</brief_title>
  <acronym>Take CHARGE!</acronym>
  <official_title>Teens Committed to Health Through Activity, Relationships, and Good Eating (Take CHARGE!)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the preliminary efficacy of a school-based weight management program
      for underserved adolescents. The program was designed with a phased treatment structure to
      provide more intensive treatment to participants who do not respond to treatment initially.
      Specifically, this study aims to examine differences in zBMI over time between students who
      do not respond to the first semester and receive more intensive treatment in the second
      semester, responders to first semester who receive more intensive treatment in the second
      semester, non-responders to the first semester who receive usual treatment in the second
      semester, and responders who receive usual treatment in the second semester at the end of the
      second semester, 1 year follow-up, and 2 year follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Childhood obesity has reached epidemic proportions. Schools have been identified as a focal
      point for intervention because children spend almost half their day in school. On average,
      school-based interventions have shown modest short-term improvements in weight outcomes.
      However, considerable individual variation is found within treatments. Current clinical
      guidelines for childhood obesity recommend a staged treatment approach in which every few
      months treatment plans are reevaluated based on an individual's progress toward weight
      outcomes. When an individual doesn't sufficiently progress toward outcome goals, his/her
      treatment is escalated to be more individualized, include more structure, and greater social
      support. This method parallels a treatment paradigm used in other areas of medical treatment
      in which medication type and dose are altered when an individual does not respond to initial
      care. Obesity treatment provided in the school setting does not follow a similar structure of
      care. Despite the recognized variation between individuals, school-based obesity
      interventions are typically evaluated by mean changes in weight outcomes over time. Although
      this is sufficient to evaluate the efficacy of a program, it does not identify individuals
      who are not responsive to treatment. Following clinical best practices, it is likely that
      treatment needs to be escalated for those who do not respond to initial treatment. Currently
      no escalated treatment options, like that provided in clinical settings, are available in
      schools. This is a critical gap given the immense individual variability to treatment
      response and pediatric tracking of BMI. This study will develop and evaluate an escalated
      school-based treatment for individuals resistant to initial treatment, called Take CHARGE!
      (Teens Committed to Health through Activity, Relationships, and Good Eating). Specifically, a
      pilot randomized control trial will A.) examine differences in zBMI between Take CHARGE and a
      treatment as usual condition over an academic school semester among low SES, racial/ethnic
      minority youth resistant to initial treatment, and will B.) determine the proportion of
      students resistant to school-based behavioral obesity treatment. Understanding the proportion
      of children who are resistant to school-based intervention is a critical first step in
      treating this high-risk group of children.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Standardized BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Examine zBMI over the course of the intervention between study arms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Social Network</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>students asked to list their friends in the class</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Carotenoid levels</measure>
    <time_frame>up to two years</time_frame>
    <description>Veggie Meter carotenoid measures</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">392</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity, Childhood</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ReCHARGE</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>intervention intensity is increased through: the creation of family groups, greater involvement of school staff, separate lessons for females, health screeners will be home and families are invited to a nutrition counseling session with a registered dietitian.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PE class as usual which consisted of choice time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ReCHARGE</intervention_name>
    <description>During their PE class, all participants (both arms) participate in an intensive lifestyle intervention with established efficacy among this population for the academic fall semester. The following semester, participants are randomized to different treatment arms. ReCHARGE increases the intensity of treatment provided in the first semester by increasing social support and addressing common barriers youth have to adhering to intervention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ReCHARGE</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAU</intervention_name>
    <description>PE class as usual led by PE teacher.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment as Usual (TAU)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 10-17 years old

          -  Student enrolled in a Physical Education (PE) class at the YES Prep Brays Oak Campus
             during either the 2018-2019 or 2019-2020 school year

          -  provides written parental consent and student assent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is pregnant or becomes pregnant during the study.

          -  Is unable to participate in PE class for more than 5 consecutive school days.

          -  Does not meet all of the inclusion criteria listed above
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig A Johnston, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>YES Prep Brays Oaks</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Craig A Johnston</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

