<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04369222</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COPANA5064</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04369222</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Copenhagen Analgesic Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>COPANA</acronym>
  <official_title>The Copenhagen Analgesic Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fundamental aspects of reproductive function are established in fetal life and there is a
      present increased awareness of the potential effects of fetal exposures on reproductive
      health of offspring. Experimental studies strongly suggest detrimental effects of prenatal
      exposure to mild analgesics such as acetaminophen (e.g. paracetamol) and non-steroidal
      anti-inflammatory drugs, NSAIDs (e.g. ibuprofen and acetylsalicylic acid) on male as well as
      female gonadal development. Declining fertility has become a growing problem in developing
      countries, potentially resulting in severe socioeconomic challenges, and fetal exposure of
      mild analgesics causes part of these alarming observations.This is the first prospective
      human study designed primarily to assess the effect of fetal exposure of mild analgesics on
      male and female reproductive function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fetal gonadal development is essential for adult reproductive health. Experimental studies
      strongly suggest that maternal use of mild analgesics (e.g. paracetamol and non-steroidal
      anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)) during pregnancy affect fetal gonadal development with
      possible severe reproductive repercussions.

      In rodents, paracetamol and NSAIDs administered in therapeutic doses in early and
      mid-pregnancy are endocrine disruptive in the fetus causing reduced prostaglandin synthesis
      and delayed transition from germ cell mitosis to meiosis resulting in fetal germ cell
      apoptosis in both female and male gonads. Female offspring were born with reduced ovarian
      weight and concerning reduction (40-50%) in number of ovarian follicles. Females are born
      with a defined number of follicles that depletes throughout their reproductive lifespan,
      inevitably leading to menopause. Establishment of the primordial follicle pool during fetal
      life is therefore essential for female reproductive health and disruption of this process has
      important and lasting consequences. Although spermatogenesis is not restricted to fetal life,
      essential aspects of male gonadal development are tightly regulated in utero and in rodents
      exposure to mild analgesics causes decreased testosterone production and decreased fertility
      in male offspring.

      In adulthood, exposed animals exhibited longer time to conceive and gave birth to fewer pubs
      per litter compared with controls. Furthermore, studies of rodents suggest that in both males
      and females, adverse reproductive effects are passed on to the next generation indicating
      altered genetic programming, i.e. epigenetic changes.

      Analgesics are sold over the counter and up to 56% of pregnant women use mild analgesics
      during pregnancy. The bioavailability of acetaminophen is high (app. 90%), and the reactive
      metabolite passes freely over the placenta to the fetus.

      Declining fertility has become a growing problem in developing countries, potentially
      resulting in severe socioeconomic challenges.

      The anogenital distance (AGD) is defined as the distance from the anus to genital tubercle
      and is strongly affected by androgens in fetal life resulting in a longer AGD in males than
      in females.

      The AGD has shown to be a sensitive marker of androgen exposure in fetal life, and remains
      the most sensitive parameter when evaluating prenatal exposure to endocrine disruptive
      environmental agents. Therefore, AGD has been identified as an endpoint in the US
      Environmental Protection Agency guidelines for reproductive toxicity studies.

      In humans, use of mild analgesic during the first and second trimester was associated with
      reduced male AGD, congenital cryptorchidism and hypospadias suggestive of insufficient
      androgenic action. In male infants born with hypospadias, the reduction in AGD can be seen as
      early as in the third trimester where fetal AGD is below the fifth percentile compared to
      normative fetal AGD data. Thus, fetal AGD may assist in early detection of insufficient
      androgenic action and genital abnormalities.

      In adult life, consequences can be impaired testosterone production, sub- and infertility as
      well as testis cancer.

      Assessment of reproductive function in early life - minipuberty Minipuberty is a term used to
      describe the transient activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal (HPG) axis during
      infancy in both boys and girls and is a window of opportunity for diagnosis of endocrine
      disorders as well as future reproductive function. Reproductive hormones exert effects on
      target tissue resulting in follicle maturation, growth of breast tissue and thickening of
      uterine endometrium (females) as well as testicular- and penile growth (males). The
      minipuberty is followed by a quiescent period during mid childhood until pubertal
      reactivation of the HPG axis at pubertal onset.

      To date, no prospective human studies have assessed the effect of analgesic exposure on
      reproductive function. The few retrospective studies that are published are hampered by
      recall bias and/or lack of thorough reproductive evaluation, and no studies have in detail
      assessed human female reproductive function after the use of mild analgesics during
      pregnancy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ovarian volume (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Ovarian volumen, measured by abdominal ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ovarian follicle count (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Ovarian follicle count, measured by abdominal ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Serum metabolites Anti Müllarian Hormone (AMH)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Testes volumen (male infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Testes volumen, measured by ultrasound</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (male infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Serum metabolites testosterone, free testosterone.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Length in cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Weight in kilograms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Head circumference (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Head circumference measured with a measurement tape, mm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abdominal circumference (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Abdonimal circumference measured with a measurement tape, mm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height (fathers)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Height in cm, by stadiometer (Holtain Ltd, Crymych, UK) with a precision of 0.1 cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight (fathers)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Weight in kilograms, by digital scale with a precision of 0.1 kg (SECA delta, model 707)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biceps skinfold (father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured above the biceps, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Triceps skinfold(father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured above the triceps, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Flank skinfold (father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured at the flank, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scapula skinfold (father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured below the scapula all on the left side, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biceps skinfold (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured above the biceps, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Triceps skinfold (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured above the triceps, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Flank skinfold (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured at the flank, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Scapula skinfold (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Skinfold measured below the scapula all on the left side, measured in mm (Harpenden skinfold Caliper, British Indicators Ltd, London, UK)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asphyxia, adverse events (newborn)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Asphyxia (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Meconium, adverse events (newborn)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Meconium in amionic fluids (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Partus mode</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Partus mode (vaginal delivery, cesarean section, instrumental delivery) (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth weight (newborn)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Birth weight, grams</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth length (newborn)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Birth length, cm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gestational age (newborn)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within 1 year of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Gestational age at birth, weeks and days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug intake (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient questionnaire postpartum within one year</time_frame>
    <description>Pre- and perinatal drug intake, filled in by mother during the whole prengancy every two weeks online</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy outcome, preeclampsia (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within one year</time_frame>
    <description>Preeclampsia (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy outcome, gestational hypertension (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within one year</time_frame>
    <description>Gestational hypertension (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pregnancy outcome, induction of labor (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrieved from patient files postpartum within one year</time_frame>
    <description>In duction of labor (yes/no)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical history and exposure (parents)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrived from questionnaire within a half year</time_frame>
    <description>General- and reproductive health, the pregnancy, own birth weight, lifestyle, drinking and smoking habits from questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pubertal history (parents)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retrived from questionnaire within a half year</time_frame>
    <description>Pubertal history including age at menarche, pubertal timing with regard to peers, age at menopause of the mother of the parents etc. from questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12 and 2.5 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be drawn from an antecubital vein and will be measured for steroid hormone metabolites and metabolites of reproductive hormones.
Testosterone, androstenedione, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA), dehydroepiandrosterone sulphate (DHEAS), Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, 17-hydroxyprogesterone: in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).
Luteinizing hormone (LH), follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), Sex hormone Binding Globulin (SHBG): Time-resolved immuno- flouroimmunoassay; Delfia, Turko, Finland.
Inhibin B: Specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; Beckman Coulter GenII. Anti- Müllerian hormone (AMH): Specific enzyme immuno-metric assay; Immunotech Beckman Coulter.
INSL3: Time-resolved immuno- flouroimmunoassay. IGF-I and IGFBP-3 will be analyzed using an immunoassay (iSYS, iDS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine sample (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12 and 2.5 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>The urine sample will be collected in a cup and analyzed for:
Steroid hormone metabolites using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).
Glycoprotein hormones, specifically FSH and LH, using immunoassays.
Endocrine disrupting chemicals, specifically phthalates, phenols, perfluorinated compounds and parabens also using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be drawn from an antecubital vein and will be measured for steroid hormone metabolites and metabolites of reproductive hormones:
Testosterone, androstenedione, dehydroepiandrosterone (DHEA), dehydroepiandrosterone sulphate (DHEAS), Estradiol, Estrone, Progesterone, 17-hydroxyprogesterone: in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).
Luteinizing hormone (LH), follicle stimulating hormone (FSH), Sex hormone Binding Globulin (SHBG): Time-resolved immuno- flouroimmunoassay; Delfia, Turko, Finland.
Inhibin B: Specific enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay; Beckman Coulter GenII. Anti- Müllerian hormone (AMH): Specific enzyme immuno-metric assay; Immunotech Beckman Coulter.
INSL3: Time-resolved immuno- flouroimmunoassay. IGF-I and IGFBP-3 will be analyzed using an immunoassay (iSYS, iDS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine sample (father)</measure>
    <time_frame>Gestational week 12</time_frame>
    <description>The urine sample will be collected in a cup and analyzed for:
Steroid hormone metabolites using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).
Glycoprotein hormones, specifically FSH and LH, using immunoassays.
Endocrine disrupting chemicals, specifically phthalates, phenols, perfluorinated compounds and parabens also using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anogenital distance (AGD) (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Distance from anus to genital tubercle, measured in mm with a ruler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anogenital distance (AGD) (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>App. gestational age 30 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Distance from anus to genital tubercle, third trimester ultrasound</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>(estradiol and inhibin B, luteinizing hormone (LH)/follicular stimulating hormone (FSH) ratio)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sample (male infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Serum metabolites of reproductive hormones (AMH, inhibin B levels, ratios of inhibin B/FSH and LH/FSH)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Classification of external genitalia with an external masculinization score (EMS) (male and female infants). EMS provides an objective aggregate score of the extent of masculinization of the external genitalia.</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>It is an individual score with a maximum of 12 points. The following is assessed:
Classification of genital tubercle, measured length with a ruler (mm) &gt;30mm = 3 points, 21-30mm = 2 points, 11-20mm = 1 point,&lt; 10mm = 0 points) Location of gonads, (objectively assessed): labioscrotal = 1,5 points, inguino-scrotal = 1, inguinal = 0,5 points, impalpable = 0 points Site of the urinary meatus (objectively assessed): typical male = 3 points, coronal/glandular = 2,5 points, penile = 2 points, peno-scrotal = 1,5 points, perineal = 0,5 points, typical female = 0 points.
Labia/scrotal fusion (objectively assessed): fused = 3 points, posterior fusion = 1,5 points, unfused = 0 points.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pubertal staging (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Pubertal staging using Tanners classification (including testicular size in boys assessed by Prader's orchidometer)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Penile measurements (male infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Penile measurements with a ruler</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Epigenetic profiling (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>Single determination, 2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Epigenetic variation of loci regulating hormone signalling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine sample (10 mL) (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Steroid hormone metabolites using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).
Glycoprotein hormones, specifically FSH and LH, using immunoassays.
Endocrine disrupting chemicals, specifically phthalates, phenols, perfluorinated compounds and parabens also using in-house mass-spectrometry; Turboflow (LC-MS/MS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical report (mother)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 2 weeks from enrollment in early pregnancy to birth</time_frame>
    <description>Specific medical report on medicine consumption incl. analgesics</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Genetic profiling (male and female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>Single determination, 2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Genotyping of different genetic loci (genetic variation of loci regulating) hormone signalling, e.g. FSHB, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endometrial thickness (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Endometrial thickness, measured by abdominal ultrasound</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uterine volume (female infants)</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 months old</time_frame>
    <description>Uterine volume, measured by abdominal ultrasound</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Gonad Regulating Hormone Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <condition>Analgesic Adverse Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children born from mothers with no consumption of mild analgesics 3 months before or during pregnancy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children born from mothers with consumption of mild analgesics 3 months before or during pregnancy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Observational</intervention_name>
    <description>Maternal consumption of mild analgesics</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exposed</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Acetaminophen</other_name>
    <other_name>Non steroidal antiinflammatory drugs</other_name>
    <other_name>Acetyl salicylic acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      DNA EDTA-Blood Serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This study is a population based prospective cohort study of 600 families (healthy pregnant
        mothers, biological fathers and their healthy male/female offspring.

        Pregnant women, meeting the inclusion criteria, and the fathers-to-be followed at the
        Department of Obstetrics, Rigshospitalet will be invited to participate.

        There are two groups of participants in this study:

          1. Healthy infants recruited specifically for this study

          2. The parents, i.e. the mother and father, of the healthy infants

        The two groups will include the following numbers (approximately) of participants:

          1. 600 healthy infants (based on expected son to daughter ratio of 105 to 100 in Denmark,
             we expect approximately equal distribution of boys and girl).

          2. 600 mothers and 600 fathers of healthy infants
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        Infants:

          -  Singleton pregnancies

          -  Term pregnancy (week 37+0 to 42+0)

        Parents:

          -  Maternal and paternal Caucasian origin

          -  Maternal pre-pregnancy BMI between 18 and 35 kg/m2

        Exclusion criteria:

        Infants:

        • Fetal malformations or chromosomal disorders

        Parents:

          -  Serious maternal illness, including pre-existing maternal diabetes or thyroid gland
             diseases

          -  Gestational diabetes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anders Juul, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Growth and Reproduction, Rigshospitalet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margit B. Fischer, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>0045 28790715</phone>
    <email>mfis0039@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Growth and Reproduction, Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anders Juul, M.D., DMSc</last_name>
      <phone>0045 35455064</phone>
      <email>anders.juul@rh.regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Margit B. Fischer, M.D., PhD.-student</last_name>
      <phone>0045 28790715</phone>
      <email>mfis0039@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anders Juul, M.D., DMSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margit B. Fischer, M.D., PhD.-student</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Casper Hagen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kristian Almstrup, MSc, PhD.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Obstetrics and Section of fetal medicine, Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Damm, M.D., DMSc, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>0045 35451334</phone>
      <email>peter.damm@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Damm, M.D., DMSc, PhD.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karin Sundberg, M.D., DMSc, PhD.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Hanne K. Heegaard, Associated professor, PhD.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rikke N. Møller, Head midwife</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ane L. Rom, Midwife, PhD.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.epa.gov/.</url>
    <description>United States Environmental Protection Agency.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dean A, van den Driesche S, Wang Y, McKinnell C, Macpherson S, Eddie SL, Kinnell H, Hurtado-Gonzalez P, Chambers TJ, Stevenson K, Wolfinger E, Hrabalkova L, Calarrao A, Bayne RA, Hagen CP, Mitchell RT, Anderson RA, Sharpe RM. Analgesic exposure in pregnant rats affects fetal germ cell development with inter-generational reproductive consequences. Sci Rep. 2016 Jan 27;6:19789. doi: 10.1038/srep19789.</citation>
    <PMID>26813099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arendrup FS, Mazaud-Guittot S, Jégou B, Kristensen DM. EDC IMPACT: Is exposure during pregnancy to acetaminophen/paracetamol disrupting female reproductive development? Endocr Connect. 2018 Jan;7(1):149-158. doi: 10.1530/EC-17-0298. Epub 2018 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>29305399</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen DM, Mazaud-Guittot S, Gaudriault P, Lesné L, Serrano T, Main KM, Jégou B. Analgesic use - prevalence, biomonitoring and endocrine and reproductive effects. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2016 Jul;12(7):381-93. doi: 10.1038/nrendo.2016.55. Epub 2016 May 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27150289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kristensen DM, Hass U, Lesné L, Lottrup G, Jacobsen PR, Desdoits-Lethimonier C, Boberg J, Petersen JH, Toppari J, Jensen TK, Brunak S, Skakkebaek NE, Nellemann C, Main KM, Jégou B, Leffers H. Intrauterine exposure to mild analgesics is a risk factor for development of male reproductive disorders in human and rat. Hum Reprod. 2011 Jan;26(1):235-44. doi: 10.1093/humrep/deq323. Epub 2010 Nov 8.</citation>
    <PMID>21059752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holm JB, Mazaud-Guittot S, Danneskiold-Samsøe NB, Chalmey C, Jensen B, Nørregård MM, Hansen CH, Styrishave B, Svingen T, Vinggaard AM, Koch HM, Bowles J, Koopman P, Jégou B, Kristiansen K, Kristensen DM. Intrauterine Exposure to Paracetamol and Aniline Impairs Female Reproductive Development by Reducing Follicle Reserves and Fertility. Toxicol Sci. 2016 Mar;150(1):178-89. doi: 10.1093/toxsci/kfv332. Epub 2016 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>26732887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>BAKER TG. A QUANTITATIVE AND CYTOLOGICAL STUDY OF GERM CELLS IN HUMAN OVARIES. Proc R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 1963 Oct 22;158:417-33.</citation>
    <PMID>14070052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reel JR, Lawton AD, Lamb JC 4th. Reproductive toxicity evaluation of acetaminophen in Swiss CD-1 mice using a continuous breeding protocol. Fundam Appl Toxicol. 1992 Feb;18(2):233-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1601223</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansson HK, Jacobsen PR, Hass U, Svingen T, Vinggaard AM, Isling LK, Axelstad M, Christiansen S, Boberg J. Perinatal exposure to mixtures of endocrine disrupting chemicals reduces female rat follicle reserves and accelerates reproductive aging. Reprod Toxicol. 2016 Jun;61:186-94. doi: 10.1016/j.reprotox.2016.03.045. Epub 2016 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>27049580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ersbøll AS, Hedegaard M, Damm P, Johansen M, Tabor A, Hegaard HK. Changes in the pattern of paracetamol use in the periconception period in a Danish cohort. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 2015 Aug;94(8):898-903. doi: 10.1111/aogs.12667. Epub 2015 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25939806</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lind DV, Main KM, Kyhl HB, Kristensen DM, Toppari J, Andersen HR, Andersen MS, Skakkebæk NE, Jensen TK. Maternal use of mild analgesics during pregnancy associated with reduced anogenital distance in sons: a cohort study of 1027 mother-child pairs. Hum Reprod. 2017 Jan;32(1):223-231. Epub 2016 Nov 16.</citation>
    <PMID>27852690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rebordosa C, Zelop CM, Kogevinas M, Sørensen HT, Olsen J. Use of acetaminophen during pregnancy and risk of preeclampsia, hypertensive and vascular disorders: a birth cohort study. J Matern Fetal Neonatal Med. 2010 May;23(5):371-8. doi: 10.3109/14767050903334877.</citation>
    <PMID>19929241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nitsche JF, Patil AS, Langman LJ, Penn HJ, Derleth D, Watson WJ, Brost BC. Transplacental Passage of Acetaminophen in Term Pregnancy. Am J Perinatol. 2017 May;34(6):541-543. doi: 10.1055/s-0036-1593845. Epub 2016 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>27806383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myrskylä M, Kohler HP, Billari FC. Advances in development reverse fertility declines. Nature. 2009 Aug 6;460(7256):741-3. doi: 10.1038/nature08230.</citation>
    <PMID>19661915</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tromp M, Ravelli AC, Reitsma JB, Bonsel GJ, Mol BW. Increasing maternal age at first pregnancy planning: health outcomes and associated costs. J Epidemiol Community Health. 2011 Dec;65(12):1083-90. doi: 10.1136/jech.2009.095422. Epub 2010 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>20709858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallavan RH Jr, Holson JF, Stump DG, Knapp JF, Reynolds VL. Interpreting the toxicologic significance of alterations in anogenital distance: potential for confounding effects of progeny body weights. Reprod Toxicol. 1999 Sep-Oct;13(5):383-90.</citation>
    <PMID>10560587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juul A, Almstrup K, Andersson AM, Jensen TK, Jørgensen N, Main KM, Rajpert-De Meyts E, Toppari J, Skakkebæk NE. Possible fetal determinants of male infertility. Nat Rev Endocrinol. 2014 Sep;10(9):553-62. doi: 10.1038/nrendo.2014.97. Epub 2014 Jun 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24935122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dean A, Sharpe RM. Clinical review: Anogenital distance or digit length ratio as measures of fetal androgen exposure: relationship to male reproductive development and its disorders. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Jun;98(6):2230-8. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-4057. Epub 2013 Apr 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23569219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leverrier-Penna S, Mitchell RT, Becker E, Lecante L, Ben Maamar M, Homer N, Lavoué V, Kristensen DM, Dejucq-Rainsford N, Jégou B, Mazaud-Guittot S. Ibuprofen is deleterious for the development of first trimester human fetal ovary ex vivo. Hum Reprod. 2018 Mar 1;33(3):482-493. doi: 10.1093/humrep/dex383.</citation>
    <PMID>29408962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snijder CA, Kortenkamp A, Steegers EA, Jaddoe VW, Hofman A, Hass U, Burdorf A. Intrauterine exposure to mild analgesics during pregnancy and the occurrence of cryptorchidism and hypospadia in the offspring: the Generation R Study. Hum Reprod. 2012 Apr;27(4):1191-201. doi: 10.1093/humrep/der474. Epub 2012 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22301570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilboa Y, Perlman S, Kivilevitch Z, Messing B, Achiron R. Prenatal Anogenital Distance Is Shorter in Fetuses With Hypospadias. J Ultrasound Med. 2017 Jan;36(1):175-182. doi: 10.7863/ultra.16.01006. Epub 2016 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27925677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mendiola J, Stahlhut RW, Jørgensen N, Liu F, Swan SH. Shorter anogenital distance predicts poorer semen quality in young men in Rochester, New York. Environ Health Perspect. 2011 Jul;119(7):958-63. doi: 10.1289/ehp.1103421. Epub 2011 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21377950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuiri-Hänninen T, Sankilampi U, Dunkel L. Activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-gonadal axis in infancy: minipuberty. Horm Res Paediatr. 2014;82(2):73-80. doi: 10.1159/000362414. Epub 2014 Jul 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25012863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lanciotti L, Cofini M, Leonardi A, Penta L, Esposito S. Up-To-Date Review About Minipuberty and Overview on Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Gonadal Axis Activation in Fetal and Neonatal Life. Front Endocrinol (Lausanne). 2018 Jul 23;9:410. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2018.00410. eCollection 2018. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30093882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 20, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 5, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anders Juul</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetaminophen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salicylic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salicylates</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents, Non-Steroidal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anti-Inflammatory Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

