<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04360148</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP 19/23</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04360148</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Th Effect of Ketogenic Metabolic Nutritional Pattern on High-frequency Episodic Migraine (EMIKETO)</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMIKETO</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized-controlled Study for Evaluation of Ketogenic Metabolic Nutritional Pattern in Subjects With High-frequency Episodic Migraine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New Penta SRL</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>IRCCS San Raffaele</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New Penta SRL</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aims to investigate the impact of 2 nutritional patterns on high-frequency episodic
      migraine. Subjects enrolled will be randomized in two arms: a)
      very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet (VLCKD), b) hypocaloric balanced non ketogenic-diet (HBD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled trial aims to:

        -  investigate the impact of very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet (VLCKD) compared to
           hypocaloric balanced non ketogenic-diet (HBD) on high-frequency episodic migraine

        -  evaluate the impact of VLCKD or HBD on immune system, with particular regard to
           inflammatory and regulatory T cells

        -  assess aldosterone blood levels before and after VLCKD or HBD treatment The
           randomization will be carry out at the single center using an a proper software.

      All the eligible subjects (please, see the inclusion and exclusion criteria), will be
      randomized in two groups. Both VLCKD or HBD will be undergone to 24 weeks of diet. For VLCKD-
      group, the ketogenic period will be maintained for 8 weeks. In the following four weeks,
      carbohydrates are gradually reintroduced, starting from foods with the lowest glycemic index
      (fruit, dairy products), followed by foods with moderate and high glycemic index (bread,
      pasta and cereals). The goal is to achieve a hypocaloric balanced diet (HBD), as well as the
      controlled group. From the 12th week to the 24 th week, all subjects enrolled will continue
      follow-up with HBD. Periodically, subjects will be monitored through physical examination
      (anthropometric measurements, blood pressure, heart rate, etc.) and laboratory analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 14, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in migraine frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (V2), at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6) and at 24 weeks -the end of follow-up (V7)</time_frame>
    <description>Migraine Disability Assessment Score Questionnaire (MIDAS) is used in order to evaluate how severity migraine affects patient's life. MIDAS score: 0-25</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of migraine episode on daily activities</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (V2), at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6) and at 24 weeks -the end of follow-up (V7)</time_frame>
    <description>Headache Impact Test (HIT-6) is used in order to determine how severely migraine impacts on daily activities.
HIT-6 total score: 36-78</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight loss</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (V2), at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6) and at 24 weeks -the end of follow-up (V7)</time_frame>
    <description>Physical examination will be carried out in each visit. Weight will be detected</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in immune system parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>at the screening (V1),at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6)</time_frame>
    <description>Immune system plays a key role in overweight subjects susceptibility to inflammatory diseases. Lymphocyte subpopulation will be studied before and after VLCKD or HBD through blood tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (V2), at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6)</time_frame>
    <description>Health Survey-36 (SF-36) is used in order to evaluate the impact of migraine on quality of life.
SF-36 score: The SF-36, as described in the name, is a 36-item patient-reported questionnaire that covers eight health domains: physical functioning (10 items), bodily pain (2 items), role limitations due to physical health problems (4 items), role limitations due to personal or emotional problems (4 items), emotional well-being (5 items), social functioning (2 items), energy/fatigue (4 items), and general health perceptions (5 items). Scores for each domain range from 0 to 100, with a higher score defining a more favorable health state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in analgesic consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>On migraine-diary, subjects will reported analgesic consumption during diet-treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of pain</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline (V2), at 8 weeks- the end ok ketogenic period (V5) and at 12 weeks-the end of diet (V6)</time_frame>
    <description>Visual analogue scale (VAS) is used in order to evaluate pain intensity. VAS score: 0-10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">58</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <condition>Ketogenic Dieting</condition>
  <condition>Weight Loss</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Brain Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet (VLCKD) for 12 weeks; hypocaloric-balanced-diet (HBD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypocaloric-balanced-diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hypocaloric-balanced-diet (HBD)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet</intervention_name>
    <description>VLCKD-group will undergone to VLCKD for 8 weeks. VLCKD is based on protein preparations of high biological value. Total daily energy intake is &lt; 800 kcal.Daily carbohydrate intake is lower than 30 g/day, while daily protein intake is approximately 1.2-1.5 g/kg of ideal body weight. The following four weeks, carbohydrates are gradually reintroduced, starting from foods with the lowest glycemic index (fruit, dairy products), followed by foods with moderate and high glycemic index (bread, pasta and cereals). The goal is to achieve a hypocaloric balanced diet (HBD), as well as the controlled group. From the 12th week to the 24 th week, all subjects enrolled will continue follow-up with HBD.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Very-low-calorie-ketogenic-diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hypocaloric-balanced-diet</intervention_name>
    <description>HBD-group will undergone to hypo caloric balanced diet for 24 weeks. Total daily average energy intake is 1500-1600 kcal/day. 30% of total daily energy is composed by lipids (10% MUFA, 10% PUFA, 10% SFA), 55% carbohydrates, while daily protein intake is approximately 0.8-1.5 g /kg of ideal body weight.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hypocaloric-balanced-diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index &gt;27 kg/m2

          -  Migraine onset &lt;50 years with monthly frequency of 8-14 days in the last 3 months

          -  Absence of prophylaxis therapy for migraine in the previous 3 months

          -  Signing of the informed consent

          -  Agreement to follow all study procedures, including follow-up visits

          -  Negative pregnancy test, performed on urine sample

          -  Use of contraceptive method for all participants throughout the duration of the study

          -  Agreement for all study participants not to publish study information

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index&gt; 35 kg / m2;

          -  prophylaxis treatment for migraine in the previous 3 months

          -  antidepressant and neuroleptic drugs treatment during the study (including follow-up)

          -  non-potassium-sparing diuretics treatment during the study (including follow-up)

          -  Use or implantation of stimulators for migraine

          -  Migraine with or without excessive drug use, tension-type headache, cluster headache,
             sporadic or familial hemiplegic migraine, ophthalmoplegic migraine, basic migraine
             defined according to the ICHD-3 beta classification in the previous 3 months

          -  head trauma

          -  psychiatric diseases that can influence adherence to treatment

          -  Type I diabetes mellitus or type II diabetes mellitus treated with insulin therapy

          -  Taking supplements which affect weight

          -  Taking supplements containing sugars in their composition

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Abuse of alcohol

          -  Other neurological, cardiovascular, liver, respiratory, hematologic, autoimmune
             diseases or alterations to laboratory tests that could compromise the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Piero Barbanti, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRCCS San Raffaele Pisana, 00163 Rome-Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS San Raffaele Pisana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00163</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>GBD 2015 Neurological Disorders Collaborator Group. Global, regional, and national burden of neurological disorders during 1990-2015: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2015. Lancet Neurol. 2017 Nov;16(11):877-897. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(17)30299-5. Epub 2017 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28931491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lipton RB, Bigal ME, Diamond M, Freitag F, Reed ML, Stewart WF; AMPP Advisory Group. Migraine prevalence, disease burden, and the need for preventive therapy. Neurology. 2007 Jan 30;68(5):343-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17261680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bigal ME, Lipton RB, Holland PR, Goadsby PJ. Obesity, migraine, and chronic migraine: possible mechanisms of interaction. Neurology. 2007 May 22;68(21):1851-61. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17515549</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Roth J, Nash JM, Wing RR. Migraine and obesity: epidemiology, possible mechanisms and the potential role of weight loss treatment. Obes Rev. 2011 May;12(5):e362-71. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-789X.2010.00791.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20673279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peterlin BL, Sacco S, Bernecker C, Scher AI. Adipokines and Migraine: A Systematic Review. Headache. 2016 Apr;56(4):622-44. doi: 10.1111/head.12788. Epub 2016 Mar 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27012149</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yumuk V, Tsigos C, Fried M, Schindler K, Busetto L, Micic D, Toplak H; Obesity Management Task Force of the European Association for the Study of Obesity. European Guidelines for Obesity Management in Adults. Obes Facts. 2015;8(6):402-24. doi: 10.1159/000442721. Epub 2015 Dec 5. Erratum in: Obes Facts. 2016;9(1):64.</citation>
    <PMID>26641646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basciani S, Costantini D, Contini S, Persichetti A, Watanabe M, Mariani S, Lubrano C, Spera G, Lenzi A, Gnessi L. Safety and efficacy of a multiphase dietetic protocol with meal replacements including a step with very low calorie diet. Endocrine. 2015 Apr;48(3):863-70. doi: 10.1007/s12020-014-0355-2. Epub 2014 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25063307</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellulu MS, Patimah I, Khaza'ai H, Rahmat A, Abed Y. Obesity and inflammation: the linking mechanism and the complications. Arch Med Sci. 2017 Jun;13(4):851-863. doi: 10.5114/aoms.2016.58928. Epub 2016 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28721154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lutas A, Yellen G. The ketogenic diet: metabolic influences on brain excitability and epilepsy. Trends Neurosci. 2013 Jan;36(1):32-40. doi: 10.1016/j.tins.2012.11.005. Epub 2012 Dec 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23228828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klosinski LP, Yao J, Yin F, Fonteh AN, Harrington MG, Christensen TA, Trushina E, Brinton RD. White Matter Lipids as a Ketogenic Fuel Supply in Aging Female Brain: Implications for Alzheimer's Disease. EBioMedicine. 2015 Nov 3;2(12):1888-904. doi: 10.1016/j.ebiom.2015.11.002. eCollection 2015 Dec.</citation>
    <PMID>26844268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paoli A, Bianco A, Damiani E, Bosco G. Ketogenic diet in neuromuscular and neurodegenerative diseases. Biomed Res Int. 2014;2014:474296. doi: 10.1155/2014/474296. Epub 2014 Jul 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25101284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Almeida Rabello Oliveira M, da Rocha Ataíde T, de Oliveira SL, de Melo Lucena AL, de Lira CE, Soares AA, de Almeida CB, Ximenes-da-Silva A. Effects of short-term and long-term treatment with medium- and long-chain triglycerides ketogenic diet on cortical spreading depression in young rats. Neurosci Lett. 2008 Mar 21;434(1):66-70. doi: 10.1016/j.neulet.2008.01.032. Epub 2008 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18281154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bough KJ, Wetherington J, Hassel B, Pare JF, Gawryluk JW, Greene JG, Shaw R, Smith Y, Geiger JD, Dingledine RJ. Mitochondrial biogenesis in the anticonvulsant mechanism of the ketogenic diet. Ann Neurol. 2006 Aug;60(2):223-35.</citation>
    <PMID>16807920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mattson MP, Moehl K, Ghena N, Schmaedick M, Cheng A. Intermittent metabolic switching, neuroplasticity and brain health. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2018 Feb;19(2):63-80. doi: 10.1038/nrn.2017.156. Epub 2018 Jan 11. Review. Erratum in: Nat Rev Neurosci. 2020 Aug;21(8):445.</citation>
    <PMID>29321682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waeber C, Moskowitz MA. Migraine as an inflammatory disorder. Neurology. 2005 May 24;64(10 Suppl 2):S9-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15911785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puchalska P, Crawford PA. Multi-dimensional Roles of Ketone Bodies in Fuel Metabolism, Signaling, and Therapeutics. Cell Metab. 2017 Feb 7;25(2):262-284. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2016.12.022. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28178565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jeong EA, Jeon BT, Shin HJ, Kim N, Lee DH, Kim HJ, Kang SS, Cho GJ, Choi WS, Roh GS. Ketogenic diet-induced peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-γ activation decreases neuroinflammation in the mouse hippocampus after kainic acid-induced seizures. Exp Neurol. 2011 Dec;232(2):195-202. doi: 10.1016/j.expneurol.2011.09.001. Epub 2011 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21939657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang Y, Xu J, Zhang K, Yang W, Li B. The Anticonvulsant Effects of Ketogenic Diet on Epileptic Seizures and Potential Mechanisms. Curr Neuropharmacol. 2018;16(1):66-70. doi: 10.2174/1570159X15666170517153509. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28521671</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim DY, Hao J, Liu R, Turner G, Shi FD, Rho JM. Inflammation-mediated memory dysfunction and effects of a ketogenic diet in a murine model of multiple sclerosis. PLoS One. 2012;7(5):e35476. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0035476. Epub 2012 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22567104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yudkoff M, Daikhin Y, Horyn O, Nissim I, Nissim I. Ketosis and brain handling of glutamate, glutamine, and GABA. Epilepsia. 2008 Nov;49 Suppl 8:73-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1528-1167.2008.01841.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19049594</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Lorenzo C, Currà A, Sirianni G, Coppola G, Bracaglia M, Cardillo A, De Nardis L, Pierelli F. Diet transiently improves migraine in two twin sisters: possible role of ketogenesis? Funct Neurol. 2013 Oct-Dec;28(4):305-8. doi: 10.11138/FNeur/2013.28.4.305.</citation>
    <PMID>24598400</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Lorenzo C, Coppola G, Sirianni G, Di Lorenzo G, Bracaglia M, Di Lenola D, Siracusano A, Rossi P, Pierelli F. Migraine improvement during short lasting ketogenesis: a proof-of-concept study. Eur J Neurol. 2015 Jan;22(1):170-7. doi: 10.1111/ene.12550. Epub 2014 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>25156013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Lorenzo C, Coppola G, Bracaglia M, Di Lenola D, Evangelista M, Sirianni G, Rossi P, Di Lorenzo G, Serrao M, Parisi V, Pierelli F. Cortical functional correlates of responsiveness to short-lasting preventive intervention with ketogenic diet in migraine: a multimodal evoked potentials study. J Headache Pain. 2016;17:58. doi: 10.1186/s10194-016-0650-9. Epub 2016 May 31.</citation>
    <PMID>27245682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fery F, Bourdoux P, Christophe J, Balasse EO. Hormonal and metabolic changes induced by an isocaloric isoproteinic ketogenic diet in healthy subjects. Diabete Metab. 1982 Dec;8(4):299-305.</citation>
    <PMID>6761185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>VLCKD</keyword>
  <keyword>migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>diet</keyword>
  <keyword>weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>ketone bodies</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammatory state</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

