<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04364789</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TT00920US01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04364789</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of TT-00920 in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, First-In-Human, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Single-Ascending-Dose and Multi-Ascending- Dose Study of TT-00920 in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>TransThera Biosciences Co., Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>TransThera Biosciences Co., Ltd</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a first-in-human, phase I clinical study with TT-00920, a novel, potent, and highly
      selective phosphodiesterase 9 inhibitor intended as an oral treatment for heart failure. The
      study contains two parts: SAD and MAD, each with multiple cohorts dosing orally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Part 1: SAD For the SAD part, there will be 5 cohorts (including 1 cohort for food effect
      assessment). Each subjects per cohort will be enrolled and randomized to assess the safety,
      tolerability, and PK profile.Safety, tolerability, and PK data for each cohort will be
      reviewed by the Safety Review Committee (SRC) before the dose escalation in the next cohort.

      * Food Effect (SAD) One of the 5 cohorts (Cohort X) will be crossed-over to the fed condition
      to assess the effect of food. Subjects will receive a TT-00920/placebo single oral regimen on
      Day 1 of each period.

      The dose level in the food effect cohort could be a middle to higher dose level and will be
      decided by the SRC. The dose to be administered in the food effect cohort will not exceed the
      maximum dose tested in the Part 1 SAD study.

      Part 2:MAD MAD may be initiated during dose escalation of SAD based on safety, tolerability,
      and PK data from Part 1 (SAD) cohorts, per the discretion of the SRC.Subjects will receive
      TT-00920 or placebo for 7 consecutive days, assessing multiple PK and safety.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 5, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This study contains two parts: SAD and MAD, each with multiple cohorts dosing orally (SAD: 6 subjects administered with TT-00920 and 2 subjects with placebo; MAD: 8 subjects with TT-00920 and 2 subjects with placebo) . Subjects per cohort will be enrolled and randomized to assess the safety, tolerability, and PK profile.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double (Paticipant, Investigator)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numbers of Treatment Emergent Adverse Events(TEAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Abnormal Laboratory Values</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma drug concentration versus time curve</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of First Occurrence of Cmax （tmax) Time of first Occurance of Cmax（tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal half-life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination rate (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of distribution (Vz/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>PK parameters of TT-00920</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma drug concentration versus time curve</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of first Occurance of Cmax（tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal half-life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination rate (λz)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of distribution (Vz/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (CL/F)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of food on the PK of TT-00920 following an oral dose</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of ethnicity on the PK profile of TT-00920 in healthy Chinese and non-Chinese subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma drug concentration versus time curve</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>the effect of ethnicity on the PK profile of TT-00920 in healthy Chinese and non-Chinese subjects</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolite characterization in plasma and estimation of observed drug-related material in plasma to determine the presence of any metabolite &gt;10%</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Exploratory outcome measures</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP) levels in plasma and urine</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Exploratory outcome measures</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SAD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the SAD part, there will be 5 cohorts (including 1 cohort for food effect assessment).To assess the safety, tolerability, and PK profile. The starting dose will be 50 mg.In each cohort, TT-00920 will be administered to 6 subjects and placebo will be administered to 2 subjects.Safety, tolerability, and PK data for each cohort will be reviewed by the Safety Review Committee (SRC) before the dose escalation in the next cohort.
One of the 5 cohorts (Cohort X) will be crossed-over to the fed condition to assess the effect of food. Subjects will receive a TT-00920/placebo single oral regimen on Day 1 of each period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MAD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>MDA will comprise of at least 3 cohorts. The dose in each cohort will be decided by the SRC, based on safety, tolerability, and PK data from Part 1 and/or any preceding dose cohorts from Part 2.Subjects will receive TT-00920 or placebo for 7 consecutive days, once or twice daily based on the PK profile of Part 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TT-00920</intervention_name>
    <description>Specified dose on Specified days</description>
    <arm_group_label>MAD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SAD</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TT920</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebos</intervention_name>
    <description>Specified dose on Specified days</description>
    <arm_group_label>MAD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SAD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent must be obtained before any assessment is performed.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years and ≤ 55 years, male or female of non-childbearing potential (confirmed
             with follicle stimulating hormone [FSH] test. A bilateral tubal ligation is acceptable
             as long as there is no fertility potential).

               -  For Chinese subjects: subject is of Chinese descent as evidenced by verbal
                  confirmation of familial heritage (a subject has all 4 Chinese grandparents or 2
                  Chinese parents born in mainland China, Hong Kong, or Taiwan).

               -  For non-Chinese subjects (Part 2 only): subjects must be of non-Asian descent, as
                  evidenced by verbal confirmation that all 4 grandparents are non-Asian, and 2
                  parents are non-Asian.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 30 kg/m2, inclusive, and weighs at least 50 kg.

          -  No clinically significant findings in medical examination, including physical
             examination, 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG), clinical laboratory tests and visual
             tests (wearing glasses or contact lens to correct vision is allowed).

          -  Male subject and his female spouse/partner who is of childbearing potential must be
             using highly effective contraception consisting of 2 forms of birth control (at least
             1 of which must be a barrier method) starting at Screening and continuing throughout
             the study period and for 90 days after final study drug administration. Highly
             effective contraception is defined as:

               -  Established use of oral, injected, or implanted hormonal methods of
                  contraception.

               -  Placement of an intrauterine device or intrauterine system.

               -  Barrier methods of contraception: condom with spermicidal foam, gel, film, cream,
                  suppository, or occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal
                  foam, gel, film, cream, or suppository.

          -  Male subjects must not donate sperm starting at Screening,throughout the study period
             and for at least 90 days after final study drug administration.

          -  Able to sign the informed consent and to comply with the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any history of clinically serious disease.

          -  Any active or unstable clinically significant medical condition as judged by the
             Investigator.

          -  Hypersensitivity or allergy to any of the study drugs or drugs of similar chemical
             classes.

          -  Received any investigational drug within 30 days or 5x T1/2 (whichever is longer, if
             known) before the study.

          -  Subject who has undergone major surgery ≤ 2 months before study drug administration.

          -  Impaired cardiac function including clinically significant arrhythmias or clinically
             significant abnormality in clinical test, including but not limited to any of the
             following at Screening and Admission, repeat testing is allowed for verification, at
             the discretion of the Investigator.

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  Subject who has a known history of, or a positive test result for, hepatitis B surface
             antigen (HBsAg), immunoglobulin M (IgM) antibody to hepatitis B core antibody
             (anti-HBc) (IgM anti-HBc), hepatitis C virus antibody (anti-HCV), or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV) types 1 or 2 at Screening.

          -  Subject with a history of severe visual diseases; or visual changes including flushing
             lights, blurry vision, color changes, or other visual changes; or abnormal finding
             with visual tests [color discrimination (Ishihara test) and visual acuity (Snellen
             chart).

          -  Subject who has used prescription or over-the-counter (OTC) medication (other than ≤ 2
             g/day paracetamol [acetaminophen] or ≤ 800 mg/day ibuprofen), vitamins, or herbal
             remedies, within 2 weeks or 5 half-lives (if known) before study drug administration,
             whichever is longer.

          -  Subject who has had a loss of more than 100 mL blood (e.g., a blood donation) within 2
             months before study drug administration, or has received any blood, plasma, or
             platelet transfusions within 3 months before Admission, or plans to donate blood
             during the study or within 3 months after the study.

          -  Subject who has a history of alcohol abuse (defined as an alcohol intake more than 21
             units for males and 14 units for females per week) or a history of drug abuse within
             the 6 months before study drug administration, or a history of substance abuse deemed
             significant by the Investigator. A unit of alcohol is defined as 240 mL of beer, 120
             mL of wine, or 1 single shot of spirits.

          -  Subject who smokes cigarettes or uses other nicotine-containing products (e.g., snuff,
             nicotine patch, nicotine chewing gum, mock cigarettes, or inhalers), and has done so
             in the 3 months prior to Screening.

          -  Subject who has a positive test for alcohol or drugs of abuse (opiates, methadone,
             buprenorphine, methamphetamine, cocaine, cannabinoids, amphetamines, or cotinine) at
             Screening or Admission.

          -  Subject is unable to complete this study for other reasons or the Investigator
             believes that he or she should be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gevorkyan Hakop, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Early Phase Clinical Unit Glendale Adventist Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zejuan Sheng, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>8602586901529</phone>
    <email>sheng_zejuan@transtherabio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Hui Wang</last_name>
    <phone>8602586901159</phone>
    <email>wang_hui@transtherabio.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Early Phase Clinical Unit Glendale Adventist Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gevorkyan Hakop, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicole Huynh</last_name>
      <phone>+1888-228-7425</phone>
      <email>nicole.huynh@parexel.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

