<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04360720</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3992</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04360720</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PercutaNEOus Coronary Intervention folloWed by Monotherapy INstead of Dual Antiplatelet Therapy in the SETting of Acute Coronary Syndromes: The NEO-MINDSET Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEOMINDSET</acronym>
  <official_title>PercutaNEOus Coronary Intervention folloWed by Monotherapy INstead of Dual Antiplatelet Therapy in the SETting of Acute Coronary Syndromes: The NEO-MINDSET Trial A Drug Reduction Study for Patients Wityh Acute Coronary Syndrome in the Unified Health System in Brazil</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phase-3, randomized, multicenter, parallel-group study with blind evaluation of endpoints and
      intention-to-treat analysis.

      The general purpose of the study is evaluate the non-inferiority hypothesis for ischemic
      events and the superiority hypothesis for bleeding events resulting from platelet P2Y12
      receptor inhibitors given as monotherapy in comparison with conventional dual antiplatelet
      therapy in acute coronary syndrome patients treated with percutaneous coronary intervention
      in the context of the Unified Health System in Brazil.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Based on current scientific evidence, acute coronary syndrome (ACS) subjects should be
      treated with dual antiplatelet therapy (DAPT), which consists of the association of
      acetylsalicylic acid (ASA) with an oral antagonist of platelet P2Y12 receptor. Clinical
      trials have shown that DAPT reduces ischemic events, despite of increasing the risk of
      bleeding complications. Because DAPT has a positive net effect, such an approach is currently
      recommended by international guidelines and recognized as the therapy of choice for ACS
      subjects. It is known that the ASA dose is directly proportional to the bleeding risk.
      However, so far, all new antiplatelet drugs have been tested and used in association with ASA
      for a varying period of time. This study is carried out in such context and intends to
      evaluate the clinical performance of new inhibitors of platelet P2Y12 receptor given solely,
      as monotherapy, to acute coronary syndrome patients, to test the hypothesis that an
      antithrombotic monotherapy with such agents (i.e., ASA withdrawal) sustains efficacy by
      preventing ischemic complications while reducing the bleeding potential of this drug dosage
      regimens. It is a Phase-3, randomized, multicenter, parallel-group study with blind
      evaluation of endpoints and intention-to-treat analysis. Subjects with acute coronary
      syndrome treated with a successful percutaneous coronary intervention will be enrolled. The
      general purpose of the study is to test the non-inferiority hypothesis for ischemic events
      and the superiority hypothesis for bleeding events resulting from platelet P2Y12 receptor
      inhibitors given as monotherapy in comparison with conventional dual antiplatelet therapy in
      the context of the Unified Health System in Brazil.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 23, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite endpoint of all-cause mortality, cerebrovascular accident, myocardial infarction or urgent target vessel revascularization.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Co-Primary Efficacy Endpoint (non-inferiority hypothesis)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BARC type-2, -3 or -5 bleeding event</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Co-Primary Safety Endpoint (superiority hypothesis)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total of deaths, and cardiac and non-cardiac deaths</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total of deaths, and cardiac and non-cardiac deaths</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sudden death</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Sudden death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebrovascular accident</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cerebrovascular accident</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial Infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Myocardial Infarction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stent thrombosis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Stent thrombosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-scheduled invasive coronary treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Non-scheduled invasive coronary treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BARC 1-5 type bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>BARC 1-5 type bleeding</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite net adverse event (occurrence of co-primary efficacy endpoint or co-primary safety endpoint)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Composite net adverse event (occurrence of co-primary efficacy endpoint or co-primary safety endpoint)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cost-effectiveness ratio</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3400</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAPT-Dual antiplatelet therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to DAPT Control Group will be categorized as high risk of bleeding (see above) and treated with a regimen of ASA combined with ticagrelor for at least 6 months, and after such period ticagrelor may be discontinued (ASA will be continued) at the discretion of the local investigator.
Subjects randomized to DAPT Control Group who are not categorized as high risk of bleeding (see above) will be treated with a regimen of ASA combined with prasugrel until the end of the study, at Month 12.
ASA (100 mg/day) + ticagrelor (90 mg twice daily)(pts at high risk of bleeding) Or ASA + prasugrel (10 mg once daily)(pts at no high risk of bleeding)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Antiplatelet Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group will have ASA discontinued immediately after randomization.
Subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group who are categorized as high risk of bleeding (see above) will be treated with ticagrelor alone until the end of the study, at Month 12. Subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group who are not categorized as high risk of bleeding (see above) will be treated with prasugrel alone until the end of the study, at Month 12.
Ticagrelor alone (90 mg twice daily)(pts at high risk of bleeding) Or Prasugrel alone (10 mg once daily)(pts at no high risk of bleeding)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antiplatelet Monotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group will have ASA discontinued immediately after randomization.
Subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group who are categorized as high risk of bleeding will be treated with ticagrelor alone until the end of the study, at Month 12. Subjects randomized to Monotherapy Group who are not categorized as high risk of bleeding will be treated with prasugrel alone until the end of the study, at Month 12.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Antiplatelet Monotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subjects must meet ALL the criteria below:

          1. Age &gt;=18 years;

          2. Clinical presentation compatible with acute coronary syndrome with onset &lt; 24 hours
             before admission (see definitions in Appendix);

          3. Successful percutaneous coronary intervention(s) of all target lesions (culprit and
             non-culprit) with new-generation drug-eluting stents;

          4. Length of stay in hospital at randomization &lt;96 hours; Subjects will be informed about
             the nature of the study and must agree to comply and give an informed consent in
             writing using a form approved in advance by the local Ethics Committee.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects meeting ANY of the following criteria will be excluded:

          1. Acute coronary syndrome on index admission treated in a conservative way or by
             unsuccessful percutaneous intervention or surgically;

          2. &quot;Bleeding Risk&quot; assessment not assessible or incomplete (See Appendix);

          3. Presence of residual lesions which are likely to require future treatment in the next
             12 months;

          4. Fibrinolytic therapy &lt; 24 hour before randomization;

          5. Need of oral anticoagulation with warfarin or new anticoagulants;

          6. Chronic bleeding diathesis;

          7. Active or recent major bleeding (in-hospital);

          8. Prior intracranial hemorrhage;

          9. Ischemic cerebrovascular accident &lt; 30 days;

         10. Presence of brain arteriovenous malformation;

         11. Index event of non-atherothrombotic etiology (i.e., stent thrombosis, coronary
             embolism, spontaneous coronary artery dissection, myocardial ischemia due to
             supply/demand imbalance);

         12. Potential or scheduled cardiac or non-cardiac surgery in the next 12 months;

         13. Platelet count &lt; 100,000 cells/mm3 or &gt; 700,000 cells/mm3;

         14. Total WBC count &lt; 3,000 cells/mm3;

         15. Suspected or documented active liver disease (including laboratory evidence of
             hepatitis B or C);

         16. Receiver of heart transplant;

         17. Known allergies or intolerance of ASA, clopidogrel, ticlopidine, ticagrelor,
             prasugrel, heparin or antiproliferative agents from the limus-family of drugs;

         18. Subject with life expectation lower than 1 year;

         19. Any significant medical condition that, in the investigator's opinion, could interfere
             with the ideal participation of the subject in the study;

         20. Participation in other study in the past 12 months, unless a direct benefit to the
             subject can be expected.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pedro A Lemos, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pedro A Lemos, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+55 (11) 98317-5000</phone>
    <email>pedro.lemos@einstein.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Marcelo Franken, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+55 (11) 99277-3509</phone>
    <email>marcelo.franken@einstein.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Israelita Albert Einstein</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <zip>05652- 900</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pedro A Lemos, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+55 (11) 2151-0449</phone>
      <email>pedro.lemos@einstein.br</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcelo Franken, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valgimigli M, Bueno H, Byrne RA, Collet JP, Costa F, Jeppsson A, Jüni P, Kastrati A, Kolh P, Mauri L, Montalescot G, Neumann FJ, Petricevic M, Roffi M, Steg PG, Windecker S, Zamorano JL, Levine GN; ESC Scientific Document Group; ESC Committee for Practice Guidelines (CPG); ESC National Cardiac Societies. 2017 ESC focused update on dual antiplatelet therapy in coronary artery disease developed in collaboration with EACTS: The Task Force for dual antiplatelet therapy in coronary artery disease of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and of the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS). Eur Heart J. 2018 Jan 14;39(3):213-260. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehx419.</citation>
    <PMID>28886622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montalescot G, Wiviott SD, Braunwald E, Murphy SA, Gibson CM, McCabe CH, Antman EM; TRITON-TIMI 38 investigators. Prasugrel compared with clopidogrel in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention for ST-elevation myocardial infarction (TRITON-TIMI 38): double-blind, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2009 Feb 28;373(9665):723-31. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)60441-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19249633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallentin L, Becker RC, Budaj A, Cannon CP, Emanuelsson H, Held C, Horrow J, Husted S, James S, Katus H, Mahaffey KW, Scirica BM, Skene A, Steg PG, Storey RF, Harrington RA; PLATO Investigators, Freij A, Thorsén M. Ticagrelor versus clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromes. N Engl J Med. 2009 Sep 10;361(11):1045-57. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0904327. Epub 2009 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19717846</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feres F, Costa RA, Siqueira D, Costa JR Jr, Chamié D, Staico R, Chaves ÁJ, Abizaid A, Marin-Neto JA, Rassi A Jr, Botelho R, Alves CMR, Saad JA, Mangione JA, Lemos PA, Quadros AS, Queiroga MAC, Cantarelli MJC, Figueira HR. DIRETRIZ DA SOCIEDADE BRASILEIRA DE CARDIOLOGIA E DA SOCIEDADE BRASILEIRA DE HEMODINÂMICA E CARDIOLOGIA INTERVENCIONISTA SOBRE INTERVENÇÃO CORONÁRIA PERCUTÂNEA. Arq Bras Cardiol. 2017 Jun;109(1 Suppl 1):1-81. doi: 10.5935/abc.20170111. Review. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>28792984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serebruany VL, Steinhubl SR, Berger PB, Malinin AI, Baggish JS, Bhatt DL, Topol EJ. Analysis of risk of bleeding complications after different doses of aspirin in 192,036 patients enrolled in 31 randomized controlled trials. Am J Cardiol. 2005 May 15;95(10):1218-22.</citation>
    <PMID>15877994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xian Y, Wang TY, McCoy LA, Effron MB, Henry TD, Bach RG, Zettler ME, Baker BA, Fonarow GC, Peterson ED. Association of Discharge Aspirin Dose With Outcomes After Acute Myocardial Infarction: Insights From the Treatment with ADP Receptor Inhibitors: Longitudinal Assessment of Treatment Patterns and Events after Acute Coronary Syndrome (TRANSLATE-ACS) Study. Circulation. 2015 Jul 21;132(3):174-81. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.114.014992. Epub 2015 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>25995313</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahaffey KW, Wojdyla DM, Carroll K, Becker RC, Storey RF, Angiolillo DJ, Held C, Cannon CP, James S, Pieper KS, Horrow J, Harrington RA, Wallentin L; PLATO Investigators. Ticagrelor compared with clopidogrel by geographic region in the Platelet Inhibition and Patient Outcomes (PLATO) trial. Circulation. 2011 Aug 2;124(5):544-54. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.111.047498. Epub 2011 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21709065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colombo A, Hall P, Nakamura S, Almagor Y, Maiello L, Martini G, Gaglione A, Goldberg SL, Tobis JM. Intracoronary stenting without anticoagulation accomplished with intravascular ultrasound guidance. Circulation. 1995 Mar 15;91(6):1676-88.</citation>
    <PMID>7882474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vranckx P, Valgimigli M, Jüni P, Hamm C, Steg PG, Heg D, van Es GA, McFadden EP, Onuma Y, van Meijeren C, Chichareon P, Benit E, Möllmann H, Janssens L, Ferrario M, Moschovitis A, Zurakowski A, Dominici M, Van Geuns RJ, Huber K, Slagboom T, Serruys PW, Windecker S; GLOBAL LEADERS Investigators. Ticagrelor plus aspirin for 1 month, followed by ticagrelor monotherapy for 23 months vs aspirin plus clopidogrel or ticagrelor for 12 months, followed by aspirin monotherapy for 12 months after implantation of a drug-eluting stent: a multicentre, open-label, randomised superiority trial. Lancet. 2018 Sep 15;392(10151):940-949. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(18)31858-0. Epub 2018 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>30166073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kogame N, Modolo R, Tomaniak M, Cavalcante R, de Martino F, Tinoco J, Ribeiro EE, Mehran R, Campos CM, Onuma Y, Lemos PA, Serruys PW; Collaborators. Prasugrel monotherapy after PCI with the SYNERGY stent in patients with chronic stable angina or stabilised acute coronary syndromes: rationale and design of the ASET pilot study. EuroIntervention. 2019 Aug 9;15(6):e547-e550. doi: 10.4244/EIJ-D-19-00131.</citation>
    <PMID>31012851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehran R, Rao SV, Bhatt DL, Gibson CM, Caixeta A, Eikelboom J, Kaul S, Wiviott SD, Menon V, Nikolsky E, Serebruany V, Valgimigli M, Vranckx P, Taggart D, Sabik JF, Cutlip DE, Krucoff MW, Ohman EM, Steg PG, White H. Standardized bleeding definitions for cardiovascular clinical trials: a consensus report from the Bleeding Academic Research Consortium. Circulation. 2011 Jun 14;123(23):2736-47. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.009449.</citation>
    <PMID>21670242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valgimigli M, Garcia-Garcia HM, Vrijens B, Vranckx P, McFadden EP, Costa F, Pieper K, Vock DM, Zhang M, Van Es GA, Tricoci P, Baber U, Steg G, Montalescot G, Angiolillo DJ, Serruys PW, Farb A, Windecker S, Kastrati A, Colombo A, Feres F, Jüni P, Stone GW, Bhatt DL, Mehran R, Tijssen JGP. Standardized classification and framework for reporting, interpreting, and analysing medication non-adherence in cardiovascular clinical trials: a consensus report from the Non-adherence Academic Research Consortium (NARC). Eur Heart J. 2019 Jul 1;40(25):2070-2085. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehy377. Erratum in: Eur Heart J. 2019 Sep 1;40(33):2774.</citation>
    <PMID>29992264</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Myles PS, Smith JA, Forbes A, Silbert B, Jayarajah M, Painter T, Cooper DJ, Marasco S, McNeil J, Bussières JS, Wallace S; ATACAS Investigators of the ANZCA Clinical Trials Network. Stopping vs. Continuing Aspirin before Coronary Artery Surgery. N Engl J Med. 2016 Feb 25;374(8):728-37. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1507688.</citation>
    <PMID>26933848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valgimigli M, Frigoli E, Leonardi S, Rothenbühler M, Gagnor A, Calabrò P, Garducci S, Rubartelli P, Briguori C, Andò G, Repetto A, Limbruno U, Garbo R, Sganzerla P, Russo F, Lupi A, Cortese B, Ausiello A, Ierna S, Esposito G, Presbitero P, Santarelli A, Sardella G, Varbella F, Tresoldi S, de Cesare N, Rigattieri S, Zingarelli A, Tosi P, van 't Hof A, Boccuzzi G, Omerovic E, Sabaté M, Heg D, Jüni P, Vranckx P; MATRIX Investigators. Bivalirudin or Unfractionated Heparin in Acute Coronary Syndromes. N Engl J Med. 2015 Sep 10;373(11):997-1009. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1507854. Epub 2015 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26324049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thygesen K, Alpert JS, Jaffe AS, Simoons ML, Chaitman BR, White HD; Writing Group on the Joint ESC/ACCF/AHA/WHF Task Force for the Universal Definition of Myocardial Infarction, Thygesen K, Alpert JS, White HD, Jaffe AS, Katus HA, Apple FS, Lindahl B, Morrow DA, Chaitman BA, Clemmensen PM, Johanson P, Hod H, Underwood R, Bax JJ, Bonow RO, Pinto F, Gibbons RJ, Fox KA, Atar D, Newby LK, Galvani M, Hamm CW, Uretsky BF, Steg PG, Wijns W, Bassand JP, Menasché P, Ravkilde J, Ohman EM, Antman EM, Wallentin LC, Armstrong PW, Simoons ML, Januzzi JL, Nieminen MS, Gheorghiade M, Filippatos G, Luepker RV, Fortmann SP, Rosamond WD, Levy D, Wood D, Smith SC, Hu D, Lopez-Sendon JL, Robertson RM, Weaver D, Tendera M, Bove AA, Parkhomenko AN, Vasilieva EJ, Mendis S; ESC Committee for Practice Guidelines (CPG). Third universal definition of myocardial infarction. Eur Heart J. 2012 Oct;33(20):2551-67. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs184. Epub 2012 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22922414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garcia-Garcia HM, McFadden EP, Farb A, Mehran R, Stone GW, Spertus J, Onuma Y, Morel MA, van Es GA, Zuckerman B, Fearon WF, Taggart D, Kappetein AP, Krucoff MW, Vranckx P, Windecker S, Cutlip D, Serruys PW; Academic Research Consortium. Standardized End Point Definitions for Coronary Intervention Trials: The Academic Research Consortium-2 Consensus Document. Circulation. 2018 Jun 12;137(24):2635-2650. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.117.029289. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29891620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Urban P, Mehran R, Colleran R, Angiolillo DJ, Byrne RA, Capodanno D, Cuisset T, Cutlip D, Eerdmans P, Eikelboom J, Farb A, Gibson CM, Gregson J, Haude M, James SK, Kim HS, Kimura T, Konishi A, Laschinger J, Leon MB, Magee PFA, Mitsutake Y, Mylotte D, Pocock S, Price MJ, Rao SV, Spitzer E, Stockbridge N, Valgimigli M, Varenne O, Windhoevel U, Yeh RW, Krucoff MW, Morice MC. Defining high bleeding risk in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention: a consensus document from the Academic Research Consortium for High Bleeding Risk. Eur Heart J. 2019 Aug 14;40(31):2632-2653. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehz372.</citation>
    <PMID>31116395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lansky AJ, Messé SR, Brickman AM, Dwyer M, Bart van der Worp H, Lazar RM, Pietras CG, Abrams KJ, McFadden E, Petersen NH, Browndyke J, Prendergast B, Ng VG, Cutlip DE, Kapadia S, Krucoff MW, Linke A, Scala Moy C, Schofer J, van Es GA, Virmani R, Popma J, Parides MK, Kodali S, Bilello M, Zivadinov R, Akar J, Furie KL, Gress D, Voros S, Moses J, Greer D, Forrest JK, Holmes D, Kappetein AP, Mack M, Baumbach A. Proposed Standardized Neurological Endpoints for Cardiovascular Clinical Trials: An Academic Research Consortium Initiative. Eur Heart J. 2018 May 14;39(19):1687-1697. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehx037.</citation>
    <PMID>28171522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frigoli E, Smits P, Vranckx P, Ozaki Y, Tijssen J, Jüni P, Morice MC, Onuma Y, Windecker S, Frenk A, Spaulding C, Chevalier B, Barbato E, Tonino P, Hildick-Smith D, Roffi M, Kornowski R, Schultz C, Lesiak M, Iñiguez A, Colombo A, Alasnag M, Mullasari A, James S, Stankovic G, Ong PJL, Rodriguez AE, Mahfoud F, Bartunek J, Moschovitis A, Laanmets P, Leonardi S, Heg D, Sunnåker M, Valgimigli M. Design and rationale of the Management of High Bleeding Risk Patients Post Bioresorbable Polymer Coated Stent Implantation With an Abbreviated Versus Standard DAPT Regimen (MASTER DAPT) Study. Am Heart J. 2019 Mar;209:97-105. doi: 10.1016/j.ahj.2018.10.009. Epub 2018 Nov 22.</citation>
    <PMID>30703644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 22, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Coronary Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Antithrombotic Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Dual Antiplatelet Therapy with ASA</keyword>
  <keyword>Monotherapy without ASA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

