<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02491177</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-0331</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HD080477-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02491177</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mother and Infant Visit Adherence and Treatment Engagement Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>MOTIVATE!</acronym>
  <official_title>Maximizing Adherence and Retention for Women and Infants in the Context of Option B+</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Alabama at Birmingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kenya Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 2x2 factorial cluster randomized trial of two interventions to improve retention
      and adherence for women and infants on Option B+. The overall goal is to determine which
      intervention (or combination of interventions) maximizes antiretroviral therapy (ART)
      adherence and retention in care in the context of Option B+ and thus improves maternal and
      infant health outcomes.The proposed study will be conducted in rural Nyanza Province, Kenya
      at 20 low-resource primary health care facilities and associated communities supported by
      Family AIDS Care and Education Services (FACES), a President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief
      (PEPFAR)-funded HIV prevention care, and treatment program, ((AIDS) acquired immune
      deficiency syndrome, (HIV) human immunodeficiency virus) . The investigators will assess both
      process and outcome indicators using a 2x2 factorial design, in which equal numbers of
      clusters will be randomized to one of the interventions (community-based mentor mothers or
      theory-based mobile text messages), both interventions, or standard of care. The
      interventions will be added to fully integrated high quality HIV and antenatal, maternal,
      neonatal, and child health (ANC/MNCH) services already offered at these sites.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In order to eliminate new pediatric HIV infections, save maternal lives, and simplify
      antiretroviral therapy (ART) implementation in settings with generalized HIV epidemics,
      current World Health Organization (WHO) guidance recommends lifelong triple ART for all
      pregnant and breastfeeding women (Option B+). However, despite the promise of Option B+ to
      remove logistical barriers and to promote maternal health through life-long ART, this
      strategy brings challenges. Key amongst these challenges are adherence to ART and continuous
      retention in HIV care, especially for women who do not require ART for their own health.
      Barriers to adherence and retention in care for prevention of mother-to-child transmission
      (PMTCT) have been identified at the individual, interpersonal, community, and health facility
      levels; yet specific barriers in the context of Option B+ are not well understood. The
      investigators' study will be conducted at 20 health facilities and associated communities in
      Nyanza Province, Kenya where Mother to Child Transmission (MTCT) rates prior to Option B+
      roll-out remained near 10%, despite the wide availability of PMTCT services. As Option B+ is
      scaled up in Kenya, it is essential to identify effective methods to ensure long-term
      adherence and retention in care for mother-baby pairs, throughout pregnancy, breastfeeding,
      and beyond. Building on the investigating team's prior research experience in this setting,
      the investigators propose to gain understanding of and address potential barriers at the
      individual, community, and health facility levels through formative research with
      HIV-positive pregnant and postpartum women, their male partners, and health care providers.
      This information will be used to refine two proposed interventions that are highly likely to
      maximize ART adherence and retention in care among HIV-infected pregnant women and
      HIV-exposed infants. These interventions will be rigorously tested in rural Kenya, using a
      cluster randomized 2x2 factorial design. The evidence-based interventions to be tested will
      include 1) community Mentor Mothers (cMM) who will provide support for ART adherence and
      retention in care for HIV-positive women in the community and 2) individually tailored,
      theory based mobile phone text messages to help retain women and infants in HIV care. The
      investigators' overall goal is to determine which intervention (or combination of
      interventions) maximizes ART adherence and retention in care in the context of Option B+ and
      thus improves maternal and infant health outcomes. The investigators' primary outcomes will
      include ART adherence at 12 months postpartum and retention in care, measured by a documented
      HIV care visit within 90 days prior to 12 months postpartum. Secondary outcomes will include
      MTCT at 6 weeks, 12 months and 18 months; as well as maternal viral loads and CD4 counts.
      Results from this study will inform the scale-up of Option B+ in Kenya by identifying
      effective interventions and combinations of interventions that can reduce barriers and
      increase facilitators of optimal ART adherence and retention in care with the aims of
      reaching the elimination of mother to child transmission of HIV and significantly improving
      maternal health.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-reported adherence on antiretroviral therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence on antiretroviral therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Viral load&lt;100 copies/ml based on medical records</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence on antiretroviral therapy (infant)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Use of ARVs for the infant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention in care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of women who have an HIV care visit within 90 days at 12 months after the birth</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence on antiretroviral therapy (dried blood spots)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Viral load&lt;100 copies/ml based on dried blood spots</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal CD4 count change</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Change in CD4 count baseline to 6 months after baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal viral load count change</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Change in viral load from baseline to 6 months after baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant retention in care (feeding method)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Infant feeding method</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant retention in care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Retention in care through 12 and 18 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant retention in care (survival status)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Survival status of infant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of intervention services (Number/types of text messages sent)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number/types of text messages sent</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of intervention services (receipt of text messages)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Receipt of text messages</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of intervention services (home visits)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of home visits received</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of intervention services (support groups attended)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of support groups attended.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mother-to-Child-Transmission</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks, 9 months and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Result of infant HIV test at 6 wks, 9,18 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant testing</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks, 9 months and 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Uptake and date of infant testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant enrollment in care</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Infant enrollment in HIV care</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Male partner involvement</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months post-partum</time_frame>
    <description>Composite variable including Y/N response to indicate if male partner attended a health visit with his female partner, encouraged facility delivery, reminded to take HIV medication, reminded to go for HIV care, provided transport money to go to the clinic/dispensary, reminded to give the infant prophylaxis, helped giving the infant prophylaxis medication, collected medication for the woman or infant, encouraged specific infant feeding, and encouraged pediatric HIV testing. These are assessed in the follow-up questionnaires completed at 12 months post-partum.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1338</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cMM and Text Messaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this arm will receive both the community mentor mother and mobile phone text messaging intervention. The community mentor mother intervention will consist of home visits conducted by the community mentor mother who will assist with safe disclosure, support safe infant feeding, promote safer sex and family planning, encourage early infant testing and follow up, and promote ART adherence and return for HIV care visits. The text messaging intervention will entail participants receiving tailored mobile phone text messages at their preferred frequency and in their preferred language.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>cMM Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this arm will receive the community mentor mother intervention only.The community mentor mother intervention will consist of home visits conducted by the community mentor mother who will assist with safe disclosure, support safe infant feeding, promote safer sex and family planning, encourage early infant testing and follow up, and promote ART adherence and return for HIV care visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Text Messaging Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this arm will receive the mobile phone text messaging intervention only. The text messaging intervention will entail participants receiving tailored mobile phone text messages at their preferred frequency and in their preferred language.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neither cMM nor Text Messaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to this arm will receive standard of care with no interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cMM</intervention_name>
    <description>Home visits from community mentor mothers</description>
    <arm_group_label>cMM Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>cMM and Text Messaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text Messaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Text messages received on mobile phone</description>
    <arm_group_label>Text Messaging Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>cMM and Text Messaging</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 years or older,

          -  HIV-infected pregnant women and their HIV-exposed infants pairs,

          -  attends the antenatal care (ANC) clinic at one of the study sites.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 18 years of age,

          -  HIV-infected women not currently pregnant,

          -  not HIV-infected at the time of the first ANC visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Abuogi, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kenya Medical Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nairobi</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 7, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV Transmission</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention of Mother to Child Transmission</keyword>
  <keyword>Linkage to care</keyword>
  <keyword>Retention in care</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Mentor Mothers</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile phone text messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral therapy adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal CD4/viral loads</keyword>
  <keyword>Early infant diagnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Acceptability of interventions</keyword>
  <keyword>Vertical transmission</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

