<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03955887</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BLOT MSD-APJ 2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03955887</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mitochondrial Dysfunction of Alveolar and Circulating Immune Cells During Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome: Impact of Infectious Aggression and Alveolar Stretching as a Result of Mechanical Ventilation.</brief_title>
  <acronym>PNEUMOCHONDRIE</acronym>
  <official_title>Mitochondrial Dysfunction of Alveolar and Circulating Immune Cells During Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome: Impact of Infectious Aggression and Alveolar Stretching as a Result of Mechanical Ventilation.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Dijon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Dijon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Sepsis leads to a deregulated host response that can lead to organ failure. During sepsis,
      experimental and clinical data suggest the occurrence of mitochondrial dysfunctions,
      particularly in circulating muscle and monocytes, which may contribute to organ failure and
      death.

      Lower respiratory infection is the leading cause of death from infectious causes. Mechanical
      ventilation (MV) is required in 20% of cases of bacterial pneumopathy with Streptococcus
      pneumoniae (S.p.) , with mortality reaching 50%. There are then frequently criteria for acute
      respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), combining bilateral lung involvement and marked
      hypoxemia.

      Cyclic stretching of lung cells induced by MV causes sterile inflammation and tissue damage
      (i.e. ventilator-induced lung injury [VILI]), which can cause cellular dysfunction that alter
      the immune response, particularly during ARDS. This is why the application of a so-called
      protective MV is then required. However, this does not prevent about one-third of patients
      from showing signs of alveolar overdistension, as evidenced by an increase in motor pressure
      (MP) (MP≥ 15 cmH2O), associated with an increase in mortality.

      The deleterious effects of MV could be explained by the occurrence of mitochondrial
      abnormalities. Indeed, the cyclic stretching of lung cells leads to dysfunction in the
      respiratory chain and the production of free oxygen radicals (FOS), altering membrane
      permeability. These phenomena could promote VILI, facilitate the translocation of bacteria
      from the lung to the systemic compartment and lead to alterations in immune response.

      In our model of S.p. pneumopathy in rabbits, animals on MV develop more severe lung disorders
      (lack of pulmonary clearance of bacteria, bacterial translocation in the blood, excess
      mortality), compared to animals on spontaneous ventilation (SV). Intracellular pulmonary
      mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) concentrations, a reflection of the mitochondrial pool, are
      significantly decreased in ventilated rabbits compared to SV rabbits and in infected rabbits
      compared to uninfected rabbits. At the same time, the mitochondrial content of circulating
      cells decreased early (H8) in all infected rabbits, but was only restored in rabbits in SV,
      those who survived pneumonia (Blot et al, poster ECCMID 2015, submitted article). These data
      suggest an alteration in the mechanisms that restore mitochondrial homeostasis (mitochondrial
      biogenesis and mitophagy) during the dual infection/MV agression, which may explain the
      observed excess mortality. Other work by our team illustrates the importance of these
      phenomena by showing in a mouse model of polymicrobial infection that inhibition of
      mitophagia in macrophages promotes survival (Patoli et al, in preparation). Human data on
      this subject are non-existent.

      The phenomena of mitochondrial dysfunction nevertheless deserve to be explored in humans
      during the combined MV/pneumopathy aggression in order to understand its possible impact on
      the effectiveness of the host's immune response. In a personalized medicine approach, these
      data would open up prospects for targeted therapies, capable of activating mitochondrial
      biogenesis and/or modulating mitophagia, to prevent organ dysfunction and mortality during
      severe CALs treated with antibiotic therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Active mitochondria content of alveolar macrophages</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 19 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Mechanical Ventilation</condition>
  <condition>Bronchoalveolar Lavage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with severe acute lung disease requiring mechanical ventilation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients receiving routine bronchoalveolar lavage for a pathology not suspected of acute infection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BAL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Recovery of a 10 mL volume of BAL fluid, performed as part of patient care</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venous blood</intervention_name>
    <description>Collection of 3 additional blood tubes (12 ml) during a blood sample taken as part of patient care</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Bronchialveolar lavage fluid (10 mL) Venous blood (12 mL)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients admited in the Intensive Care Unit and the Pneumology Intensive Care Unit of the
        CHU Dijon Bourgogne
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient who has given his non-opposition (or non-opposition obtained from close
             relative of ventilated patients, who will be informed as soon as possible).

          -  Adult patient

          -  Group 1: patient with:

               -  Acute pneumonitis defined by: Signs and acute symptoms of pneumonia (new or
                  worsening within the last 7 days), at least 2 of which are:

                    -  Coughing

                    -  Purulent sputum

                    -  Dyspnea

                    -  Chest pain

                    -  Temperature &lt; 35°C or ≥ 38°C And a new pulmonary radiological infiltrate
                       (x-ray or CT scan on admission)

               -  Not acquired under mechanical ventilation

               -  Complicated from ARDS according to the new Berlin definition, Chest x-ray finding
                  bilateral parenchymal opacities not fully explained by pleural effusions, nodules
                  or atelectasis. Respiratory distress not explained by cardiac dysfunction or
                  overfilling. An echocardiogram will be performed in case of diagnostic
                  uncertainty. PaO2/FiO2 report &lt; 300 and PEP ≥ 5 cmH2O

               -  Requiring the use of MV.

               -  With a diagnostic BAL performed within 72 hours of the start of the MV

          -  Group 2: Patients:

               -  No fever during the last 15 days (reported or measured ≥ 37.8°C).

               -  Not under MV,

               -  Undergoing BAL for a reason other than acute infection (e.g. chronic interstitial
                  syndrome, nodule or lung mass).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient not affiliated to the national health insurance system

          -  Major under judicial protection

          -  Pregnant, parturient or breastfeeding woman

          -  Known primary or secondary immune deficiency (radiotherapy, chemotherapy,
             immunosuppressive therapy or systemic corticosteroid therapy (&gt;10mg/day prednisone
             equivalent for more than 7 days) within 6 months before inclusion, HIV infection,
             primary cellular immune deficiency)

          -  Patients with treatment known to modulate mitochondrial function, biogenesis and/or
             mitophagia (chloroquine, hydroxychloroquine, rapamycin, carbamazepine, resveratrol,
             metformin, sildenafil)

          -  Patients with pulmonary fibrosis or cystic fibrosis known to be associated with
             mitochondrial alterations
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mathieu Blot</last_name>
    <phone>03 80 29 33 05</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>mathieu.blot@chu-dijon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Dijon Bourogne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dijon</city>
        <zip>21000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mathieu BLOT</last_name>
      <phone>03.80.29.33.05</phone>
      <email>mathieu.blot@chu-dijon.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 13, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 14, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aggression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

