<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03959852</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-040</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03959852</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sub-Dissociative Ketamine and Fentanyl to Treat Moderate to Severe Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Combination Study With Sub-Dissociative Ketamine and Fentanyl to Treat Moderate to Severe Pain in the Emergency Department</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mercy Health Ohio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mercy Health Ohio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the potential opioid-sparing effect associated
      with the novel combination of fentanyl and sub-dissociative ketamine in adult patients with
      moderate to severe pain in the emergency department.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pain is a very common complaint in the emergency department (ED). The use of opioids to treat
      moderate to severe pain has increased over the last decade as well as the number of opioid
      related deaths. In 1999 to 2016, more than 630,000 people died from a drug overdose.
      Treatment for acute pain has been assessed in the ED, with review of several different pain
      medications. Sub-dissociative ketamine (SDK) has become a valuable treatment option for acute
      pain and in recent years, has been of increased interest due to the growing concerns
      regarding opioid abuse and opioid shortage in the United States. Sub-dissociative ketamine,
      an NMDA receptor antagonist, has been studied in dose ranges of 1-4.5 mg/kg for dissociative
      sedation, as well as dose ranges of 0.1-0.3 mg/kg to treat pain. The onset of action for an
      IV dose of 2 mg/kg has been studied, with onset usually within 30 seconds after injection and
      anesthetic effect lasting 5-10 minutes. Common side effects include elevated blood pressure,
      diplopia or nystagmus, nausea and vomiting. More rare and more severe side effects in
      dissociative doses include respiratory depression, emergency phenomenon, tonic and clonic
      movements, and anaphylaxis. However, these were rarely, if ever seen, findings in
      sub-dissociative doses. Several studies indicate that SDK is a safe and effective alternative
      to opioids for patients with complaints of moderate to severe pain that provides adequate
      analgesic effect by itself. In particular, several studies have compared SDK versus morphine,
      particularly looking at pain in individuals with abdominal pain, flank pain, low back pain or
      musculoskeletal pain, and acute fractures. SDK has also shown to decrease opioid consumption
      and the need for rescue analgesia. The studies showed that that there was no difference in
      average pain scores, but the amount of morphine required was significantly decreased. SDK has
      proven to be a safe alternative, but the side effects, although short, make it less desirable
      to use. To the investigator's knowledge, there has never been a study focusing on the use of
      combination fentanyl and SDK. Fentanyl, an opioid agonist, has been studied in low dose forms
      of 2 mcg/kg for pain, moderate dose forms of 2-20 mcg/kg for major surgical procedures, and
      high dose forms of 20-50 mcg/kg for orthopedic and open heart surgeries. Onset of action is
      almost immediate when given IV, and maximal effect of the drug may take several minutes. The
      usual duration of action is 30-60 minutes. Common side effects include hypertension,
      hypotension, dizziness, blurred vision, nausea, vomiting and laryngospasm. Serious side
      effects included respiratory depression, apnea, rigidity, bradycardia, serotonin syndrome,
      adrenal insufficiency, and if left untreated could cause cardiac arrest and circulatory
      depression. There have been several combination studies with SDK, but none regarding fentanyl
      and ketamine. In one study, combination SDK and reduced dose hydromorphone produced rapid
      pain relief without significant side effects. Another study indicated that morphine and SDK
      both provided adequate pain relief alone, but combined morphine and SDK required less
      morphine administration, had faster onset of relief, and provided sustained reduction in pain
      intensity for up to 2 hours.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 18, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesia of combination fentanyl and SDK as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</measure>
    <time_frame>ED encounter (less than 24 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Analgesia of combination fentanyl and SDK as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesia of fentanyl as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</measure>
    <time_frame>ED encounter (less than 24 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Analgesia of fentanyl as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Analgesia of ketamine as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</measure>
    <time_frame>ED encounter (less than 24 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Analgesia of katamine as assessed using the pain scale 1-10</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OARRS report</measure>
    <time_frame>ED encounter (less than 24 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>A retrospective review of OARRS report will be performed with each patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid sparing response as assessed by number of times additional rescue doses of fentanyl were required</measure>
    <time_frame>ED encounter (less than 24 hours)</time_frame>
    <description>Opioid sparing response as assessed by number of times additional rescue doses of fentanyl were required</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">334</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-Dissociative Ketamine alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.3 mg/kg of Sub-Dissociative Ketamine IV administered over at least 1 minute</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 mg/kg of Fentanyl IV administered over at least 1 minute</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-dissociative Ketamine and Fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combined dose of 0.15 mg/kg of Sub-dissociative Ketamine and 0.5 mg/kg of Fentanyl IV administered over at least 1 minute</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg/kg of Fentanyl IV administered over at least 1 minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fentanyl alone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fentanyl Citrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl and Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Combined dose of 0.15 mg/kg of Sub-dissociative Ketamine and 0.5 mg/kg of Fentanyl IV administered over at least 1 minute.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-dissociative Ketamine and Fentanyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>0.3 mg/kg of Sub-Dissociative Ketamine IV administered over at least 1 minute</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sub-Dissociative Ketamine alone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ketamine Hydrochloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 - 65 years old

          -  Moderate pain defined as 4-6 out of 10, severe pain defined as ≥ 7 out of 10 as
             defined by the numeric rating pain scale (NRS)

          -  Proficient in reading and understanding English

          -  Are deemed by the attending physician to require opioid therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give consent,

          -  Inability to use the numeric rating scale (NRS) score

          -  Long-term use of opioids, history of chronic pain

          -  Known substance abuse known as excessive use of a drug such as (e.g. alcohol,
             narcotics or cocaine)

          -  Known hypersensitivity to ketamine or fentanyl

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Alcohol intoxication

          -  Depression

          -  Anxiety

          -  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

          -  Asthma

          -  Cirrhosis

          -  On dialysis

          -  Acute ischemic stroke

          -  Heart rate (HR) less &lt; 60 bpm or &gt; 120 bpm

          -  Systolic blood pressure (SBP) &lt; 90 mmHg or &gt; 180 mmHg

          -  Ischemic heart disease

          -  Ketamine prior to arrival

          -  Trauma patients

          -  Sepsis or septic shock

          -  Weight &gt; 100 kg.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Gemmel</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Director of Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda Mason, DO</last_name>
    <phone>3307747142</phone>
    <email>afmason@mercy.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kenneth Shum, DO</last_name>
    <phone>4024304243</phone>
    <email>Kshum2@mercy.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Elizabeth Boardman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boardman</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44512</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda Mason, DO</last_name>
      <phone>330-774-7142</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.cdc.gov/drugoverdose/epidemic/index.html</url>
    <description>(WONDER), W.-r. o. (2017, August 30). Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Retrieved August 18, 2018, from CDC.gov: https://www.cdc.gov/drugoverdose/epidemic/index.html</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/drugshortages/</url>
    <description>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. (2018, October 15). U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Retrieved October 15, 2018, from https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/drugshortages/</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebsgaard S, Mannering A, Zwisler ST. Assessment of acute pain in trauma-A retrospective prehospital evaluation. J Opioid Manag. 2016 Sep/Oct;12(5):347-353. doi: 10.5055/jom.2016.0351.</citation>
    <PMID>27844474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motov SM, Nelson LS. Advanced Concepts and Controversies in Emergency Department Pain Management. Anesthesiol Clin. 2016 Jun;34(2):271-85. doi: 10.1016/j.anclin.2016.01.006. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27208710</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Todd KH. A Review of Current and Emerging Approaches to Pain Management in the Emergency Department. Pain Ther. 2017 Dec;6(2):193-202. doi: 10.1007/s40122-017-0090-5. Epub 2017 Nov 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29127600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowers KJ, McAllister KB, Ray M, Heitz C. Ketamine as an Adjunct to Opioids for Acute Pain in the Emergency Department: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Acad Emerg Med. 2017 Jun;24(6):676-685. doi: 10.1111/acem.13172. Epub 2017 Mar 22.</citation>
    <PMID>28177167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duncan C, Riley B. BET 2: Low-dose ketamine for acute pain in the ED. Emerg Med J. 2016 Dec;33(12):892-893. doi: 10.1136/emermed-2016-206440.2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27864394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jennings PA, Cameron P, Bernard S, Walker T, Jolley D, Fitzgerald M, Masci K. Long-term pain prevalence and health-related quality of life outcomes for patients enrolled in a ketamine versus morphine for prehospital traumatic pain randomised controlled trial. Emerg Med J. 2014 Oct;31(10):840-3. doi: 10.1136/emermed-2013-202862. Epub 2013 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23851034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee EN, Lee JH. The Effects of Low-Dose Ketamine on Acute Pain in an Emergency Setting: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. PLoS One. 2016 Oct 27;11(10):e0165461. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0165461. eCollection 2016. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27788221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller JP, Schauer SG, Ganem VJ, Bebarta VS. Low-dose ketamine vs morphine for acute pain in the ED: a randomized controlled trial. Am J Emerg Med. 2015 Mar;33(3):402-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2014.12.058. Epub 2015 Jan 7.</citation>
    <PMID>25624076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motov S, Rockoff B, Cohen V, Pushkar I, Likourezos A, McKay C, Soleyman-Zomalan E, Homel P, Terentiev V, Fromm C. Intravenous Subdissociative-Dose Ketamine Versus Morphine for Analgesia in the Emergency Department: A Randomized Controlled Trial. Ann Emerg Med. 2015 Sep;66(3):222-229.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2015.03.004. Epub 2015 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>25817884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Motov S, Rosenbaum S, Vilke GM, Nakajima Y. Is There a Role for Intravenous Subdissociative-Dose Ketamine Administered as an Adjunct to Opioids or as a Single Agent for Acute Pain Management in the Emergency Department? J Emerg Med. 2016 Dec;51(6):752-757. doi: 10.1016/j.jemermed.2016.07.087. Epub 2016 Sep 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27693070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pourmand A, Mazer-Amirshahi M, Royall C, Alhawas R, Shesser R. Low dose ketamine use in the emergency department, a new direction in pain management. Am J Emerg Med. 2017 Jun;35(6):918-921. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2017.03.005. Epub 2017 Mar 2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28285863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sin B, Ternas T, Motov SM. The use of subdissociative-dose ketamine for acute pain in the emergency department. Acad Emerg Med. 2015 Mar;22(3):251-7. doi: 10.1111/acem.12604. Epub 2015 Feb 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25716117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abbasi S, Bidi N, Mahshidfar B, Hafezimoghadam P, Rezai M, Mofidi M, Farsi D. Can low-dose of ketamine reduce the need for morphine in renal colic? A double-blind randomized clinical trial. Am J Emerg Med. 2018 Mar;36(3):376-379. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2017.08.026. Epub 2017 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>28821365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahern TL, Herring AA, Miller S, Frazee BW. Low-Dose Ketamine Infusion for Emergency Department Patients with Severe Pain. Pain Med. 2015 Jul;16(7):1402-9. doi: 10.1111/pme.12705. Epub 2015 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>25643741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dickenson AH. NMDA receptor antagonists: interactions with opioids. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 1997 Jan;41(1 Pt 2):112-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9061093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galinski M, Dolveck F, Combes X, Limoges V, Smaïl N, Pommier V, Templier F, Catineau J, Lapostolle F, Adnet F. Management of severe acute pain in emergency settings: ketamine reduces morphine consumption. Am J Emerg Med. 2007 May;25(4):385-90.</citation>
    <PMID>17499654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lilius TO, Jokinen V, Neuvonen MS, Niemi M, Kalso EA, Rauhala PV. Ketamine coadministration attenuates morphine tolerance and leads to increased brain concentrations of both drugs in the rat. Br J Pharmacol. 2015 Jun;172(11):2799-813. doi: 10.1111/bph.12974.</citation>
    <PMID>25297798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiesenfeld-Hallin Z. Combined opioid-NMDA antagonist therapies. What advantages do they offer for the control of pain syndromes? Drugs. 1998 Jan;55(1):1-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9463786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahern TL, Herring AA, Stone MB, Frazee BW. Effective analgesia with low-dose ketamine and reduced dose hydromorphone in ED patients with severe pain. Am J Emerg Med. 2013 May;31(5):847-51. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2013.02.008. Epub 2013 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23602757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmadi O, Isfahani MN, Feizi A. Comparing low-dose intravenous ketamine-midazolam with intravenous morphine with respect to pain control in patients with closed limb fracture. J Res Med Sci. 2014 Jun;19(6):502-8.</citation>
    <PMID>25197290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beaudoin FL, Lin C, Guan W, Merchant RC. Low-dose ketamine improves pain relief in patients receiving intravenous opioids for acute pain in the emergency department: results of a randomized, double-blind, clinical trial. Acad Emerg Med. 2014 Nov;21(11):1193-202. doi: 10.1111/acem.12510.</citation>
    <PMID>25377395</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bossard AE, Guirimand F, Fletcher D, Gaude-Joindreau V, Chauvin M, Bouhassira D. Interaction of a combination of morphine and ketamine on the nociceptive flexion reflex in human volunteers. Pain. 2002 Jul;98(1-2):47-57.</citation>
    <PMID>12098616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jennings PA, Cameron P, Bernard S, Walker T, Jolley D, Fitzgerald M, Masci K. Morphine and ketamine is superior to morphine alone for out-of-hospital trauma analgesia: a randomized controlled trial. Ann Emerg Med. 2012 Jun;59(6):497-503. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2011.11.012. Epub 2012 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22243959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansson P, Kongstad P, Johansson A. The effect of combined treatment with morphine sulphate and low-dose ketamine in a prehospital setting. Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med. 2009 Nov 27;17:61. doi: 10.1186/1757-7241-17-61.</citation>
    <PMID>19943920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Moderate</keyword>
  <keyword>Severe</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

