<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03950791</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>48784</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23DA047473</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03950791</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Session Class to Reduce Opioid Use in Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single Session Pain Catastrophizing Class: Efficacy &amp; Mechanisms for Reducing Opioid Use Among Chronic Pain Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Prescription opioids are one of the most commonly used treatments for chronic pain, despite
      limited evidence of their efficacy and high morbidity and mortality risks. The study aims to
      determine the efficacy of a targeted single-session psychology class in reducing opioid use
      among patients with chronic pain. The information gained from this study has the potential to
      identify patients who achieve a meaningful reduction in opioid use and inform opioid
      reduction strategies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The opioid epidemic is a serious national crisis that affects public health as well as social
      and economic welfare, with increasing and alarming mortality rates in the United States.
      Consequently, there is an urgent need for effective and efficient interventions to address
      opioid use to prevent the risk of opioid misuse and better address it once it is established.
      One of the greatest predictors for increased opioid use among patients with chronic pain is
      pain catastrophizing (PC), defined as persistent negative cognitive and emotional responses
      to actual or anticipated pain. Untreated PC can lead to increased opioid use and facilitate
      the risk for misuse and overuse of medications, particularly when surgery and pharmacologics
      are the focal medical care plan. Despite critical need, there are no targeted interventions
      that efficiently address the key psychological factors that can amplify both pain, need for
      opioids, and increased risk for misuse. This project aims to address this urgent need for
      efficient and effective solutions. A 2-hour targeted, single-session pain catastrophizing
      class (PC-class) has been developed, rooted in cognitive-behavior therapy (CBT) approaches,
      aimed at reducing opioid use by reducing pain catastrophizing in chronic pain. This targeted,
      brief treatment obviates many of the existing barriers and burdens to usual comprehensive
      pain-CBT, such as the time required to attend 8 sessions, insurance coverage, travel costs,
      lack of skilled clinicians, patient attrition, and copayments. The investigators will
      implement a randomized controlled trial comparing the PC-class to a health education control
      class. Aim 1, To determine the efficacy of the PC class in reducing opioid use among patients
      with mixed-etiology pain conditions. Aim 2, To collect daily data that will allow the conduct
      of analyses on the daily experience of catastrophizing and how it relates to opioid use, as
      well as its dynamic response to treatment. The investigators will use this daily data to
      characterize the mechanistic influence of catastrophizing on opioid use both on the
      daily-level and prospectively. Patient outcomes will be longitudinally tracked at 1, 3, 6,
      and 12 months after the intervention session. This project aims to identify patients who
      achieve a meaningful reduction in opioid use, which will enable better characterization of
      treatment responders and refining opioid reduction strategies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 23, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 15, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Opioid Use</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically minimal reduction is defined as &gt;15% reduction in opioid use (MEDD, which is the recommended unit of measurement in studies of opioid use)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Score; measured with Pain Catastrophizing Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pain Catastrophizing Scale is a 13-item measure with a total score ranging from 0-52 with higher scores indicative of more catastrophizing. We aim to obtain &gt;30% reduction in PCS scores after the intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain Catastrophizing Class</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 2-hour class that will be delivered by a clinical psychologist to participant cohorts. Didactic content includes psychoeducation about opioid use, the risk for misuse, and opioid reduction education materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 2-hour in-person informational session about general health education. Participants receive a list of resources in the community.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain Catastrophizing Class</intervention_name>
    <description>A 2-hour class that will be delivered by a clinical psychologist to participant cohorts. Didactic content includes psychoeducation about opioid use, the risk for misuse, and opioid reduction education materials. It will also include mind-body science as it relates to pain and PC. Participants learn how to identify catastrophizing in the moment, and how to self-treat it. During the class, participants acquire skills and develop a plan to apply the learned skills to decrease physiological hyperarousal within the context of PC. Participants also acquire skills that improve the regulation of cognition and emotion, including PC reframing and thought restructuring, and develop a plan for implementing these skills in daily life. Finally, participants develop a plan to use behaviors that modulate attention and counteract helplessness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pain Catastrophizing Class</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Education about improving lifestyle factors to improve participants' overall health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-80 years of age

          -  Diagnosis of chronic non-cancer pain (&gt; 3 months in duration)

          -  Currently using prescription opioids ≥ 20mg morphine equivalent daily dose (MEDD) for
             ≥ 3 months;

          -  Ability and willingness to complete study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Open litigation regarding a medical condition

          -  Inability to provide informed consent and complete study procedures

          -  Active suicidality.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maisa Ziadni, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maisa Ziadni, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3137250615</phone>
    <email>mziadni@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tyler Winslow, BA</last_name>
    <phone>650-721-4016</phone>
    <email>twinslow@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maisa Ziadni</last_name>
      <phone>313-725-0615</phone>
      <email>mziadni@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maisa Ziadni</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Instructor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

