<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03954561</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A10601001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03954561</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Abdominal Compression Administered Early by the Colonoscopist During Water Exchange Colonoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Abdominal Compression Administered Early by the Colonoscopist Shortened Insertion Time of Water Exchange Colonoscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dalin Tzu Chi General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dalin Tzu Chi General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Loop formation is the most frequent cause of cecal intubation failure during colonoscopy. To
      reduce the loop formation, external abdominal pressure is widely used and proved to be
      helpful. Properly applied pressure can also decrease patients discomfort and shorten the
      cecal intubation time.

      The loop formation during water exchange is less severe as compared with during air
      insufflation and can be reduced quite readily. Traditionally an assistant is not asked to
      administer abdominal compression until the endoscopist has struggled for some time and failed
      to reduce the loops by withdrawal. The colonoscopist can administer the abdominal compression
      whenever the scope is not advancing smoothly, probably in the early stage of loop formation.
      We test the hypothesis that colonoscopist administered abdominal compression to remove loops
      in their early stage of formation hastens cecal intubation.

      A total of 120patients will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio (n=60 per group). When the tip of
      the scope doesn't advance or paradoxical movements occur, loop reduction by withdrawal of the
      scope will be implemented. If looping persists, abdominal compression will be applied. In the
      endoscopist-administered abdominal compression (endoscopist) group, the colonoscopist will
      apply the compression with his right hand and counter the pressure by pushing the back of the
      patient with his left forearm with the colonoscope in his left hand. The compression will be
      administered at left lower quadrant when the scope is in the sigmoid colon and at left lower
      quadrant and upper abdomen, respectively, when the scope tip reaches the transverse or
      ascending colon. If the formation of loop cannot be overcome, an assistant will apply the
      abdominal compression instead. In the assistant-administered abdominal compression
      (assistant) group, an endoscopic assistant will apply abdominal compression when a loop is
      formed. The assistant will apply the compression at the left lower quadrant initially, but
      quickly shift to other parts as needed depending on the tip location of colonoscope. If
      manual compressions fail, then the patients' position will be changed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cecal intubation time</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, average 15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>the time when the colonoscope is inserted from the anus to the cecum.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of patients requiring abdominal compression by an assistant</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, average 15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>proportion of patients requiring abdominal compression by an assistant</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Colonic Polyp</condition>
  <condition>Colonic Adenoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>endoscopist group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>endoscopist-administered abdominal compression group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>assistant group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>assistant-administered abdominal compression group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>endoscopist-administered abdominal compression</intervention_name>
    <description>The endoscopist administers abdominal compression when loop formation encountered.</description>
    <arm_group_label>endoscopist group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>assistant-administered abdominal compression</intervention_name>
    <description>A assistant administers abdominal compression when loop formation encountered.</description>
    <arm_group_label>assistant group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In the Buddhist Dalin Tzu Chi Hospital, Buddhist Tzu Chi Medical Foundation, Chiayi,
             Taiwan.

          -  Patients who undergo WE colonoscopy performed by the two endoscopists (YHH and CWT) at
             the endoscopic suite will be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Included patient declined to give consent,

          -  age &lt;20 years old,

          -  age &gt;80 years old,

          -  previous partial colectomy, not completely consumed bowel prep regimen, massive
             ascites, or known colonic obstruction, morbid obesity (BMI ≥ 35).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yu-Hsi Hsieh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Buddhist Dalin Tzu Chi Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Buddhist Dalin Tzu Chi Hospital, Buddhist Tzu Chi Medical Foundation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chia-Yi</city>
        <zip>622</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rex DK, Goodwine BW. Method of colonoscopy in 42 consecutive patients presenting after prior incomplete colonoscopy. Am J Gastroenterol. 2002 May;97(5):1148-51.</citation>
    <PMID>12014719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah SG, Brooker JC, Thapar C, Williams CB, Saunders BP. Patient pain during colonoscopy: an analysis using real-time magnetic endoscope imaging. Endoscopy. 2002 Jun;34(6):435-40.</citation>
    <PMID>12048623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herreros de Tejada A, Giménez-Alvira L, Van den Brule E, Sánchez-Yuste R, Matallanos P, Blázquez E, Calleja JL, Abreu LE. Severe splenic rupture after colorectal endoscopic submucosal dissection. World J Gastroenterol. 2014 Jul 28;20(28):9618-20. doi: 10.3748/wjg.v20.i28.9618.</citation>
    <PMID>25071360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waye JD, Yessayan SA, Lewis BS, Fabry TL. The technique of abdominal pressure in total colonoscopy. Gastrointest Endosc. 1991 Mar-Apr;37(2):147-51.</citation>
    <PMID>2032597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Church JM. Ancillary colonoscope insertion techniques. An evaluation. Surg Endosc. 1993 May-Jun;7(3):191-3.</citation>
    <PMID>8503077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Catalano F, Catanzaro R, Branciforte G, Bentivegna CF, Cipolla R, Brogna A, Sala LO, Migliore G, Paternuosto M. Colonoscopy technique with an external straightener. Gastrointest Endosc. 2000 May;51(5):600-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10805853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsutsumi S, Fukushima H, Kuwano H. Colonoscopy using an abdominal bandage. Hepatogastroenterology. 2007 Oct-Nov;54(79):1983-4.</citation>
    <PMID>18251143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dechêne A, Jochum C, Bechmann LP, Windeck S, Gerken G, Canbay A, Zöpf T. Magnetic endoscopic imaging saves abdominal compression and patient pain in routine colonoscopies. J Dig Dis. 2011 Oct;12(5):364-70. doi: 10.1111/j.1751-2980.2011.00524.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21955429</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsieh YH, Tseng KC, Chou AL. Patient self-administered abdominal pressure to reduce loop formation during minimally sedated colonoscopy. Dig Dis Sci. 2010 May;55(5):1429-33. doi: 10.1007/s10620-009-0876-3. Epub 2009 Jul 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19582577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung FW, Amato A, Ell C, Friedland S, Harker JO, Hsieh YH, Leung JW, Mann SK, Paggi S, Pohl J, Radaelli F, Ramirez FC, Siao-Salera R, Terruzzi V. Water-aided colonoscopy: a systematic review. Gastrointest Endosc. 2012 Sep;76(3):657-66. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2012.04.467. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22898423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsieh YH, Koo M, Leung FW. A patient-blinded randomized, controlled trial comparing air insufflation, water immersion, and water exchange during minimally sedated colonoscopy. Am J Gastroenterol. 2014 Sep;109(9):1390-400. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2014.126. Epub 2014 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24890443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cadoni S, Sanna S, Gallittu P, Argiolas M, Fanari V, Porcedda ML, Erriu M, Leung FW. A randomized, controlled trial comparing real-time insertion pain during colonoscopy confirmed water exchange to be superior to water immersion in enhancing patient comfort. Gastrointest Endosc. 2015 Mar;81(3):557-66. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2014.07.029. Epub 2014 Sep 26. Erratum in: Gastrointest Endosc. 2015 May;81(5):1303.</citation>
    <PMID>25262100</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jia H, Pan Y, Guo X, Zhao L, Wang X, Zhang L, Dong T, Luo H, Ge Z, Liu J, Hao J, Yao P, Zhang Y, Ren H, Zhou W, Guo Y, Zhang W, Chen X, Sun D, Yang X, Kang X, Liu N, Liu Z, Leung F, Wu K, Fan D. Water Exchange Method Significantly Improves Adenoma Detection Rate: A Multicenter, Randomized Controlled Trial. Am J Gastroenterol. 2017 Apr;112(4):568-576. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2016.501. Epub 2016 Dec 6.</citation>
    <PMID>27922025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsieh YH, Tseng CW, Hu CT, Koo M, Leung FW. Prospective multicenter randomized controlled trial comparing adenoma detection rate in colonoscopy using water exchange, water immersion, and air insufflation. Gastrointest Endosc. 2017 Jul;86(1):192-201. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2016.12.005. Epub 2016 Dec 15.</citation>
    <PMID>27988288</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rex DK. Water exchange vs. water immersion during colonoscope insertion. Am J Gastroenterol. 2014 Sep;109(9):1401-3. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2014.235.</citation>
    <PMID>25196871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leung JW, Thai A, Yen A, Ward G, Abramyan O, Lee J, Smith B, Leung F. Magnetic endoscope imaging (ScopeGuide) elucidates the mechanism of action of the pain-alleviating impact of water exchange colonoscopy - attenuation of loop formation. J Interv Gastroenterol. 2012 Jul;2(3):142-146. Epub 2012 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23805397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kudo Se, Lambert R, Allen JI, Fujii H, Fujii T, Kashida H, Matsuda T, Mori M, Saito H, Shimoda T, Tanaka S, Watanabe H, Sung JJ, Feld AD, Inadomi JM, O'Brien MJ, Lieberman DA, Ransohoff DF, Soetikno RM, Triadafilopoulos G, Zauber A, Teixeira CR, Rey JF, Jaramillo E, Rubio CA, Van Gossum A, Jung M, Vieth M, Jass JR, Hurlstone PD. Nonpolypoid neoplastic lesions of the colorectal mucosa. Gastrointest Endosc. 2008 Oct;68(4 Suppl):S3-47. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.07.052. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18805238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>The Paris endoscopic classification of superficial neoplastic lesions: esophagus, stomach, and colon: November 30 to December 1, 2002. Gastrointest Endosc. 2003 Dec;58(6 Suppl):S3-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14652541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai EJ, Calderwood AH, Doros G, Fix OK, Jacobson BC. The Boston bowel preparation scale: a valid and reliable instrument for colonoscopy-oriented research. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Mar;69(3 Pt 2):620-5. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.05.057. Epub 2009 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19136102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dalin Tzu Chi General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yu-Hsi hsieh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief of Gastroenterology Endoscopy Suite</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>cecal intubation time</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Polyps</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

