<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03952429</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPIRA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03952429</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Smartphone Based Intervention for the Prevention of Relapse in Alcohol Dependence</brief_title>
  <acronym>SPIRA</acronym>
  <official_title>SPIRA: Development of a Smartphone Based Intervention for the Prevention of Relapse in Alcohol Dependence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Salus Klinik Lindow</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Cambridge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Salus Klinik Lindow</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The rate of relapse following an inpatient alcohol rehabilitation program has been around 50%
      for a number of years. Offered treatments mainly focus on conscious and controllable aspects
      of behaviour, but research has found that much of the craving in addiction is guided by
      automatic processes, which are for a large part unconscious and poorly controlled by the
      individual. One way to influence these automatic processes is by applying cognitive bias
      modification, a cognitive-behavioural intervention that can be applied by a computer
      application. In alcohol addition, a common cognitive bias is the Alcohol-Approach bias. The
      Anti-Alcohol Training is a form of cognitive bias modification that was developed to reduce
      this approach bias and it has been shown to reduce the rates of relapse by 4-8%. A drawback
      of the training is that patients do not continue this at home after discharge. One way to
      increase accessibility is to offer the training in an app-game form.

      In this study the investigators have developed a smartphone based training app that allows
      patients to more easily use the Anti-Alcohol training at home after discharge. The study aims
      to assess whether use of the app further reduces the alcohol bias and whether it can reduce
      yearly relapse rates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rate of relapse following an inpatient alcohol rehabilitation program has been around 50%
      for a number of years, in spite of many initiatives to try and reduce relapse. One of the
      reasons could be that the offered treatments mainly focus on conscious and controllable
      aspects of behaviour. Recent research has however found that much of the craving in addiction
      is guided by automatic processes, which are for a large part unconscious and poorly
      controlled by the individual. Unsurprisingly, many attempts have therefore been made in
      addition research to reduce these automatic impulsive behaviour and improve the control
      processes.

      One way to influence these automatic processes is by applying cognitive bias modification, a
      cognitive-behavioural intervention that can be applied by a computer application. In alcohol
      addition, a common cognitive bias is the Alcohol-Approach bias, the tendency to automatically
      approach alcohol. The Anti-Alcohol Training is a form of cognitive bias modification that was
      developed to reduce this approach bias. Studies have shows that this training can reduce the
      rates of relapse by 4-8%.

      A drawback of the training is that patients often do not continue this at home after
      discharge, probably due to low motivation. One way to resolve this issue could be to offer
      the training in an App-game form, which would make it more accessible and inviting to
      continue using it after return home.

      In this study the investigators have developed a smartphone based training app that allows
      patients to more easily use the Anti-Alcohol training at home after discharge. The study aims
      to assess whether alcohol dependent patients continue to use this app at home, whether the
      use of the app further reduces the alcohol bias, and finally whether it can reduce yearly
      relapse rates.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a parallel study, participants will be randomised into 2 groups: one will be given the App with cognitive bias modification, whilst the other one will receive the app without the modification</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants will be notified there are 2 versions of the app and they will randomly be assigned to one of the 2 conditions, but will not know which one. Therapists giving the users input on how to use the app do not know in which condition the patient is either. Outcome (relapse rates) are assessed by interns and admin staff of the clinic who are independent from the study. The study investigators do not know the patients and only receive anonymized data on group and outcome variables.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relapse Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months after care</time_frame>
    <description>Relapse rates after leaving inpatient care, assessed through standard clinic follow-ups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>App Usage</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months after leaving care</time_frame>
    <description>Number of times App training has been completed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Craving</measure>
    <time_frame>after 5 training sessions of the app</time_frame>
    <description>Craving for alcohol assessed in app, 5 point likert scale with alcohol images</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alcohol Units consumed</measure>
    <time_frame>after 5 training sessions of the app</time_frame>
    <description>average number of alcohol units consumed, assessed through self-report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months after care, assessed through questions on the app</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first relapse after leaving inpatient care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Abuse</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Cognitive Bias App</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the Anti-Alcohol App with the Active Cognitive Bias modification, as well as participant diaries assessing alcohol consumption and several questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive Cognitive Bias Modification</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the Anti-Alcohol App with the Inactive Cognitive Bias Modification, as well as participant diaries assessing alcohol consumption and several questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti Alcohol App with Active Cognitive Bias</intervention_name>
    <description>The active version includes an active form of cognitive bias modification, i.e. the user has to avoid alcohol stimuli 90% of the time, while they approach soft drinks 90% of the time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Cognitive Bias App</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Inactive Cognitive Bias Modification</intervention_name>
    <description>The control version includes an placebo form of cognitive bias modification, i.e. the users avoid and approach alcohol and softdrink stimuli for an equal number of trials.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive Cognitive Bias Modification</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A diagnosis of Alcohol dependence / Alcohol Use disorder

          -  Taking part in alcohol rehabilitation program in Salus Clinic Lindow or being part of
             a self-help group

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Visual or motor impairments that would affect the use of smartphones
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Prof Johannes Lindemeyer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medizinische Hochschule Brandenburg Theodor Fontane</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prof Johannes Lindenmeyer</last_name>
    <phone>49 3391 39-14210</phone>
    <email>mail@salus-lindow.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nele Peerenboom</last_name>
    <phone>49 3391 39-14210</phone>
    <email>nap42@cam.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>alcohol dependence</keyword>
  <keyword>alcohol abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>withdrawal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymised participant data will be shared with the collaborators at Cambridge University</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Analytic Code</ipd_info_type>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

