<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03952598</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190096</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-C-0096</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03952598</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Studying the Biology of IDH-mutant Gliomas Via Longitudinal Observation of 2-hydroxyglutarate (2-HG) Using MR Spectroscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studying the Biology of IDH-mutant Gliomas Via Longitudinal Observation of 2-Hydroxyglutarate (2-HG) Using MR Spectroscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Glioma is a type of brain cancer. Some of these tumors have gene mutations. These mutations
      can cause a substance called 2-HG to build up in the brain. This makes the tumors more
      aggressive. Researchers want to better understand 2-HG buildup in the brain. They hope this
      can help them design better ways to test for gliomas.

      Objective:

      To monitor the level of 2-HG in the brains of people with gliomas that have mutations in the
      IDH1 or IDH2 genes.

      Eligibility:

      People ages 18 and older with gliomas with mutations in the IDH1 or IDH2 genes

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

      Medical and cancer history

      Physical exam

      Reviews of their symptoms and ability to perform normal activities

      Blood and urine tests

      MRI scan

      Samples of their tumor from a past surgery

      Documentation of their diagnosis and mutation status

      Participants will have an initial evaluation. This will include repeats of screening tests.
      It will also include:

      Neurological exam

      MRS and MRI scans of the brain: Participants will lie on a table that slides into a metal
      cylinder. A coil or soft padding will be placed around their head. They will have a contrast
      agent injected into a vein. Pictures will be taken of the brain.

      Participants will have follow-up visits every 2-6 month for the rest of their life. Visits
      will include scans.

      ...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Glioma is the most common malignant brain tumor. Genes coding for isocitrate
           dehydrogenase (IDH), a metabolic enzyme, are frequently mutated in gliomas, particularly
           lower-grade gliomas (LGGs). IDH mutation causes a unique tumor biology, including the
           accumulation of 2-hydroxyglutarate (2-HG), an oncometabolite, which in turn causes
           genomic hypermethylation and tumorigenesis.

        -  Despite having a better prognosis compared to their IDH WT counterparts, IDH-mutant LGGs
           undergo a slow but unremitting higher-grade transformation (HT) and eventually become
           high grade gliomas (HGGs). A subset of patients with transformed HGGs develop a
           hypermutator phenotype (HMP), possibly related to previous treatment with alkylating
           agents and radiotherapy. The timeline for the development of HT and HMP is unpredictable
           and there is no known way to prevent them from happening, largely due to a lack of
           understanding their biological mechanisms and lack of a non-invasive approach for
           potential early detection.

        -  Proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) of the brain can detect 2-HG in a tumor
           harboring IDH mutation. There has been an increased interest in using quantitative 2-HG
           by MRS as a biomarker for IDH-mutant gliomas. This clinical study will allow a
           longitudinal monitoring of quantitative 2-HG by MRS in patients with IDH-mutant gliomas.
           We hypothesize that a significant increase in 2HG level is correlated with HT and/or
           HMP. The change in 2-HG level in conjunction with evaluation of tumor cellularity and
           other metabolite markers such as choline, creatinine and N-acetyl aspartate (NAA) will
           likely to provide insights into metabolic alterations that may correlate with HT/HMP and
           potentially provide the predictive biomarker for early detection of HT.

      Objective:

      -To monitor the quantitative levels of 2-hydroxyglutarate (2-HG) longitudinally in patients
      with IDH-mutant gliomas via proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (1H-MRS).

      Eligibility:

        -  IDH 1 or 2 mutation confirmed by DNA sequencing.

        -  Age greater than or equal to18 years, KPS greater than or equal to 60%

      Design:

        -  This is prospective observational study. We will recruit at least 250 eligible patients
           in the next 5 years.

        -  The relationship between the occurrence of HT and the changes in 2-HG level using the
           proportional hazard model.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To monitor the quantitative levels of 2-hydroxyglutarate (2-HG) longitudinally in patients with IDH mutant gliomas via proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (1H-MRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the level of 2-HG correlate with the occurrence of higher-grade transformation (HT) and/or development of hypermutator phenotype (HMP) in patients with IDH-mutant gliomas</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">270</enrollment>
  <condition>Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Gliomas</condition>
  <condition>High Grade Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Low Grade Glioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1/Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Monitoring of quantitative levels of 2-hydroxyglutarate (2- HG) via proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy (1H-MRS)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>3T MRI scanner</intervention_name>
    <description>Research proton MRS (lH-MRS)followed by DW-MRI</description>
    <arm_group_label>1/Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed glioma with IDH1 or IDH2 mutation
             confirmed by DNA sequencing.

          -  Patients must have grade II, III or IV glioma.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease.

          -  Age greater than or equal to18 years. Tumor biology of IDH-mutant gliomas are
             different in pediatric tumors. Therefore, children will be excluded from the study.

          -  Karnofsky performance greater than or equal to 60%.

          -  Patients must have normal kidney function as defined below:

               -  creatinine within normal institutional limits OR

               -  creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 mL/min/1.73 m(2) for patients
                  withcreatinine levels above institutional normal (Measured or calculated
                  creatinine clearance (GFR can also be used in place of creatinine or CrCl)).

          -  Ability of subject or Legally Authorized Representative (LAR) to understand and the
             willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects with any coexisting medical or psychiatric condition that is likely to
             interfere with study procedures and/or results (such as allergy to gadolinium
             contrast, metal implants and so on).

          -  Pregnant women are excluded because MRI contrast, planned to be used on this study,
             may be dangerous for the fetus. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for
             adverse events in nursing infants secondary to using of MRI c ntrast, breastfeeding
             should be discontinued for 72 hours following study imaging.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jing Wu, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Matthew R Lindsley, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6534</phone>
    <email>matthew.lindsley@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>888-624-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-C-0096.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 31, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 1, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Higher-Grade Transformation</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarker for Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>High Grade Gliomas</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

