<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03958370</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB17-053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03958370</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of Consumer Activity Monitors in Postoperative Total Arthroplasty Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validation of Consumer Activity Monitors in Postoperative Total Arthroplasty Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Benaroya Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Virginia Mason Hospital/Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Benaroya Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mobilization and rehabilitation are essential components of a successful functional recovery
      following total hip and knee arthroplasties. Currently, we have no good measure of how mobile
      patients are after their surgery. Recent technological advances in personal activity
      monitors, such as the Fitbit, might provide medical providers and patients the opportunity to
      more objectively monitor their postoperative mobility and recovery course. However, these
      consumer activity monitors have yet to be validated in terms of their accuracy and utility
      for monitoring mobility in the immediate postoperative setting in arthroplasty patients. Our
      goal is to validate one of the most popular consumer activity monitors, the Fitbit Zip, in
      the postoperative total joint arthroplasty patient population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Early mobilization following total hip and knee arthroplasty surgeries is important in
      decreasing the risk of complications such as deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolus,
      pneumonia, and urinary retention. It is also generally accepted that early mobilization may
      help prevent late complications such as joint stiffness or arthrofibrosis. Aside from these
      complications, patient satisfaction and length of hospital stay both seem to be correlated
      with early mobilization with poor mobility negatively impacting both outcomes. Therefore, it
      is important for clinicians to ensure that patients are adequately mobilizing in the
      immediate postoperative period to promote a successful recovery after total hip or knee
      arthroplasty.

      Consumer activity monitors are generally manufactured to be used in a relatively healthy,
      ambulatory population. Their accuracy has been validated in multiple studies in healthy
      subjects in a variety controlled settings. Based on these validity studies, it is clear that
      some of these consumer activity monitors have worse accuracy in certain situations, such as
      slower-paced walking or in people using assistive devices for ambulation, such as canes. The
      limitations of these devices in these settings could be problematic for monitoring
      post-arthroplasty patients since all these patients ambulate slowly, with an altered gait,
      and with a walker. No studies to date have looked at the accuracy of consumer activity
      monitors in the immediate postoperative arthroplasty population.

      The consumer activity monitor market is rapidly evolving and changing, so much so that
      monitors used just last year might be obsolete this year. Therefore, rather than examining
      the accuracy of one device versus another, it is more applicable to determine what location
      is most accurate for placement of these monitors to help providers counsel patients on proper
      use postoperatively.

      Our goal for this study is to validate and to determine the best location for placement of
      the Fitbit Zip in the postoperative total joint arthroplasty patient population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of Step Count Obtained from Fitbit</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative day 0-2</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing Fitbit step counts to observer counted steps during physical therapy sessions during inpatient stay</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of Step Count to Distance and Time Ambulated</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative day 0-2</time_frame>
    <description>See if Fitbit counts are more or less accurate depending on distance and time ambulated</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthropathy of Knee</condition>
  <condition>Arthritis Knee</condition>
  <condition>Arthritis, Degenerative</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitbit</intervention_name>
    <description>Fitbit use during physical therapy session</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fitbit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Any person who is over 18 years old, a procedural candidate (having a total arthroplasty
        surgery at Virginia Mason Medical Center), and can understand English sufficiently to
        consent for the study can be included
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  primary unilateral total knee arthroplasty

          -  ASA class I-IV

          -  expected to ambulate with PT on postoperative day 1 or 2

          -  no history of chronic opioid or alcohol use

          -  no history of delirium

          -  ability to read and understand English

          -  patient agreement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patient refusal,

          -  bilateral arthroplasty patients,

          -  patients who are non- ambulatory preoperatively (e.g. wheelchair bound),

          -  patients who are not expected to ambulate with PT either due to intraoperative or
             postoperative complications,

          -  patients with contact precautions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David B Auyong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>206-223-6980</phone>
    <email>David.Auyong@virginiamason.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Mason Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98101</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David B Auyong, MD</last_name>
      <phone>206-223-6980</phone>
      <email>David.Auyong@virginiamason.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David B Auyong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shin-e Lin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fitbit</keyword>
  <keyword>Activity Monitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Step Count</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Knee Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Arthroplasty</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

