<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03958058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TBE-LB observational</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03958058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tick-borne Encephalitis and Possible Borrelial Serology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tick-Borne Encephalitis Virus and Lyme Borreliae Causing Coillness, Coinfection, or Just Coincidence. A Prospective Observational Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ljubljana School of Medicine, Slovenia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In Europe, tick-borne encephalitis (TBE) virus causing TBE is transmitted by the bite of
      Ixodes ricinus tick, which can also transmit Lyme borreliae , the causative agent of Lyme
      borreliosis (LB). Since TBE and LB are both endemic with high incidence rates in Slovenia, we
      should be attentive to the possibility of double infections. Double infections with TBE virus
      and Lyme borreliae were reported to occur rarely even in endemic countries, however reliable
      data on coinfection rates are rather limited. Microbiological diagnosis of TBE virus
      infection is quite straightforward, and there is no specific therapy for TBE available so
      far. This markedly differs from borrelial infection, in which case interpretation of
      serological test results demands more caution, but there is highly efficient antibiotic
      treatment available for LB. This may lead to over prescribing of antibiotics to TBE patients
      with documented borrelial antibodies in serum indicating possible coinfection with Lyme
      borreliae, but missing clinical or microbiological criteria for proven borrelial coinfection.
      Approximately 10% of patients who had been treated appropriately for LB and about one third
      of patients after TBE report nonspecific subjective complaints, such as fatigue, headache,
      arthralgia, and myalgia, termed post-Lyme and post-encephalitic symptoms, respectively. These
      may not be differentiated clearly from nonspecific symptoms occurring with a rather
      substantial incidence also in the general population. A trend of ascribing medically
      unexplained nonspecific subjective symptoms to LB in subjects with positive borrelial
      antibodies in serum puzzles the situation further.

      The aim of this prospective observational study was to assess the proportion and clinical
      implication of proven and possible coinfection with Lyme borreliae in patients with TBE, and
      to evaluate the association between anti-borrelial antibiotic therapy and clinical outcome in
      the subgroup of patients with possible coinfection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with objective manifestations of Lyme borreliosis</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>At each visit physical examination was performed and clinical signs indicating objective manifestations of Lyme borreliosis, such as erythema migrans, were searched for and documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of nonspecific symptoms such as headache, fatigue, arthralgia, myalgia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>At each visit patients were asked to report the presence of nonspecific symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">690</enrollment>
  <condition>Tick Borne Encephalitis</condition>
  <condition>Lyme Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-borrelial antibiotic therapy</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No antibiotics</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who received symptomatic therapy (paracetamol, Lekadol®, granisetron, Kytril®, metamizol, Analgin®, parenteral hydration with saline). Patients reported the presence of nonspecific symptoms such as headache, fatigue, arthralgia, myalgia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anti-borrelial antibiotic therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Beside symptomatic therapy, patients received oral doxycycline 100 mg (Doxy®) twice daily or ceftriaxone 2 g (Lendacin®) once daily for 14 days. Antibiotic therapy was left to the discretion of treating physicians. Patients reported the presence of nonspecific symptoms such as headache, fatigue, arthralgia, myalgia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-borrelial antibiotic therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No antibiotic.</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who received symptomatic therapy (paracetamol, Lekadol®, granisetron, Kytril®, metamizol, Analgin®, parenteral hydration with saline). Patients reported the presence of nonspecific symptoms such as headache, fatigue, arthralgia, myalgia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No antibiotics</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adult patients with tick-borne encephalitis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age ≥18 years

          -  admitted between January 2007 and December 2013 at the University Medical Centre
             Ljubljana, Slovenia

          -  tick-borne encephalitis defined according to European criteria (febrile illness with
             symptoms and/or signs of meningitis or meningoencephalitis, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)
             pleocytosis (&gt;5 × 106 cells/L), and demonstration of acute TBE virus infection (the
             presence of specific tick-borne encephalitis virus IgM and IgG antibodies in serum or
             demonstration of intrathecal production of specific TBE virus IgM and/or IgG
             antibodies in patients previously vaccinated against tick-borne encephalitis)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Lyme borreliosis in the past
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Ljubljana</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ljubljana</city>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Medical Centre Ljubljana</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daša Stupica</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prinicipal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lyme Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis, Tick-Borne</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Encephalitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anti-Bacterial Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibiotics, Antitubercular</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

