<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03959397</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSPC-KAL-BC-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03959397</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Paclitaxel Injection (Albumin-bound) for Neoadjuvant Treatment of Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Real-world Study of Paclitaxel Injection (Albumin-bound) for Neoadjuvant Treatment of Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jilin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jilin University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Neoadjuvant chemotherapy is a systemic cytotoxic drug therapy for non-metastatic tumors
      before local therapy, Now it has become an important part of standard treatment for a stage
      II, III, and the first clinical Ⅳ breast cancer .Both domestic and foreign authoritative
      guidelines recommend the use of albumin-binding paclitaxel in the neoadjuvant treatment of
      breast cancer .In addition, clinical studies at home and abroad have preliminarily confirmed
      the application value and therapeutic benefit of albumin-binding paclitaxel in breast cancer
      neoadjuvant therapy, and the toxic and side effects can be tolerated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data were collected on the efficacy and safety of neoadjuvant therapy in patients receiving
      albumin-binding taxol regimens,Subgroup analysis was performed for different treatment
      regimens, dosages, molecular subtypes and tumor stages,To further screen the dominant
      population and the chemotherapy regimen with clinical benefit of albumin paclitaxel, so as to
      provide evidence-based medical evidence for breast cancer neoadjuvant clinical diagnosis and
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the Pathological complete remission(pCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Histopathological examination of breast and axillary lymph node specimens without invasive cancer cell remnants. Complete pathological response is also considered to be achieved if only in situ cancer cell remnants are present in the surgical specimens.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the time from the beginning of randomization to recurrence or death due to disease progression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the time between enrollment in the study (i.e., ICF) and death from any cause.Subjects who survived the last contact were deleted on the last contact date</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast conserving rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>after neoadjuvant treatment, the percentage of patients undergoing breast conserving surgery in the total number of evaluable cases.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AE)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events (AE) were monitored on an ongoing basis and classified according to National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI CTCAE), version 5.0.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Stage</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>nab-paclitaxel monotherapy or combination therapeutic regimen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nab-paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>nab-paclitaxel monotherapy or combination therapeutic regimen</description>
    <arm_group_label>nab-paclitaxel</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ABRAXANE ，Albumin-binding paclitaxel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed informed content obtained prior to treatment. The patients were fully explained
             and understood the purpose, contents, predicted efficacy, pharmacological effects, and
             risks of this study.

          2. target population 1)The histologic diagnosis of the primary invasive breast cancer and
             clinical stage I - III, first option Ⅳ period; 2) One of the following
             conditions:Large mass (&gt;3cm);Axillary lymph node metastasis;her-2 positive;
             tri-negative; For those who are willing to preserve breast, but have difficulty in
             breast conserving due to the large proportion of tumor size and breast volume; 3) The
             clinician determined that the patient was suitable for the treatment with
             albumin-binding taxol regimen;4) The subjects have good compliance, can be treated and
             followed up, and voluntarily comply with the relevant provisions of this study 5)No
             contraindications for nab-paclitaxel.

          3. Age and reproductive status 1) Age ≥ 18 years 2) Subjects of child-bearing age must
             agree to take effective contraceptive measures during the study period; Serum or urine
             pregnancy tests must be negative for women of childbearing age 24 hours before the
             start of chemotherapy; 3) Women must not lactate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Allergy to paclitaxel for injection (albumin binding) and/or its adjuvants has been
             demonstrated;

          2. Pregnant or lactating women

          3. Abnormal results of physical examination and laboratory examination 1) Absolute
             neutrophil count (ANC) 90g/L 1.5 × 109/L; Platelets (PLT) 90g/L 100 × 109/L;
             Hemoglobin (Hgb) ＜ 90g/L 2) Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic
             oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]/ alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamic
             pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) ＞2.5 × institutional upper limit of normal (ULN), ＞5 ×
             institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) (hepatic metastases); Total bilirubin
             (TBIL)＞1.5 × ULN; 3) Creatinine (CRE)＞ 1.5 × ULN 4) Prothrombin time (PT) and
             international normalized ratio (INR) ＞ 1.5 × ULN. Unless the subject had received
             anticoagulant treatment

          4. Paclitaxel for injection (albumin binding type) contraindications in patients

          5. Participating in clinical trials of other taxoids

          6. Patients with concomitant other tumors, other than cured carcinoma in situ of the
             cervix and non-melanoma skin cancer

          7. Participation in any trial drug treatment or another interventional clinical trial 30
             days before screening period.

          8. The researchers considered that there were other conditions that were not suitable for
             enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fan zhimin, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>First Affiliated Hospital of Jilin University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fan zhimin, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>13904321567</phone>
    <email>13364308696@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shi aiping</last_name>
    <phone>15804301451</phone>
    <email>13364308696@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>the first hospital of Jilin University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jilin</city>
        <state>Changchun</state>
        <zip>130021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Untch M, Jackisch C, Schneeweiss A, Conrad B, Aktas B, Denkert C, Eidtmann H, Wiebringhaus H, Kümmel S, Hilfrich J, Warm M, Paepke S, Just M, Hanusch C, Hackmann J, Blohmer JU, Clemens M, Darb-Esfahani S, Schmitt WD, Dan Costa S, Gerber B, Engels K, Nekljudova V, Loibl S, von Minckwitz G; German Breast Group (GBG); Arbeitsgemeinschaft Gynäkologische Onkologie—Breast (AGO-B) Investigators. Nab-paclitaxel versus solvent-based paclitaxel in neoadjuvant chemotherapy for early breast cancer (GeparSepto-GBG 69): a randomised, phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2016 Mar;17(3):345-356. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00542-2. Epub 2016 Feb 8. Erratum in: Lancet Oncol. 2016 Jul;17 (7):e270.</citation>
    <PMID>26869049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gluz O, Nitz U, Liedtke C, Christgen M, Grischke EM, Forstbauer H, Braun M, Warm M, Hackmann J, Uleer C, Aktas B, Schumacher C, Bangemann N, Lindner C, Kuemmel S, Clemens M, Potenberg J, Staib P, Kohls A, von Schumann R, Kates R, Kates R, Schumacher J, Wuerstlein R, Kreipe HH, Harbeck N. Comparison of Neoadjuvant Nab-Paclitaxel+Carboplatin vs Nab-Paclitaxel+Gemcitabine in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer: Randomized WSG-ADAPT-TN Trial Results. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2018 Jun 1;110(6):628-637. doi: 10.1093/jnci/djx258.</citation>
    <PMID>29228315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zong Y, Wu J, Shen K. Nanoparticle albumin-bound paclitaxel as neoadjuvant chemotherapy of breast cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Oncotarget. 2017 Mar 7;8(10):17360-17372. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.14477. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28061451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nahleh ZA, Barlow WE, Hayes DF, Schott AF, Gralow JR, Sikov WM, Perez EA, Chennuru S, Mirshahidi HR, Corso SW, Lew DL, Pusztai L, Livingston RB, Hortobagyi GN. SWOG S0800 (NCI CDR0000636131): addition of bevacizumab to neoadjuvant nab-paclitaxel with dose-dense doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide improves pathologic complete response (pCR) rates in inflammatory or locally advanced breast cancer. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2016 Aug;158(3):485-95. doi: 10.1007/s10549-016-3889-6. Epub 2016 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27393622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jilin University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aiping shi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief physician and associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast cancer; neoadjuvant therapy; Nab-paclitaxel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

