<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03952975</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MUGLA SKU</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03952975</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimal Timing for Performing Loop Electrosurgical Excision Procedure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimal Timing for Performing Loop Electrosurgical Excision Procedure According to Different Menstrual Phase: Which is Best?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erzincan Military Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erzincan Military Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cervical precancerous lesions (cervical intraepithelial neoplasia) are frequently diagnosed
      and treated in women of reproductive-aged [1]. Loop electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP)
      is the standard surgical treatment in CIN 2 or 3 [1]. This procedure is an inexpensive, easy
      to learn and provide specimens for pathological examination with the least major surgical
      morbidity [2].

      Although LEEP is a safe procedure, complications such as postoperative bleeding have been
      reported. These haemorrhages make patients anxious, undergo unnecessary follow-ups,
      additional procedures to stop bleeding and interfere in patients daily activities. Various
      interventions have been attempted to prevent and/or reduce perioperative and/or postoperative
      haemorrhage after LEEP including vasopressiın, tranexamic acid, Monsel's solution, or local
      hemostats (TochoSil or Tisseel), but have failed to show a definite advantage over routine
      practice [2-4].

      A hormonal variation during the menstrual cycle is known to affect hemostasis [5] and the
      blood flow of the genital organ [6,7]. A systematic review of the literature through PubMed,
      OvidSP, Google Scholar, and Scopus identified only one previous investigation of menstrual
      cycle period affect blood loss during the LEEP procedure. The authors showed that women had
      less perioperative bleeding during the follicular phase than during the luteal phase [8]. Two
      retrospective studies have also demonstrated rhinoplasty and mammoplasty caused more bleeding
      during the luteal phase and menstruation than during the follicular phase [9,10]. In
      contrast, other retrospective studies have shown no relation between operative blood loss and
      the menstrual cycle for hysterectomy, myomectomy, and ovarian cystectomy [11-13] To answer
      this clinically relevant question, the investigators performed a randomized study comparing
      perioperative and postoperative bleeding between patients underwent LEEP procedure during the
      follicular or luteal phase of the menstrual cycle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 18, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean early postoperative blood loss</measure>
    <time_frame>6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Estimated early postoperative blood loss was calculated using the difference in hematocrit values taken after LEEP procedure and 6 hours after procedure, according to the following formula: Estimated Blood Loss = estimated blood volume X (hematocrit 1 - hematocrit 2)/hematocrit 1, where the estimated blood volume in milliliters = woman's weight in kilograms X 85</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mean intraoperative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>During the LEEP procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The volume of intraoperative blood loss was measured by weighing a gauze sponge during the procedure. Because it is important to collect the blood accurately, we used a specially designed operating gauze sponge and an electronic scale to weigh all the material (with a 1-g deviation range). The LEEP procedure was performed ensuring that all blood lost during the procedure was absorbed with gauzes. We took care to clean all the bleeding with gauze obtained during the procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the rate of late postoperative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>bleeding that occur within four weeks after the home dischard</time_frame>
    <description>late postoperative bleeding (defined as bleeding that occur within four weeks after the home dischard, and required hemostatic interventions such as electrocauterization, gause packing, or cervical suturing, excluding menstrual bleeding).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Precancerous Lesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>follicular phase group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The menstrual dates of patients were normalized to a 28-day cycle with the following formula: adjusted day of the menstrual cycle = (14 X day of the cycle at the time of surgery) / (cycle length of the patient - 14). In light of this formula patients were classified into the follicular phase group (defined as &lt;15 adjusted days, group A).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>luteal phase group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The menstrual dates of patients were normalized to a 28-day cycle with the following formula: adjusted day of the menstrual cycle = (14 X day of the cycle at the time of surgery) / (cycle length of the patient - 14) [14]. In light of this formula, patients were classified into the luteal phase group (defined as ≥15 adjusted days, group B).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaginal bleeding</intervention_name>
    <description>Vaginal bleeding was classified into four categories according to the timing. Intraoperative bleeding (defined as bleeding that occur during the LEEP procedure), early postoperative bleeding (defined as bleeding that occur between end of the LEEP procedure and home discard), late postoperative bleeding (defined as bleeding that occur within two weeks after the home discard, and required hemostatic interventions such as electrocauterization, gauze packing, or cervical suturing, excluding menstrual bleeding), and persistent postoperative bleeding (defined as vaginal bleeding that occurs more than 2 weeks after the procedure with or without required hemostatic interventions, excluding menstrual bleeding).</description>
    <arm_group_label>follicular phase group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>luteal phase group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women was ≥ 21 years old

          2. Women was not pregnant

          3. Women were not menstruating or menopausal status

          4. Women with the normal regular menstrual cycle (defined as an interval between 21 and
             35 days and duration between 3 and 10 days)

          5. Women had one of the following indications for LEEP procedure

               1. a histology-proven, persistent, low grade squamous intraepithelial lesions
                  (LGSIL),

               2. a histology-proven high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions (HGSIL),

               3. discrepancies between cytological reports and colposcopic impressions,

               4. investigation for unsatisfactory colposcopy,

               5. micro invasion or adenocarcinoma in situ on cervical punch biopsy

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with cervical or vaginal infection,

          -  Women with the abnormal menstrual cycle,

          -  Women taking any medication (or injection) such as oral contraceptives, GnRH agonist,
             medroxyprogesterone acetate, or anticoagulants

          -  Women with coagulation defect,

          -  Women with mental incapacity,

          -  Women with a history of neurologic deficit,

          -  Women with previous hysterectomy with removal of the cervix,

          -  Women with a history of cervical cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kemal Gungorduk</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muğla</city>
        <zip>35460</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Paraskevaidis E, Davidson EJ, Koliopoulos G, Alamanos Y, Lolis E, Martin-Hirsch P. Bleeding after loop electrosurgical excision procedure performed in either the follicular or luteal phase of the menstrual cycle: a randomized trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2002 Jun;99(6):997-1000.</citation>
    <PMID>12052589</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 12, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 12, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 15, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Erzincan Military Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kemal GUNGORDUK</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Loop electrosurgical excision procedure</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

