<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03957538</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17/DEC/7157</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03957538</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>UHW Angiogram Video Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>VIRTUAL CATH</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of a VIrtual RealiTy Immersive Experience Upon Anxiety Levels in Patients Undergoing CArdiac caTHeterisation: The VIRTUAL CATH Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital of Wales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital of Wales</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a randomised control trial which aims to assess whether the use of an immersive
      virtual reality angiogram experience decreases peri-procedural anxiety in patients undergoing
      cardiac catheterisation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients undergoing cardiac catheterisation are understandably anxious. This is due to a lack
      of familiarity with both the hospital environment and the planned procedure. Anxiety may
      negatively affect their patient experience. Appropriate patient information can help improve
      understanding and reduce anxiety. In particular, video-based patient information prior to
      cardiac catheterisation has been shown to improve patient's knowledge and reduce
      peri-procedural anxiety. Generic video-based patient information about the cardiac
      catheterisation procedure is widely available. Ideally any patient information delivered
      pre-cardiac catheterization would be specific to the hospital delivering care. The use of
      virtual reality (VR) in healthcare is novel, but expanding rapidly. The immersive nature of
      VR allows patients a unique opportunity to prepare for the procedure and environment within
      which they will be treated. To date, the use of VR to prepare patients for invasive cardiac
      procedures has not been studied.

      The aim of this study is to assess whether the use of an immersive VR experience decreases
      peri-procedural anxiety in patients undergoing cardiac catheterisation. The investigators
      will also assess whether the VR experience improves overall patient satisfaction.

      With the help of a local media company, a VR cardiac catheterisation video was produced
      (Figure 1 depicts a screenshot from the VR video). The video is watched with a VR headset to
      create a 360 immersive experience. The investigators are undertaking a single-centre
      randomised control trial comparing the use of an immersive VR experience 1 week prior to
      catheterisation with standard pre-procedural care. Pre procedural anxiety levels and
      procedural knowledge are assessed by questionnaire, using the validated six-item short-form
      of the Strait Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). A satisfaction questionnaire is also completed
      before the patient is discharged.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in pre and post procedural anxiety scores between patients receiving standard care and those who experienced the immersive VR experience</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Study data collection will be via questionnaire, including the validated six-item short-form of the Strait Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). The STAI is a well-established and validated measure of anxiety that can be used in various clinical settings. The investigators chose the STAI as the primary outcome measure as it has been validated as a measure of anxiety in patients undergoing invasive cardiac procedures. Total score available is 32, minimum score 8. The higher the score the higher the anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in post procedure satisfaction scores between patients receiving standard care and those who experienced the immersive VR experience</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>After cardiac catheterisation study patients will be asked to complete a satisfaction questionnaire. This is a modification of an accepted and validated post cardiac catheterisation patient satisfaction questionnaire. Total score available 60. Minimum score 6. Higher score indicates better satisfaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard consent and explanation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual reality</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Addition of VR headset</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual reality angiogram experience video</intervention_name>
    <description>The VR video is watched via the VR headset, and describes the pre- procedural and procedural experience. Concurrent audio will be provided through earplugs to compete the patients' immersive experience. The video was written and directed by the team, and care has been taken to ensure that the same procedural information is contained within both the British Heart Foundation cardiac catheterisation video and of VR immersive video. Filming was performed within the cardiac catheterisation labs at our tertiary centre using the professional services of Orchard Media (Cardiff, UK). The investigators utilized real physicians and nurses to re-enact a typical day for a mock patient undergoing an uncomplicated procedure. There is also a short explanation of the procedure and animations explaining technical aspects of the procedure contained within the VR video.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Virtual reality</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - All patients undergoing their first cardiac catheterisation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who cannot comprehend English or Welsh

          -  Those who have significant visual or auditory impairment meaning they would be unable
             to fully appreciate the video material
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sean Gallagher, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital of Wales</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Holly Morgan</last_name>
    <phone>07930337919</phone>
    <email>morganhp@cf.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sean Gallagher</last_name>
    <email>sean.gallagher@wales.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of Wales</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cardiff</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Holly Morgan</last_name>
      <phone>02920747747</phone>
      <email>holly.morgan2@wales.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Hospital of Wales</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Holly Morgan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cardiology Spr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

