<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04437979</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-397</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04437979</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epicardial Fat Thickness and Inflammation in People With Metabolic Syndrome and Obesity</brief_title>
  <official_title>Association of Epicardial Fat Thickness and Inflammation With the Presence of Metabolic Syndrome in People With Obesity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Antalya Training and Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Antalya Training and Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Epicardial adipose tissue (EAT) is a type of visceral adipose tissue, functioning as a
      metabolically active endocrine organ and suggested to play an important role in the
      progression of metabolic syndrome (MetS). Obesity and MetS are commonly associated with an
      inflammatory status. The aim of our study was to evaluate the association of
      echocardiographically measured epicardial fat thickness (EFT) and inflammation, on the basis
      of c-reactive protein (CRP) and neutrophyl-lymphocyte ratio (NLR), with MetS and its
      components in people with obesity.

      A total of 104 patients with body mass index (BMI)≥30 kg/m² were enrolled to the study. In
      all participants, EFT was measured with transthorasic echocardiography at end-systole. The
      patients were then classified into two groups according to whether they had MetS or not. EFT,
      clinical and biochemical parameters were compared between the two groups
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Epicardial adipose tissue (EAT) is a kind of VAT, between the surface of the myocardium and
      the epicardium. It can easily be measured by standard two-dimensional (2D) echocardiography.
      EAT serves as an endocrin organ that secretes hormones, inflammatory citokins and chemokines.
      Previous data suggests that EAT can play an active role in the development of metabolic
      syndrome (MetS). Previous studies have investigated the relationship between EAT/inflammatory
      markers and MetS/MetS components. However, there was lack of enough evidence regarding this
      relationship in people with obesity with or without MetS. The aim of the present study was to
      evaluate the association of echocardiographically measured EAT and inflammation, on the basis
      of CRP and NLR, as simple and reliable indicators of inflammation, with MetS and its
      components in people with obesity who have similar BMI values. In this cross-sectional study,
      104 consecutive patients with BMI ≥30 kg/m2 who presented to the 'Obesity Solution Center 'of
      our hospital were included . Patients with manifest heart disease such as, coronary heart
      disease, cardiac failure, cardiac valve disease or arrythmia, renal failure, hepatic failure,
      infection, chronic systemic inflammatory disease, pulmonary disease , malignancy and
      inadequate transthorasic echocardiographic images were excluded. The study protocol was
      approved by the local ethics committee and informed consent was obtained from each subject.

      Clinical information and current cardiovascular medication use were provided from each
      patient. Height, weight, WC and hip circumference (HC) were measured when fasting and
      standing up with standard measuring tools. Patients were defined as having hypertension (HT)
      if their SBP was &gt;140 mmHg, their DBP was &gt;90 mmHg, or they were using an antihypertensive
      medication. Blood samples were obtained after overnight fasting. Fasting blood glucose, urea,
      creatinine, total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol, high-density
      lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol, triglycerides, CRP, fasting and postprandial insulin, C-peptid
      levels, vitamin D, ferritine and complete blood counts were measured using standard methods.
      Homeostasis model assessment of insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) was calculated using the method
      described by Mathews et al. ). NLR was defined as the log e neutrophil count/log e lymphocyte
      count within the peripheral blood. Patients were defined as having diabetes mellitus (DM) if
      they had a history of taking an oral antidiabetic or insulin medication, or if their fasting
      plasma glucose was ≥ 126 mg/dl. The patients were classified into two groups according to
      whether they had MetS or not. MetS was diagnosed according to the National Cholesterol
      Education Programme Adult Treatment Panel III (NCEP ATP III). Epicardial fat thickness (EFT)
      was identified as the echo-free space in the pericardial layers on 2D echocardiography. EFT
      was measured on the free wall of the right ventricle at end-systole from both parasternal
      long axis and parasternal short axis views using the mean of three consecutive beats.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the epicardial fat thickness in the presence of metabolic syndrome in people with obesity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Transthorasic echocardiography was performed to all participants with body mass index &gt; 30 kg/m2 and epicardial fat thickness was measured. Epicardial fat thickness (EFT) was identified as the echo-free space in the pericardial layers on 2D echocardiography. EFT was measured on the free wall of the right ventricle at end-systole from both parasternal long axis and parasternal short axis views using the mean of three consecutive beats The patients were classified into two groups according to whether they had MetS or not. MetS was diagnosed according to the National Cholesterol Education Programme Adult Treatment Panel III. We evaluated the difference in epicardial fat thickness according to whether having metabolic syndrome or not, regardless of body mass index.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of inflammation in the presence of metabolic syndrome in people with obesity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>C-reactive protein and neutrophyl-to-lymphocyte ratio were used to determine inflammation. The patients were classified into two groups according to whether they had MetS or not. MetS was diagnosed according to the National Cholesterol Education Programme Adult Treatment Panel III. We evaluated the difference in inflammatory mediators according to whether having metabolic syndrome or not, regardless of body mass index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Metabolic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with BMI ≥30 kg/m2, &gt;18 years old and without manifest heart disease such as,
        coronary heart disease, cardiac failure, cardiac valve disease or arrythmia, renal failure,
        hepatic failure, infection, chronic systemic inflammatory disease, pulmonary disease and
        malignancy
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:104 consecutive patients with BMI ≥30 kg/m2 who presented to the
        'Obesity Solution Center 'of our hospital were included.

        -

        Exclusion Criteria:. Patients with manifest heart disease such as, coronary heart disease,
        cardiac failure, cardiac valve disease or arrythmia, renal failure, hepatic failure,
        infection, chronic systemic inflammatory disease, pulmonary disease , malignancy and
        inadequate transthorasic echocardiographic images were excluded.

        -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Duygu Ersan Demirci, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Antalya Research and Training Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Antalya Research and Training Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antalya</city>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Antalya Training and Research Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Duygu Ersan Demirci</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>medical doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>epicardial fat thickness</keyword>
  <keyword>metabolic syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

