<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04432766</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BAT2020-001-CR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04432766</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 1 Study to Assess BAT2020 in Hospitalized Patients Infected With SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Multi-Center, Open-Label, Randomized Study to Assess Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of BAT2020 in Hospitalized Patients Infected With SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bio-Thera Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bio-Thera Solutions</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-Label, randomized study to assess safety, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy of
      BAT2020 in Hospitalized Patients Infected With COVID-19. This study is composed of two Parts:
      single ascending dose (Part 1) and multiple ascending dose escalation or treatment period
      with a double-blind, placebo-controlled design (Part 2).

      Part 1. Single ascending dose (SAD) SAD: The patients will receive a single IV infusion of
      BAT2020 on day 1, and will be followed for up to 28 days. Safety, efficacy and PK information
      will be collected during this period. A total of 24 subjects, 3 cohorts of 8 subjects each,
      will be enrolled in this study. Screening for the study will begin 3 days prior to the actual
      dosing.

      Treatment cohorts are planned as following:

      Cohort 1: BAT2020 1 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo (n=2) Cohort 2: BAT2020 3 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo
      (n=2) Cohort 3: BAT2020 10 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo (n=2) After a cohort completes the study on
      Day 28, data on safety and tolerability for each cohort will be evaluated by the Safety
      Monitoring Committee (SMC). Administration of the next higher dose to a new dosing cohort
      will be permitted only if adequate safety and tolerability have been demonstrated. If
      encouraging clinical benefit is observed at a certain dose level, the study may proceed to a
      to Part 2 based on emerging data.

      Part 2. Treatment Period (double-blind, Placebo-controlled study) The SMC will review safety,
      PK, PD, and efficacy data of each cohort prior to Part 2. Part 2 is a double-blind,
      placebo-controlled, multi-center, Phase 2-like study in hospitalized adult patients with
      laboratory confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection. A total of 100~150 patients will be enrolled a
      2-arm (1:1 randomization of BAT2020 vs. standard supportive care) or a 3-arm (1:1:1 two
      dosing regimens of BAT2020 vs. standard supportive care) trial with 50 patients in each arm
      (the sample size and statistical analysis may be amended based on emerging data from Part 1).
      An independent data and safety monitoring board (DSMB) will actively monitor interim data to
      allow early stopping for futility, efficacy, or safety. Patients will be assessed daily while
      hospitalized. Discharged patients will be asked to attend study visits at Days 15 and 28. All
      subjects will undergo a series of efficacy, safety, and laboratory assessments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 20, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 18, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 3, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Part 1: Open label; Part 2: double blinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>SAE, TEAEs, mortality, those resulting in treatment discontinuation, and changes from baseline in safety laboratory assessments</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of survival and free of respiratory failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 28</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients reporting each severity rating on an 8-point ordinal scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 15</time_frame>
    <description>The ordinal scale is as follows:
Death;
Hospitalized, on invasive mechanical ventilation or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO);
Hospitalized, on non-invasive ventilation or high flow oxygen devices;
Hospitalized, requiring supplemental oxygen; 5) Hospitalized, not requiring supplemental oxygen - requiring ongoing medical care (COVID-19 related or otherwise);
Hospitalized, not requiring supplemental oxygen - no longer requires ongoing medical care;
Not hospitalized, limitation on activities and/or requiring home oxygen;
Not hospitalized, no limitations on activities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in National Early Warning Score (NEWS) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 7, 14, 21, 28</time_frame>
    <description>This score is based on 7 clinical parameters (respiration rate, oxygen saturation, any supplemental oxygen, temperature, systolic blood pressure, heart rate, level of consciousness). Maximum=20, Minimun=0, the higher the worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of respiratory progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as SPO2≤ 94% on room air or PaO2/FiO2&lt; 300mmHg and requirement for supplemental oxygen or more advanced ventilator support</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by oropharyngeal swabs, nasopharyneal and blood samples for virology</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 7, 14, 21, 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of Grade 3 and 4 adverse events (AEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>Grade 3 AEs are defined as events that interrupt usual activities of daily living, or significantly affects clinical status, or may require intensive therapeutic intervention. Severe events are usually incapacitating.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Grade 4 AEs are defined as events that are potentially life threatening</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of serious adverse events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of new non-invasive ventilation or high flow oxygen use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of new oxygen use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of new ventilator or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of new non-invasive ventilation or high flow oxygen use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of new oxygen use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of new ventilator or extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) use</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of non-invasive ventilation/high flow oxygen free days</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of oxygenation free days</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventilator/extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) free days</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject 28-day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>viral load change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to an improvement of one category using an ordinal scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to an improvement of two categories using an ordinal scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to discharge or to a National Early Warning Score (NEWS) of &lt;/= 2 and maintained for 24 hours, whichever occurs first</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 through Day 28</time_frame>
    <description>The NEW score has demonstrated an ability to discriminate patients at risk of poor outcomes. This score is based on 7 clinical parameters (respiration rate, oxygen saturation, any supplemental oxygen, temperature, systolic blood pressure, heart rate, level of consciousness). The NEW Score is being used as an efficacy measure.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">174</enrollment>
  <condition>COVID-19</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 1 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BAT2020 1 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo (n=2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 3 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BAT2020 3 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo (n=2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 10 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BAT2020 10 mg/kg (n=6) + Placebo (n=2)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BAT2020</intervention_name>
    <description>After a cohort completes the study on Day 28, data on safety and tolerability for each cohort will be evaluated by the Safety Monitoring Committee (SMC). Administration of the next higher dose to a new dosing cohort will be permitted only if adequate safety and tolerability have been demonstrated. If encouraging clinical benefit is observed at a certain dose level, the study may proceed to a to Part 2 based on emerging data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 1 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 10 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BAT2020 3 mg/kg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Admitted to a hospital with symptoms suggestive of COVID-19 infection. Has
             laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2 infection as determined by polymerase chain reaction
             (PCR) or other commercial or public health assay in any specimen collected &lt; 72 hours
             prior to randomization. Note - 72 hours is not necessarily time from initial
             diagnosis. If &gt; / = 72 hours since positive PCR, the PCR may be repeated to assess
             eligibility.

          2. Male or non-pregnant female adult ≥18 years of age at time of enrollment.

          3. Patient (or legally authorized representative) provides written informed consent prior
             to initiation of any study procedures.

          4. Agrees to the collection of oropharyngeal (OP) swabs,b nasopharyneal and blood samples
             for virology assessment.

          5. Illness of any duration, and at least one of the following:

               1. Radiographic infiltrates by imaging (chest x-ray, CT scan, etc.), OR

               2. Clinical assessment (evidence of rales/crackles on exam) AND SpO2 &lt; / = 94% on
                  room air, OR

               3. Requiring supplemental oxygen, OR

               4. Requiring mechanical ventilation.

          6. Women of childbearing potential must agree to either abstinence or use at least one
             primary form of contraception not including hormonal contraception from the time of
             screening through Day 28.

          7. Agrees to not participate in another clinical trial for the treatment of COVID-19 or
             SARS-CoV-2 through Day 28.

          8. Randomization within 72 hr of hospital admission

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt; 50 or requiring dialysis.

          2. Alanine Transaminase (ALT)/Aspartate Transaminase (AST) &gt; 5 times the upper limit of
             normal.

          3. Use of another SARS-CoV-2 directed medication empirically or within another clinical
             trial within the prior week

          4. Pregnancy or breast feeding

          5. Absence of dependable contraception in reproductive age women

          6. Inability to obtain or declined informed consent

          7. Anticipated transfer to another hospital which is not a study site within 72 hours.

          8. Known allergic reaction to components of BAT2020
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

