<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04433182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FIL_Copa-RB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04433182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Copanlisib With Rituximab-Bendamustine in Patients With Relapsed-Refractory Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Copanlisib in Combination With Rituximab-Bendamustine in Patients With Relapsed-Refractory Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma: a Multicentric Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione Italiana Linfomi ONLUS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione Italiana Linfomi ONLUS</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicentric single arm phase II trial, to investigate the efficacy (in terms of
      PFS) of the combination regimen rituximab-bendamustine in association with copanlisib in
      patients affected by relapsed/refractory DLBCL, not eligible to HDC and ASCT or relapsed
      after intensified regimens.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy, in terms of Progression Free
      Survival (12m-PFS) at 12 months, of a treatment with copanlisib in combination with a
      standard rituximab-bendamustine regimen in patients with relapsed-refractory DLBCL, who have
      received at least one, but no more than three lines of treatment, including rituximab-based
      immunochemotherapy, not eligible for high-dose chemotherapy and ASCT or T-cell CAR-T therapy,
      or relapsed after these treatments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-Free Survival (PFS) will be defined as the time between the date of enrolment and the date of disease progression, relapse or death from any cause. Responding patients according to Response Criteria for NHL with PET and patients who are lost to follow-up will be censored at their last assessment date.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time between the date of enrolment and the date of death from any cause. Patients who have not died at the time of the final analysis will be censored at the date of the last contact.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>End of treament (EOT), 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>ORR will be defined as the sum of CR + PR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Response Rate (CRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>End of induction (EOI), 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>CRR will be defined as the proportion of patients achieving a CR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>DOR is measured from the date when criteria for response are met (CR or PR) until the date of progression or relapse. Patients without relapse or progression will be censored at their last assessment date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Conversion rate from SD/PR to PR/CR with maintenance</measure>
    <time_frame>End of treatment (after maintenance), 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Conversion rate from SD/PR to PR/CR with maintenance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of adverse events according to the current version of the CTCAE criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of adverse events according to the current version of the CTCAE criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm Copa-RB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Induction phase with Copanlisib, Rituximab and Bendamustina. Maintenance phase (for patients who reach at least SD after induction) with Copanlisib in monotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Copanlisib</intervention_name>
    <description>Induction phase: 6 cycles of Copa-RB every 28 days according to the following schedule
Copanlisib (Copa): 60 mg/day i.v. on days 1,8,15
Rituximab (R): 375 mg/sqm i.v. day 1*
Bendamustine (B): 90 mg/sqm i.v. days 1-2*
note: during cycle 1 rituximab can be administered on day 2: in this case bendamustine will be administered on days 2-3; in the case of a frail patient or a patient with high tumor burden copanlisib could be administered on day 1, rituximab on day 2 and bendamustine on days 3-4, at physician discretion.
Maintenance phase: patients who reach at least SD after induction will receive a maintenance with copanlisib in monotherapy according to the following schedule:
• Copanlisib: 60 mg/day i.v. on days 1 and 15 in 28-day cycles for 1 year</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm Copa-RB</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ALIQOPA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of DLBCL (de-novo DLBCL or DLBCL transformed by
             indolent lymphoma; high grade double hit lymphoma can be included); new biopsy at
             relapse time is recommended, but is not mandatory.

          2. Patients must have relapsed (recurrence after complete response or presented
             progression after partial response) or refractory after at least ≥ 1 (but &lt; 4) prior
             lines of therapy, including rituximab-based immunochemotherapy.

             A previous regimen is defined as one of the following: at least 2 months of
             single-agent therapy; at least 2 consecutive cycles of polychemotherapy; autologous
             transplant; radioimmunotherapy.

          3. Patients must not be eligible to high-dose chemotherapy (HDC) and autologous stem cell
             transplantation (ASCT) or relapsed after that.

          4. Patients must not be eligible to CAR T-cell therapy or relapsed after that.

          5. Patients must have at least one bi-dimensionally measurable lesion (that has not been
             previously irradiated) according to the 2014 Lugano criteria.

          6. Male or female patient ≥ 18 years of age.

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2 if not related to
             lymphoma disease.

          8. Ann Arbor stage II-IV disease.

          9. Life expectancy of at least 3 months.

         10. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) and men must agree to use effective
             contraception when sexually active. This applies for the time period between signing
             of the informed consent form and 6 months after last administration of bendamustine or
             copanlisib or 12 months after last rituximab dose. A woman is considered of
             childbearing potential, i.e. fertile, following menarche and until becoming
             post-menopausal unless permanently sterile. Permanent sterilization methods include
             but are not limited to hysterectomy, bilateral salpingectomy and bilateral
             oophorectomy. A postmenopausal state is defined as no menses for continuous 12 months
             without an alternative medical cause. A high follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) level
             in the postmenopausal range may be used to confirm a post-menopausal state in women
             not using hormonal contraception or hormonal replacement therapy. The investigator or
             a designated associate is requested to advise the patient how to achieve highly
             effective birth control method (failure rate of less than 1%) e.g. intrauterine device
             (IUD), intrauterine hormone-releasing system (IUS), bilateral tubal occlusion,
             vasectomized partner, and sexual abstinence. The use of condoms by male patients is
             required unless the female partner is permanently sterile.

         11. Adequate liver, renal and bone marrow function, assessed by baseline laboratory values
             as assessed within 7 days before starting study treatment; as assessed by the
             following (ULN= upper level of normality):

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN (&lt; 3 x ULN for patients with Gilbert-Meulengracht
                  syndrome, patients with cholestasis due to compressive adenopathies of the
                  hepatic hilum or documented liver involvement by lymphoma).

               -  Alanine transaminase (ALT or GPT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST or GOT) &lt;
                  2.5 x ULN (&lt; 5x ULN for patients with documented liver involvement or with
                  biliary obstruction due to lymphoma).

               -  Lipase ≤ 1.5 x ULN.

               -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) ≥ 30mL/min/1.73 m2 according to the Modification
                  of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) abbreviated formula. If not on target, this
                  evaluation may be repeated once after at least 24 hours either according to the
                  MDRD abbreviated formula or by 24-hour sampling. If the latter result is within
                  acceptable range, it may be used to fulfil the inclusion criteria instead.

               -  International normalized ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 and partial thromboplastin time (PTT)
                  ≤ 1.5 x ULN. PTT can be used instead of INR if PTT ≤ 1.5 x ULN.

               -  Platelet count ≥ 75,000/mm3. For patients with lymphomatous bone marrow
                  infiltration (local assessment), platelet count ≥ 50,000/mm3. Platelet
                  transfusion should not be given less than 7 days before the exam collection.

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,000/mm3.

               -  Hemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 8 g/dL.

         12. Left ventricular ejection fraction ≥ 45%.

         13. Ability to understand and willingness to sign written informed consent. Signed
             informed consent must be obtained before any study specific procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria at the time of screening will be excluded.

          -  Previous assignment to treatment during this study. Patients permanently withdrawn
             from study participation will not be allowed to re-enter the study.

          -  Previous (within 28 days or less than 5 half-lives of the drug before start of study
             treatment) or concomitant participation in another clinical study with investigational
             medicinal product(s).

        Excluded medical conditions:

          1. Primary mediastinal B-cell Lymphoma (PMBCL)

          2. High grade B-lymphoma NOS (other morphology)

          3. Known lymphomatous involvement of the central nervous system

          4. Congestive heart failure &gt; New York Heart Association (NYHA) class 2

          5. Unstable angina (angina symptoms at rest), new-onset angina (begun within the last 3
             months).

          6. Myocardial infarction less than 6 months before start of test drug

          7. Uncontrolled arterial hypertension despite optimal medical management

          8. HbA1c&gt; 8.5%

          9. Arterial or venous thrombotic or embolic events such as cerebrovascular accident
             (including transient ischemic attacks), deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism
             within 3 months before the start of study medication

         10. Non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture

         11. Active, clinically serious infections &gt; CTCAE Grade 2

         12. History of, or current autoimmune disease

         13. Known history of Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection. All patients must be
             screened for HIV up to 28 days prior to study drug start using a blood test for HIV
             according to local regulations.

         14. Hepatitis B (HBV) or hepatitis C (HCV). All patients must be screened for HBV and HCV
             up to 28 days prior to study drug start using the routine hepatitis virus laboratorial
             panel. Patients positive for HBsAg or HBcAb will be eligible if they are negative for
             HBV-DNA, these patients should receive prophylactic antiviral therapy. Patients
             positive for anti-HCV antibody will be eligible if they are negative for HCV-RNA

         15. CMV PCR positive at baseline

         16. Previous or concurrent history of malignancies other than DLBCL within 5 years prior
             to study treatment except for curatively treated:

               -  Cervical carcinoma in situ

               -  Non-melanoma skin cancer

               -  Superficial bladder cancer (Ta [non-invasive tumor], Tis [carcinoma in situ] and
                  T1 [tumor invades lamina propria])

               -  Localized prostate cancer

         17. Patients with seizure disorder requiring medication

         18. Patients with evidence or history of bleeding diathesis. Any hemorrhage or bleeding
             event ≥ CTCAE Grade 3 within 4 weeks prior to the start of study medication

         19. Proteinuria of ≥ CTCAE Grade 3 as assessed by a 24h protein quantification or
             estimated by urine protein: creatinine ratio &gt; 3.5 on a random urine sample

         20. History or concurrent condition of interstitial lung disease of any severity and/or
             severely impaired lung function (as judged by the investigator)

         21. Concurrent diagnosis of pheochromocytoma

         22. Pregnant or breast-feeding patients. Women of childbearing potential must have a serum
             pregnancy test performed a maximum of 7 days before start of treatment, and a negative
             result must be documented before start of treatment.

         23. Unresolved toxicity higher than CTCAE Grade 1 attributed to any prior
             therapy/procedure, excluding alopecia

         24. Known hypersensitivity to any of the test drugs, test drug classes, or excipients in
             the formulation

         25. Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results

         26. Any illness or medical conditions that are unstable or could jeopardize the safety of
             patients and their compliance in the study e.g., uncontrolled diabetes, uncontrolled
             dyslipidemia, etc.)

        Excluded previous therapies and medications:

          -  Prior treatment with copanlisib.

          -  Prior exposure to idelalisib or other PI3K inhibitors, less than 28 days before start
             of treatment, unless evidence of progression since last treatment

          -  Prior treatment with bendamustine: subjects treated with bendamustine at least 24
             months before, with a response &gt; one year to bendamustine containing regimen, will be
             eligible

          -  Ongoing immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Radiotherapy or immuno-/chemotherapy less than 2-4 weeks before start of treatment
             (corticosteroids are allowed) and use of myeloid growth factors within 14 days prior
             to treatment

          -  Blood or platelet transfusion less than 7 days before start of treatment

          -  Systemic continuous corticosteroid therapy at a daily dose higher than 15 mg
             prednisone or equivalent is not allowed. Previous corticosteroid therapy must be
             stopped or reduced to the allowed dose 7 days before performing the screening PET or
             PET/CT and/or CT/MRI, whichever is performed first, and again prior to the first study
             drug administration. If a patient is on chronic corticosteroid therapy,
             corticosteroids should be de-escalated to the maximum allowed dose after the patient
             has signed the IC. Patients may be using topical or inhaled corticosteroids. A
             pre-phase with corticosteroids is allowed to control the disease in case of systemic
             symptoms and/or compressive disease with a maximum of prednisone 100 mg (or
             equivalent) daily for a maximum of 15 days prior start of treatment.

          -  Autologous transplant less than 2 months before start of treatment. Prior Autologous
             stem cell performed more than 2 months before start of treatment is allowed.

          -  History of having received an allogeneic bone marrow or organ transplant.

          -  Major surgical procedure or significant traumatic injury (as judged by the
             investigator) within 28 days before start of treatment or have not recovered from
             major side effects.

          -  Anti-arrhythmic therapy (beta blockers or digoxin are permitted).

          -  Use of CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers. Copanlisib is primarily metabolized by CYP3A4.
             Therefore, concomitant use of strong inhibitors of CYP3A4 (e.g., ketoconazole,
             itraconazole, clarithromycin, ritonavir, indinavir, nelfinavir and saquinavir), and
             strong inducers of CYP3A4 (e.g., rifampin, phenytoin, carbamazepine, phenobarbital,
             St. John's Wort) are not permitted from Day -28 of Cycle 1 until the end of copanlisib
             administration.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Umberto Vitolo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ematologia, Candiolo Cancer Institute. FPO-IRCCS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Umberto Vitolo</last_name>
    <phone>+39.011.9933714</phone>
    <email>umberto.vitolo@ircc.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Monsignor Raffaele Dimiccoli - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barletta</city>
        <state>Barletta-Andria-Trani</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giuseppe Tarantini</last_name>
      <email>giuseppetarantini0@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas - U.O. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milano</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Monica Balzarotti</last_name>
      <email>monica.balzarotti@cancercenter.humanitas.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Riferimento Oncologico - S.O.C. Oncologia Medica A</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aviano</city>
        <state>Pordenone</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michele Spina</last_name>
      <email>mspina@cro.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS-Centro di Riferimento Oncologico - UO di Ematologia e Trapianto Cellule Staminali</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rionero In Vulture</city>
        <state>Potenza</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giuseppe Pietrantuono</last_name>
      <email>ematologia45@alice.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Dell'Angelo - U.O. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mestre</city>
        <state>Venezia</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Renato Bassan</last_name>
      <email>renato.bassan@aulss3.veneto.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AOU Ospedali Riuniti - Clinica di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ancona</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guido Gini</last_name>
      <email>guido.gini@ospedaliriuniti.marche.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico S.Orsola-Malpighi - Istituto di Ematologia Seragnoli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pier Luigi Zinzani</last_name>
      <email>pierluigi.zinzani@unibo.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ASST Spedali Civili - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alessandra Tucci</last_name>
      <email>alessandra.tucci@asst-spedalicivili.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arnas Nuovo Ospedale Garibaldi Nesima - U.O.C. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ugo Consoli</last_name>
      <email>ugo.consoli144@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A.O. S. Croce e Carle - S.C. di Ematologia e Trapianto di Midollo Osseo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cuneo</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alessia Castellino</last_name>
      <email>alesimocast@tiscali.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Vito Fazzi - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecce</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nicola Di Renzo</last_name>
      <email>direnzo.ematolecce@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedali Riuniti Papardo-Piemonte - S.C. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Messina</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Donato Mannina</last_name>
      <email>donamanni@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Nazionale dei Tumori di Milano - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paolo Corradini</last_name>
      <email>paolo.corradini@unimi.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Scientifico San Raffaele - Unità Linfomi - Dipartimento Oncoematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrés Ferreri</last_name>
      <email>andres.ferreri@hsr.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero-Universitaria Policlinico di Modena - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonardo Potenza</last_name>
      <email>leonardo.potenza@unimore.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>I.R.C.C.S. Istituto Oncologico Veneto - Oncologia 1</name>
      <address>
        <city>Padova</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dario Marino</last_name>
      <email>dario.marino@iov.veneto.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>AOU Policlinico Giaccone - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palermo</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Salvatrice Mancuso</last_name>
      <email>salvatrice.mancuso@unipa.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo di Pavia - Divisione di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pavia</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luca Arcaini</last_name>
      <email>luca.arcaini@unipv.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Guglielmo da Saliceto - U.O.Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Piacenza</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Annalisa Arcari</last_name>
      <email>a.arcari@ausl.pc.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria Pisana - U.O. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pisa</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mario Petrini</last_name>
      <email>mario.petrini@med.unipi.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A.O.R. San Carlo - U.O. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Potenza</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michele Cimminiello</last_name>
      <email>miki-doc@virgilio.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Unitа Sanitaria Locale-IRCCS - Arcispedale Santa Maria Nuova - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reggio Emilia</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angelo Fama</last_name>
      <email>angelo.fama@ausl.re.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Sant'Andrea - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Agostino Tafuri</last_name>
      <email>agostino.tafuri@ospedalesantandrea.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale S. Camillo - Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luigi Rigacci</last_name>
      <email>lrigacci@scamilloforlanini.rm.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Policlinico Umberto I - Università &quot;La Sapienza&quot; Istituto Ematologia -Dipartimento di Medicina Traslazionale e di Precisione</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maurizio Martelli</last_name>
      <email>martelli@bce.uniroma1.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria Senese - U.O.C. Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siena</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alberto Fabbri</last_name>
      <email>a.fabbri@ao-siena.toscana.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera S. Maria di Terni - S.C. Oncoematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Terni</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anna Marina Liberati</last_name>
      <email>marina.liberati@unipg.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliero Universitaria Città della Salute e della Scienza - S.C.Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torino</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barbara Botto</last_name>
      <email>bbotto@cittadellasalute.to.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ospedale Ca' Foncello - S.C di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Treviso</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabetta Scarpa</last_name>
      <email>elisabetta.scarpa@aulss2.veneto.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed-Refractory</keyword>
  <keyword>DLBCL</keyword>
  <keyword>Copanlisib</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

