<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04435977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ONC-2019-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04435977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of Cabozantinib in Patients With Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>Immunocabo</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy and Safety of Cabozantinib in Patients With Hepatocellular Carcinoma Progressing on or Intolerant to Prior Treatment With Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors: A Phase II Study (Immunocabo)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label, single-center, Phase II trial designed to estimate in terms of PFS the
      efficacy of cabozantinib, given as second- or third- line treatment in HCC patients that
      progress on or are intolerant to immune checkpoint inhibitors, including anti-PD-1 and
      anti-PD-L1 antibodies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects who meet all study eligibility criteria will take tablets containing 60 mg of
      cabozantinib once daily orally. Required dose reductions will be in decrements of 20 mg
      cabozantinib (maximum two dose reductions).

      Subjects will receive study treatment as long as they continue to experience clinical benefit
      in the opinion of the investigator or until there is unacceptable toxicity.

      Primary objective of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of cabozantinib, given as second-
      or third-line treatment in HCC patients that progress on or are intolerant to immune
      checkpoint inhibitors.

      Secondary objectives for this study are as follows:

        -  To evaluate the activity of cabozantinib, in terms of ORR (CR+PR) as per RECIST 1.1,
           duration of response, time to treatment failure (TTF), time to progression (TTP), and OS

        -  To evaluate the safety and tolerability of cabozantinib
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 30, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single group assignement</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>PFS on cabozantinib treatment (considering as PFS events: clinical or radiological progressive disease, per RECIST 1.1, or death).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>ORR as per RECIST 1.1, duration of response, TTF, TTP, and OS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocarcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cabozantinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Drug: Cabozantinib Subjects who meet all study eligibility criteria will take tablets containing 60 mg of cabozantinib once daily orally. Required dose reductions will be in decrements of 20 mg cabozantinib (maximum two dose reductions).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cabozantinib 60 MG</intervention_name>
    <description>• The assigned dose for study treatment is 60 mg qd. Two dose reductions will be permitted (Table 2):
60 mg qd to 40 mg qd (level 1)
40 mg qd to 20 mg qd (level 2)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cabozantinib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological or cytological diagnosis of HCC (results of a previous biopsy will be
             accepted)

          -  A baseline tumor tissue (newly obtained) available at screening is optional. Patient
             must have a site of disease amenable to biopsy, and be a candidate for tumor biopsy
             according to the treating institution's guidelines and requirements for such
             procedure. Biopsy cannot be performed less than ten days before treatment start.

          -  The subject has disease that is not amenable to a locoregional treatment approach (eg,
             transplant, surgery, radiofrequency ablation, TACE)

          -  Patients must have documented disease progression following at least 1 and no more
             than 2 prior systemic regimens for advanced disease (nonresectable or metastatic), the
             last of which includes immune checkpoint inhibitors. Alternatively, eligible patients
             may have experienced an immune-related, requiring treatment discontinuation.

          -  Recovery to ≤ Grade 1 from toxicities related to any prior treatments, unless the
             adverse events are clinically not significant and/or stable on supportive therapy

          -  Age ≥ 18 years old on the day of consent

          -  ECOG performance status of 0 or 1 (See Appendix V)

          -  Adequate hematologic function, based upon meeting the following laboratory criteria
             within 7 days before treatment beginning:

               -  a. absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1200/mm3 (≥ 1.2 x 109/L)

               -  b. platelets ≥ 60,000/mm3 (≥ 60 x 109/L)

               -  c. hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dL (≥ 80 g/L)

          -  Adequate renal function, based upon meeting the following laboratory criteria: serum
             creatinine ≤ 1.5 × upper limit of normal or calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 40
             mL/min (using the Cockroft-Gault equation: (140 - age) x weight (kg)/(serum creatinine
             × 72 [mg/dL]) for males. (For females multiply by 0.85)

          -  Child-Pugh Score of A (See Appendix IV)

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 2 mg/dL within 7 days before treatment start

          -  Serum albumin ≥ 2.8 g/dL (≥ 28 g/L) within 7 days before treatment start

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 5.0 upper limit
             of normal (ULN)

          -  Antiviral therapy per local standard of care if active hepatitis B (HBV) infection

          -  Capable of understanding and complying with the protocol requirements and signed
             informed consent

          -  Sexually active fertile subjects and their partners must agree to use medically
             accepted methods of contraception (eg, barrier methods, including male condom, female
             condom, or diaphragm with spermicidal gel) during the course of the study and for 4
             months after the last dose of study treatment

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must not be pregnant at screening. Females
             of childbearing potential are defined as premenopausal females capable of becoming
             pregnant (ie, females who have had any evidence of menses in the past 12 months, with
             the exception of those who had prior hysterectomy). However, women who have been
             amenorrheic for 12 or more months are still considered to be of childbearing potential
             if the amenorrhea is possibly due to prior chemotherapy, antiestrogens, ovarian
             suppression, low body weight, or other reasons

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Fibrolamellar carcinoma or mixed hepatocellular cholangiocarcinoma

          -  Child-Pugh score of B or C

          -  Any type of anticancer agent (including investigational) within 2 weeks before
             treatment start

          -  Radiation therapy within 4 weeks (2 weeks for radiation for bone metastases) or
             radionuclide treatment (eg, I-131 or Y-90) within 6 weeks of treatment start. Subject
             is excluded if there are any clinically relevant ongoing complications from prior
             radiation therapy

          -  Prior cabozantinib treatment

          -  Known brain metastases or cranial epidural disease unless adequately treated with
             radiotherapy and/or surgery (including radiosurgery) and stable for at least 3 months
             before treatment start. Eligible subjects must be without corticosteroid treatment at
             the time of treatment start

          -  Concomitant anticoagulation, at therapeutic doses, with anticoagulants such as
             warfarin or warfarin-related agents, low molecular weight heparin (LMWH), thrombin or
             coagulation factor X (FXa) inhibitors, or antiplatelet agents (eg, clopidogrel).
             Low-dose aspirin for cardioprotection (per local applicable guidelines), low-dose
             warfarin (≤ 1 mg/day), and low-dose LMWH are permitted

          -  The subject has uncontrolled, significant intercurrent or recent illness including,
             but not limited to, the following conditions:

          -  a. Cardiovascular disorders including:

               -  i. Symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, or serious
                  cardiac arrhythmias

               -  ii. Uncontrolled hypertension defined as sustained BP &gt; 150 mm Hg systolic, or &gt;
                  100 mm Hg diastolic despite optimal antihypertensive treatment

               -  iii. Stroke (including TIA), myocardial infarction, or other ischemic event
                  within 6 months before treatment start.

          -  iv. Thromboembolic event within 3 months before treatment start. Subjects with
             thromboses of portal/hepatic vasculature attributed to underlying liver disease and/or
             liver tumor are eligible

          -  b. Gastrointestinal (GI) disorders including those associated with a high risk of
             perforation or fistula formation:

               -  i. Tumors invading the GI tract, active peptic ulcer disease, inflammatory bowel
                  disease (eg, Crohn's disease), diverticulitis, cholecystitis, symptomatic
                  cholangitis or appendicitis, acute pancreatitis or acute obstruction of the
                  pancreatic duct or common bile duct, or gastric outlet obstruction

               -  ii. Abdominal fistula, GI perforation, bowel obstruction, intra-abdominal abscess
                  within 6 months before treatment start

               -  Note: Complete healing of an intra-abdominal abscess must be confirmed prior to
                  treatment start

          -  c. Major surgery within 2 months before treatment start. Complete healing from major
             surgery must have occurred 1 month before treatment start. Complete healing from minor
             surgery (eg, simple excision, tooth extraction) must have occurred at least 7 days
             before treatment start. Subjects with clinically relevant complications from prior
             surgery are not eligible

          -  d. Cavitating pulmonary lesion(s) or endobronchial disease

          -  e. Lesion invading a major blood vessel including, but not limited to: inferior vena
             cava, pulmonary artery, or aorta. Subjects with lesions invading the portal
             vasculature are eligible

          -  f. Clinically significant bleeding risk including the following within 3 months of
             treatment start: hematuria, hematemesis, hemoptysis of &gt;0.5 teaspoon (&gt;2.5 mL) of red
             blood, or other signs indicative of pulmonary hemorrhage, or history of other
             significant bleeding if not due to reversible external factors

          -  g. Other clinically significant disorders such as:

               -  i. Active infection requiring systemic treatment, known infection with human
                  immunodeficiency virus (HIV), or known acquired immunodeficiency syndrome
                  (AIDS)-related illness. Subjects with active hepatitis virus infection controlled
                  with antiviral therapy are eligible

               -  ii. Serious non-healing wound/ulcer/bone fracture

               -  iii. Malabsorption syndrome

               -  iv. Uncompensated/symptomatic hypothyroidism

               -  v. Requirement for hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis

               -  vi. History of solid organ transplantation

               -  vii. Rare hereditary problems of galactose intolerance, the Lapp lactase
                  deficiency or glucose-galactose malabsorption

          -  Subjects with untreated or incompletely treated varices with bleeding or high risk for
             bleeding. Subjects treated with adequate endoscopic therapy (according to
             institutional standards)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorenza Rimassa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lorenza Rimassa, MD</last_name>
    <phone>02 8224</phone>
    <phone_ext>4573</phone_ext>
    <email>lorenza.rimassa@humanitas.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nicola Personeni, MD</last_name>
    <phone>02 8224</phone>
    <phone_ext>4516</phone_ext>
    <email>nicola.personeni@humanitas.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituto Clinico Humanitas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milano</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lorenza Rimassa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02 8224</phone>
      <phone_ext>4573</phone_ext>
      <email>lorenza.rimassa@humanitas.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Nicola Personeni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02 8224</phone>
      <phone_ext>4516</phone_ext>
      <email>nicola.personeni@humanitas.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

