<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04432376</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MZ-0120-ESP3-052</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04432376</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of Miconazole Oil Versus Vehicle on Fungal Infection of the Ear Canal (Otomycosis)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-blind, Phase III Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Miconazole Oil Versus Vehicle Oil in the Treatment of Otomycosis, Followed by an Open-label Safety Evaluation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hill Dermaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abond CRO Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hill Dermaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study involves two sequential portions, a randomized, double-blind portion and an
      open-label portion, to evaluate the efficacy and safety of Miconazole oil 2% versus its
      Vehicle in the treatment of fungal infection of the outer ear canal (Otomycosis). The
      subjects randomized in the first portion of the study will have active fungal infection of
      the ear(s) and will be treated with either Miconazole Oil or the Vehicle for 14 days twice
      daily, 5 drops into the ear(s) per dose. The subjects enrolled in the open-label portion of
      the study may or may not have active fungal infection of the ear(s), and will be given the
      Miconazole Oil active drug following the same application of 5 drops into the ear(s) twice
      daily for 14 days.

      The intention of the study is to evaluate the efficacy of Miconazol Oil on fungal infection
      of the ears when applied using 5 drops into the ear(s) twice daily for 14 days continuously.
      This study also intends to show safety of Miconazole Oil 5 drops into each ear twice a day
      for 14 consecutive days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be conducted in 2 separate, sequential portions:

        1. Enrollment A, which will consist of 2 treatment periods as follows and will be conducted
           in subjects with otomycosis:

             1. A randomized, double-blind, parallel-group treatment period. This treatment period
                will be referred to as the &quot;Randomization Period&quot; and will be followed by:

             2. An optional, open-label treatment period with miconazole oil. This treatment period
                will be referred to as the &quot;Optional Open-label Extension.&quot;

        2. Enrollment B, which will commence after completion of Enrollment A and will consist of
           open-label treatment with miconazole oil in subjects who will not be required to have
           signs and symptoms of otomycosis.

      The study will start with Enrollment A, with an estimated 220 male or female subjects with
      otomycosis. Subjects will be randomly assigned in a 1:1 ratio to receive miconazole oil or
      vehicle (placebo), for 14 days. The study drug will be administered as 5 drops per ear at ~30
      mg per drop instilled into the external ear canal of the ear(s) affected by otomycosis.

      In the Randomization Period, both the subject and the investigator and study staff are
      blinded to the contents of the study drug.

      At Screening/Baseline (Day 1), assessment of the signs and symptoms of otomycosis (pruritus,
      debris, visual examination for presence of fungal elements, and aural fullness), evaluation
      of medical history, pregnancy screening in female of childbearing potential, and, prior and
      concomitant medications, will be collected. Subjects with positive signs and symptoms of
      otomycosis and who meet all eligibility criteria will enter the study. Fungal culture of
      affected ear(s) will be taken, debris will be cleaned from the affected ear(s), and subject
      will be randomized and study drug dispensed. Treatment will be for 14 days. Day 8 On
      Treatment Visit will include clinical evaluation of otomycosis, cleaning of ear(s), and
      assessment of AEs and concomitant medications, and continue treatment up to Day 14. Day 15
      End of Treatment Visit will include clinical evaluation of otomycosis and fungal culture, AEs
      and concomitant medications assessed. Day 22 Test of Cure Visit is an assessment of clinical
      signs and symptoms of otomycosis and fungal culture, AEs and concomitant medications
      assessed, and urine pregnancy test performed in women of childbearing potential.

      The Optional Open-label Extension period will allow subjects to get miconazole oil for 14
      days. No unblinding of the subject's treatment in the Randomization Period will occur at this
      time.

      Enrollment B will begin at or after the conclusion of Enrollment A. Male or female subjects
      will be enrolled to receive miconazole oil to use for 14 days and will be evaluated for
      safety.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two phases; initial is randomized double-blind active vs placebo on a pre-determined number of subjects with otomycosis, to finish before starting second phase. Second phase is open-label use on diseased or healthy subjects to evaluate safety. Subjects from initial phase may crossover to second phase open-label if they meet the requirements, and new diseased or healthy subjects meeting requirements may enroll in this open-label phase.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Clinical Investigators, study staff and subjects randomized to the initial phase of the study are blinded to active drug and placebo.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with Therapeutic Cure</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days from first day of drug application</time_frame>
    <description>&quot;&quot;therapeutic cure&quot; is &quot;mycological cure&quot; plus &quot;clinical cure. Mycological cure is a negative mycological culture, and clinical cure is the absence of all otomycosis signs and symptoms according to the scales for each individual sign or symptom.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with mycological cure</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days from first day of drug application</time_frame>
    <description>Negative fungal culture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with clinical cure</measure>
    <time_frame>21 days from first day of drug application</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of all otomycosis signs and symptoms according to the scales for each individual sign or symptom</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">390</enrollment>
  <condition>Otomycosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with miconazole 2% oil, 5 drops into each ear twice daily for 14 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment with the vehicle oil, placebo, 5 drops into each ear twice daily for 14 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Open-label treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Application of miconazole 2% oil, 5 drops into each ear twice daily for 14 consecutive days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>miconazole 2% oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug treatment of otomycosis for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Open-label treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>active treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vehicle oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo treatment of otomycosis for 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo treatment arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Randomized blinded initial phase of study:

          -  Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating females with a clinical diagnosis of uncomplicated
             otomycosis of the external ear only,

          -  Intact tympanic membrane in the ear(s) to be treated with study drug,

          -  In general good health as determined by medical examination and medical history,

          -  Free of clinically significant disease, including diabetes mellitus, that is not
             well-controlled or that could interfere with the study.

        Open-label second phase of study:

          -  Male or non-pregnant, non-lactating females with an intact tympanic membrane in the
             ear(s) to be treated with study drug,

          -  In general good health as determined by medical examination and medical history,

          -  Free of clinically significant disease, including diabetes mellitus, that is not
             well-controlled or that could interfere with the study.

        Exclusion Criteria::

          -  Presence of dermatoses or conditions of the ear that may interfere with evaluation of
             otomycosis or with safety evaluations, including concomitant otic infections that
             require antimicrobial treatment,

          -  Disease that has spread beyond the external ear(s), or pre-existing skin atrophy of
             the affected ear(s);

          -  Tympanostomy tube or perforated tympanic membrane;

          -  History of prior surgery directly affecting and compromising the external auditory
             canal and/or tympanic membrane, except for prior tympanostomy tube(s) that have
             already been removed and completely healed;

          -  Use of any topical medicated treatments for otomycosis within 14 days of study entry;

          -  Use of any systemic antifungal therapy within 28 days of study entry, warfarin within
             28 days of study entry, immunosuppressive or immune-stimulating drugs within 28 days
             of study entry, or systemic steroids within 3 months of study entry;

          -  Fever of ≥100°F at study entry;

          -  Otomycosis that has been unresponsive to previous antifungal treatment;

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any of the components in the test formulation;

          -  Participation in another investigative trial within 28 days of study entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arnaldo Rivera, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Adelglass, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Research Your Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Quyen T Nguyen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kenneth Hodge, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Advanced ENT and Allergy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Dennis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DelRicht Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sammy Vaught, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lake ENT &amp; FPS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Fitzgibbon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>OnSite Clinical Solutions</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John Ansley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Carolina ENT</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall Ow, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DaVinci Research LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Brandt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DelRicht Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oscar DeValle, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>West Houston Clinical Research Service</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linda Woo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Head and Neck Surgery Specialists</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Miglena Entcheva, MD</last_name>
    <phone>616-892-3744</phone>
    <email>mentcheva@abondcro.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Carolyn Wright, MSRA</last_name>
    <phone>616-892-3765</phone>
    <email>cwright@abondcro.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Otomycosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Miconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

