<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04430335</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00066444</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>WFBCCC 01220</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA012197</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04430335</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telephone-Based Intervention to Treat Depression and Anxiety in Hispanic Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cultural and Linguistic Adaptation of a Telephone-Based Intervention to Treat Depression and Anxiety in Hispanic Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research is to assess the feasibility of administering a telephone-based
      intervention to treat depression and anxiety in Hispanic cancer survivors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives

        -  To assess the feasibility (participation, accrual, retention, adherence) of
           administering the intervention in Hispanic cancer survivors.

        -  To culturally adapt an existing behavioral intervention for cancer survivors based on
           stakeholder feedback.

      Exploratory Objectives

        -  To summarize emotional distress (anxiety, depressive symptoms) and fear of recurrence in
           these post-treatment Hispanic cancer survivors.

        -  To describe the therapy process in terms of satisfaction with treatment and the
           therapist-participant relationship.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participation Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>To determine participation rate, investigators will track the total number of individuals approached, the number of individuals who met all eligibility criteria and percent who agree to participate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Accrual Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Accrual rates will be calculated by calculating the mean number of participants recruited per month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention Rate - Proportion of Completed Visits</measure>
    <time_frame>13 weeks after the start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Study retention will be estimated by the proportion of participants who complete the Week 13 visit. Drop-out is defined as 100% minus the dropout %</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence - Proportion of Completed Therapy Sessions</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention adherence will be estimated as the mean percentage of therapy or check-in sessions each participant completes. Participants must complete at least 9 of the 12 sessions (75%) to be considered adherent.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety Questionnaire - General Anxiety Disorder (GAD)-7</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 7 weeks and 13 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The General Anxiety Disorder (GAD)-7 is a self-report measure of DSM-IV symptoms of general anxiety disorder. Participants rate 7 questions on a scale of 0 (not at all), 1 (several days), 2 (more than half the days) and 3 (nearly every day); one additional question assesses the interference of these symptoms with functioning. The first 7 questions are summed to create a total score. Scoring range is 0-21 with the higher score indicating a higher level of anxiety (scores 0 to less than or equal to 9 = no/mild anxiety; scores greater than or equal to 10 to less than or equal to 14 = moderate anxiety; scores greater than or equal to 15 to 21 = severe anxiety).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive Symptoms Questionnaire - Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ)-9</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, 7 weeks and 13 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ)-9 is a self-report measure of DSM-IV symptoms of Major Depressive Disorder. Participants rate how often they have experienced nine symptoms over the past 2 weeks on a scale of 0 (not at all); 1 (several days), 2 (more than half the days) and 3 (nearly every day). Responses are summed, with higher scores indicating greater depressive symptomatology. Scoring scale = 0-27 (scores 0 to less than or equal to 7 = no/mild depressive symptoms; scores greater than or equal to 8 to less than or equal to 14 = moderate depressive symptoms; scores greater than or equal to 15 to 27 = severe depressive symptoms)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and 13 weeks after start of intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory (FCRI; severity subscale) will be used to measure self-reported fear of recurrence. This 9-item subscale measures the presence and severity of the intrusive thoughts or images associated with the fear of recurrence. Scoring scale ranges from 0 (not at all or never) to 4 (a great deal or all of the time). Score ranges from 0-36. The higher the score, the greater the participants' fear of recurrence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Survivorship</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Depression, Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone-Based Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with moderate or severe anxiety and/or depressive symptoms will participate in the telephone-based intervention that consists of the CBT workbook (15 minutes daily to complete exercises), plus psychotherapy delivered by telephone with a licensed bilingual mental health provider (45-50 minute sessions weekly).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone interview</intervention_name>
    <description>Interested participants will complete a telephone interview to determine eligibility for the study. If found to be eligible for the study, participants will be registered and set up a time to speak with an assigned study coach.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone-Based Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will speak with their assigned coach over the phone for 12 weeks to discuss the cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) study workbook and provide feedback. CBT is a type of treatment that teaches people different ways to handle anxiety and/or depressive symptoms, such as by relaxing the body, changing thoughts, and solving problems. Participants will receive a workbook focused on teaching these strategies.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone-Based Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion: age?18 years;

          -  Self-identify as Hispanic ethnicity

          -  Score greater than or equal to 10 on the General Anxiety Disorder (GAD)-7 and/or
             greater than or equal to 8 on the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ)-9;

          -  History of treated (newly diagnosed or recurrent) cancers (Stage I, II, or III) or any
             stage lymphoma (Hodgkin's or non-Hodgkin's)

          -  6-60 months post-treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy, and/or
             maintenance therapies) for cancer. The timeframe applies to the most recent completion
             of treatment if a participant had a cancer recurrence. It is acceptable to be on
             hormonal therapies.

          -  Must be able to speak, read, and understand Spanish or English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current psychotherapy [regular appointment(s) with a mental health provider within the
             last 30 days]

          -  Self-reported active alcohol or substance abuse within the last 30 days

          -  Past history of prostate cancer or non-Hodgkin's lymphoma with only active
             surveillance (i.e., no surgery, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy)

          -  Progressive cancer

          -  Global cognitive impairment based on self-reported diagnosis of dementia.

          -  Self-reported psychotic symptoms in the last 30 days (Item in Screening Form: &quot;Have
             you seen things that aren't really there or have you heard voices when no one else was
             around within the last 30 days?&quot;)

          -  Active suicidal ideation with plan and intent

          -  Any change in psychotropic medications within the last 30 days

          -  Hearing loss that would preclude participating in telephone sessions (determined by
             brief hearing assessment administered by research staff). Individuals who can
             compensate for hearing loss through the use of a hearing device or TDD phone, and
             through the use of such devices are able to communicate with the study therapist by
             telephone, will be included. If the therapist cannot communicate with the participant
             by telephone, the participant will be excluded.

          -  Failure/inability/unwillingness to provide names and contact information for two
             family members or friends to serve as emergency contacts during the course of the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne C Danhauer, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Meg O'Mara, MHA</last_name>
    <phone>336-713-6525</phone>
    <email>megreen@wakehealth.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meg O'Mara, MHA</last_name>
      <email>megreen@wakehealth.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Suzanne C Danhauer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

