<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04431960</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H20-0035</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2020-67018-30852</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04431960</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blackcurrant Modifies Gut Microbiota and Reduces Osteoporosis Risk</brief_title>
  <official_title>Blackcurrant Modifies Gut Microbiota and Reduces the Risk of Postmenopausal Osteoporosis: A Pilot Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Connecticut</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Connecticut</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim to evaluate the effects of blackcurrant supplementation on changes in gut microbiome and
      bone mass in adult women.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Postmenopausal bone loss is a primary contributor to osteoporosis and osteoporotic fractures
      in adult women. Overall goal of this project is to evaluate the effects of blackcurrant (BC)
      supplementation on changes in gut microbiome and bone mass in adult women. For this purpose,
      the investigators will conduct a pilot randomized placebo-controlled clinical trial with BC
      supplementation for 6 months in peri- and early postmenopausal women aged 45-60 years.

      The primary endpoint will be lumbar spine bone mineral density (BMD); secondary endpoints
      will be gut microbial Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes (F/B) ratio. To delineate the underlying
      mechanisms of the action, changes in biomarkers for bone metabolism, bone-related immune and
      endocrine systemic biomarkers by BC supplementation will be measured in plasma and peripheral
      blood derived mononuclear cells.

      The specific objectives of the study are to investigate the effects of BC extract on: 1) bone
      mass and bone remodeling markers; 2) changes in the gut microbiota abundance and composition,
      immune and endocrine biomarkers and their relationships with changes in bone mass.

      The proposed study will provide novel insight into whether and how BC consumption reduces the
      risk of postmenopausal bone loss in adult women and will improve understanding of the
      clinical roles of gut microbiome in postmenopausal bone loss. Findings from this study will
      help increase awareness of the bone health promoting effect of BC and motivate increased
      production of BC and other berry products in response to the increasing consumer demand.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The study participants will be randomly assigned to three groups and asked to consume 1 tablet containing 450 mg blackcurrant (BC) extract per capsule (low-BC Group), 2 capsules containing 450 mg BC extract per tablet (total 900 mg/day; high-BC Group), or 1 placebo capsule (Control Group) daily with breakfast meals for 6 months.
To avoid bone deterioration related to calcium and vitamin D deficiency, all participants will take a calcium citrate caplet daily that includes 400 mg calcium and 500 IU vitamin D (Bayer AG, Germany) beginning 2 weeks before the study and lasting for the duration of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The extract and placebo will have the identical shape and color and will be packaged into coded containers.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Lumbar spine bone mineral density (BMD)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in lumbar spine BMD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gut microbial Firmicutes/Bacteroidetes (F/B) ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in the gut microbial composition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentrations of plasma P1NP</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in plasma P1NP concentrations</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentrations of plasma CTX1</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in plasma CTX1 concentrations</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Hip and forearm BMD</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in hip and forearm BMD</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Lumbar spine, hip and forearm bone mineral content (BMC)</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in lumbar spine, hip and forearm BMC</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentrations of plasma IL-1β, IL-6, TNFα, Th17 and Treg</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in plasma concentrations of immune biomarkers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Concentrations of plasma IGF-1 and cGP</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>changes in plasma concentrations of endocrine biomarkers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Postmenopausal Osteoporosis</condition>
  <condition>Gut Microbiota</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>low-BC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>consume: 1) one tablet containing 450 mg blackcurrant (BC) extract per capsule and 2) one calcium citrate caplet containing 400 mg calcium and 500 IU vitamin D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high-BC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>consume: 1) two capsules containing 450 mg BC extract per tablet (total 900 mg/day) and 2) one calcium citrate caplet containing 400 mg calcium and 500 IU vitamin D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>consume: 1) one placebo capsule and 2) one calcium citrate caplet containing 400 mg calcium and 500 IU vitamin D</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>blackcurrant (BC) extract</intervention_name>
    <description>A calcium citrate caplet (Bayer AG, Germany) will be taken by all 3 groups to avoid bone deterioration related to calcium and vitamin D deficiency</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>high-BC Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>low-BC Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  perimenopausal or early postmenopausal women aged 45-60 years old

          -  not on HRT for at least one year before the initiation of the study

          -  maintaining normal exercise level (&lt;7 h/wk) and willing to avoid exercise 24-h prior
             to blood and stool sampling and 12-h prior to bone measurements

          -  willing to ingest a dietary BC supplement or placebo (up to 900 mg/day, two 450 mg
             capsules) as well as 400 mg calcium and 500 IU vitamin D daily

          -  willing to avoid other dietary supplements for the duration of the study

          -  willing to avoid intake of foods extremely rich in anthocyanins and fermented dairy
             products containing viable Bifidobacteria or Lactobacilli

          -  willing to have 3 blood draws, 2 stool collections, and 2 bone scans

          -  willing to take urine pregnancy test if they are perimenopausal.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  those with metabolic bone disease, renal disease, cancer, cardiovascular disease,
             diabetes mellitus, respiratory disease, gastrointestinal disease, liver disease or
             other chronic diseases

          -  those with hypertension or on drugs that lower blood pressure

          -  those with planned surgery during the study period or within 2 weeks of ending the
             intervention

          -  taking medications that alter bleeding (such as antiplatelets or anticoagulants) or
             those with a bleeding disorder

          -  taking a phenothiazine drug (most commonly used for nausea or mental health
             conditions)

          -  having a sensitivity or allergy to any of ingredients for the placebo (rice powder)
             and calcium/D supplement (calcium citrate, polyethylene glycol, croscarmellose sodium,
             hydroxypropyl methylcellulose, magnesium stearate, oligofructose enriched inulin,
             propylene glycol dicaprylate/dicaprate, talc, titanium dioxide, vitamin D3)

          -  heavy smokers (&gt;20 cigarettes/day)

          -  perimenopausal women with any chance or plan of pregnancy

          -  taking prescription medications known to alter bone and Ca metabolism such as
             calcitonin, bisphosphonates, raloxifene within 3 months before the start of the study

          -  taking anabolic agents such as parathyroid hormone, growth hormone, or steroids within
             3 months before the start of the study

          -  planning any procedure that includes iodine, barium or nuclear medicine isotopes in
             next 7 months

          -  alcohol consumption exceeding 2 drinks/day (approximately 14 g ethanol per drink) or a
             total of 12/week

          -  UConn students and/or employees who any key personnel teach or who report to any key
             personnel

          -  study key personnel, spouses of key personnel, or dependents/relatives of any key
             personnel.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>perimenopausal or early postmenopausal women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ock Chun, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>18604866275</phone>
    <email>ock.chun@uconn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Junichi Sakaki</last_name>
    <phone>19084328552</phone>
    <email>junichi.sakaki@uconn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Connecticut Department of Nutritional Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Storrs</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06269</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ock Chun</last_name>
      <phone>860-486-6275</phone>
      <email>ock.chun@uconn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Junichi Sakaki</last_name>
      <phone>19084328552</phone>
      <email>junichi.sakaki@uconn.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elaine Lee, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Adams, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Connecticut</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ock Chun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>blackcurrant</keyword>
  <keyword>gut microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>menopause</keyword>
  <keyword>bone aging</keyword>
  <keyword>women</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis, Postmenopausal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Once research proceedings and manuscripts are published we will make our results available both to the community of scientists interested in postmenopausal osteoporosis and to those studying the biology of inflammation-induced bone resorption to avoid unintentional duplication of research.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Unlimited time after papers are published.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Our plan of sharing of data generated by this project includes the following:
Presentations at national scientific meetings. From the projects, it is expected that approximately two presentations at national meetings would be appropriate.
Publication in peer-reviewed journals. It is our explicit intention that the study findings and key data will be placed in a readily accessible public database. All efforts will be made to rapidly release data through publication of results as quickly as possible following our analysis of the experiment data. Data used in publications will be released in a timely manner.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

