<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04439240</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2020-03213</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2020-03213</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EAY131-W</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>EAY131-W</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA180820</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U24CA196172</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04439240</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing AZD4547 as a Potential Targeted Treatment in Cancers With FGFR Genetic Changes (MATCH-Subprotocol W)</brief_title>
  <official_title>MATCH Treatment Subprotocol W: Phase II Study of AZD4547 in Patients With Tumors With Aberrations in the FGFR Pathway</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II MATCH treatment trial identifies the effects of AZD4547 in patients whose
      cancer has genetic changes called FGFR gene alterations. AZD4547 may stop the growth of
      cancer cells by blocking FGFR proteins which may be needed for cell growth. Researchers hope
      to learn if AZD4547 will shrink this type of cancer or stop its growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

      I. To evaluate the proportion of patients with objective response (OR) to targeted study
      agent(s) in patients with advanced refractory cancers/lymphomas/multiple myeloma.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the proportion of patients alive and progression free at 6 months of treatment
      with targeted study agent in patients with advanced refractory cancers/lymphomas/multiple
      myeloma.

      II. To evaluate time until death or disease progression. III. To identify potential
      predictive biomarkers beyond the genomic alteration by which treatment is assigned or
      resistance mechanisms using additional genomic, ribonucleic acid (RNA), protein and
      imaging-based assessment platforms.

      IV. To assess whether radiomic phenotypes obtained from pre-treatment imaging and changes
      from pre- through post-therapy imaging can predict objective response and progression free
      survival and to evaluate the association between pre-treatment radiomic phenotypes and
      targeted gene mutation patterns of tumor biopsy specimens.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive FGFR inhibitor AZD4547 (AZD4547) orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 1-28.
      Cycles repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months if less than 2
      years from study entry, and then every 6 months for year 3 from study entry.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 31, 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 6, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Tumor assessments occurred at baseline, then every 2 cycles for the first 26 cycles, and every 3 cycles thereafter until disease progression, up to 3 years post registration</time_frame>
    <description>ORR is defined as the percentage of patients whose tumors have a complete or partial response to treatment among eligible and treated patients. Objective response rate is defined consistent with Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors version 1.1, the Cheson (2014) criteria for lymphoma patients, and the Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology criteria for glioblastoma patients. For each treatment arm, 90% two-sided binomial exact confidence interval will be calculated for ORR.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed every 3 months for =&lt; 2 years and every 6 months for year 3</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as time from treatment start date to date of death from any cause. Patients alive at the time of analysis are censored at last contact date. OS will be evaluated specifically for each drug (or step) using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, then every 2 cycles for the first 26 cycles, and every 3 cycles thereafter until disease progression, up to 3 years post registration</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as time from treatment start date to date of progression or death from any cause, whichever occurs first. PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Advanced Malignant Solid Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Hematopoietic and Lymphoid Cell Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Malignant Solid Neoplasm</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Plasma Cell Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (AZD4547)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive AZD4547 PO BID on days 1-28. Cycles repeat every 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FGFR Inhibitor AZD4547</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (AZD4547)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AZD4547</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have met applicable eligibility criteria in the Master MATCH Protocol
             prior to registration to treatment subprotocol

          -  Patients must have FGFR 1-3 mutation or translocation as determined by the MATCH
             screening assessment

          -  Patients must have an electrocardiogram (ECG) within 8 weeks prior to treatment
             assignment and must have no clinically important abnormalities in rhythm, conduction
             or morphology of resting ECG (e.g. complete left bundle branch block, third degree
             heart block)

          -  Patients must have an echocardiogram (ECHO) or a nuclear study (multigated acquisition
             scan [MUGA] or First Pass) within 4 weeks prior to registration to treatment and must
             not have a left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; institutional lower limit of
             normal (LLN). If the LLN is not defined at a site, the LVEF must be &gt; 50% for the
             patient to be eligible

          -  Patients must have a pre-study eye exam by an ophthalmologist. Patients with current
             evidence of corneal or retinal disorder/keratopathy are excluded

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must not have known hypersensitivity to AZD4547 or compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition

          -  Patients must not have received prior FGFR specific inhibitors (e.g. BGJ398,
             erdafitinib, BAY1163877, LY2874455). Prior non-selective FGFR inhibitor treatment
             (e.g. pazopanib, dovitinib, ponatinib, brivanib, lucitanib, lenvatinib) will be
             allowed

          -  Patients must not have any history of or current evidence of renal or endocrine
             alterations of calcium/phosphate homeostasis, or history of or current evidence of
             extensive tissue calcification (by evaluation of the clinician), including but not
             limited to, the soft tissue, kidneys, intestine, myocardium and lung with the
             exception of calcified lymph nodes and asymptomatic vascular calcification per
             investigators' judgment

          -  Patients must not be currently using medications that can elevate serum phosphorous
             and/or calcium levels

               -  Medications that increase serum calcium should be avoided. Over the counter
                  calcium supplements, antacids that contain calcium (Tums) and vitamin D
                  supplements (cholecalciferol and ergocalciferol) should be avoided. Prescription
                  medications including lithium, hydrochlorothiazide and chlorthalidone must be
                  used with caution

               -  Medications that increase serum phosphate should be avoided. Over the counter
                  laxatives that contain phosphate such as Fleets Oral or Fleets enema and Miralax
                  should be avoided
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Young Kwang Chae</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ECOG-ACRIN Cancer Research Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

