<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03603119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PONV prophylaxis</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03603119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Midazolam Versus Dexamethasone-ondansetron in Preventing Postoperative Nausea-vomiting for Laparoscopic Surgeries</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Comparison of Midazolam Versus Dexamethasone-ondansetron in Preventing Postoperative Nausea-vomiting in High Risk Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Surgeries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences, India</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative nausea and vomiting(PONV) affects 11 to 60 % of patients undergoing surgery and
      is a major cause of postoperative morbidity. Risk factors include female gender, non smokers,
      postoperative use of opioids and a past history of PONV. The simplified Apfel risk score is
      used to identify patients at risk for PONV. PONV prophylaxis is provided intraoperatively to
      patients with 2 or more risk factors. In spite of numerous drugs available, control of PONV
      remains a difficult task. Midazolam is a commonly used drug perioperatively for its
      anxiolytic and sedative properties. It decreases analgesic requirement and has also been
      found to have an antiemetic effect. This present study is designed to compare the
      prophylactic use of iv midazolam with a commonly used combination of
      dexamethasone-ondansetron in high risk patients (as defined by the modified Apfel score)
      undergoing laparoscopic surgeries.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      After Institutional Ethical Committee approval and written informed consent, 120 adult
      patients will be recruited for the study if they satisfy the inclusion and exclusion criteria
      as mentioned later. Consent will be obtained from the patients themselves. Standard protocol
      for administration of anaesthesia will be followed in all patients which is briefly
      described. All patients will receive general anaesthesia and will be induced with Propofol
      titrated to effect. Intraoperatively, isoflurane will be used as maintenance agent and
      vecuronium or atracurium as non depolarizing muscle relaxant. For analgesia, patients will
      receive intraoperative fentanyl.

      For the purpose of the study, patients will be randomized into two groups depending upon a
      computer generated randomized sheet. Group A will receive 8mg of dexamethasone i.v. after
      anaesthesia induction and 4 mg of ondansetron i.v. 30 minutes prior to the end of surgery.
      Patients in Group B will be administered 2 mg of midazolam i.v. 30 minutes prior to the end
      of surgery. Time to achieve Post anaesthesia discharge score( PADSS) of ≥9 will be noted.
      Patients will be asked to report any incidence of nausea, retching or vomiting for the first
      24 hours after surgery. The incidence of PONV and the amount of rescue antiemetic received
      will be noted at 2 hours and at 24 hours postoperatively. PONV will be scored based on the
      PONV Impact Scale score questionnaire (mentioned in the proforma)12. Rescue antiemetics will
      be administered in case the patient complains of PONV in accordance with American society of
      anesthesiologists (ASA) guidelines. The first line of rescue in Group A will be 10 mg of iv
      metaclopromide. Antihistaminics will be the second line of rescue antiemetic. In group B the
      first line of antiemetic will be 4 mg of ondansetron i.v. 10 mg of iv metaclopromide will be
      second line of rescue drug.

      Study period : It is estimated that the study will be completed within one year Sample size
      Assuming a reduction in 45 % in the incidence of PONV, with α error of 0.05 and β of 0.02, we
      would require 60 patients in each group i.e. a total of 120 patients.13 Intervention: For
      administration of PONV prophylaxis, patients will be randomized into two groups depending
      upon a computer generated randomized sheet. Group A will receive 8mg of dexamethasone i.v.
      after anaesthesia induction and 4 mg of ondansetron i.v. 30 minutes prior to the end of
      surgery. Patients in Group B will be administered 2 mg of midazolam i.v. 30 minutes prior to
      the end of surgery.

      Monitoring and assessment: Patients will be monitored 24 hours post operatively. Any
      complaints of nausea and/vomiting will be noted and rescue antiemetic will be administered as
      per the guidelines
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>concealed envelopes</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative nausea vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>the incidence of postoperative nausea and/or vomiting within first 24 hours postoperatively</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rescue antiemetic</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of antiemetic used within the first 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to achieve PADSS&gt;9</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Time taken to achieve a Post anaesthesia discharge score of ≥9</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of PON, POV, PONV at 2 hours and PON and POV at 24</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexamethasone-ondansetron</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Midazolam</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal saline, Midazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>2 cc normal saline i.v. after anaesthesia induction.2 mg of injection midazolam intravenous 30 minutes prior to the end of surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone, ondansetron</intervention_name>
    <description>8mg of dexamethasone i.v. after anaesthesia induction and 4 mg of ondansetron i.v. 30 minutes prior to the end of surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients more than 18 years of age

          -  Patients belonging to ASA-PS (American society of anesthesiologists Physical status) 1
             or 2

          -  Patients with 2 or more risk factors for developing PONV undergoing laparoscopic
             surgeries

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anticipated difficult airway

          -  Obesity (body mass index &gt;30 kg.m2),

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Patients with ASA - PS more than 2

          -  Consumption of an agent with anti-emetic properties within 24 h prior to commencement
             of the study.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to midazolam, ondansetron or dexamethasone

          -  Patients not giving consent.

          -  Patients with psychiatric illness or mental retardation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelika Prakash, DM</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of liver and biliary sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Liver and Biliary Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <state>Delhi</state>
        <zip>110070</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Ondansetron</keyword>
  <keyword>Midazolam</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>High risk</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ondansetron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

