<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03605498</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201705826</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03605498</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>OR PathTrac (Tracking Intra-operative Bacterial Transmission)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigation of Novel Technology to Bring Genomic Analysis to the Patient Bedside to Systematically Track and Report on ESKAPE Bacterial Transmission in Today's Operating Room Environments</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sundara Reddy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>B. Braun Medical Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RDB Bioinformatics, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Iowa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Healthcare-associated infections occur frequently and are associated with patient harm. These
      infections are becoming more difficult to treat due to antibiotic resistance. It is important
      that healthcare facilities take the steps necessary to prevent the spread of resistant
      bacteria between patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Two patients undergoing sedation in a randomly selected operating room will be evaluated in a
      serial manner in order to detect transmission of pathogenic bacteria. Patient care will not
      change due to their participation in this study; the patients will undergo sedation and
      surgery according to usual practice. This study involves taking microbiology cultures from
      various places in the operating room before and after each procedure. Cultures will also be
      taken from the two patients after they are asleep and from their intravenous tubing. From
      both patients anesthesiologist, surgeon and their surgical team, cRNA, and nursing staff will
      also have cultures obtained. Each cultures will be de-identified and given a study ID number
      before transport to the research laboratory for microbiological assay. The patient's medical
      record will be reviewed for 30 days after surgery to surveil for documentation of a potential
      hospital acquired infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 12, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify transmission dynamics of pathogenic bacteria (i.e. Staph aureus).</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative period</time_frame>
    <description>Focus on how Staph aureus is transmitted in the operating room by identifying key areas of origin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative clonal transmission of Staph aureus.</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative period</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor locations throughout the operating room to document clonal transmission from the area of origin.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identify the modes of transmission of pathogenic bacteria ((i.e. Staph aureus).</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative period</time_frame>
    <description>If transmission of Staph aureus from the site of origin to another site in the operating room arena is documented, identify the modes of transmission.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitor for post operative healthcare associated infections.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor for the presence or absence of healthcare associated infection after undergoing an operative procedure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surveil for molecular links between pathogenic organisms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Seek to identify molecular links between causative organisms of infection and bacteria found in the operating room at the time of surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">83</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Infections</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      The bacterial cultures can be kept and analyzed at a later date to determine how they have
      transformed into antibiotic resistant organisms.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will be surgical patients requiring peripheral intravenous and/or
        central venous catheter access and undergoing gynecology/oncology, colorectal, open
        vascular, total joint or cardiovascular procedures.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Require peripheral intravenous and/or central venous catheter placement

          -  Undergoing gynecology/oncology, colorectal, open vascular, total joint or
             cardiovascular procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Less than 18 years of age

          -  Does not require peripheral intravenous and/or central venous catheter placement

          -  Patient refusal to participate

          -  Incarceration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>105 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sundara Reddy, MBBS, FRCA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa Hospitals and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdc.gov/winnablebattles/report/progress-targets.html</url>
    <description>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention-Winnable Battles Targets</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2016/p0303-superbugs.html</url>
    <description>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention-Superbugs threaten hospital patients</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vogel TR, Dombrovskiy VY, Lowry SF. Impact of infectious complications after elective surgery on hospital readmission and late deaths in the U.S. Medicare population. Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2012 Oct;13(5):307-11. doi: 10.1089/sur.2012.116. Epub 2012 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23082877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koff MD, Brown JR, Marshall EJ, O'Malley AJ, Jensen JT, Heard SO, Longtine K, O'Neill M, Longtine J, Houston D, Robison C, Moulton E, Patel HM, Loftus RW. Frequency of Hand Decontamination of Intraoperative Providers and Reduction of Postoperative Healthcare-Associated Infections: A Randomized Clinical Trial of a Novel Hand Hygiene System. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2016 Aug;37(8):888-95. doi: 10.1017/ice.2016.106. Epub 2016 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27267310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirkland KB, Briggs JP, Trivette SL, Wilkinson WE, Sexton DJ. The impact of surgical-site infections in the 1990s: attributable mortality, excess length of hospitalization, and extra costs. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 1999 Nov;20(11):725-30.</citation>
    <PMID>10580621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization. Antimicrobial Resistance. Global Report on Surveillance, WHO. 2014</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>German RR, Lee LM, Horan JM, Milstein RL, Pertowski CA, Waller MN; Guidelines Working Group Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Updated guidelines for evaluating public health surveillance systems: recommendations from the Guidelines Working Group. MMWR Recomm Rep. 2001 Jul 27;50(RR-13):1-35; quiz CE1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>18634202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boucher HW, Talbot GH, Bradley JS, Edwards JE, Gilbert D, Rice LB, Scheld M, Spellberg B, Bartlett J. Bad bugs, no drugs: no ESKAPE! An update from the Infectious Diseases Society of America. Clin Infect Dis. 2009 Jan 1;48(1):1-12. doi: 10.1086/595011. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19035777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Koff MD, Burchman CC, Schwartzman JD, Thorum V, Read ME, Wood TA, Beach ML. Transmission of pathogenic bacterial organisms in the anesthesia work area. Anesthesiology. 2008 Sep;109(3):399-407. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318182c855.</citation>
    <PMID>18719437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Brown JR, Koff MD, Reddy S, Heard SO, Patel HM, Fernandez PG, Beach ML, Corwin HL, Jensen JT, Kispert D, Huysman B, Dodds TM, Ruoff KL, Yeager MP. Multiple reservoirs contribute to intraoperative bacterial transmission. Anesth Analg. 2012 Jun;114(6):1236-48. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31824970a2. Epub 2012 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22467892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Koff MD, Brown JR, Patel HM, Jensen JT, Reddy S, Ruoff KL, Heard SO, Yeager MP, Dodds TM. The epidemiology of Staphylococcus aureus transmission in the anesthesia work area. Anesth Analg. 2015 Apr;120(4):807-18. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3182a8c16a.</citation>
    <PMID>24937345</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Koff MD, Brown JR, Patel HM, Jensen JT, Reddy S, Ruoff KL, Heard SO, Yeager MP, Dodds TM. The dynamics of Enterococcus transmission from bacterial reservoirs commonly encountered by anesthesia providers. Anesth Analg. 2015 Apr;120(4):827-36. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000123.</citation>
    <PMID>24937346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Brown JR, Patel HM, Koff MD, Jensen JT, Reddy S, Ruoff KL, Heard SO, Dodds TM, Beach ML, Yeager MP. Transmission dynamics of gram-negative bacterial pathogens in the anesthesia work area. Anesth Analg. 2015 Apr;120(4):819-26. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000000626.</citation>
    <PMID>25790209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mabit C, Marcheix PS, Mounier M, Dijoux P, Pestourie N, Bonnevialle P, Bonnomet F; French Society of Orthopaedic Surgery, Traumatology (SOFCOT). Impact of a surgical site infection (SSI) surveillance program in orthopedics and traumatology. Orthop Traumatol Surg Res. 2012 Oct;98(6):690-5. doi: 10.1016/j.otsr.2012.08.001. Epub 2012 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22986014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Muffly MK, Brown JR, Beach ML, Koff MD, Corwin HL, Surgenor SD, Kirkland KB, Yeager MP. Hand contamination of anesthesia providers is an important risk factor for intraoperative bacterial transmission. Anesth Analg. 2011 Jan;112(1):98-105. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e3181e7ce18. Epub 2010 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>20686007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Patel HM, Huysman BC, Kispert DP, Koff MD, Gallagher JD, Jensen JT, Rowlands J, Reddy S, Dodds TM, Yeager MP, Ruoff KL, Surgenor SD, Brown JR. Prevention of intravenous bacterial injection from health care provider hands: the importance of catheter design and handling. Anesth Analg. 2012 Nov;115(5):1109-19. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31826a1016. Epub 2012 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23051883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loftus RW, Brindeiro BS, Kispert DP, Patel HM, Koff MD, Jensen JT, Dodds TM, Yeager MP, Ruoff KL, Gallagher JD, Beach ML, Brown JR. Reduction in intraoperative bacterial contamination of peripheral intravenous tubing through the use of a passive catheter care system. Anesth Analg. 2012 Dec;115(6):1315-23. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31826d2aa4. Epub 2012 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23144441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowlands J, Yeager MP, Beach M, Patel HM, Huysman BC, Loftus RW. Video observation to map hand contact and bacterial transmission in operating rooms. Am J Infect Control. 2014 Jul;42(7):698-701. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2014.02.021.</citation>
    <PMID>24969122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koff MD, Loftus RW, Burchman CC, Schwartzman JD, Read ME, Henry ES, Beach ML. Reduction in intraoperative bacterial contamination of peripheral intravenous tubing through the use of a novel device. Anesthesiology. 2009 May;110(5):978-85. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181a06ec3.</citation>
    <PMID>19352154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koff MD, Corwin HL, Beach ML, Surgenor SD, Loftus RW. Reduction in ventilator associated pneumonia in a mixed intensive care unit after initiation of a novel hand hygiene program. J Crit Care. 2011 Oct;26(5):489-495. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrc.2010.12.013. Epub 2011 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21439767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards JR, Peterson KD, Mu Y, Banerjee S, Allen-Bridson K, Morrell G, Dudeck MA, Pollock DA, Horan TC. National Healthcare Safety Network (NHSN) report: data summary for 2006 through 2008, issued December 2009. Am J Infect Control. 2009 Dec;37(10):783-805. doi: 10.1016/j.ajic.2009.10.001.</citation>
    <PMID>20004811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zerbino DR, Birney E. Velvet: algorithms for de novo short read assembly using de Bruijn graphs. Genome Res. 2008 May;18(5):821-9. doi: 10.1101/gr.074492.107. Epub 2008 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>18349386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perdiz LB, Yokoe DS, Furtado GH, Medeiros EA. Impact of an Automated Surveillance to Detect Surgical-Site Infections in Patients Undergoing Total Hip and Knee Arthroplasty in Brazil. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2016 Aug;37(8):991-3. doi: 10.1017/ice.2016.86. Epub 2016 Apr 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27072598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheadle WG. Risk factors for surgical site infection. Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2006;7 Suppl 1:S7-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16834549</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owens CD, Stoessel K. Surgical site infections: epidemiology, microbiology and prevention. J Hosp Infect. 2008 Nov;70 Suppl 2:3-10. doi: 10.1016/S0195-6701(08)60017-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19022115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qureshi ZA, Paterson DL, Pakstis DL, Adams-Haduch JM, Sandkovsky G, Sordillo E, Polsky B, Peleg AY, Bhussar MK, Doi Y. Risk factors and outcome of extended-spectrum β-lactamase-producing Enterobacter cloacae bloodstream infections. Int J Antimicrob Agents. 2011 Jan;37(1):26-32. doi: 10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2010.09.009. Epub 2010 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21075605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paryavi E, Stall A, Gupta R, Scharfstein DO, Castillo RC, Zadnik M, Hui E, O'Toole RV. Predictive model for surgical site infection risk after surgery for high-energy lower-extremity fractures: development of the risk of infection in orthopedic trauma surgery score. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2013 Jun;74(6):1521-7. doi: 10.1097/TA.0b013e318292158d.</citation>
    <PMID>23694882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arnold C. Outbreak Breakthrough: Using Whole-Genome Sequencing to Control Hospital Infection. Environ Health Perspect. 2015 Nov;123(11):A281-6. doi: 10.1289/ehp.123-A281.</citation>
    <PMID>26523889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rupp ME, Fitzgerald T, Puumala S, Anderson JR, Craig R, Iwen PC, Jourdan D, Keuchel J, Marion N, Peterson D, Sholtz L, Smith V. Prospective, controlled, cross-over trial of alcohol-based hand gel in critical care units . Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2008 Jan;29(1):8-15. doi: 10.1086/524333.</citation>
    <PMID>18171181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moureau NL, Flynn J. Disinfection of Needleless Connector Hubs: Clinical Evidence Systematic Review. Nurs Res Pract. 2015;2015:796762. doi: 10.1155/2015/796762. Epub 2015 May 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26075093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schweizer ML, Chiang HY, Septimus E, Moody J, Braun B, Hafner J, Ward MA, Hickok J, Perencevich EN, Diekema DJ, Richards CL, Cavanaugh JE, Perlin JB, Herwaldt LA. Association of a bundled intervention with surgical site infections among patients undergoing cardiac, hip, or knee surgery. JAMA. 2015 Jun 2;313(21):2162-71. doi: 10.1001/jama.2015.5387.</citation>
    <PMID>26034956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips M, Rosenberg A, Shopsin B, Cuff G, Skeete F, Foti A, Kraemer K, Inglima K, Press R, Bosco J. Preventing surgical site infections: a randomized, open-label trial of nasal mupirocin ointment and nasal povidone-iodine solution. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2014 Jul;35(7):826-32. doi: 10.1086/676872. Epub 2014 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24915210</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bode LG, Kluytmans JA, Wertheim HF, Bogaers D, Vandenbroucke-Grauls CM, Roosendaal R, Troelstra A, Box AT, Voss A, van der Tweel I, van Belkum A, Verbrugh HA, Vos MC. Preventing surgical-site infections in nasal carriers of Staphylococcus aureus. N Engl J Med. 2010 Jan 7;362(1):9-17. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0808939.</citation>
    <PMID>20054045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Konvalinka A, Errett L, Fong IW. Impact of treating Staphylococcus aureus nasal carriers on wound infections in cardiac surgery. J Hosp Infect. 2006 Oct;64(2):162-8. Epub 2006 Aug 23.</citation>
    <PMID>16930768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen YQ, Hu C, Wang Y. Attributable risk function in the proportional hazards model for censored time-to-event. Biostatistics. 2006 Oct;7(4):515-29. Epub 2006 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>16478758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehrotra DV, Li X, Liu J, Lu K. Analysis of longitudinal clinical trials with missing data using multiple imputation in conjunction with robust regression. Biometrics. 2012 Dec;68(4):1250-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1541-0420.2012.01780.x. Epub 2012 Sep 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22994905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpenter J, Pocock S, Lamm CJ. Coping with missing data in clinical trials: a model-based approach applied to asthma trials. Stat Med. 2002 Apr 30;21(8):1043-66.</citation>
    <PMID>11933033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raudenbush SW. Hierarchical Linear Models: Applications and Data Analysis Methods. Newbury Park, CA: Sage; 2002.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wikler M, Cockerill F, Craig W, Dudley M, Eliopoulos G, Hecht P, Hindler J, Low D, Sheehan D, Tenover F, Turnidge J, Weinstein M, Zimmer B. Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute: Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Disk Susceptibility Tests; Approved Standard-9th 10th edition. 2009, Wayne, PA, Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute, 2006, pp M2 M02-A9A10</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Iowa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sundara Reddy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bacterial Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>All of the individual participant data collected during the trial, after deidentification will be shared with researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal, to achieve aims in the approved proposal. IPD will be available for sharing immediately after publication and ending 5 years following article publication.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>IPD will be available for sharing immediately after publication and ending 5 years following article publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>IPD will be accessible to researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal, to achieve aims in the approved proposal</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

