<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03600142</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21TW011053-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21TW011053-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03600142</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Stigma Reduction Intervention at Time of Entry Into Antenatal Care to Improve PMTCT Services in Tanzania</brief_title>
  <acronym>Maisha</acronym>
  <official_title>A Stigma Reduction Intervention at Time of Entry Into Antenatal Care to Improve PMTCT Services in Tanzania (Maisha)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre, Tanzania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>John E. Fogarty International Center (FIC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will pilot test a brief, scalable intervention called Maisha (Swahili for life),
      to address HIV stigma for women presenting to antenatal care in Tanzania and male partners
      who accompany them. The intervention will include: 1) a video and brief counseling that
      addresses HIV stigma at the start of the ANC visit (prior to HIV testing), and 2) two
      stigma-based counseling sessions for individuals who are HIV infected, building on the video
      content to provide emotional support, promote acceptance, address stigma, and reinforce care
      engagement. The primary intervention outcome is engagement in PMTCT care among women who are
      HIV infected. The investigators will also examine HIV stigma outcomes (enacted, anticipated,
      internalized) among all groups of participants, including individuals who are already
      established on ART and indiviudals who are HIV uninfected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HIV-related stigma has been identified as a significant reason for loss to follow up in
      prevention of mother-to-child transmission of HIV (PMTCT) programs. Antenatal care (ANC)
      provides a unique and important entry point to address HIV stigma. Stigma-based counseling
      during the first ANC visit can promote readiness to initiate or sustain treatment among those
      who are HIV infected, and can address stigmatizing attitudes and behaviors among those who
      are uninfected. We are proposing to pilot test a brief, scalable intervention called Maisha
      (Swahili for life), to address HIV stigma for women and their partners presenting to ANC in
      Tanzania. The intervention will include: 1) a video and brief counseling for women and their
      partners (if present) that addresses HIV stigma at the start of the ANC visit (prior to HIV
      testing), and 2) two stigma-based counseling sessions for women who are HIV infected,
      building on the video content to provide emotional support, promote acceptance, address
      stigma, and reinforce care engagement, with the opportunity for male partners to attend the
      first follow-up counseling session after testing. The primary intervention outcome is
      engagement in PMTCT care among women who are HIV infected. As a secondary outcome we will
      also look at linkage to HIV care among men who are HIV infected. We will also examine HIV
      stigma outcomes (enacted, anticipated, internalized) among all groups of people, including
      those who are already established on ART and those who are HIV uninfected. The intervention
      content is based on principles of cognitive-behavioral therapy (addressing automatic negative
      thoughts about the self, future and the world) to address and mitigate multiple forms of HIV
      stigma (internalized, anticipated and enacted). We will conduct a pilot RCT of the
      intervention, enrolling all women who attend a first ANC appointment at two clinics in the
      Moshi district. If women come to the ANC visit with a male partner, the partner will be
      invited to enroll as well. Maisha will be compared to the standard of care HIV counseling. In
      addition to a baseline assessment, all participants who are identified as HIV-infected and
      their partners will get a follow-up assessment three months after enrollment. A subset of
      participants who are identified as HIV-uninfected but who report high levels of HIV
      stigmatizing attitudes at baseline will also receive a follow-up assessment three months
      after enrollment. Measures will include health outcomes (care engagement, adherence,
      depression), stigma outcomes, and HIV disclosure. Quality assurance data will be collected
      and the feasibility and acceptability of the intervention and RCT will be described.
      Statistical analysis will examine differences between conditions in health outcomes and
      stigma measures, stratified by HIV status. We hypothesize that 1) among HIV infected
      individuals, individuals receiving the Maisha intervention will report better engagement in
      PMTCT care/linkage to HIV care and lower levels of internalized HIV stigma, as compared to
      individuals receiving the standard of care, and 2) among HIV uninfected individuals,
      individuals receiving the pre-test video and counseling will report lower levels of
      stigmatizing attitudes when compared with the control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 8, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV care engagement (female HIV-infected participants only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-assessment (3 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>For HIV-infected female participants, retention in care will be assessed via medical record review, with retention defined as having no more than a 60 day gap between PMTCT visits at the study clinic, or having record of an official transfer to another clinic.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Internalized HIV stigma (HARSI) (HIV-infected participants only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-assessment (3 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report, measured by Scale A of the HIV and Abuse Related Shame Inventory (HARSI) (Neufeld, Sikkema, Lee, Kochman, &amp; Hansen, 2012), plus one added item.
Scoring: Item scores range 0-4. Item 12 (added item) must be reverse scored, then items summed. Total scores range 0-52 with higher scores indicating higher shame.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Attitudes toward people living with HIV (HIV-uninfected participants only)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-assessment (3 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report, measured by a modified version of personal and attributed stigma scales (Visser, Kershaw, Makin, &amp; Forsyth, 2008)
Scoring: Item scores range from 0-3 (Strongly Disagree to Strongly Agree). Item responses are totaled for a summary score. Total scores range 0-54 (three items were added), with higher scores indicating greater stigma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality Assurance (QA data)</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-assessment (3 months after enrollment)</time_frame>
    <description>Quality assurance data will be collected on feasibility, acceptability, and fidelity of Maisha session to the intervention manual. Sessions will be recorded and a subset of recordings will be reviewed to assess whether core components of the sessions were completed. Follow-up surveys will include items on participant satisfaction with the intervention format, session content, and interventionist. A subset of participants will also be selected to give additional qualitative feedback.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1543</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care (SoC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the control condition will receive the standard HIV counseling protocol in the clinic, which is administered by clinic nurses. According to the Tanzania PMTCT guidelines, HIV pre-test counseling should provide education about HIV and prepare a woman (and her partner, if present) for HIV testing. For anyone who tests positive for HIV, counseling should help the woman/couple to accept an HIV test result and discuss implications for treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SoC + stigma counseling (Maisha)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the intervention condition will receive the SoC counseling plus Maisha, a brief, scalable, theory-based counseling intervention that addresses HIV stigma at entry into antenatal care. Maisha involves a video delivered to all women prior to HIV testing, and, if a woman tests positive for HIV, two counseling sessions. If a male partner is present with the women, he may also be enrolled and participate in the first two counseling sessions together with the woman.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mashia</intervention_name>
    <description>Maisha is a brief, scalable, theory-based counseling intervention that addresses HIV stigma at entry into antenatal care. The intervention will be developed in a formative phase and includes 1) a video and counseling session prior to HIV testing that addresses HIV stigma, and 2) two post-test HIV counseling sessions for HIV-infected individuals, building on the video content to provide emotional support, address stigma, and reinforce the value of care engagement.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SoC + stigma counseling (Maisha)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  If female: Pregnant and attending first antenatal care (ANC) appointment for the
             current pregnancy at one of the two study sites

          -  If male: Accompanying an enrolled woman to her first ANC appointment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Impaired mental status

          -  Does not speak Swahili
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa Watt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Blandina Mmbaga, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moshi</city>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Utah</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melissa Watt</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Population Health Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stigma</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Tanzania</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive-behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Retention in care</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention of mother to child transmission</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data from the formative and pilot trial work in this R21 will be shared within the constraints required for the protection of confidentiality for study subjects. With a data transfer agreement from our Institutional Review Board, the investigators are willing to share raw data with researchers and program leaders from other institutions.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be shared starting 6 months after publication.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Data will be shared with investigators who are interested in secondary data analysis or inclusion in meta-analyses. The investigators will work with individuals requesting data access to put in place an appropriate data transfer agreement. The study PI will review all requests for data sharing.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>November 27, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/42/NCT03600142/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

