<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03604367</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>72777</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03604367</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gait Mate: Examining Neural Networks Engaged During Lower Extremity Movement in the MRI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gait Mate: Examining Neural Networks Engaged During Lower Extremity Movement in the MRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>MUSC Center for Biomedical Research Excellence (COBRE) in Stroke Recovery</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Less than 50% of stroke survivors progress to independent community ambulation. Even among
      the stroke survivors who achieve independent ambulation, significant residual deficits
      persist in balance and gait speed, with 60% of persons post-stroke reporting limitations in
      mobility related to walking.Consequently maximizing recovery of locomotor function is the
      focus of neurorehabilitation efforts worldwide. A recently completed clinical trial from
      members of this investigative team demonstrated that 6 weeks of treadmill training elicits
      substantial improvements in over ground walking speed and symmetry in persons following
      stroke. Consistent with the goals of the South Carolina Stroke Rehabilitation Research Center
      (SCSRRC) and NIH Brain Initiative, the investigators now plan to investigate the effects
      treadmill-assisted gait training have on cortical control of bipedal movement in chronic
      stroke patients. Although previous investigators have assessed neural activity during
      simulated walking using motor imagery, motor imagery does not simulate the typical sensory
      feedback associated with active movement. To move the field forward, it is necessary to
      measure active bipedal movement in the MR-environment in healthy volunteers, before moving
      forward in stroke patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overarching goal of this Discovery Proposal is to evaluate neural activity during
      unipedal and bipedal movement in a cohort of healthy individuals (Aim 1).

      The rigor and reproducibility will be evaluated by comparing the results of 1) active
      movement -Bipedal with 2) active movement -unipedal 4 and 3) imagined movement.

      Dependent measures include: 1) head motion during the fMRI task, 2) BOLD signal in the
      ipsilateral and contralateral motor cortex during the fMRI task, 3) force applied during the
      fMRI task, and 4) participant feedback using a modified version of the Presence Questionnaire
      (a standard tool to assess ecological validity of virtual environments.

      Each Aim has a development and evaluation aspect. Through this 1 year proposal the
      investigators will determine if the bipedal fMRI protocol (active movement) is able to engage
      neural networks more robustly (e.g. greater effect size) than bipedal imagery alone in
      Healthy Volunteers.

      Specific Aim #1: Healthy volunteers: The investigators will test the hypothesis that with
      active bipedal movement there will be 1) no difference in head movement, but 2) greater motor
      cortex BOLD signal, 3) smoother force exchange between the feet, 4) higher participant
      satisfaction than unipedal movement or motor imagery alone. This sample size was selected
      based on a prior publication of imagined movement. The outcome of this aim may result in the
      first publication in the field to evaluate bipedal movement in an MR-environment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 14, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 14, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI protocols will measure neural function activity during active bipedal movement in healthy volunteers</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the study, approximately 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determine if the bipedal fMRI protocol (active movement) is able to engage neural networks more robustly (e.g. greater effect size) than bipedal imagery alone in healthy volunteers.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Motor Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GAITRite assessment</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will undergo the GAITRite assessment of functional walking and then complete the Functional MRI Bipedal paradigm followed by questionnaires and assessments regarding the virtual environment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GAITRite assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>The fMRI Bipedal Paradigm will allow investigators to study the effects treadmill-assisted gait training have on cortical control of bipedal movement in chronic stroke patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GAITRite assessment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fMRI Bipedal Paradigm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Healthy volunteers will be screened for eligibility who are right hand dominant.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Age 21-65

          -  Right hand dominant

          -  Able to read and understand questionnaires and informed consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Self reported history of cardiac disease, COPD or oxygen dependence, neurological and
             psychiatric disorders, dementia or previous stroke, major head trauma, severe visual
             impairment, osteoarthritis, orthopedic problems that limit passive range of motion,
             illegal drug or alcohol dependence, claustrophobia

          -  Non-mri compatible metal implants in the body

          -  Pregnant females
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Colleen A Hanlon, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>fMRI</keyword>
  <keyword>BOLD Signal</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data from the primary outcome measurement will be shared via manuscripts and after study completion by request to the Principal Investigator.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The data will be available immediately after first publication of the results. This is estimated to be at the end of 2019.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Interested parties should contact the Principal Investigator directly</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

