<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03601806</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMC-100</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2017-00390</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>AMC-100</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>AMC-100</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>AMC-100</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1CA121947</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03601806</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pomalidomide in Treating Patients With Kaposi Sarcoma and Human Immunodeficiency Virus Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Multicenter Study of Pomalidomide Monotherapy in HIV-Positive Individuals With Kaposi Sarcoma (KS) in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>AIDS Malignancy Consortium</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Emmes Company, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Arkansas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>AIDS Malignancy Consortium</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II clinical trial studies the side effects of pomalidomide and how well it works
      in treating patients with Kaposi sarcoma and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.
      Biological therapies, such as pomalidomide, may stimulate the immune system in different ways
      and stop tumor cells from growing and it may also block the growth of new blood vessels
      necessary for tumor growth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine if pomalidomide monotherapy induces a minimal level of antitumor efficacy to
      justify its further development for HIV-associated Kaposi sarcoma (KS) in sub-Saharan Africa
      and is safe and tolerable.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To evaluate the effects of pomalidomide monotherapy on standard measures of HIV control,
      i.e., CD4 counts and HIV viral loads, in this participant population.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the effect of pomalidomide treatment on serum cytokine levels. II. To evaluate
      if changes in serum cytokine levels correlate with clinical response.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive pomalidomide orally (PO) once daily (QD) on days 1-21. Treatment repeats
      every 28 days for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable
      toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 12 weeks for 48 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The binomial proportion and its 95% exact confidence interval will be used to estimate the overall response rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The binomial proportion and its 95% exact confidence interval will be used to estimate the complete response rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events defined as grade 3 or higher toxicities graded according to the National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 5.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days after the last dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The binomial proportion and its 95% exact confidence interval will be used to estimate the proportion of participants who experience a grade 3 or higher toxicity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in CD4 T cell count</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 30 days after last dose of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in CD4 counts and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) viral load will be evaluated using generalized estimating equations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in HIV viral load as measured by HIV quantitative polymerase chain reaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 30 days after last dose of study drug</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in CD4 counts and HIV viral load will be evaluated using generalized estimating equations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum cytokine levels as measured by Luminex assay</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>General estimating equations will be used to evaluate changes in cytokine levels over time. Logistic regression analyses will be used to evaluate the association between cytokine levels and clinical response.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus 1 Positive</condition>
  <condition>Skin Kaposi Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive pomalidomide PO QD on days 1-21. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pomalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pomalidomide)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>4-Amino thalidomide</other_name>
    <other_name>Actimid</other_name>
    <other_name>CC-4047</other_name>
    <other_name>Imnovid</other_name>
    <other_name>Pomalyst</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have measurable cutaneous KS that has been pathologically confirmed
             by an acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) Malignancy Consortium (AMC)-approved
             pathologist; diagnostic tissue must be available to satisfy the tissue submission
             requirements for central pathology review

          -  Participants may not show evidence for ongoing improvement in KS lesions in the 4
             weeks prior to enrollment

          -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or
             chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and
             confirmed by a licensed western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than
             the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen, plasma HIV-1 ribonucleic acid
             (RNA) viral load.

        NOTE: The term &quot;licensed&quot; refers to a United States (U.S.) Food and Drug Administration
        (FDA)-approved kit or for sites located in countries other than the U.S., a kit that has
        been certified or licensed by an oversight body within that country and validated
        internally.

        World Health Organization (WHO) and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)
        guidelines mandate that confirmation of the initial test result must use a test that is
        different from the one used for the initial assessment; a reactive initial rapid test
        should be confirmed by either another type of rapid assay or an E/CIA that is based on a
        different antigen preparation and/or different test principle (e.g., indirect versus
        competitive), or a western blot or a plasma HIV-1 ribonucleic acid (RNA) viral load

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky
             performance status [KPS] &gt;= 50)

          -  Life expectancy &gt;= 12 weeks

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 8 g/dL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC): &gt;= 1,000 cells/mm^3 (1.0 x 10^9/L)

          -  Platelets: &gt;= 75,000 cells/mm^3 (75.0 x 10^9/L)

          -  Total bilirubin: =&lt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN), unless the participant
             is receiving an antiretroviral drug known to be associated with increased bilirubin,
             in which case the direct fraction should be =&lt; 2 times the ULN

          -  Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT)
             / alanine aminotransferase (ALT) serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) =&lt; 2.5 x
             ULN

          -  Estimated or measured creatinine clearance &gt; 60 mL/minute (1.00 mL/s) (serum
             creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dL / 176.8 umol/L)

          -  Currently receiving local standard of care antiretroviral therapy (ART) for &gt;= 12
             weeks, with HIV viral load =&lt; 400 copies/mL; participants are required to be on
             antiretroviral regimens that are in accordance with the current International AIDS
             Society guidelines concurrently with chemotherapy; the specific agents are at the
             discretion of the investigator and the use of investigational agents currently
             available on an expanded access basis is allowed

          -  A female of childbearing potential (FCBP) is a female who has achieved menarche at
             some point and who meets one of the following criteria: 1) has not undergone a
             hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy, or 2) has not been naturally postmenopausal
             (amenorrhea following cancer therapy does not rule out childbearing potential) for at
             least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has had menses at any time in the preceding 24
             consecutive months), or 3) does not have a serum or plasma follicle stimulating
             hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 mIU/mL and a history of amenorrhea x &gt;= 1 year

               -  FCBP must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at
                  least 25 mIU/mL within 10-14 days prior to and again within 24 hours of starting
                  pomalidomide and must either commit to continued abstinence from heterosexual
                  intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth control, including one of
                  the following highly effective, long-acting methods, DepoProvera, an intrauterine
                  device (IUD), an implant*, or bilateral tubal ligation, if it can be verified
                  that the procedure was performed, and one additional effective method AT THE SAME
                  TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking pomalidomide; FCBP must also
                  agree to ongoing pregnancy testing

               -  NOTE: Implants containing levonorgestrel and etonogestrel are prohibited in women
                  receiving efavirenz, as drug interactions will render the implants ineffective

               -  Men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact with a FCBP even if
                  they have had a vasectomy

               -  All participants must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy
                  precautions and risks of fetal exposure; serum or urine pregnancy testing will be
                  repeated in FCBP, and must be negative, within 24 hours of starting each new
                  cycle of pomalidomide

          -  Able to take aspirin (&gt;= 81 mg) daily as prophylactic anticoagulation

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Any prior use of thalidomide, lenalidomide, or pomalidomide

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to pomalidomide

          -  Visceral disease requiring cytotoxic chemotherapy (i.e., pulmonary KS, symptomatic
             gastrointestinal KS). KS-related lymphedema is permitted.

          -  Use of agents containing zidovudine (including Combivir and Trizivir) are prohibited;
             in order to be eligible, participants taking zidovudine must change to a different
             regimen at least 7 days prior to therapy initiation; changes to antiretroviral therapy
             (ART) therapy during the study may be made if medically necessary (toxicity, failure
             of regimen, etc.)

               -  Use of medications or substances that are strong inhibitors of CYP1A2, which
                  include amiodarone, cimetidine, fluoroquinolones (e.g., ciprofloxacin, enoxacin),
                  fluvoxamine, and ticlopidine is prohibited

               -  Use of erythropoietin is prohibited

               -  Co-administration of corticosteroids greater than doses required for treatment of
                  adrenal insufficiency is prohibited

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection for which the participant has not completed at least 14 days of therapy
             prior to study enrollment and/or is not clinically stable; symptomatic congestive
             heart failure; unstable angina pectoris; cardiac arrhythmia; or psychiatric
             illness/social situations that, in the opinion of the investigator, would limit
             compliance with study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with pomalidomide

          -  Specific KS therapy, including cytotoxic chemotherapy but not including ART, within
             the past 4 weeks

          -  Use of other anticancer treatments or agents within the past 4 weeks

          -  History of malignant tumors other than KS, unless:

               -  In complete remission for &gt;= 1 year, or

               -  Completely resected basal cell carcinoma, or

               -  In situ squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix or anus

          -  Grade &gt;= 3 peripheral neuropathy

          -  History of myocardial infarction (MI), cerebrovascular accident, or venous or arterial
             thromboembolism, unless line-related thrombosis without embolus occurring within 1
             year prior to study entry

          -  Known procoagulant disorder including prothrombin gene mutation 20210, antithrombin
             III deficiency, protein C deficiency, protein S deficiency and antiphospholipid
             syndrome but not including heterozygosity for the factor V Leiden mutation or the
             presence of a lupus anticoagulant in the absence of other criteria for the
             antiphospholipid syndrome

          -  Any condition, including the presence of current laboratory abnormalities or other
             factor that, in the opinion of the investigator, places the participant at
             unacceptable risk if they were to participate in the study or confounds the ability to
             interpret data from the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan E. Krown, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>AIDS Malignancy Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Samantha Vogt, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moi University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eldoret</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Naftali Busakhala</last_name>
      <phone>254-722-496-933</phone>
      <email>nbusakhala@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Naftali Busakhala, MBChB MMed</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bugando Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mwanza</city>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nestory Masalu</last_name>
      <phone>255-783-0-00004</phone>
      <email>nmasalu2000@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nestory Masalu, MD MMed</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Uganda Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abrahams Omoding</last_name>
      <phone>256-772-555-865</phone>
      <email>omo2009abra@yahoo.co.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Abrahams Omoding, MBChB MMED</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Zimbabwe Clinical Research Centre / Parirenyatwa Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harare</city>
        <country>Zimbabwe</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Margaret Borok-Williams</last_name>
      <phone>263-4-791631</phone>
      <phone_ext>2272</phone_ext>
      <email>mborok@mweb.co.zw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margaret Borok-Williams, MBChB</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
    <country>Uganda</country>
    <country>Zimbabwe</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Kaposi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immunologic Deficiency Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pomalidomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

