<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03607903</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHDR1807</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03607903</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adalimumab Microneedles in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-controlled, Double-dummy Study to Assess Microneedle Delivery in Comparison to Subcutaneous Injection of Adalimumab in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre for Human Drug Research, Netherlands</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leiden University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Leiden Academic Center for Drug Research, the Netherlands</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre for Human Drug Research, Netherlands</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adalimumab (Humira, AbbVie) is a highly effective treatment for a variety of
      auto-immune/auto-inflammatory diseases including juvenile idiopathic arthritis (JIA).
      Adalimumab works by binding to tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF), hereby preventing its
      interaction with the TNF receptor. In the presence of complement, adalimumab can also lyse
      TNF-expressing cells.

      Adalimumab is administered via subcutaneous injection, which has the major drawback of being
      perceived as unpleasant and painful, especially during long term use for both adults and
      children. As subcutaneous administration may therefore eventually jeopardize treatment
      adherence, there is a clear need for less invasive alternatives to administer highly
      effective biological drugs such as adalimumab.

      Microneedles may be a potential alternative for invasive drug administration. Microneedles
      are currently widely investigated for the administration of various vaccines. The experience
      with administration of biological drugs is rather limited. The sparse available data suggests
      similar pharmacokinetics of adalimumab when administered either subcutaneous or intradermal
      in healthy volunteers. Moreover, the first studies report good tolerability of microneedles.
      However, no systematic studies have been performed yet i) to investigate pain, acceptability,
      and local tolerability for intradermal versus subcutaneous adalimumab administration ii) to
      evaluate safety, PK and immunogenicity for intradermal versus subcutaneous adalimumab and
      iii) to explore the usability of optical coherence tomography, clinical photography, thermal
      imaging and laser speckle contrast imaging in the evaluation of intradermal injections.

      This study will directly compare the pain perception and hence acceptability of a single dose
      (40 mg) of adalimumab administered subcutaneously (SC) versus intradermally (ID) via
      microneedles in healthy adult volunteers. Furthermore, the pharmacokinetic profile,
      pharmacodynamics, the immunogenicity and the tolerability will be assessed. This study will
      enable bridging to a future study in children and adolescents with JIA, in which the
      suitability of microneedles for the administration of adalimumab in pediatric patients will
      be examined. The overarching aim of these studies is to make administration of biologicals in
      children as pain free as possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective(s)

        1. To evaluate the pain, acceptability and local tolerability of intradermal microneedle
           injection compared to subcutaneous injection in healthy volunteers.

        2. To evaluate the safety, pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics and immunogenicity of
           adalimumab after administration using microneedles versus subcutaneous injection in
           healthy volunteers.

        3. To explore the usability of optical coherence tomography, clinical photography, laser
           speckle contrast imaging, and thermal imaging in the evaluation of intradermal
           injections.

      Definitions Method: ID or SC injection Compound: adalimumab or saline Treatment: combination
      of method and compound Arm: sequence of treatments

      Design This is a double blind, placebo controlled, double-dummy study. The study physician
      will administer the injection and is thus unblinded to the type of injection. All injection
      site assessments will be performed by (a) study independent member of the clinical staff.

      Sterile saline injection will be used as a negative control. Subjects will receive an
      injection with both sterile saline (SC or ID) and adalimumab (SC or ID). Subjects will be
      randomized to one of the four arms:

      1A) adalimumab SC and saline ID

        1. B) saline ID and adalimumab SC

        2. A) saline SC and adalimumab ID

      2B) adalimumab ID and saline SC

      The maximum duration between treatments will be 5 minutes.

      After a single dose of adalimumab, pharmacokinetic, pharmacodynamics, tolerability and
      immunogenicity data will be collected and monitored for a total of 70 days post dose, as the
      half-life of adalimumab after subcutaneous injection in adults is approximately two weeks.

      Investigational drug/device combination In children, adalimumab is commonly used in a dose of
      40 mg SC every two weeks (1). For adults with rheumatoid arthritis the same dose is used (2).
      It was therefore chosen to administer adalimumab in a single dose of 40 mg in 0.4 mL either
      subcutaneously or intradermally in the upper thigh. For saline injection the same volume will
      be used.

      For intradermal administration, the MicronJet600 (NanoPass Technologies) will be used
      (hereafter referred to as microneedle). This CE-marked microneedle consists of an array of
      three hollow pyramid-shaped microneedles with a length of 600 micrometer (3).

      Subjects / Groups A total of 24 healthy subjects (N=6 per arm and N=12 per treatment
      (Adalimumab SC, Adalimumab ID, Saline SC, Saline ID).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 23, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a double blind, placebo controlled, double-dummy study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>This study is double blind. Investigator, study staff, and subjects, are blinded until study closure. Investigational drug and matching placebo are indistinguishable and will be packaged similarly. Injection site assessments will be performed by (a) study-independent physician(s). The study physician will administer the injection, thus unblinded to type of injection. This physician will not reveal the route of administration to others. The investigator receives sealed emergency codes to be broken in case of emergency situations. If the identity of study drug administered needs to be known to manage the subject's condition i.e., in case of a medical emergency or in the case a SUSAR occurs, the treatment emergency code for that subject may be broken and the study drug identified. All such occurrences should be documented in the study file. Just prior to database lock unused emergency code labels will be checked and a statement that all are intact (or not) is made on database lock form.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of pain</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be measured using a standard 100 points visual analogue scale (0: no pain, 100: extreme pain).
Insertion, injection and post-injection pain will be assessed separately.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adalimumab pharmacokinetics</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Individual serum adalimumab concentrations will be plotted versus time per individual.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-adalimumab antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All subjects who received study medication will be monitored for serum anti-adalimumab antibodies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ex vivo cytokine levels</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Ex vivo whole blood challenge will be performed to assess the effect of adalimumab on the release of cytokines by circulating immune cells and activation of these cells. Whole blood will be stimulated with 2ng/mL lipopolysaccharide and 25 ug/mL aluminium ydroxide for 24 hours at 37 degrees Celsius, 5% carbon dioxide. Culture supernatants will be assayed for release of pro-inflammatory cytokines including tumor necrosis factor alpha, interleukin 6, interleukin 1 beta, interleukin 8, and interferon gamma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of pain</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pain will be measured using Dutch version of the faces pain scales revised (0-2-4-6-8-10, 0: no pain, 10: very much pain).
Insertion, injection and post-injection pain will be assessed separately.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preference for subjects for either injection (SC versus ID)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 days</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be asked multiple choice questions on the acceptability of both injections.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of injection site reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Injection site assessment for the following:
Pain (grade 1/2/3) Tenderness (grade 1/2/3) Pruritus (grade 1/2/3) Erythema (absent/present) Induration (grade 1/2/3) Blister (absent/present) Ulceration (absent/present) Necrosis (absent/present) Ecchymosis (absent/present) If any of these signs or symptoms is present, it is regarded an injection site reaction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of (serious) adverse events per treatment arm</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Injection Site</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subcutaneous adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>adalimumab SC (40 mg in 0.4 mL) and saline ID (0.9%, 0.4 mL)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PLacebo and subcutaneous adalimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>saline ID (0.9%, 0.4 mL) and adalimumab SC (40 mg in 0.4 mL)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo and intradermal adalimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>saline SC (0.9%, 0.4 mL) and adalimumab ID (40 mg in 0.4 mL)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intradermal adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>adalimumab ID (40 mg in 0.4 mL) and saline SC (0.9%, 0.4 mL)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adalimumab ID</intervention_name>
    <description>Adalimumab intradermal using MicronJet600 microneedle from NanoPass</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intradermal adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo and intradermal adalimumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adalimumab SC</intervention_name>
    <description>Adalimumab subcutaneous using regular needle</description>
    <arm_group_label>PLacebo and subcutaneous adalimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Subcutaneous adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline ID</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline intradermal using MicronJet600 microneedle from NanoPass</description>
    <arm_group_label>PLacebo and subcutaneous adalimumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Subcutaneous adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline SC</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline subcutaneous using regular needle</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intradermal adalimumab and placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo and intradermal adalimumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Eligible subjects must meet all of the following inclusion criteria at screening:

          1. Healthy male / female subjects, 18 to 45 years of age, inclusive at screening;

          2. Good health, based upon the results of medical history, physical examination, vital
             signs, ECG, and laboratory profiles of both blood and urine;

          3. Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 30 kg/m2, inclusive at screening, and with a
             minimum weight of 50 kg;

          4. Willing to practice an approved method of birth control and not breastfeeding
             throughout the study and for five months after study drug administration, as advised
             in the drug formulary (2). If the trial subject is female, surgical sterilization or
             postmenopausal status for &gt;1 year will satisfy this requirement. All female subjects
             are required to have a negative pregnancy test at screening and at baseline
             (pre-dose);

          5. Fitzpatrick skin type I-II (Caucasian type);

          6. Suitable site for intradermal injection on the legs, as assessed by the investigator;

          7. Able and willing to provide written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Eligible subjects must meet none of the following exclusion criteria at screening:

          1. Immune-compromised (known or expected immune deficiency, disease, or use of medication
             that may affect the immune system);

          2. Diagnosed with tuberculosis (TB, as per positive skin test [Mantoux] or interferon
             gamma release assay), or history of TB, or latent TB, or recent contact with TB
             (patient); having travelled to countries where TB is endemic within eight weeks of
             planned drug administration or planning to travel to countries where TB is endemic
             from the moment of drug administration until three months after the end of the study;

          3. Any confirmed significant allergic reactions (urticaria or anaphylaxis) against any
             drug (including adalimumab);

          4. History of chronic infection, or infections within the past two years requiring
             hospitalization or administration of intravenous antibiotics;

          5. Receipt of any live vaccination within three months prior to study drug
             administration, or intention to undergo live vaccinations from the moment of drug
             administration until four months after the end of study;

          6. Positive hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab), or human
             immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIV Ab) at screening;

          7. Evidence of any active or chronic disease (hematologic, renal, hepatic,
             cardiovascular, neurologic, endocrinal, gastrointestinal, oncologic, pulmonary,
             immunologic, or psychiatric disorder) or condition that could interfere with, or for
             which the treatment of might interfere with the conduct of the study, or that would
             pose an unacceptable risk to the subject in the opinion of the investigator (following
             a detailed medical history, physical examination, vital signs (systolic and diastolic
             blood pressure, and body temperature) and ECG). Minor deviations from the normal range
             may be accepted, if judged by the investigator to have no clinical relevance;

          8. History of abuse of addictive substances (alcohol, illegal substances) or current use
             of more than 21 units alcohol per week, drug abuse, or regular user of sedatives,
             hypnotics, tranquillisers, or any other addictive agent;

          9. Consumption of alcohol within the 48-hour period prior to study drug administration;

         10. Smoke more than 10 cigarettes per day prior to screening or use tobacco products
             equivalent to more than 10 cigarettes per day and/or unable to abstain from smoking
             whilst in the unit;

         11. Positive screen for recreational drugs or alcohol;

         12. Is demonstrating excess in xanthine consumption (more than eight cups of coffee or
             equivalent per day);

         13. Unlikely to comply with the study protocol and/or to complete the study or required
             study procedures, including being unlikely or unable to return for follow-up visits;

         14. Use of any medication (prescription or over-the-counter (OTC) within 14 days of study
             drug administration, or use of herbal supplements, dietary supplements or
             multivitamins within 7 days of study drug administration or less than five half-lives
             (whichever is longer), or receipt of any drug by injection within 30 days of study
             drug administration, with the exception of contraceptives, hormonal replacement
             therapies, and paracetamol (up to 4g/day). Other exceptions will only be made if the
             rationale is clearly documented by the investigator;

         15. Donation of over 500 mL of blood within three months prior to screening or donation of
             plasma within 14 days prior to screening;

         16. Previous exposure to any biological;

         17. Participation in an investigational drug or device study within 3 months prior to
             screening or more than 4 times in the past year;

         18. Excessive sun exposure of the injection site area within 3 weeks of enrollment;

         19. Consideration by the investigator, for any reason, that the subject is an unsuitable
             candidate to receive adalimumab or otherwise participate in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Rissmann, RPh PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre for Human Drug Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Human Drug Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 CL</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intradermal</keyword>
  <keyword>adalimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>microneedle</keyword>
  <keyword>subcutaneous</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adalimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>CHDR will provide NanoPass with a written report summarizing the results of the Clinical Study such as the publication or manuscript, including but not limited to, promptly sharing any severe or potentially reportable safety or adverse event potentially related to the MicronJet600.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

