<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03608787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R44AA024992</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03608787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stop-Service to Obviously-Impaired Patrons</brief_title>
  <acronym>SSTOP</acronym>
  <official_title>Stop-Service to Obviously-Impaired Patrons</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RRF Field Services LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pacific Institute for Research and Evaluation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RRF Field Services LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Responsible Retailing Forum (&quot;RRF&quot;) seeks to develop a new intervention, Stop Service to
      Obviously- Impaired Patrons (&quot;S-STOP&quot;), to reduce the incidence and harm associated with
      overservice of alcohol. Modeled after RRF's effective program to reduce alcohol sales to
      minors using Mystery Shopper feedback on staff ID-checking conduct, SSTOP would (1) conduct
      &quot;Pseudo-Intoxicated&quot; Mystery Shop&quot; (&quot;P-I/MS&quot;) inspections of serving establishments,
      employing actors who seek to purchase an alcohol beverage while showing obvious signs of
      intoxication, (2) provide licensees with confidential feedback on actual staff conduct and a
      video link to view the behavior of the P-I/MS that visited their establishments, (3) provide
      staff with brief online training in the recognition and skillful refusal of service to
      intoxicated patrons, and (4) provide communities with a measure of the prevalence of
      overservice. The proposed study will: (1) determine the effectiveness of S-STOP in improving
      recognition and refusal to serve an obviously- impaired customer. To do this, we will
      implement S-STOP in 10 pairs of demographically matched college and university communities,
      employing a cross-over design. After a 3-month baseline, we will implement S- STOP in one
      community in each pair (Cohort 1), while the second community serves as a control (Cohort 2).
      After 6 months, we will end S-STOP in Cohort 1 communities but continue inspections to
      measure the effects of decay; and we will begin S-STOP in Cohort 2. (2) examine how licensees
      utilize the S-STOP program and the extent to which utilization moderates the effectiveness of
      the program. To do this, we will measure the number and percentage of managers who visit the
      S-STOP website and register their staff for training, measure the number of staff that
      complete the training, and conduct analyses to investigate the dose-response relationship
      between utilization of the S-STOP program and likelihood of overservice. (3) investigate why
      some owner/managers did not participate in S-STOP. To achieve this, we will interview 20
      owner-managers who did not access the S-STOP website.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Responsible Retailing Forum (RRF) has developed a community-based program − S-STOP (Stop
      Service To Obviously-Impaired Patrons) − that assists communities and their on-premises
      alcohol establishments to address the problems of over-service of alcoholic beverages. S-STOP
      is a six-month program, administered by RRF, which:

        -  Conducts Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shop (P-I/MS) visits at on-premises establishments
           employing actors who seek to be served an alcoholic beverage while showing obvious signs
           of intoxication;

        -  Provides on-premises owner-operators and managers with confidential feedback on staff
           conduct and an Internet link to a video that shows how the P-I/MS that visited their
           establishments typically would have behaved;

        -  Provides resources to licensees to assist them in complying with over-service laws;

        -  Provides on-premises staff with a brief online training module on how to recognize and
           skillfully refuse service to potentially intoxicated patrons;

        -  Provides community stakeholders with aggregated data on the prevalence of alcohol
           over-service in their communities.

      In this project, we will conduct and evaluate S-STOP in selected college and university
      communities in California.

      Specific Aim 1 of this project is to demonstrate the effectiveness of S-STOP in reducing
      over-service. To achieve this, RRF will conduct a randomized control trial using a cross-over
      design. We will:

        -  Identify ten pairs of demographically matched college/university communities for a total
           of 20 communities and, in each community, recruit a minimum of 12 on-premises serving
           establishments for participation in the project;

        -  Conduct 3 P-I/MS baseline inspections in all 20 communities to observe pre-intervention
           over-service conduct;

        -  Randomly assign one community from each pair to receive S-STOP immediately (Cohort 1)
           and the other (Cohort 2) to serve as a control group and then to receive S-STOP later;

        -  Implement S-STOP in Cohort 1 communities for 3 months and conduct P-I MS in Cohort 2
           control communities with no feedback to the licensees or community. At the end of the 3
           months, we will end S-STOP in Cohort 1 communities, but continue unreported P-I/MS and
           begin S-STOP in Cohort 2 communities for 3 months;

      Specific Aim 2 is to examine how licensees utilize the S-STOP program within their
      establishments and the extent to which utilization moderates the effectiveness of the
      program. To achieve this aim, we will:

        -  Measure the number and percentage of owner-operators and managers who visit the S-STOP
           website to view the typical behavior of P-I/MS inspectors and register their staff for
           training;

        -  Measure the number of staff who complete the S-STOP online training;

        -  Investigate the dose-response relationship between utilization of the S-STOP program
           (number of owner-manager visits to S-STOP website; percentage of staff completing S-STOP
           training) and likelihood of over-service as assessed by the P-I/MS.

      Specific Aim 3 is to investigate why some owner/managers did not participate in S-STOP in
      order to improve the program. We will:

      • Interview 20 owner-managers who did not access the S-STOP website to find out why and
      determine how the program might be modified to encourage their use of it.

      The S-STOP program has three key components:

        -  Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shops (P-I/MS). S-STOP conducts P-I/MS inspections by actors
           who seek to be served an alcoholic beverage while showing obvious signs of impairment.
           In order to appear realistic, the P-I/MSs act out levels of intoxication that staff of
           bars, clubs, and restaurants are likely to encounter in the course of their jobs.
           Owner-operators and managers are notified by mail that the S-STOP inspections recently
           occurred and are provided with the results (refused service/did not refuse service) of
           inspections in their own establishment. In addition, the mailings include materials
           describing best practices for on-premises serving establishments, providing guidance on
           what steps staff should take if a customer is obviously impaired and describing the
           potential legal consequences for licensees and staff who serve alcohol to an
           obviously-impaired customer. The mailings also provide a link to an internet site with a
           video showing the typical behavior of actors during the P-I/MS visits and for
           registration of staff for online training.

        -  Online refresher training in over-service recognition and refusal. S-STOP provides a
           brief online training module for staff on how to recognize and skillfully refuse service
           to potentially intoxicated patrons. The online training presents staff with scenarios
           involving customers who have been drinking and models several ways in which staff can
           firmly, but respectfully decline to serve. The video also reinforces the importance of
           management supervision and reinforcement of responsible beverage service practices. The
           online training lasts under 4 minutes and can be accessed using a mobile device, tablet,
           or computer. Owners/managers will be notified when their staff members complete the
           training.

        -  Community engagement. S-STOP also reports aggregated community-level P-I/MS results to
           licensees, their industry partners, and public health, safety, and licensing agencies to
           provide these community stakeholders with a measure of over-service prevalence and
           changes in refusal rates in their communities over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>We will: (a) identify ten pairs of matched college/university communities for a total of 20 communities; (b) recruit a minimum of 12 on-premises serving establishments in each community for participation in the project; (c) conduct 3 Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shop (P-I/MS) baseline inspections in all participating outlets in all 20 communities to observe pre-intervention over-service conduct; (d) randomly assign one community from each pair to receive S-STOP immediately (Cohort 1) and the other (Cohort 2) to serve as a control group and then to receive S-STOP later; (e) implement S-STOP in Cohort 1 communities for 3 months and conduct P-I MS in Cohort 2 control communities with no feedback to the licensees or community; (f) at the end of the 3 months, end S-STOP in Cohort 1 communities, but continue unreported P-I/MS and begin S-STOP in Cohort 2 communities for 3 months.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Refusal of Service</measure>
    <time_frame>Once monthly over 9 months (3 months baseline; 3 months Early Intervention; 3 months Delayed Intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is service/refusal of service to a pseudo-intoxicated patron.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Intoxication Alcohol</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Early Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline, participating outlets in this arm will receive the S-STOP program consisting of Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shops (P-I/MS) with performance feedback for 3 months. After 3 months they will receive no further intervention, but will continue to receive Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shops (P-I/MS).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Delayed Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Following baseline, participating outlets in this arm will receive receive Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shops (P-I/MS) with no feedback. After 3 months they will receive the S-STOP program consisting of Pseudo-Intoxicated Mystery Shops (P-I/MS) with performance feedback.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>S-STOP</intervention_name>
    <description>Pseudo-intoxicated patrons will enter each participating establishment and attempt to be served an alcoholic beverage. In the intervention phases, feedback on staff performance will be provided to owners/managers along with supporting materials and a link to a website with a video of a typical pseudo-intoxicated patron. Staff will be provided with a link to a website providing tips for preventing overservice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1-Early Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2-Delayed Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be server/bartender in sampled on-premises alcohol serving establishment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Establishment must have at least 3 servers/bartenders on staff.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brad Krevor, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Responsible Retailing Forum</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maureen DeJong</last_name>
    <phone>(508) 661-9706</phone>
    <email>dejong@rrforum.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Brad Krevor, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(781) 647-0858</phone>
    <email>krevor@rrforum.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>RRForum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waltham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02451-0621</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brad Krevor, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>781-647-0858</phone>
      <email>krevor@rrforum.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alcohol Intoxication</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Overservice</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Serving Establishments</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholic Intoxication</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

