<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03606980</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHKDSM-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03606980</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Iontophoresis With Dexamethasone and Physical Therapy to Treat Apophysitis of the Knee in Pediatrics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Iontophoresis With Dexamethasone in Combination With Physical Therapy for the Treatment of Pediatric Patients Diagnosed With Apophysitis of the Knee: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Health System, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Health System, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to determine if there is a difference in time to
      meet return to sport criteria for Pediatric patients with apophysitis of the knee who receive
      iontophoresis with Dexamethasone Sodium Phosphate (DSP) and Physical Therapy (PT) as those
      who receive iontophoresis with placebo and PT or PT alone.

      Approximately 147 patients will be enrolled in this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Iontophoresis is a treatment that allows medication to be delivered across your skin to the
      painful area without having to have an injection into your muscle or soft tissue, through a
      vein in your arm, or taking a pill. Instead, liquid medication is placed on a patch (like a
      large Band-Aid) and then placed on your knee over the location where it hurts. A plastic
      device, like a battery, is then attached to the patch for three minutes. During this time,
      this device begins to deliver the medication through your skin and into the area that hurts,
      and also charges the patch so it can continue to deliver the medication for two hours once
      the device is removed. The medication is delivered by a mild electrical current. The most
      common drug used with iontophoresis for pain caused by such things as apophysitis of the knee
      is dexamethasone sodium phosphate (dexamethasone).

      This is an investigational study. Dexamethasone is a steroid medication that has been
      approved by the U.S Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to treat many types of problems (such
      as joint problems, skin and allergy problems, eye, stomach, and lung problems), but has not
      been approved to treat apophysitis of the knee using iontophoresis. In this study, it is an
      experimental drug.

      Participants will be randomized to one of three treatment groups:

        -  Physical therapy with iontophoresis using Dexamethasone

        -  Physical therapy with iontophoresis using an inactive drug called a placebo

        -  Physical therapy alone

      Participants will be asked to attend study visits twice/week for up to 8 weeks or until they
      are able to pass the Return To Sport Checklist, whichever is sooner. Participants will the
      receive a 30-Day Follow Up phone call and complete a survey at the 90-Day mark, making each
      participant's study duration approximately five (5) months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 16, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 17, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional outcome as measured in length of time to meet Return To Sport criteria (measured in days)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at each Study Treatment Visit for a maximum of 12 Study Treatment Visits over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return to Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner</time_frame>
    <description>The Return To Sport Criteria is met when all items on the Return To Sport Checklist can be successfully achieved. There are no units of measure for any of the criteria listed as they are either achieved/passed or not achieved/failed based on the criteria listed. Once all criteria can be passed, this date is noted. The number of days from Visit 1 to the date when all criteria are achieved is calculated. This outcome is measured in days.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome - percent difficulty with activities as measured by the Lower Extremity Function Scale (LEFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Treatment Visit 1, 5 and 12 (or after 8 Weeks of treatment or when Return To Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner) and again 30-Days after meeting Return To Sport Criteria.</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will be asked to attend 2 Study Treatments per week for a maximum of 12 treatments over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return To Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner. The LEFS is a patient reported questionnaire that measures difficult of completing 20 activities. The maximum possible score of the LEFS is 80 points, indicating very high function. The minimum possible score is 0 points, indicating very low function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome - activity level as measured by the Godin Leisure-Time Activity Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Study Treatment Visit 1 and 30-Days after Return To Sport Criteria are met and 90-Days after Return To Sport Criteria are met.</time_frame>
    <description>The Godin Leisure-Time Activity Questionnaire measures physical activity. Scores of 24 and above indicate the individual is &quot;Active&quot;, scores of 14-23 indicate the individual is &quot;Moderately Active&quot;, and scores of 14 and below indicate the individual is insufficiently active/sedentary.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported outcome - pain as measured by the Wong-Baker FACES Pain Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at each Study Treatment Visit up to 12 Study Treatment Visits over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return to Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner, and again 2-3 days after meeting Return To Sport Criteria.</time_frame>
    <description>This scale was created for children to help them communicate their pain. The scale shows a series of faces ranging from a happy face at 0, &quot;No hurt&quot; to a crying face at 10 &quot;Hurts worst&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as measured by the number and intensity of iontophoresis or DSP-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at each Study Treatment Visit (up to 12 Study Treatment Visits over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return to Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner), then again 2 - 3 days, 30 days, and 90 days after Return To Sport Criteria are met.</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events that occur during participation in this research study, whether or not considered intervention-related, will be collected.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">147</enrollment>
  <condition>Apophysitis; Juvenile</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Iontophoresis is a non-invasive delivery mechanism for transmitting a medication to a local area of the body. The I-Bresis™ System and I-Bresis™ Patch will be the delivery system used for this study. The I-Bresis™ Patch is an adhesive patch. 1.5 ml of the dexamethasone sodium phosphate (4ml/1mL) will be placed on one side and 1.5 ml of 0.9% sodium chloride (saline) solution will be placed on the other. Duration of exposure: 123 minutes. Frequency of exposure: twice per week for a total of 12 sessions over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return to Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner. Participants will also receive the standard PT protocol for apophysitis of the knee. This will involve up to 20 visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Sodium Chloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Iontophoresis is a non-invasive delivery mechanism for transmitting a medication to a local area of the body. The I-Bresis™ System and I-Bresis™ Patch will be the delivery system used for this study. The I-Bresis™ Patch is an adhesive patch. 1.5 ml of 0.9% sodium chloride (saline) solution will be placed on one side and 1.5 ml of 0.9% saline solution will be placed on the other. Duration of exposure: 123 minutes. Frequency of exposure: twice per week for a total of 12 sessions over a maximum of 8 weeks or until Return to Sport Criteria are met, whichever is sooner. Participants will also receive the standard PT protocol for apophysitis of the knee. This will involve up to 20 visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Therapy alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will only receive the standard PT protocol for apophysitis of the knee. This will involve up to 20 visits.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone Sodium Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Dexamethasone sodium phosphate administered via iontophoresis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Iontophoresis</intervention_name>
    <description>Iontophoresis on affected knee</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Sodium Chloride</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Physical therapy of affected knee</description>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Iontophoresis with Sodium Chloride</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Therapy alone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written approval from the referring physician for potential subject to be considered
             for enrollment into this study

          2. Provision of signed and dated informed consent form

          3. Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and availability for the
             duration of the study

          4. In good general health as evidenced by written approval from referring physician for
             potential inclusion in study.

          5. Has the ability to effectively identify pain/burns and communicate with the
             investigators or their parents that they are experiencing pain or burning during
             treatment

          6. Referred to CHKD Sports Medicine PT by CHKD Primary Care Sports Medicine physicians or
             CHKD Orthopedics physicians with a diagnosis of apophysitis of the knee and with a
             prescription for standard PT treatment with iontophoresis

          7. Able and willing to complete iontophoresis treatments within eight (8) weeks of first
             treatment

          8. Must be ambulatory

          9. Males 7 to 14 years of age who have not reached skeletal maturity (skeletal maturity
             based on referring physician's clinical judgement or as demonstrated via radiograph
             images taken within 90 days of enrollment)

         10. Females 7 to 14 years of age who have not reached skeletal maturity (skeletal maturity
             based on referring physician's clinical judgement or as demonstrated via radiograph
             images taken within 90 days of enrollment) and who meet one of the following criteria:

               1. Pre-menarcheal

               2. Within two (2) year post onset of menses

         11. Males or females over the age of 14 only with radiographic evidence of skeletal
             immaturity, with images taken within 90 days of enrollment

         12. Index knee symptomatic for pain with activities of daily living or while playing
             sports.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Index knee symptomatic for pain only with palpation and not with activities of daily
             living or while playing sport

          2. Diagnosis of bilateral apophysitis of the knee where both knees meet all of the
             inclusion criteria

          3. Systemic fungal infections

          4. Has an implanted electronic device

          5. Has a known sensitivity to DSP

          6. Presence of damaged skin, denuded skin, or other recent scar tissue on index knee

          7. Presence of active dermatologic conditions in the affected area (e.g., eczema,
             psoriasis)

          8. Presence of an abnormal neurological exam that indicates the subject would have a
             reduced ability to perceive pain (e.g. peripheral neuropathy)

          9. Has a known sensitivity to electrical current

         10. Is currently taking systemic steroids

         11. Has had iontophoresis with DSP treatment within the past 30 days

         12. Previously enrolled in this study

         13. Currently enrolled in another treatment research study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of the Kings Daughters</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    <phone>757-668-4894</phone>
    <email>Dana.Reesman@chkd.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapy - Oakbrooke</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chesapeake</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23320</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapy - Butler Farms</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hampton</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23666</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapy - Tech Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newport News</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23602</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physicial Therapy - Ghent</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norfolk</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23507</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapy - Loehmann's Plaza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Virginia Beach</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23452</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapy - Landstown</name>
      <address>
        <city>Virginia Beach</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23456</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dana Reesman, PT, DPT</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gholve PA, Scher DM, Khakharia S, Widmann RF, Green DW. Osgood Schlatter syndrome. Curr Opin Pediatr. 2007 Feb;19(1):44-50. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17224661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maffulli N, Longo UG, Spiezia F, Denaro V. Sports injuries in young athletes: long-term outcome and prevention strategies. Phys Sportsmed. 2010 Jun;38(2):29-34. doi: 10.3810/psm.2010.06.1780.</citation>
    <PMID>20631461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Circi E, Atalay Y, Beyzadeoglu T. Treatment of Osgood-Schlatter disease: review of the literature. Musculoskelet Surg. 2017 Dec;101(3):195-200. doi: 10.1007/s12306-017-0479-7. Epub 2017 Jun 7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28593576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kujala UM, Kvist M, Heinonen O. Osgood-Schlatter's disease in adolescent athletes. Retrospective study of incidence and duration. Am J Sports Med. 1985 Jul-Aug;13(4):236-41.</citation>
    <PMID>4025675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Joshi A, Stagni G, Cleary A, Patel K, Weiss DS, Hagins M. Iontophoresis successfully delivers dexamethasone sodium phosphate to dermis as measured by microdialysis. J Pharm Sci. 2014 Jan;103(1):191-6. doi: 10.1002/jps.23771. Epub 2013 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24338751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nirschl RP, Rodin DM, Ochiai DH, Maartmann-Moe C; DEX-AHE-01-99 Study Group. Iontophoretic administration of dexamethasone sodium phosphate for acute epicondylitis. A randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled study. Am J Sports Med. 2003 Mar-Apr;31(2):189-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12642251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Runeson L, Haker E. Iontophoresis with cortisone in the treatment of lateral epicondylalgia (tennis elbow)--a double-blind study. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2002 Jun;12(3):136-42.</citation>
    <PMID>12135445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amirjani N, Ashworth NL, Watt MJ, Gordon T, Chan KM. Corticosteroid iontophoresis to treat carpal tunnel syndrome: a double-blind randomized controlled trial. Muscle Nerve. 2009 May;39(5):627-33. doi: 10.1002/mus.21300.</citation>
    <PMID>19347928</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neeter C, Thomeé R, Silbernagel KG, Thomeé P, Karlsson J. Iontophoresis with or without dexamethazone in the treatment of acute Achilles tendon pain. Scand J Med Sci Sports. 2003 Dec;13(6):376-82.</citation>
    <PMID>14617059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marovino T, Graves C. Iontophoresis in Pain Management. Practical Pain Management . 2011; 8(2): 1-2. Available from: https://www.practicalpainmanagement.com/treatments/interventional/iontophoresis-pain-management, Accessed May 17, 2018</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dexamethasone sodium phosphate. In: Micromedex Solutions DRUGDEX® System. IBM Watson Health. Ann Arbor, MI. [cited April 22, 2018]. Available from: http://micromedexsolutions.com</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dhote V, Bhatnagar P, Mishra PK, Mahajan SC, Mishra DK. Iontophoresis: a potential emergence of a transdermal drug delivery system. Sci Pharm. 2012 Jan-Mar;80(1):1-28. doi: 10.3797/scipharm.1108-20. Epub 2011 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22396901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaur J, Malik M, Sharma P, Sangwan P, Rani M. Effect of iontophoresis with dexamethasone in pain. Indian Journal of Physiotherapy and Occupational Therapy. 2017; 11(3).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clijsen R, Taeymans J, Baeyens JP, Barl AO, Clarys P. The effects of iontophoresis in the treatment of musculoskeletal disorders - a systematic review and meta-analysis. Drug Delivery Letters. 2012: 2(3).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goyal M, Kumar A, Mahajan N, Moitra M. Treatment of plantar fasciitis by taping vs. iontophoresis: a randomized clinical trial. Journal of Exercise Science and Physiotherapy. 2013: 9(1):34-39</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mina R, Melson P, Powell S, Rao M, Hinze C, Passo M, Graham TB, Brunner HI. Effectiveness of dexamethasone iontophoresis for temporomandibular joint involvement in juvenile idiopathic arthritis. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2011 Nov;63(11):1511-6. doi: 10.1002/acr.20600.</citation>
    <PMID>22034112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stefanou A, Marshall N, Holdan W, Siddiqui A. A randomized study comparing corticosteroid injection to corticosteroid iontophoresis for lateral epicondylitis. J Hand Surg Am. 2012 Jan;37(1):104-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jhsa.2011.10.005.</citation>
    <PMID>22196293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaishya R, Azizi AT, Agarwal AK, Vijay V. Apophysitis of the Tibial Tuberosity (Osgood-Schlatter Disease): A Review. Cureus. 2016 Sep 13;8(9):e780. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27752406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>WHO Physical activity and young people [Internet]. World Health Organization; c2018 [cited 2018 June 20]. Available from: http://www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/factsheet_young_people/en/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>WHO Physical activity [Internet]. World Health Organization; c2018 [cited 2018 June 20]. Available from: http://www.who.int/dietphysicalactivity/pa/en/</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>I-Bresis™ Charging Station (1360) - Instructions For Use [Internet]. Rev. B 2017 [cited 2018 May 17]. Available from: http://www.djoglobal.com/sites/default/files/Charging%20Station%20IFU.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>I-Bresis™ Controller (1361) - Instructions For Use, [Internet]. Rev. B 2017 [cited 2018 May 17]. Available from: http://www.djoglobal.com/sites/default/files/Controller%20IFU.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>I-Bresis™ Patch (5000060) - Instructions For Use, [Internet]. Rev. B 2017 [cited 2018 May 17]. Available from: http://www.djoglobal.com/sites/default/files/Electrode%20IFU.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sodium Chloride Injection, USP [package insert]. Deerfield, IL: Baxter Corporation; 2018 [cited 2018 April 25]. Available from http://baxterpi.com/pi-pdf/Sodium_Chloride_Injection_Viaflex_PI.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>2007 Standard Operating Procedures of the Eastern Virginia Medical School Institutional Review Board [Internet]. July 2007 [cited 2018 May 17]. Available from: https://www.evms.edu/media/evms_public/departments/research_administration/research_subjects_protections/2007_EVMS_IRB_SOPs.pdf</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 6, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Health System, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dana Reesman, DPT</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>CHKD Sports Medicine Physical Therapist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone 21-phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

