<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03605797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TBP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03605797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fixation of Sacral Fractures by Posterior Plate</brief_title>
  <official_title>Fixation of Sacral Fractures by Posterior Tension Band Plating</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The sacrum is the mechanical nucleus of the axial skeleton, serving as the base for the
      spinal column as well as the keystone for the pelvic ring.

      Sacral fractures occur in approximately 45% of all pelvic fractures. the mechanism of injury
      resulting in sacral fractures typically is one of high energy from motor vehicle accidents
      and fall from a height.

      Approximately 30% of sacral fractures are identified late. Unrecognized and inadequately
      treated sacral fractures may lead to painful deformity and progressive loss of neurological
      function. Delayed surgery for posttraumatic sacral deformity is complex, and the results are
      often less favorable than those of early surgery. Therefore, determination of an integrated
      diagnostic and therapeutic approach to sacral fractures should be a goal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most sacral fractures can be treated non operatively. These include stable, non displaced
      sacral fractures without a significant associated pelvic ring disruption, fractures not
      involving the lumbosacral junction, and fractures without neurologic injury.

      Surgical options range from minimally invasive techniques to formal open reduction and
      internal fixation. Techniques for neural decompression include laminotomy and foraminotomy,
      anterior bone disimpaction, and lumbosacral plexus neurolysis. Anterior sacral and pelvic
      stabilization techniques involve various methods of anterior stabilization of the pelvic ring
      (e.g., application of a sacroiliac plate). Posterior stabilization techniques include
      percutaneous sacroiliac screw fixation, bilateral sacroiliac screw fixation with posterior
      tension-band plate fixation, posterior alar plate fixation, and lumbopelvic segmental
      fixation.

      Percutaneously placed iliosacral screws are commonly used for the fixation of sacroiliac
      joint disruptions and for sacral fractures. Adequate experience and intraoperative imaging is
      necessary to safely insert these screws, since the safe corridor for placement is fairly
      small. In some patients, such as those with a dysmorphic sacrum.

      Transiliac posterior tension band fixation, offers an alternative method for stabilization of
      the posterior pelvic ring.

      It is indicated in:vertically unstable comminuted sacral fractures, for which iliosacral
      screws may be insufficient. It is also indicated in patients with a dysmorphic sacrum in whom
      there is no safe corridor for placement of iliosacral screws. Threaded rods or a posterior
      plate may be secured to the posterior ilium.Also it can be used in bilateral sacral fracture;
      Late presented (neglected) sacral fractures and in osteoporotic sacral fracture.It is
      Minimally invasive technique with Less exposure to irradiation, image-independent, Easy,
      reproducible technique, Economic conventional implant and stable fixation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 6, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Majeed functional outcome score</measure>
    <time_frame>6th month</time_frame>
    <description>it is a pelvic injury-specific assessment divided into seven items such as pain, work, sitting, sexual intercourse, standing, gait unaided, and walking distance, with a total score range of 0-100 in order of decreasing disability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Sacral Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention</arm_group_label>
    <description>To study the indication and results of fixing the sacral fracture by tension band plating</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>follow up of cases fixed by posterior tension band plate</intervention_name>
    <description>Follow up of the reduction and functional outcome evaluation using the Majeed functional outcome score</description>
    <arm_group_label>No intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        fixation of sacral fractures by posterior tenstion band plate then follow up of the
        functional outcome by majeed outcome score at 6th month post operative
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  comminuted sacral fracture,

          -  bilateral sacral fracture,

          -  osteoporotic sacral fractures,

          -  spinopelvic dissociation and

          -  late presented (neglected) sacral fracture.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a preoperative diagnosis of a Morel- Lavallee lesion,

          -  unfit patients

          -  immature skeleton will be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut faculty of medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <zip>71111</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suzuki T, Hak DJ, Ziran BH, Adams SA, Stahel PF, Morgan SJ, Smith WR. Outcome and complications of posterior transiliac plating for vertically unstable sacral fractures. Injury. 2009 Apr;40(4):405-9. doi: 10.1016/j.injury.2008.06.039. Epub 2008 Dec 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19095233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Padalkar P, Pereira BP, Kathare A, Sun KK, Kagda F, Joseph T. Trans-iliosacral plating for vertically unstable fractures of sacral spine associated with spinopelvic dissociation: A cadaveric study. Indian J Orthop. 2012 May;46(3):274-8. doi: 10.4103/0019-5413.96376.</citation>
    <PMID>22719112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sasso RC, Vaccaro AR, Chapman JR, Best NM, Zdeblick TA, Harris MB. Sacral fractures. Instr Course Lect. 2009;58:645-55.</citation>
    <PMID>19385574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bahaaeldin Mohamed Abdelhafez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

