<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03601949</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>105-17-0002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03601949</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lateral Branch Cooled Radiofrequency Denervation vs. Conservative Therapy for Sacroiliac Joint Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Multi-center, Randomized, Assessor Blind, Controlled Study Comparing Lateral Branch Cooled Radiofrequency Denervation to Conservative Therapy as Treatment for Sacroiliac Joint Pain in a Military and Civilian Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Avanos Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Avanos Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, controlled, multi-center clinical study. Approximately 208
      subjects will be enrolled at approximately 12-15 active duty military, veterans' care, and
      civilian sites. Eligible subjects will be randomized in 1:1 ratio to receive either
      Sacroiliac denervation using CRF (treatment group) or standard medical management (&quot;SMM,&quot;
      control group).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a 12-month prospective, randomized, controlled, prospective, open-label,
      multi-center clinical study. Adult subjects over the age of 21 with diagnosed chronic
      intractable sacroiliac joint pain (≥ 3 months), who have been previously unresponsive to
      conservative therapy and who meet the selection criteria are eligible to participate in this
      study. Approximately 208 subjects will be enrolled at up to 15 sites in a 1:1 randomization
      ratio to receive either denervation using the SInergy System (cooled radiofrequency (CRF),
      treatment group) or standard medical management (SMM, control group). Follow-up will be
      conducted for a total of 12 months post-Coolief (cooled radiofrequency ablation) procedure,
      with the primary endpoint being completed at month 3. The control arm will utilize physician
      prescribed standard medical management (SMM). For this protocol, this includes, but is not
      limited to, medications, physical therapy, lifestyle changes, acupuncture, yoga,
      chiropractic, and therapeutic injections. An optional crossover-to-treatment design was
      adopted for subjects randomized to standard medical management after their 3-month visit,
      because it would be considered unethical to withhold treatment that could potentially offer
      pain relief to those subjects undergoing standard medical management who continue to suffer
      from pain.

      Eligibility includes BOTH of the following:

        -  50% pain relief lasting for the expected duration of anesthetic or medication from a
           therapeutic or diagnostic sacroiliac joint injection; AND

             -  50% pain relief lasting for the expected duration of anesthetic from a standardized
                set of lateral branch blocks, with total volume of no more than 1 milliliter (ml)
                of 0.5% Bupivacaine, Ropivacaine (or similar). Ideally, 0.5 ml will be utilized at
                L5 and the remaining 0.5 ml should be divided in at least two locations along the
                foramen line

      After the CRF treatment, the CRF treatment group subjects will visit the blinded assessor for
      follow up at 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months. At the month 3 visit (three months
      post-randomization), subjects initially randomized to the conservative therapy group will be
      assessed to determine eligibility to receive CRF treatment.

        -  If the conservative treatment subjects fail conservative therapy at 3 months (defined as
           failure to obtain a 2-point decrease in average pain score from baseline AND failure to
           obtain a rating of at least 5 on the Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) scale),
           they will be given the option of receiving CRF treatment.

        -  Subjects who choose to cross-over will ideally receive treatment within 30 days of their
           3-month visit but they must receive treatment within 90 days of their 3-month visit.
           They will then be followed-up at 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months following CRF denervation
           (new Day 0).

        -  If the conservative treatment group subjects refuse or don't qualify for CRF treatment
           at 3 months, they will subsequently be followed-up at 6, 9, and 12 months from their Day
           0.

      Primary Analysis is planned after all initially treated subjects have completed their 3-month
      post-procedure visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 29, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study is an assessor blinded trial and deliberate action will be needed to ensure the blind remains. This begins with randomization procedures and carries through the follow up visits. It is suggested that all follow up visit documentation not contain the visit number, but instead utilize visit dates to track progress.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in average daily pain Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) - score range = 0 - 10. &quot;0&quot; corresponds to &quot;no pain&quot; and &quot;10&quot; indicates &quot;worst pain imaginable&quot;. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of subjects with at least a 2 points decrease or 30% drop in average daily pain related NRS score AND a rating of at least 5 on the Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) - score range = 0 - 10. &quot;0&quot; corresponds to &quot;no pain&quot; and &quot;10&quot; indicates &quot;worst pain imaginable&quot;. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group. PGIC - score range = 1 - 7. &quot;1&quot; corresponds to &quot;very much improved&quot; and &quot;7&quot; indicates &quot;very much worse&quot; pertaining to overall activity, symptoms, emotions, and quality of life. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in score of Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>PGIC - score range = 1 - 7. &quot;1&quot; corresponds to &quot;very much improved&quot; and &quot;7&quot; indicates &quot;very much worse&quot; pertaining to overall activity, symptoms, emotions, and quality of life. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in score of Short Form 36-Physical Functioning (SF36-PF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Short Form 36-PF - score range = 0 - 100. &quot;0&quot; corresponds to &quot;greatest disability&quot; and &quot;100&quot; indicates &quot;no disability&quot;. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in score of Oswestry Disability Index (ODI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>ODI - score range = 0 - 100. &quot;0&quot; corresponds to &quot;no disability&quot; and &quot;100&quot; indicates the &quot;maximum disability possible&quot;. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in score of EuroQuol (EQ) 5D-5L</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This tool involves two components: 1) descriptive system - five questions that are scored 1-5, each with &quot;1&quot; indicating no problems and &quot;5&quot; indicating the worst problem related to the question, and 2) EQ-Visual Analog Scale (VAS) - score range = 0 - 100. &quot;0&quot; corresponds to the &quot;worst imaginable health state&quot; and &quot;100&quot; indicates the &quot;best imaginable health state&quot;. The means of these scores and their respective standard deviations are reported for each study group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The mean change in pain-related medication</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The absolute mean difference between analgesic use at baseline and that at 3 months post-randomization.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Used to evaluate the use or need for other healthcare treatments (e.g., physical therapy, visit(s) to chiropractor). The evaluation is not based on a point-based scale, but rather is based on responses made by trial subjects to the questions, with the determination made by the investigator.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time from treatment to return to work/duty</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Trial subject will be asked if/when she/he returned to work/duty</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time from treatment to return of pain date</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Trial subject will be asked if/when she/he experienced a return of pain</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">208</enrollment>
  <condition>Sacroiliac Joint Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SInergy Cooled Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Halyard Health SInergy Cooled Radiofrequency in addition to standard medical management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medical Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard Medical Management</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SInergy Cooled Radiofrequency</intervention_name>
    <description>ablation of low back pain</description>
    <arm_group_label>SInergy Cooled Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SInergy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Medical Management</intervention_name>
    <description>physical therapy, medications, lifestyle changes</description>
    <arm_group_label>Medical Management</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SInergy Cooled Radiofrequency</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Standard Medical Management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater than or equal to 21 years.

          2. Able to understand the informed consent, and able to complete outcome measures.

          3. Sacroiliac joint (SIJ) pain that is refractory to standard of care treatments such as
             non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS), physical therapy, etc.

          4. At least one positive SIJ pain provocation test (Distraction, Gaenslen's, FABER,
             Sacral Sulcus tenderness, thigh thrust, compression or sacral thrust).

          5. Back pain is predominantly below the lumbar (L) 5 vertebrae.

          6. Chronic low back pain lasting for longer than three months.

          7. Greater than 50% pain relief lasting for the expected duration of anesthetic or
             medication from a therapeutic or diagnostic SIJ injection.

          8. Greater than 50% pain relief lasting the duration of anesthetic from lateral branch
             block (done on different days than SIJ injection).

          9. Stabilized on pain medication regimen for &gt; 2 months, as defined by a &lt; 10% change in
             dosage.

         10. Numeric rating scale indicating an average pain score of &gt; 4 over the last seven days.
             (returned to pre-lateral branch block baseline pain).

         11. All other possible sources of low back pain have been ruled out as the primary pain
             generator, including, but not limited to: suspected advanced degenerative joint
             disease, the intervertebral discs, bone fracture, the zygapophyseal joints, the hip
             joint, symptomatic spondylolisthesis, tumor, and other regional soft tissue structures
             (this is done by physical exam, medical history, and magnetic resonance
             imaging/computed tomography/X-ray, as required).

         12. Willing to utilize double barrier contraceptive method, if of child-bearing potential.

         13. Willingness to provide informed consent and to comply with the requirements of this
             protocol for the full duration of the study.

         14. Physician believes ablation of the SIJ is an appropriate treatment for the patient.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Poorly controlled severe psychiatric illness or ongoing psychological barriers to
             recovery, as determined by the treating physician.

          2. Spinal pathology that may impede recovery such as spina bifida occulta, grade II or
             higher spondylolisthesis at vertebrae L5/sacroiliac (S) 1, or scoliosis.

          3. Symptomatic moderate or severe foraminal or central canal stenosis.

          4. Systemic infection or localized infection at anticipated introducer entry site.

          5. Uncontrolled immunosuppression (e.g., acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS),
             cancer, diabetes, etc.)

          6. Chronic severe conditions such as rheumatoid/inflammatory arthritis.

          7. Pregnancy or recent delivery (within three months).

          8. Active radiculopathy pain from lumbar spine.

          9. Active hip pathology.

         10. Major surgery within three months prior to signing informed consent.

         11. Prior radiofrequency denervation of the lateral sacral nerves.

         12. Ongoing/unresolved worker's compensation, injury litigation, military medical board,
             or disability remuneration claims.

         13. Allergy to injected substances or medications used in procedure.

         14. Body mass index (BMI) &gt; 40 kilograms/meter (squared).

         15. Current prescribed opioid medications equivalent to 90 mg of morphine per 24 hours or
             greater.

         16. Subject is currently implanted with pacemaker, stimulator, or defibrillator.

         17. Participation in another clinical trial/investigation that could interfere with this
             trial 30 days prior to signing informed consent.

         18. Subject is unwilling or unable to comply with the protocol requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Curd, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Avanos Medical</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>William Keck, BS</last_name>
    <phone>470-448-5509</phone>
    <email>william.keck@avanos.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Curd, MS</last_name>
    <phone>470-448-5178</phone>
    <email>david.curd@avanos.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mehul Desai</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mehul Desai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-808-8295</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Millennium Pain Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bloomington</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>61704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ricardo Vallejo, MD</last_name>
      <phone>309-220-9852</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ochsner Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Orleans</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yashar Eshraghi, MD</last_name>
      <phone>504-894-2864</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shravani Durbhakula</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shravani Durbhakula, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-2393</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Walter Reed National Military Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20889</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Reece</last_name>
      <phone>301-295-8572</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chestnut Hill</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pradeep Dinakar, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-732-9816</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sean Li</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shrewsbury</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sean Li, MD</last_name>
      <phone>732-930-2423</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Adam Carinci</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Adam Carinci, MD</last_name>
      <phone>585-273-5875</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Womack Army Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fort Bragg</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28307</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chang Min Ho</last_name>
      <phone>315-254-9831</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Center for Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Leonardo Kapural, MD</last_name>
      <phone>336-714-8381</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest Baptist Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Hurley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>336-716-1228</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Investigations</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmond</city>
        <state>Oklahoma</state>
        <zip>73013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Douglas Beall, MD</last_name>
      <phone>405-601-2325</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kim Mauer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandy Christensen, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Kim Mauer</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lynn Kohan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lynn Kohan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>434-243-5675</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Michael DePalma</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23235</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael DePalma, MD</last_name>
      <phone>804-330-0303</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 12, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 12, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Back Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Low Back Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Sacroiliac Back Pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

