<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03609996</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ML29652</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03609996</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Retrospective Review of Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Retrospective Review of Patients With Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy and Regression of PDR After Treatment With Ranibizumab</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Elman Retina Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Roche-Genentech</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Elman Retina Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of the protocol is to determine if intravitreal ranibizumab alone
      decreases retinal neovascularization from Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy (PDR) with
      deferred panretinal photocoagulation (PRP) and/or vitrectomy at one year after treatment with
      ranibizumab has been initiated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Current standard treatment for Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy (PDR) is panretinal
      photocoagulation (PRP), but this treatment is inherently destructive and has several
      potential adverse effects on aspects of visual function, including constriction of peripheral
      visual fields and decreases in night vision, contrast sensitivity and color perception. Thus,
      therapeutic alternatives that might delay or obviate the need for PRP are desirable. It has
      been demonstrated that retinal neovascularization from PDR is highly responsive to anti-VEGF
      therapy, but it is unclear how long regression of retinal neovascularization is sustained
      after anti- VEGF therapy is halted in clinical practice.

      It is possible that intravitreal ranibizumab treatment could prevent laser-associated vision
      loss by precluding the need for PRP as long as the eye continued to receive ranibizumab. Even
      if ranibizumab treatment was discontinued, it is possible that initial treatment with
      anti-VEGF therapy might improve visual outcomes substantially by delaying or preventing the
      need for PRP, and the infrequent frequency of administration of ranibizumab for DME (median 2
      to 3 times in the second year of treatment) after the DME initially has resolved on anti-VEGF
      therapy suggests that monthly ranibizumab might not be needed to achieve control of PDR.

      The Diabetic Retinopathy Clinical Research Network (DRCR network) is currently evaluating
      intravitreal ranibizumab treatment to see if can prevent laser-associated vision loss by
      precluding the need for PRP as long as the eye continued to receive ranibizumab. However,
      intravitreal injections carry the risk of serious complications. Ophthalmic complications
      include endophthalmitis in 2% of all injected patients cumulatively. Endophthalmitis is a
      vision threatening and can cause severe and permanent vision loss and even loss of the eye.
      Other complications include vitreous hemorrhage, retinal detachment, uveitis and glaucoma.
      This study will evaluate ranibizumab usage as the primary treatment for PDR in a busy private
      clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical regression of neovascularization not requiring further treatment beyond RBZ</measure>
    <time_frame>2009-2018</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical regression of neovascularization not requiring further treatment beyond RBZ</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Proliferative Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Laser</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Lucentis</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Panretinal Photocoagulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Laser treatment for PDR</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Lucentis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lucentis</intervention_name>
    <description>Intraviteral injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Laser</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PDR treated with Lucentis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Approximately 160 eyes that have been diagnosed with PDR that have been treated with
        ranibizumab will be looked at retrospectively.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &gt;= 18 years Individuals &lt;18 years old are not being included because PDR is so
             rare in this age group that the diagnosis of PDR may be questionable.

          2. Diagnosis of diabetes mellitus (type 1 or type 2)

             Any one of the following will be considered to be sufficient evidence that diabetes is
             present:

               -  Current regular use of insulin for the treatment of diabetes

               -  Current regular use of oral anti-hyperglycemia agents for the treatment of
                  diabetes

               -  Documented diabetes by ADA and/or WHO criteria (see Procedures Manual for
                  definitions

          3. Presence of PDR which the investigator has treated the study eye(s) with ranibizumab

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of prior panretinal photocoagulation prior to initiating ranibizumab

          2. Tractional retinal detachment involving the macula.

               -  A tractional retinal detachment is not an exclusion if it is outside of the
                  posterior pole (not threatening the macula)

          3. History of vitrectomy prior to initiating ranibizumab

          4. Treatment with Ranibizumab within six months of treatment regimen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Elman</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Elman Retina Group, P.A.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Elman Retina Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21237</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>July 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ranibizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

