<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03765957</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018-MSC/CSU/PS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03765957</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Research on Treatment of Psoriasis by Human Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Research on Treatment of Psoriasis by Human Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Central South University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Central South University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the effect and safety of treatment of psoriasis by human umbilical cord
      blood-derived mesenchymal stem cell
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Psoriasis is a chronic and recurrent inflammatory skin disease and its histological features
      are characterized by epidermal hyperplasia, increased angiogenesis and immune cell
      infiltration. Psoriasis prevalence is about 0.1%-3%, affecting approximately 125 million
      people worldwide. In China, there are about 10 million psoriasis patients.

      Human umbilical cord blood-derived MSC (hUCB-MSC) has many advantages for the treatment of
      immune disease. Because it was demonstrated that hUCB-MSCs are effective in modulating immune
      cells and treating diseases and it has low immunogenicity. Furthermore, hUCB-MSCs do not
      raise ethical issue for clinical applications.

      Some experimental results and cases has showed that mesenchymal stem cell (MSC) can prevent
      or treat psoriasis. This clinical study is conducted to provide more data to evaluate the
      effect and safety of treatment of psoriasis by human umbilical cord blood-derived mesenchymal
      stem cell.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving Psoriasis Area and Severity Index ≥75% (PASI 75) Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI combines assessments of the extent of body-surface involvement in 4 anatomical regions (head, trunk, arms, and legs) and the severity of desquamation (scaling), erythema, and plaque induration/infiltration (thickness) in each region, yielding an overall score of 0 for no psoriasis to 72 for the most severe disease. Participants achieving PASI 75 was defined as having an improvement of at least 75% in the PASI scores compared to baseline.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving a Static Physician Global Assessment (sPGA) of (0, 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The sPGA is a physician's determination of the participant's psoriasis lesions overall at a given time point categorized by descriptions for induration, erythema, and scaling. For the analysis of responses, the participant's psoriasis is assessed as clear (0), minimal (1), mild (2), moderate (3), severe (4), or very severe (5). An sPGA (0,1) response was defined as a post-baseline sPGA score of 0 or 1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving an sPGA (0)</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The sPGA is a physician's determination of the participant's psoriasis lesions overall at a given time point categorized by descriptions for induration, erythema, and scaling. For the analysis of responses, the participant's psoriasis is assessed as clear (0), minimal (1), mild (2), moderate (3), severe (4), or very severe (5). An sPGA (0) response was defined as a post-baseline sPGA score of 0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving ≥90% (PASI 90) Improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI combines assessments of the extent of body-surface involvement in 4 anatomical regions (head, trunk, arms, and legs) and the severity of desquamation (scaling), erythema, and plaque induration/infiltration (thickness) in each region, yielding an overall score of 0 for no psoriasis to 72 for the most severe disease. Participants achieving PASI 90 were defined as having an improvement of at least 90% in the PASI scores compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Achieving 100%</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI combines assessments of the extent of body-surface involvement in 4 anatomical regions (head, trunk, arms, and legs) and the severity of desquamation (scaling), erythema, and plaque induration/infiltration (thickness) in each region, yielding an overall score of 0 for no psoriasis to 72 for the most severe disease. Participants achieving PASI 100 were defined as having an improvement of at least 100% in the PASI scores compared to baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI) Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Month 6</time_frame>
    <description>The DLQI is a simple, participant-administered, 10 question, validated, quality-of-life questionnaire that covers 6 domains: symptoms and feelings, daily activities, leisure, work and school, personal relationships, and treatment. Response categories include &quot;not at all,&quot; &quot;a lot,&quot; and &quot;very much,&quot; with corresponding scores of 1, 2, and 3, respectively, and unanswered (&quot;not relevant&quot;) responses scored as &quot;0.&quot; Totals range from 0 to 30 (less to more impairment), and a 5 point change from baseline is considered clinically relevant. Least Square (LS) Means in total DLQI score were calculated using Mixed Model Repeated Measures (MMRM) with baseline score as covariate, treatment, pooled center, visit and treatment-by-visit interaction as fixed effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mesenchymal stem cells will be derived from human umbilical cord. The subjects will be injected intravenously with 1x10E6/kg （according to the weight of subject）mesenchymal stem cells at baseline and every 2 weeks until week 6.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Methotrexate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The subjects will be treated with oral methotrexate 7.5-15mg every week (The dose will start from 7.5mg/w and increase to 15mg/w depending on the response of subjects). This is a conventional systemic treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</intervention_name>
    <description>The subjects will be injected intravenously with 1x10E6/kg （according to the weight of subject）Human Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells at baseline and every 2 weeks until week 6. Besides MSC, conventional moisturizer such 10% boric acid ointment is given to all patients in the treatment and follow-up period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Human Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>The subjects will be treated with oral methotrexate 7.5-15mg every week (The dose will start from 7.5mg/w and increase to 15mg/w depending on the response of subjects). Besides methotrexate, conventional moisturizer such 10% boric acid ointment is given to all patients in the treatment and follow-up period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral Methotrexate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosed according to Classification criteria for Psoriasis vulgaris for more than 6
             months;

          2. Body Mass Index (BMI) between 18.5-35;

          3. Resistance to phototherapy, systemic therapy, or a combination of these therapies

          4. BSA(body surface area)&gt;10%, sPGA&gt;3 and PASI&gt;10 at baseline;

          5. Understanding the whole process of the study, voluntary participation and signed the
             informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. WBC(white blood cell count ) &lt;3.0x109/L, blood platelet count&lt;100x109/L,
             hemoglobin&lt;100g/L serum creatinine&gt;1.5 x ULN(upper limit of normal), bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x
             ULN(upper limit of normal), AST(SGOT,glutamic-oxalacetic
             transaminase)/ALT(SGPT,glutamic-pyruvic transaminase) &gt;2.5 x ULN(upper limit of
             normal);

          2. Pregnant women, or women who ready for pregnancy or lactating;

          3. Have a serious heart, lung, kidney and other vital organs and endocrine system lesions
             and the history;

          4. Patients suffering from malignant tumor;

          5. Patients suffering from any acute or chronic infectious diseases;

          6. Mental disorders, history of alcohol abuse, drug or other substance abuse;

          7. Patients participated in any clinical trials within 3 months or any stem cell therapy
             within 6 months;

          8. Having a serious allergic history or being allergic to two or more than 2 kinds of
             food or drugs;

          9. Patients who have received systemic therapy within recent one month or topical therapy
             in two weeks;

         10. Either HIV-antibody(human immunodeficiency virus-antibody), HBV-antibody (hepatitis B
             virus-antibody ) or syphilis antibody is positive;

         11. Other cases which researchers believe that can not enroll.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mi Zhang</last_name>
    <phone>08615116331788</phone>
    <phone_ext>08615116331788</phone_ext>
    <email>648979182@qq.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Comella K, Parlo M, Daly R, Dominessy K. First-in-man intravenous implantation of stromal vascular fraction in psoriasis: a case study. Int Med Case Rep J. 2018 Mar 21;11:59-64. doi: 10.2147/IMCRJ.S163612. eCollection 2018.</citation>
    <PMID>29606893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee YS, Sah SK, Lee JH, Seo KW, Kang KS, Kim TY. Human umbilical cord blood-derived mesenchymal stem cells ameliorate psoriasis-like skin inflammation in mice. Biochem Biophys Rep. 2016 Oct 8;9:281-288. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrep.2016.10.002. eCollection 2017 Mar.</citation>
    <PMID>28956015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boehncke WH, Schön MP. Psoriasis. Lancet. 2015 Sep 5;386(9997):983-94. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61909-7. Epub 2015 May 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26025581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owczarczyk-Saczonek A, Krajewska-Włodarczyk M, Kruszewska A, Placek W, Maksymowicz W, Wojtkiewicz J. Stem Cells as Potential Candidates for Psoriasis Cell-Replacement Therapy. Int J Mol Sci. 2017 Oct 20;18(10). pii: E2182. doi: 10.3390/ijms18102182. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29053579</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guan LX, Guan H, Li HB, Ren CA, Liu L, Chu JJ, Dai LJ. Therapeutic efficacy of umbilical cord-derived mesenchymal stem cells in patients with type 2 diabetes. Exp Ther Med. 2015 May;9(5):1623-1630. Epub 2015 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>26136869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ra JC, Kang SK, Shin IS, Park HG, Joo SA, Kim JG, Kang BC, Lee YS, Nakama K, Piao M, Sohl B, Kurtz A. Stem cell treatment for patients with autoimmune disease by systemic infusion of culture-expanded autologous adipose tissue derived mesenchymal stem cells. J Transl Med. 2011 Oct 21;9:181. doi: 10.1186/1479-5876-9-181.</citation>
    <PMID>22017805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dahbour S, Jamali F, Alhattab D, Al-Radaideh A, Ababneh O, Al-Ryalat N, Al-Bdour M, Hourani B, Msallam M, Rasheed M, Huneiti A, Bahou Y, Tarawneh E, Awidi A. Mesenchymal stem cells and conditioned media in the treatment of multiple sclerosis patients: Clinical, ophthalmological and radiological assessments of safety and efficacy. CNS Neurosci Ther. 2017 Nov;23(11):866-874. doi: 10.1111/cns.12759. Epub 2017 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28961381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cui GH, Wang YY, Li CJ, Shi CH, Wang WS. Efficacy of mesenchymal stem cells in treating patients with osteoarthritis of the knee: A meta-analysis. Exp Ther Med. 2016 Nov;12(5):3390-3400. Epub 2016 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27882169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Central South University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yijing He</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal Stem Cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

