<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04233905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KJPP 2017-00679</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04233905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Factors Influencing Selective Mutism</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Psychometric Questionnaire Study With a Control Group Design of Children and Young People With Selective Mutism, as Well as on Adults Who Suffered Selective Mutism Earlier in Life</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Susanne Walitza</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study's goal is to check and verify basic assumptions of a new selective mutism
      developmental model from Melfsen and Walitza through standardized and routinely used patient
      questionnaires. The primary emphasis is the question of a connection between selective mutism
      and high sensitivity, dissociation, emotional regulation, family structure, social anxiety
      and self-esteem.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms severity of selective mutism</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The parent report &quot;Selective Mutism Questionnaire (SMQ)&quot; is a 17-item parent-rating measure designed to assess the severity of selective mutism. The test uses a 4-point scale to rate the frequency of the child`s speaking behaviour in school (6 items), home/family (6 items) and public settings outside school (5 items) from 0 (never) to 3 (always) each, with a total score of 51. Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;Highly Sensitive Person Scale&quot; (HSP) is a self-report questionnaire with 27 items to be answered on a seven-point Likert scale (from 1 &quot;not at all&quot; to 7 &quot;absolutely&quot;). The total score divided by item number ranges from 0 to 7. Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Family relation structure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;Parent-Image-Questionnaire for Children and Adolescents (EBF-KJ)&quot; is a self-reporting questionnaire for children and adolescents to record the family relationship structure with 36 items on a five-point Likert scale from 0 (never) to 4 (always). Higher score means a stronger characteristic.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotion regulation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Emotion regulation is measured using the German questionnaire &quot;Fragebogen zur Erhebung der Emotionsregulation bei Kindern und Jugendlichen (FEEL-KJ). It is a multi-dimensional tool for the emotion-specific detection of emotion regulation strategies. It measures fear, sadness and anger. Adaptive strategies include problem-oriented behavior, dispersion, mood elevation, acceptance, forgetting, revaluation and cognitive problem solving. Maladaptive strategies include abandonment, aggressive behavior, withdrawal, self-devaluation and perseveration. A total of 90 items is to be rated on the basis of a five-level rating scale with regard to their frequency. Higher scores mean more adaptive or maladaptive strategies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of selective mutism</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Symptom severity is assessed by using the &quot;Checklist for speaking behaviour, parent report&quot; (CheckS). It assesses the communicative burden of various socially interactive situations for children suffering from selective mutism on a five-point scale (from 0 = &quot;never&quot; to 4 = &quot;always&quot;). A distinction is made between different contexts, namely the persons to be spoken to, the type of communication, the length of the spoken answers, the conversational situations, the contents of the conversation, the places and surroundings, the expectations of those present and the unpredictability of contexts. The total score ranges from 0 to 4.Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dissociation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The German translation of the &quot;Child Dissociative Checklist&quot; (CDC) is a parent report of 20 items using a three-point Likert scale (0 = &quot;very true&quot;, 1 =&quot;somewhat true&quot;, 2 =&quot;not true&quot;). Parents are asked to report dissociative behavioural problems of their child within the past 12 months. Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dissociation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The children and adolescents completed the &quot;Self-Perception Questionnaire for Children and Adolescents&quot; (A-DES) to assess dissociative symptoms. 30 items are to be assessed on an 11-point rating scale (from 0 = &quot;never&quot; to 10 = &quot;always&quot;) in terms of their frequency. Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Social anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The German version of the &quot;Social phobia and anxiety inventory for children (SPAIK) is used to asses social anxiety in children and adolescents. The questionnaire consists of 26 situations assessing somatic, cognitive and behavioural aspects of social anxiety. They measure characteristic aspects of social anxiety on a three-point Likert scale (from 0 = &quot;never or seldom&quot; to 3 = &quot;most of the time or always&quot;) with a total score of 52. Higher score means a worse outcome.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-esteem</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;List of statements on self-esteem for children and adolescents&quot; (ALS) uses the same 18 items to differentiate the self-esteem of children and adolescents in three areas: family, school and leisure. Higher score means a stronger self-esteem.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">92</enrollment>
  <condition>Selective Mutism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mute children</arm_group_label>
    <description>mute children and their mothers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy children</arm_group_label>
    <description>healthy children control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mute adults</arm_group_label>
    <description>formerly mute adults</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy adults</arm_group_label>
    <description>healthy adults control group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychometric questionnaire study</intervention_name>
    <description>Four groups participate in the psychometric questionnaire study. A group of mute children and their mothers (EG:A), as well as a normal, healthy control group (KG:A) with roughly the same age and sex characteristics fill out one-time questionnaires about current daily life experiences. In addition, another group of formerly mute adults (EG:B) as well as a comparable age/sex normal control group will be retrospectively questioned using the same specifically tailored questionnaire.</description>
    <arm_group_label>healthy adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>healthy children</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>mute adults</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>mute children</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The sample consist of pupils with selective mutism aged 8 to 18 years.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children and young people from 8-18 years of age who fulfill the international
             classification of diseases tenth edition (ICD-10) for selective mutism

          -  Adults who suffered selective mutism when they were children or adolescents

          -  All study participants or their legal representative have given written permission for
             their experiences to be documented in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Temporary mutism, e.g. from emotional disturbances or separation anxiety (F93.0), or
             depression

          -  Profound developmental disturbances (F84.2) like early childhood autism (F84.0),
             atypical autism (F84.1), Rett Syndrome (F84.2), alternative disintegrative childhood
             disturbances (F84.3), hyperactivity disturbance with decrease of intelligence and
             movement stereotypes (F84.5), or Asperger's Syndrome.

          -  Schizophrenia (F20)

          -  Profound mental retardation

          -  Delineated development disturbances of speech and language (F80)

          -  Organic brain disease with loss of language or disturbance of speech development
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susanne Walitza, Prof. Dr. med. Dipl.-Psych.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sponsor-Investigator</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric University Clinics, Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <state>ZH</state>
        <zip>8032</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susanne Walitza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of the Department of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mutism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

