<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04236570</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-3022</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04236570</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Endogenous Pain Modulation Mechanisms With Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Endogenous Pain Modulation Mechanisms With Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Université de Sherbrooke</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Université de Sherbrooke</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A number of chronic pain conditions are characterized by imbalances in excitatory and/or
      inhibitory mechanisms and these deficits appear correlated with the response to certain
      treatments. Evaluating these mechanisms among people who suffer from chronic pain could allow
      clinicians to adapt the treatment to each patient according to the deficits observed. To
      evaluate excitatory and inhibitory mechanisms, a thermode (hot plate) and a cold water bath
      can be used (standardized protocol). Unfortunately, these tools are expensive, time-consuming
      and require complex equipment and software. As such, it is not realistic for clinicians to
      use them for routine patient assessment. A potential alternative to study these mechanisms is
      TENS (transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation). TENS is frequently used in rehabilitation
      and unlike thermode and cold water bath, is affordable, easy to use and requires very little
      time and equipment. The objective of this study are to determine if the TENS can replace the
      thermode and cold water bath (standardized protocol) for the evaluation of excitatory and
      inhibitory mechanisms. Also, to determine if there will be a correlation with the
      standardized protocol. 50 healthy participants between 18 and 60 years old will participate
      in this study. Each participant will attend two experimental sessions. In one of the two
      sessions, the evaluation will be done with the TENS; in the other session, the evaluation
      will be done with the standardized protocol (thermode and cold water bath).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate excitatory and inhibitory mechanisms, the investigators will used the modified
      CPM testing procedure consisting of test stimulus (TS) administered before and after a
      conditioning stimulus (CS). For the standardized protocol, the TS will consisted of a noxius
      heat stimulus generated by a thermode (hot plate), applied for two minutes on the
      non-dominant anterior forearm. The CS will consisted of a cold pressor test (CT), wherein
      participants immersed their dominant forearm in a cold water bath for two minutes. For the
      TENS protocol, the TS will consisted of a noxius electrical stimulus generated by TENS,
      applied for 5 seconds on the non-dominant knee at a frequency of 1 Hz and 5 Hz. The CS will
      consisted of a noxius electrical stimulus generated by TENS' applied for 120 seconds on the
      non dominant knee and ankle at a frequency of 2 Hz.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 15, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 15, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will attended two experimental sessions at the Research Center on Aging of the Centre Intégré Universitaire de Santé et de Services Sociaux de l'Estrie, Sherbrooke, during which the efficacy of their excitatory and inhibitory mechanisms was assessed. In one session, this assessment was done using TENS protocol; in the other, using a standardized protocol (thermode and cold water bath). Session order was randomized between participants (randomization by block of 4 stratified by sex, using a random number table). The two sessions were separated by 24 to 72 hours and lasted approximately one hour each.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate excitatory mechanisms, specifically temporal summation</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcomes (excitatory pain mechanisms) will be evaluated at both sessions (V1 [day 0] and V2 [day 7])</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate excitatory mechanisms ,we will calculated if there is an increase of pain levels during the test stimulus (TS). Pain levels will be measured with a computerized visual analogue scale (CoVAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate inhibitory mechanisms, specifically conditioning pain modulation (CPM)</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome (mechanisms) will be evaluated at both sessions (V1 [day 0] and V2 [day 7])</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate inhibitory mechanisms ,we will calculated if there is an decrease of pain levels after the conditioning stimulus (CS). Pain levels will be measured with a computerized visual analogue scale (CoVAS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain tests with the standardized protocol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will consisted of pain tests using the standardized protocol (thermode(hot plate) and cold water bath)). The investigators will used the modified CPM testing procedure consisting of stimulus test (TS) administered before and after a conditioning stimulus (CS). For the standardized protocol, the TS will consisted of a noxius heat stimulus generated by a thermode (hot plate), applied for two minutes on the non-dominant anterior forearm. The CS will consisted of a cold pressor test (CT), wherein participants immersed their dominant forearm in a cold water bath for two minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pain tests with the TENS protocol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will consisted of pain tests using the TENS protocol. The investigators will used the modified CPM testing procedure consisting of stimulus test (TS) administered before and after a conditioning stimulus (CS). For the TENS protocol, the TS will consisted of a noxius electrical stimulus generated by TENS, applied for 5 seconds on the non-dominant knee at a frequency of 1 Hz and 5 Hz. The CS will consisted of a noxius electrical stimulus generated by TENS' applied for 120 seconds on the non dominant knee and ankle at a frequency of 2 Hz</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Thermode(hot plate) and cold water bath</intervention_name>
    <description>Standardized protocol will consisted of stimulus test (TS) generated by thermode and conditioning stimulus (CS) using cold water bath.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pain tests with the standardized protocol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TENS(transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation)</intervention_name>
    <description>TENS protocol will consisted of test stimulus (TS) and conditioning stimulus (CS) both generated by TENS</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pain tests with the TENS protocol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Man or woman between 18 and 60 years old (inclusive)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic pain

          -  Neurological disorders

          -  Musculoskeletal disorders

          -  Depression

          -  Raynaud syndrome

          -  History of non-efficacy with TENS

          -  History of epilepsy

          -  Presence of a pacemaker or metal implants

          -  Antidepressant

          -  Anticonvulsant

          -  Analgesics

          -  Caffeine
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Guillaume Léonard, Pht; Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>8197802220</phone>
    <phone_ext>45246</phone_ext>
    <email>guillaume.leonard2@usherbrooke.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Monica Sean, B.Sc</last_name>
    <phone>8197802220</phone>
    <phone_ext>45681</phone_ext>
    <email>monica.sean@usherbrooke.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de Recherche sur le Vieillissement</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherbrooke</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>J1H 4C4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guillaume Léonard, Pht; Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>8197802220</phone>
      <phone_ext>45246</phone_ext>
      <email>guillaume.leonard2@usherbrooke.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monica Sean, B.Sc</last_name>
      <phone>8197802220</phone>
      <phone_ext>45681</phone_ext>
      <email>monica.sean@usherbrooke.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Guillaume Léonard, Pht; Ph.D</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 22, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 31, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Université de Sherbrooke</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Guillaume Léonard</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Excitatory mechanisms</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhibitory mechanisms</keyword>
  <keyword>Thermode(hot plate)</keyword>
  <keyword>Cold water bath</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

