<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04231331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2019-1690</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04231331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ertugliflozin for Functional Mitral Regurgitation</brief_title>
  <acronym>EFFORT</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicenter, Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Phase 3 Study to Assess the Efficacy of Ertugliflozin on Reduction of Mitral Regurgitation in Patients With Functional Mitral Regurgitation Secondary to Left Ventricular Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In patients with heart failure (HF) and left ventricular (LV) dilation, adverse LV remodeling
      causes tethering of mitral valve (MV) preventing sufficient coaptation of normal leaflets and
      resulting in functional MR. Because secondary functional MR usually develops as a result of
      LV dysfunction, guideline-directed medical therapy for HF forms the mainstay of therapy.
      However, beta blockers, angiotensin-converting-enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, and angiotensin
      receptor blockers (ARB) fail to reverse adverse LV remodeling and functional MR, and the
      morbidity and mortality of patients with functional MR remain high despite standard medical
      therapy. Randomized trials to explore cardiovascular (CV) benefit of the sodium-glucose
      co-transporter-2 (SGLT2) inhibitor have been performed and showed a significant reduction on
      the risk of CV death or hospitalization for HF. However, its effect on cardiac structure and
      function was not evaluated and further mechanistic studies are needed to interpret beneficial
      clinical effects of the SGLT2 inhibitors. Based on studies demonstrating SGLT2 inhibitors'
      favorable effects on LV modeling, investigators hypothesize that SGLT2 inhibitor,
      ertugliflozin, is effective on improving MR in patients with functional MR secondary to LV
      dysfunction and try to examine this hypothesis in a multicenter, double-blind, randomized
      comparison study using echocardiography.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In patients with heart failure (HF) and left ventricular (LV) dilation, adverse LV remodeling
      causes tethering of mitral valve (MV) preventing sufficient coaptation of normal leaflets and
      resulting in functional MR. Because secondary functional MR usually develops as a result of
      LV dysfunction, guideline-directed medical therapy for HF forms the mainstay of therapy.
      However, beta blockers, angiotensin-converting-enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, and angiotensin
      receptor blockers (ARB) fail to reverse adverse LV remodeling and functional MR, and the
      morbidity and mortality of patients with functional MR remain high despite standard medical
      therapy. A recent randomized trial proved that reduction of functional MR by transcatheter MV
      repair resulted in a lower rate of hospitalization for HF and lower mortality in patients
      with HF and significant secondary MR, and investigators recently demonstrated that the
      angiotensin receptor-neprilysin inhibitor (ARNI) is more effective in improving functional MR
      associated with HF than the ARB in a double-blind, randomized trial. In this trial,
      investigators enrolled 118 stable HF patients with functional MR, whose effective regurgitant
      orifice area (EROA) larger than 0.1 cm2, lasting &gt; 6 months despite standard medical
      treatment, and the primary end point of change in EROA was significantly different between
      the ARNI group and the ARB group (-0.058±0.095 versus -0.018±0.105 cm2; P=0.032), and a
      decrease in end-diastolic volume index of the LV was also significantly greater in the ARNI
      group than in the ARB group (P=0.044).

      Sodium-glucose co-transporter-2 (SGLT2) inhibitors reduce cardiac preload and afterload by
      natriuresis and lowering arterial stiffness, similar to the neprilysin inhibitor that
      facilitates sodium excretion and has vasodilating effects. In addition, effects on blood
      pressure reduction and weight loss may ultimately have a beneficial effect on LV remodeling.
      Recently it has been reported that SGLT2 inhibitors have a multifaceted effect on cardiac
      function including improvement in endothelial dysfunction and aortic stiffness, reduction in
      epicardial fat accumulation as well as in visceral adipocyte hypertrophy. Randomized trials
      to explore cardiovascular (CV) benefit of the SGLT2 inhibitor have been performed and showed
      a significant reduction on the risk of CV death or hospitalization for HF. However, its
      effect on cardiac structure and function was not evaluated and further mechanistic studies
      are needed to interpret beneficial clinical effects of the SGLT2 inhibitors. Based on studies
      demonstrating SGLT2 inhibitors' favorable effects on LV modeling, investigators hypothesize
      that SGLT2 inhibitor, ertugliflozin, is effective on improving MR in patients with functional
      MR secondary to LV dysfunction and try to examine this hypothesis in a multicenter,
      double-blind, randomized comparison study using echocardiography.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of EROA</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of effective regurgitant orifice area (EROA) of functional mitral regurgitation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of regurgitant volume</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of regurgitant volume of functional mitral regurgitation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of end-systolic volume</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of left ventricular end-systolic volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of end-diastolic volume</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of left ventricular end-diastolic volume</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of NT-proBNP</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of NT-proBNP (N-terminal of the prohormone brain natriuretic peptide)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of GLS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change of left ventricular global longitudinal strain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">224</enrollment>
  <condition>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</condition>
  <condition>Left Ventricular Systolic Dysfunction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will receive placebo in addition to their usual medications. Titration of HF medications should be completed and patients must take a stable, optimized dose of a β-blocker and an ACE inhibitor (or ARB) for at least 4 weeks prior to study entry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ertugliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All patients will receive ertugliflozin 5 mg qd in addition to their usual medications. Titration of HF medications should be completed and patients must take a stable, optimized dose of a β-blocker and an ACE inhibitor (or ARB) for at least 4 weeks prior to study entry.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ertugliflozin</intervention_name>
    <description>Ertugliflozin 5mg qd for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ertugliflozin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Steglatro</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo qd for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must agree to the study protocol and provide written informed consent

          -  Outpatients ≥ 20 years of age, male or female

          -  Non-diabetic or type2 DM patients with HbA1c 7.0-10.5%

          -  Patients with secondary functional MR (stage B and C) and LV dysfunction

               -  Symptoms due to coronary ischemia or heart failure may be present but symptoms
                  due to MR should be absent

               -  Normal mitral valve leaflets and chords

               -  Regional or global wall motion abnormalities with mild or severe tethering of
                  leaflet

               -  MR whose ERO &gt; 0.10 cm2 and which lasted &gt; 6 months under medical treatment with
                  a β-blocker and an ACE inhibitor (or ARB)

               -  35% &lt; LV ejection fraction &lt; 50%

          -  Dyspnea of NYHA functional class II or III

          -  Titration of HF medications should be completed and patients must take a stable,
             optimized dose of a β-blocker and an ACE inhibitor (or ARB) for at least 4 weeks prior
             to study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of hypersensitivity or allergy to the study drug, drugs of similar chemical
             classes, or SGLT-2 as well as known or suspected contraindications to the study drug

          -  Current use or prior use of a SGLT-2 inhibitor or combined SGLT-1 and 2 inhibitor

          -  Known history of angioedema

          -  Any evidence of structural mitral valve disease, including prolapse of mitral leaflets
             and rupture of chords or papillary muscles

          -  Current acute decompensated heart failure or dyspnea of NYHA functional class IV

          -  Medical history of hospitalization within 6 weeks

          -  Symptomatic hypotension and/or a SBP &lt; 100 mmHg at screening

          -  Estimated GFR &lt; 45 mL/min/1.73m2

          -  History of ketoacidosis

          -  Evidence of hepatic disease as determined by any one of the following: AST or ALT
             values exceeding 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN) at screening visit (Visit 0), history
             of hepatic encephalopathy, history of esophageal varices, or history of portacaval
             shunt.

          -  Acute coronary syndrome, stroke, major CV surgery, PCI within 3 months

          -  Substantial myocardial ischemia requiring coronary revascularization, a plan of
             coronary revascularization or mitral valve intervention within 1 year

          -  Indication of cardiac resynchronization therapy, a plan of heart transplantation or
             implantation of cardiac resynchronization therapy

          -  History of severe pulmonary disease

          -  Significant aortic valve disease

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, unless they are using a barrier method plus a hormonal method

          -  Pregnant or nursing (lactating) women

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality identified at the screening visit, physical
             examination, laboratory tests, or electrocardiogram which, in the judgment of the
             investigator, would preclude safe completion of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>DUK HYUN KANG, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Asan Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>DUK HYUN KANG, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+82230103166</phone>
    <email>dhkang@amc.seoul.kr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samsung Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Seung Woo Park, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>parksmc@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Seung Woo Park, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seoul National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yong-Jin Kim, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>kimdamas@snu.ac.kr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yong-Jin Kim, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 14, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Duk-Hyun Kang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>5-(4-chloro-3-(4-ethoxybenzyl)phenyl)-1-hydroxymethyl-6,8-dioxabicyclo(3.2.1)octane-2,3,4-triol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

