<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04234399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UVMCC1905</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BED-IIT 280</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04234399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Determination of the Diagnostic Detection Rate of Axumin (Fluciclovine) Digital PET/CT, Post-prostatectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Determination of the Diagnostic Detection Rate of Axumin (Fluciclovine) PET/CT Utilizing the High Resolution Digital Philips Vereos Scanner, in Patients With Biochemical Recurrence After Radical Prostatectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Vermont</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Vermont</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fluciclovine F18 (Axumin) has been demonstrated to provide good delineation of recurrence of
      prostate cancer after definitive therapies. Fluciclovine in conjunction with the
      high-resolution digital Vereos (Phillips) PET-CT scanner may detect low volume recurrence in
      the prostatectomy bed or metastatic site (s).

      20-40 % of men will suffer a biochemical recurrence of their prostate cancer after radical
      prostatectomy, depending on their final pathological staging, defined as a rising PSA &gt; 0.2
      ng/ml.

      The ability to more accurately diagnose local recurrence (i.e. pelvis) or oligometastasis may
      lead to the opportunity of precise therapy of these sites with more durable cancer responses,
      less morbidity and potential cure in selective men after Radical Prostatectomy.

      The ability to diagnose widespread metastatic Prostate Cancer after Radical Prostatectomy, or
      disease that is inaccessible to local selective therapies would spare these men the cost and
      morbidity of inappropriate therapy.

      The diagnosis of true stage D0 Prostate Cancer (No objective evidence of metastases) in men
      after Radical Prostatectomy would yield improved overall and disease specific survival if
      Androgen Deprivation Therapy was initiated at its earliest stage. This would also obviate the
      need for inappropriate local therapies (i.e. pelvic radiotherapy).

      The aim is to compare the detection rate of standard of care (CT Pelvis/Abdomen, MR Pelvis,
      Bone Scan) with Fluciclovine PET/CT performed on the Vereos Philips Scanner. The study aims
      to compare the performance of Digital (high resolution) PET to CT/MRI/Bone scan rather than
      analog (lower resolution) PET. Prior studies have tested analog PET compared to other
      modalities. One could make an inference that if our study's Digital PET performs better than
      the performance of Analog PET in those studies, then Digital PET should have a better
      detection rate than Analog PET. However, investigators are not making a direct comparison
      between digital and Analog in our comparison.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim:

      Compare the detection rate of standard of care (CT Pelvis/Abdomen, MR Pelvis, Bone Scan) with
      Fluciclovine PET/CT performed on the Vereos Philips Scanner. The study aims to compare the
      performance of Digital (high resolution) PET to CT/MRI/Bone scan rather than analog (lower
      resolution) PET. This was reported in Michopoulou S, O'Shaughnessy E, Thomson K, Guy MJ.
      Discovery Molecular Imaging Digital Ready PET/CT performance evaluation according to the NEMA
      NU2-2012 standard. Nucl Med Commun. 2018 Nov 27; doi:10.1097/MNM.0000000000000962. Prior
      studies have tested analog PET compared to other modalities. One could make an inference that
      if our study's Digital PET performs better than the performance of Analog PET in those
      studies, then Digital PET should have a better detection rate than Analog PET. However,
      investigators are not making a direct comparison between digital and Analog in our
      comparison.

      Background:

      Fluciclovine F18 (Fluciclovine) has been demonstrated to provide good delineation of
      recurrence of prostate cancer after definitive therapies (Odewole OA et al 2016).
      Fluciclovine in conjunction with the high-resolution digital Vereos (Phillips) PET-CT scanner
      may detect low volume recurrence in the prostatectomy bed or metastatic site (s).

      20-40 % of men will suffer a biochemical recurrence of their prostate cancer after radical
      prostatectomy, depending on their final pathological staging, defined as a rising PSA &gt; 0.2
      ng/ml.

      The ability to more accurately diagnose local recurrence (i.e. pelvis) or oligometastasis may
      lead to the opportunity of precise therapy of these sites with more durable cancer responses,
      less morbidity and potential cure in selective men after Radical Prostatectomy.

      The ability to diagnose widespread metastatic Prostate Cancer after Radical Prostatectomy, or
      disease that is inaccessible to local selective therapies would spare these men the cost and
      morbidity of inappropriate therapy.

      The diagnosis of true stage D0 Prostate Cancer (No objective evidence of metastases) in men
      after Radical Prostatectomy would yield improved overall and disease specific survival if
      Androgen Deprivation Therapy was initiated at its earliest stage. This would also obviate the
      need for inappropriate local therapies (i.e. pelvic radiotherapy).

      Preliminary Studies:

      The safety, efficacy, reproducibility, and reliability of Fluciclovine was initially
      evaluated by the Emory group in men with suspected recurrence of prostate cancer based on
      rising PSA levels following radical prostatectomy and/or radiotherapy. Fluciclovine's safety,
      detection rate, and diagnostic performance was further validated in a multi-site data
      aggregation study using data from Emory, Noway, and Italy.

      The performance of Fluciclovine seems to be affected by degree of PSA elevation.
      Statistically significant difference in performance compared to CT was found at PSA levels &gt;1
      ng/ml. However, at a PSA level of &lt;1 ng/ml, no statistically significant difference was found
      by Odewole et al. These findings were independent of PSA doubling time and Gleason Score.

      The Bologna study evaluated the concordance between Fluciclovine and C11 Choline scans in
      patients with median PSA value of 1.44 ng/ml (interquartile range = 0.78 to 2.8 ng/ml).5 The
      accuracy of Fluciclovine was 38% vs 32% for C11 Choline. In a subsequent Emory study which
      studied Fluciclovine without a correlative imaging test, Fluciclovine scan detected
      recurrence in 72% (18/25) of patients with PSA of &lt;1 ng/ml. However, there was no
      reconciliation of false positive examinations, as all abnormal radiotracer uptake were deemed
      a true positive. Performance of Fluciclovine was again noted to improve with increasing PSA
      levels, at 83% (5/6) for PSA of 1-&lt;2 ng/ml and 100% (11/11) for PSA&gt;= 2 ng/ml.

      Rationale:

      A Fluciclovine scan can detect and localize recurrent prostate cancer. Fluciclovine is an
      FDA-approved diagnostic imaging agent, also known as a &quot;tracer,&quot; which may help determine if
      and where the prostate cancer has recurred.

      Procedures:

      Fluciclovine is used as a tracer for a PET/CT scan. Patients will need to prepare for the
      Fluciclovine (fluciclovine F 18) injection and scan. They will need avoid any significant
      exercise for at least a full 24 hours prior to Fluciclovine PET/CT scan and not eat or drink
      for at least 4 hours prior to PET/CT scan (other than small amounts of water for taking
      medications).

      With respect to determining if a finding is true positive, investigators will follow the
      following process. The research PET scan of each patient and SOC imaging will be read by
      radiologists blinded to the results of the other test. The results of both will then be
      reviewed by PI for concordance. If the research PET scan finds sites of disease that were not
      identified on SOC imaging, the case will be brought to Interdisciplinary UVMMC Genitourinary
      tumor board. Depending on the site of disease and presence of other concordant sites of
      metastatic disease between scans, it may have no impact on the SOC treatment. If it is deemed
      by the UVMMC Genitourinary Tumor Board that it will have a meaningful impact on treatment
      decisions and the detected lesion is accessible to be safely sampled, the patient will be
      approached by their treating physician to discuss the discordant findings, their
      significance, and the rationale behind a biopsy and its impact on their care.

      The sampling will then be performed a part of standard-of-care work-up, given that these
      patients would have been eligible for Fluciclovine PET imaging in this setting, per FDA
      label. Given the low PSA range of our target population in this study, the likelihood that
      these lesions would be amenable to sampling using conventional image guidance is low.
      Therefore, in cases where the research scan finds additional disease that would alter
      therapy, the decision of whether to act on it will be based on the overall clinical scenario
      of each patient, and will be decided by the treating team with the support of the UVMMC
      Genitourinary Tumor Board.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Detection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be scheduled for both SOC imaging as well as the Fluciclovine PET within 4 weeks of screening and signing of informed consent. The detection rates between SOC and Fluciclovine scans will be compared.</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of Fluciclovine digital PET/CT with standard of care imaging. Single time point.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients receiving SOC imaging and Axumin PET scans.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluciclovine PET/CT using a digital PET/CT</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluciclovine is a radiotracer that will be used in conjunction with the high resolution digital Vereos PET/CT scanner.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Prostatectomy patients with previously undetectable PSA and subsequent biochemical
        recurrence defined by PSA between 0.2 ng/ml and 1.0 ng/ml within 4 weeks prior to
        Fluciclovine scan
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Prostatectomy patients with previously undetectable PSA and subsequent biochemical
             recurrence defined by PSA between 0.2 ng/ml and 1.0 ng/ml within 4 weeks prior to
             Fluciclovine scan

          2. Age &gt;40

          3. Ability to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of allergic reaction to Fluciclovine

          2. Anti Androgen treatment in the 6 months prior to enrollment

          3. Any patient whose body habitus, as determined by radiology personnel, will effectively
             inhibit the ability to obtain PET/CT imaging or will interfere with the images so as
             to make them clinically uninterpretable.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aida Arapovic</last_name>
    <phone>802-847-6845</phone>
    <email>Aida.Arapovic@uvmhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dmitriy Akselrod, MD</last_name>
    <phone>802-847-2700</phone>
    <email>Dmitriy.Akselrod@uvmhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UVM Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Burlington</city>
        <state>Vermont</state>
        <zip>05401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aida Arapovic, MS</last_name>
      <phone>802-847-6845</phone>
      <email>Aida.Arapovic@uvmhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dmitriy G Akselrod, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2016/208054s000lbl.pdf</url>
    <description>Axumin FDA prescribing information</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.astro.org/Patient-Care-and-Research/Clinical-Practice-Statements/ASTRO-39;s-guideline-on-adjuvant-and-salvage-RT-af</url>
    <description>ASTRO/AUA Guideline on Adjuvant and Salvage Radiation Therapy After Prostatectomy</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schuster DM, Nieh PT, Jani AB, Amzat R, Bowman FD, Halkar RK, Master VA, Nye JA, Odewole OA, Osunkoya AO, Savir-Baruch B, Alaei-Taleghani P, Goodman MM. Anti-3-[(18)F]FACBC positron emission tomography-computerized tomography and (111)In-capromab pendetide single photon emission computerized tomography-computerized tomography for recurrent prostate carcinoma: results of a prospective clinical trial. J Urol. 2014 May;191(5):1446-53. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2013.10.065. Epub 2013 Oct 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24144687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Odewole OA, Oyenuga OA, Tade F, Savir-Baruch B, Nieh PT, Master V, Chen Z, Wang X, Jani AB, Bellamy LM, Halkar RK, Goodman MM, Schuster DM. Reproducibility and reliability of anti-3-[¹⁸F]FACBC uptake measurements in background structures and malignant lesions on follow-up PET-CT in prostate carcinoma: an exploratory analysis. Mol Imaging Biol. 2015 Apr;17(2):277-83. doi: 10.1007/s11307-014-0797-1.</citation>
    <PMID>25281411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schuster DM, Savir-Baruch B, Nieh PT, Master VA, Halkar RK, Rossi PJ, Lewis MM, Nye JA, Yu W, Bowman FD, Goodman MM. Detection of recurrent prostate carcinoma with anti-1-amino-3-18F-fluorocyclobutane-1-carboxylic acid PET/CT and 111In-capromab pendetide SPECT/CT. Radiology. 2011 Jun;259(3):852-61. doi: 10.1148/radiol.11102023. Epub 2011 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21493787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Odewole OA, Tade FI, Nieh PT, Savir-Baruch B, Jani AB, Master VA, Rossi PJ, Halkar RK, Osunkoya AO, Akin-Akintayo O, Zhang C, Chen Z, Goodman MM, Schuster DM. Recurrent prostate cancer detection with anti-3-[(18)F]FACBC PET/CT: comparison with CT. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2016 Sep;43(10):1773-83. doi: 10.1007/s00259-016-3383-8. Epub 2016 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>27091135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nanni C, Zanoni L, Pultrone C, Schiavina R, Brunocilla E, Lodi F, Malizia C, Ferrari M, Rigatti P, Fonti C, Martorana G, Fanti S. (18)F-FACBC (anti1-amino-3-(18)F-fluorocyclobutane-1-carboxylic acid) versus (11)C-choline PET/CT in prostate cancer relapse: results of a prospective trial. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2016 Aug;43(9):1601-10. doi: 10.1007/s00259-016-3329-1. Epub 2016 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26960562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akin-Akintayo OO, Jani AB, Odewole O, Tade FI, Nieh PT, Master VA, Bellamy LM, Halkar RK, Zhang C, Chen Z, Goodman MM, Schuster DM. Change in Salvage Radiotherapy Management Based on Guidance With FACBC (Fluciclovine) PET/CT in Postprostatectomy Recurrent Prostate Cancer. Clin Nucl Med. 2017 Jan;42(1):e22-e28.</citation>
    <PMID>27749412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bruce JY, Lang JM, McNeel DG, Liu G. Current controversies in the management of biochemical failure in prostate cancer. Clin Adv Hematol Oncol. 2012 Nov;10(11):716-22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23271258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paller CJ, Antonarakis ES. Management of biochemically recurrent prostate cancer after local therapy: evolving standards of care and new directions. Clin Adv Hematol Oncol. 2013 Jan;11(1):14-23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23416859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ost P, Reynders D, Decaestecker K, Fonteyne V, Lumen N, De Bruycker A, Lambert B, Delrue L, Bultijnck R, Claeys T, Goetghebeur E, Villeirs G, De Man K, Ameye F, Billiet I, Joniau S, Vanhaverbeke F, De Meerleer G. Surveillance or Metastasis-Directed Therapy for Oligometastatic Prostate Cancer Recurrence: A Prospective, Randomized, Multicenter Phase II Trial. J Clin Oncol. 2018 Feb 10;36(5):446-453. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2017.75.4853. Epub 2017 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>29240541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Radwan N, Phillips R, Ross A, Rowe SP, Gorin MA, Antonarakis ES, Deville C, Greco S, Denmeade S, Paller C, Song DY, Diehn M, Wang H, Carducci M, Pienta KJ, Pomper MG, DeWeese TL, Dicker A, Eisenberger M, Tran PT. A phase II randomized trial of Observation versus stereotactic ablative RadiatIon for OLigometastatic prostate CancEr (ORIOLE). BMC Cancer. 2017 Jun 29;17(1):453. doi: 10.1186/s12885-017-3455-6.</citation>
    <PMID>28662647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith MR, Saad F, Chowdhury S, Oudard S, Hadaschik BA, Graff JN, Olmos D, Mainwaring PN, Lee JY, Uemura H, Lopez-Gitlitz A, Trudel GC, Espina BM, Shu Y, Park YC, Rackoff WR, Yu MK, Small EJ; SPARTAN Investigators. Apalutamide Treatment and Metastasis-free Survival in Prostate Cancer. N Engl J Med. 2018 Apr 12;378(15):1408-1418. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1715546. Epub 2018 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>29420164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bach-Gansmo T, Nanni C, Nieh PT, Zanoni L, Bogsrud TV, Sletten H, Korsan KA, Kieboom J, Tade FI, Odewole O, Chau A, Ward P, Goodman MM, Fanti S, Schuster DM, Willoch F. Multisite Experience of the Safety, Detection Rate and Diagnostic Performance of Fluciclovine ((18)F) Positron Emission Tomography/Computerized Tomography Imaging in the Staging of Biochemically Recurrent Prostate Cancer. J Urol. 2017 Mar;197(3 Pt 1):676-683. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2016.09.117. Epub 2016 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>27746282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andriole GL, Kostakoglu L, Chau A, Duan F, Mahmood U, Mankoff DA, Schuster DM, Siegel BA; LOCATE Study Group. The Impact of Positron Emission Tomography with 18F-Fluciclovine on the Treatment of Biochemical Recurrence of Prostate Cancer: Results from the LOCATE Trial. J Urol. 2019 Feb;201(2):322-331. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2018.08.050.</citation>
    <PMID>30179618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 14, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Vermont</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dmitriy Akselrod, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Recurrence</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluciclovine</keyword>
  <keyword>Axumin</keyword>
  <keyword>PSA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

