<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04234698</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>B0661148</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04234698</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Characteristics, Treatment Patterns And Incidence Of Events (Discontinuation, Persistence, Key Primary Clinical Outcomes) In NVAF Patients Initiating OAC Therapy In Colombia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient Characteristics, Treatment Patterns and Incidence of Events (Discontinuation, Persistence, Key Primary Clinical Outcomes) in NVAF Patients Initiating OAC Therapy in Colombia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pfizer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aim to assess demographic and clinical characteristics , treatment patterns and as
      exploratory analysis will descriptively assess the time to clinical events of NVAF patients
      treated with oral anticoagulants (OACs) in Colombia through observational, descriptive study
      of a retrospective cohort of adult patients diagnosed with NVAF in selected Health
      Maintenance Organizations (HMO) of Colombia. The information will be used in the study comes
      exclusively form secondary sources: claim databases and medical records.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study has the following primary objectives:

        -  To assess demographic and clinical characteristics of NVAF patients treated with oral
           anticoagulants (OACs) in Colombia.

        -  To describe treatment patterns (eg OAC usage,dose, concomitant medications, persistance)

      And as exploratory analysis to descriptively assess the time to clinical events
      (Effectiveness and Safety Outcomes) among patients persistent on OAC therapy

      It is an observational, descriptive study of a retrospective cohort of adult patients
      diagnosed with NVAF in selected Health Maintenance Organizations (HMO) of Colombia. These
      patients will be identified from the drug claim database, whose index date of the study will
      be the first prescription with any of the oral anticoagulants, that is, they are patients
      with NVAF for the first time starting a therapy with any of the NOACs between January 1, 2013
      and June 30, 2018 and follow up period will be among January 2013 to July 2019, to ensure
      that the last patients can provide follow-up for one year. Patients will be required to have
      an NVAF diagnosis before or on the index date and health plan for 6 months pre-index date
      (baseline period). Colombia. The information will be used in the study comes exclusively form
      secondary sources: claim databases and medical records.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage distribution of clinical and demographic characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Demographic (age, sex, race, and geographical distribution) and clinical (BMI, comorbidities, HASBLED,CHAD2DS2-VAC, NVAF time) characteristic will be measured according to report in medical records at baseline</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of use of OACs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to ocurrence of discontinuation, switch of treatment, death or first event of stroke/ systemic embolism, major bleeding event, death or end of follow-up, whichever came first , assessed up to 156 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>It includes frequency of use per OACs describing the dosage, discontinuation and persistence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rate of Stroke/ Systemic Embolism</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to ocurrence of discontinuation, switch of treatment, death or first event of stroke/ systemic embolism, major bleeding event, death or end of follow-up, whichever came first , assessed up to 156 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rate will be calculated by the number of first event of stroke/systemic embolism from baseline until the ocurrence of discontinuation, switch of treatment, death or first event of stroke/ systemic embolism, major bleeding event, death or end of follow-up divided by patient-months estimated by calculating all of the months that patients were exposed to OACs during follow up.The ICD-10 codes relative to these events will be used to identified the events in medical records</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rate of major bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to ocurrence of discontinuation, switch of treatment, death or first event of stroke/ systemic embolism, major bleeding event, death or end of follow-up, whichever came first , assessed up to 156 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rate will be calculated by the number of first event of major bleeding from baseline until the ocurrence of discontinuation, switch of treatment, death or first event of stroke/ systemic embolism, major bleeding event, death or end of follow-up divided by patient-months estimated by calculating all of the months that patients were exposed to OACs during follow up.The ICD-10 codes relative to these events will be used to identified the events in medical records</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The total population of patients treated with any oral anticoagulant between January 1,
        2013 and June 30, 2018 will be analyzed in the claim database. This means that patients who
        start warfarin and NOACs would be included within this period. Patients who initiate NOACs
        within the established period and who have been exposed to warfarin before 2013 will also
        be included.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of AF considered according to the following diagnoses as per
             the 10th revision of the International classification of diseases (ICD-10) I48 codes
             at some point before or on the index date, without recorded valvular disease;

          -  Patients who have started treatment with apixaban, dabigatran, rivaroxaban and
             warfarin for the first time during the identification period, understanding as start
             of drug delivery by insurer, and after the diagnosis of AF between January 1, 2013 to
             June 30, 2018;

          -  Patients starting apixaban, dabigatran, rivaroxaban from January 1, 2013 to June 30,
             2018 in patients previously exposed to warfarin;

          -  Patient had continuous health plan enrolment for 6 months pre-index date (baseline
             period);

          -  Patients older than 18 years old on the index date;

          -  NVAF diagnosis before or on the index date.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with any of the following diagnoses prior to the use of the treatments of
             interest or index date:

               -  Valvular heart disease or valve replacement - ICD-10 codes: I05, I06, I07, I08,
                  I09, I21, I22, I34, I35, I36, I37, I38, I39, I700, I702-I709; Q22, Q23, Q25, T82,
                  Z95

               -  Pregnancy during the study period. ICD-10 O00-O9A

               -  Diagnosis of venous thromboembolism (VTE) - ICD-10 codes: I26, I80 - I82;

          -  Individuals with a transitory diagnosis of NVAF prior to the use of the treatments of
             interest or index date;

          -  Exposure to more than one OAC on or after the index date, during the follow-up period;

          -  NOAC doses different from those recommended by the manufacturing laboratories.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Pfizer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pfizer CT.gov Call Center</last_name>
    <phone>1-800-718-1021</phone>
    <email>ClinicalTrials.gov_Inquiries@pfizer.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 21, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>oral anticoagulants</keyword>
  <keyword>apixaban</keyword>
  <keyword>rivaroxaban</keyword>
  <keyword>dabigatran</keyword>
  <keyword>warfarin</keyword>
  <keyword>non valvular atrial fibrillation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Pfizer will provide access to individual de-identified participant data and related study documents (e.g. protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP), Clinical Study Report (CSR)) upon request from qualified researchers, and subject to certain criteria, conditions, and exceptions. Further details on Pfizer's data sharing criteria and process for requesting access can be found at: https://www.pfizer.com/science/clinical_trials/trial_data_and_results/data_requests.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

