<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04230239</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LAMVYX</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2018-004353-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04230239</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Toxicity of Induction and Consolidation With CPX-351 for Patients Aged 60 to 75 Years With Secondary or High-risk Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>LAMVYX</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Multicentre, Open Label Clinical Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Toxicity of Induction and Consolidation With CPX-351 for Patients Aged 60 to 75 Years With Secondary or High-risk Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PETHEMA Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PETHEMA Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This protocol corresponds to a prospective, multicentre, open label, phase II study designed
      to evaluate the efficacy of CPX-351 in elderly patients with secondary or high-risk AML. The
      clinical trial is divided into pre-treatment, treatment (induction and consolidation cycles)
      and follow-up periods and consists of a single arm group. Patients will be enrolled at
      diagnosis to follow the treatment arm. After that will start induction chemotherapy with
      CPX-351 regimen (14 days maximum screening period). Once a patient have been evaluated for
      response and recovered from major complications, he/she will start second course
      (consolidation 1), unless the bone marrow and peripheral blood assessment is showing less
      than a complete response, then a second induction may be offered. If a CR or CRi is obtained
      after the second induction course, patients will start the third course after a rest and
      recovery period. Patients aged between 60 and 65 years old are recommended to undergo an
      allo-SCT after first consolidation if they are considered fit for this procedure and they
      have a full matched related or unrelated donor. Patients aged between 65 and 70 years old can
      be proposed for an allo-SCT in CR/CRi if they have a composite HSCT co-morbidity index /age
      less than 4 and a suitable fully matched related donor. In patients over 70 years old, an
      allo-SCT in first CR should be avoided although the decision should be taken on an individual
      basis. Patients with CR/CRi who are not considered for an allo-SCT, will follow 6 maintenance
      cycles with modified courses of CPX-351 schedule. Patients showing unacceptable toxicity
      along all therapeutic phases that, in consideration of the investigator, will be prematurely
      discontinued. All patients will be followed-up for survival. The study will be analyzed on an
      intention to treat basis. Bone marrow and response assessments will be done after each
      induction and consolidation course, and every 3 months during the first 12 months after
      starting maintenance therapy. Patients will be followed-up for a minimum period of 1 year
      after the enrolment of the last patient. Additionally, after the end of the trial, patients
      will be followed-up for 2 years in order to verify survival and the evolution of the disease.
      Study design allows a maximum of 59 patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, multicenter, open-label, phase II study to assess efficacy of CPX-351
      in elderly patients (60 to 75 years of age) with newly diagnosed high risk AML. The study
      includes a single arm group. The primary endpoint of the study is to assess the CR/CRi rate
      after induction with CPX-351.

      Patients will be enrolled at diagnosis to follow the treatment arm. After that they will
      start induction chemotherapy with CPX-351 regimen (14 days maximum screening period). Once a
      patient has been evaluated for response and recovered from major complications (minimum 42
      days and maximum 80 days after starting the first course), he/she will start second course
      (consolidation 1), unless the bone marrow and peripheral blood assessment is showing less
      than a partial response. If a CR or CRi is obtained after the second course, patients will
      start the third course after a rest and recovery period (minimum 42 days and maximum 80 days
      after starting the second course). After the third course an assessment of response will be
      done.

      Patients aged between 60 and 65 years old are recommended to undergo an allo-SCT after first
      consolidation if they are considered fit for this procedure and they have a full matched
      related or unrelated donor. Patients with age less than 65-70 years old can be proposed for
      an allogeneic HSCT in CR/CRi if they have a composite HSCT co-morbidity index /age less than
      4 and a suitable fully matched related donor. In patients over 70 years old, an allo-SCT in
      first CR should be avoided although the decision should be taken on an individual basis.

      Patients with CR/CRi who are not considered for an allo-SCT, will follow 6 maintenance cycles
      with modified courses of CPX-351 schedule. Patients showing unacceptable toxicity along all
      therapeutic phases that, in consideration of the investigator, will be prematurely
      discontinued. All patients will be followed-up for survival. The study will be analyzed on an
      intention to treat basis. Bone marrow and response assessments will be done after each
      induction and consolidation course, and every 3 months after starting maintenance therapy.
      Patients will be followed-up for a minimum period of 3 years after the enrollment of the last
      patient in order to know OS, disease-free, and relapse free survival (RFS), as well as on the
      duration of remission and cumulative incidence of relapse. Patients may be admitted in
      hospital to receive the experimental treatment.

      The clinical trial is divided into pre-treatment (screening), treatment periods (induction,
      consolidation and maintenance cycles) and follow-up:

      Induction cycle (1 cycle):

      It will consist of priming with daily administration of G-CSF on days -1, 1 and 2 (300
      mcg/m2/day) subcutaneously, CPX-351 day 1, 3 and 5 (100 units/m2/day) IV in 90 minutes
      infusion, and subcutaneous G-CSF from day 10 to recovery (5 mg/kg/day). The chemotherapy
      course may be administered in hospital. If a complete response is obtained after the first
      cycle of treatment, the patient will receive consolidation cycle. If a partial response is
      obtained after the first cycle of treatment, the patient will receive induction 2. Response
      to treatment will be determined by the local investigator and will be the basis for treatment
      decisions. However, if there is any doubt, it should be discussed with the Study coordinator.

      Induction 2 (1 cycle, only for patients with PR after induction 1):

      It will consist of priming with daily administration of G-CSF on days -1, 1 and 2 (300
      mcg/m2/day) subcutaneously, CPX-351 day 1 and 3 (100 units/m2/day) IV in 90 minutes infusion,
      and subcutaneous G-CSF from day 10 to recovery (5 mg/kg/day). The chemotherapy course may be
      administered in hospital.

      Consolidation cycle (up to 2 cycles):

      It will consist of priming with daily administration of G-CSF on days -1, 1 and 2 (300
      mcg/m2/day) subcutaneously, CPX-351 day 1 and 3 (65 units/m2/day) IV in 90 minutes infusion,
      and subcutaneous G-CSF from day 10 to recovery (5 mg/kg/day). The chemotherapy course may be
      administered in hospital. Patients aged between 60 and 65 years old are recommended to
      undergo an allo-SCT after first consolidation if they are considered fit for this procedure
      and they have a full matched related or unrelated donor. Patients with age between 65-70
      years old can be proposed for an allogeneic HSCT in CR/CRi if they have a composite HSCT
      co-morbidity index /age less than 4 and a suitable fully matched related donor. In patients
      over 70 years old, an allo-SCT in first CR should be avoided although the decision should be
      taken on an individual basis.

      Maintenance cycle (up to 6 cycles):

      For patients in CR and when an allo-SCT is not feasible or recommended, a maintenance
      treatment could be started for up to 6 additional cycles, on every 4 to 8 weeks courses,
      according to hematologic recovery.

      It will consist of CPX-351 day 1 (50 units/m2/day) IV in 90 minutes infusion. Subcutaneous
      G-CSF may be used to recovery (5 mg/kg/day) in patients with grade 4 neutropenia and
      confirmed CR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This protocol corresponds to a prospective, multicenter, open-label, phase II study to assess efficacy of CPX-351 in elderly patients (60 to 75 years of age) with newly diagnosed high risk AML. In the context of this protocol, a treatment cycle is defined as the first day of study drug administration (Day 1) up to and including the day before the first day of the treatment cycle immediately afterwards. The treatment cycles will begin after Day 42 but no later than Day 80, counting from Day 1 of the treatment cycle immediately before.
Treatment cycles may be administered while the patient is hospitalized. Patients will receive a maximum of 4 treatment cycles (up to 2 inductions and 2 consolidations) and 6 maintenance cycles. Clinical conditions in the care of patients with acute leukemia require the need for flexibility. However, deviations from the study treatment defined in this section must be prospectively discussed with the coordinator.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the CR/CRi rate after induction with CPX-351</measure>
    <time_frame>After 1 or 2 cycles of induction (between 12 and 16 weeks approximately)</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint of the study is to evaluate the CR/CRi rate after induction with CPX-351. The responses for CR, CRi, PR, therapeutic failure, and disease recurrence are defined for this study based on the revised recommendations of the International Working Group for response criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Adverse Events (Safety and Tolerability) of the CPX-351 induction regimen.</measure>
    <time_frame>The induction cycles (up to 2 cycles) will have a mean estimated duration of 6 weeks per cycle. Safety/toxicity assessments will be done in day 1, 8, 15, 22, 29 and 36 of the induction cycles.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and description of adverse events occurred during induction regimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effect of priming with G-CSF with the CPX-351 regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Priming with G-CSF will be done in the induction cycles (up to 2 cycles) and in the consolidation cycles (up to 2 cycles) that will have an an estimated duration of 6 weeks per cycle.</time_frame>
    <description>Differences of leukocytes values (x10^9/L) from baseline values, will be checked in order to know the effect of priming with G-CSF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Adverse Events (Safety and Tolerability) of the CPX-351 consolidation regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Safety/toxicity assessments will be done in day 1, 8, 15, 22, 29 and 36 of the consolidation cycles</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and description of adverse events occurred during consolidation regimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Adverse Events (Safety and Tolerability) of the CPX-351 maintenance regimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Safety/toxicity assessments will be done every 2 weeks during the manteinance cycles (24 to 40 weeks of maintenance).</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and description of adverse events occurred during maintenance regimen.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Estimated 1, 2 and 3 year OS</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free, disease-free, and relapse free survival (RFS), as well as on the duration of remission and cumulative incidence of relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 2 and 3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of hematologic and non-hematologic adverse events occurred during the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 9 months, which is approximately the estimated mean treatment time.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence and description of hematologic and non-hematologic adverse events occurred during the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the impact on the quality of life, using the European Quality of Life-5 Dimensions (EQ5D) form, in patients treated with CPX-351</measure>
    <time_frame>The cycles will have a mean estimated duration of 6 weeks and Quality of life questionnaire following EQ-5D will be performed at screening, after induction (day 36), after consolidation 2 ( day 36 of cycle 3) and/or prior to allo-SCT</time_frame>
    <description>European Quality of Life-5 Dimensions (EQ-5D)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the impact on the use of medical resources during induction and consolidation phase.</measure>
    <time_frame>The cycles will have a mean estimated duration of 6 weeks and patients may have up to 2 cycles of induction and up to 2 cycles of consolidation.</time_frame>
    <description>Frequencies and descriptions of medical resources (antibiotics, transfusions, etc)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the quality of CR (by study of minimal residual disease percentages in the bone marrow using multiparametric flow cytometry)</measure>
    <time_frame>After first cycle of induction (6 weeks) and after consolidation 1 (cycle 2: 6 weeks after consolidation 1 onset) only in patients achieving CR/CRi after consolidation 1</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate early mortality (first 60 days) in patients initially treated with CPX-351</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 60</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the results with a matched-paired historical cohort of the PETHEMA registry</measure>
    <time_frame>Once the study is completed ( an average of 30 months through study completion)</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the different results between patients included in the CPX-351 trial and a retrospective cohort of patients with similarities characteristics at diagnosis (paired analysis). For this purposes, data will be obtained from the retrospective control cohort of the PETHEMA Epidemiologic Registry of Adult AML. Patients will be matched by age (≤65 vs &gt;65, secondary AML vs therapy-related AML vs high-risk according to 2017ELN).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the rate of allo-SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>After consolidation 1 (aprox 12 weeks) or after consolidation 2 (aprox 18 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate 100 day mortality after allo-SCT</measure>
    <time_frame>100 day after allo-SCT</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess compliance of the maintenance schedule</measure>
    <time_frame>After maintenance (aprox 36 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Measure the number and percentage of patients that start maintenance cycles, and how many discontinues during the manteinance phase or complete all manteinance according to protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Newly Diagnosed Secondary or High Risk AML</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPX-351</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CPX-351</intervention_name>
    <description>CPX-351 has IV administration Vyxeos contains 2.2 mg/mL and 5 mg/mL powder for concentrate for solution for infusion of Daunorubicin and cytarabine.
Each vial contains 44 mg of daunorubicin and 100 mg of cytarabine. After reconstitution, the solution contains 2.2 mg/mL daunorubicin and 5 mg/mL cytarabine</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPX-351</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent in accordance with national, local, and institutional
             guidelines. The patient must provide informed consent prior to the first screening
             procedure. Informed consent form must be signed by the patient and the investigator.

          2. Age 60 to 75 years at the time of diagnosis of AML.

          3. Newly confirmed diagnosed of AML according to WHO 2008 criteria.

          4. Secondary or high risk AML, defined as one of the following:

               -  t-AML: documentation of prior cytotoxic therapy or radiation therapy for an
                  unrelated disease in a discharge summary or pharmacy records or radiation therapy
                  records

               -  MDSAML: bone marrow documentation of MDS prior to diagnosis of AML (could have
                  been treated previously with hypomethylating or standard chemotherapy)

               -  CMMoLAML: bone marrow documentation of CMMoL prior to diagnosis of AML (could
                  have been treated previously with hypomethylating or standard chemotherapy)

               -  de novoAML with FISH or cytogenetic changes linked to MDS per WHO 2016 criteria.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0-2.

          6. Ability to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements.

          7. Laboratory values fulfilling the following:

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/mL

               -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or total
                  bilirubin &lt; 3 times the upper limit of normal (ULN, subjects with elevated liver
                  enzymes related to disease were instructed to contact the Sponsor) (subjects with
                  Gilbert's Syndrome were instructed to contact the sponsor).

          8. Subjects with second malignancies in remission may have been eligible if there was
             clinical evidence of disease stability for a period ≥ 6 months off cytotoxic
             chemotherapy, documented by imaging, tumor marker studies at screening. Subjects
             maintained on long-term nonchemotherapy treatment such as hormonal therapy were
             eligible.

          9. Cardiac ejection fraction ≥ 50% assessed by echocardiography or MUGA.

         10. Eligible to receive intensive chemotherapy.

         11. Female patients of child-bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             at screening and agree to use reliable methods of contraception for three months after
             their last dose of medication. Male patients must use a reliable method of
             contraception (if sexually active with a female of child-bearing potential).

         12. Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory
             tests and other study procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with genetic diagnosis of acute promyelocytic leukemia.

          2. Age &lt;60 years or &gt;75 years.

          3. Blastic phase of bcr/abl chronic myeloid leukemia.

          4. Patients with de novo AML without FISH or cytogenetic changes linked to MDS per WHO
             2016 criteria.

          5. Clinical evidence of active central nervous system (CNS) leukemia.

          6. Subjects with active (uncontrolled, metastatic) second malignancies.

          7. Any major surgery or radiation therapy in 4 weeks.

          8. Subjects with myocardial impairment of any cause (eg, cardiomyopathy, ischemic heart
             disease, significant valvular dysfunction, hypertensive heart disease, and congestive
             heart failure) resulting in heart failure by New York Heart Association Criteria
             (Class III or IV staging).

          9. Uncontrolled infection; subjects with an infection receiving treatment (antibiotic,
             antifungal, or antiviral treatment) could be entered into the study provided the
             subject was respiratory and hemodynamically stable for ≥ 72 hours.

         10. Current evidence of invasive fungal infection (blood or tissue culture); subjects with
             recent fungal infection must have had subsequent negative cultures to be eligible;
             known HIV (new testing not required) or evidence of active hepatitis B or C infection
             (with rising transaminase values).

         11. Hypersensitivity to cytarabine, daunorubicin or liposomal products.

         12. Presence of any severe psychiatric disease or physical condition that, according to
             the physician´s criteria, contraindicates the inclusion of the patient into the
             clinical trial.

         13. Serum creatinine ≥ 20 mg/dL (unless it is attributable to AML activity).

         14. Bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, or SGOT &gt; 3 times the ULN (unless it is attributable
             to AML activity).

         15. Subjects with prior cumulative anthracycline exposure of greater than 368 mg/m2
             daunorubicin (or equivalent).

         16. History of Wilson's disease or other copper-metabolism disorder.

         17. Patients who have received an investigational agent (for any indication) within 5
             half-lives of the agent and until toxicity from this has resolved to grade 1 or less;
             if the half-life of the agent is unknown, patients must wait 4 weeks prior to first
             dose of study treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pau Montesinos Fernández, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario La Fe</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>José Antonio Pérez Simón, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospitales Universitarios Virgen del Rocío</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carmen López-Carrero García</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación Pethema</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Olga García Calduch</last_name>
    <phone>0034 609128678</phone>
    <email>olga.garcia.calduch@fundacionpethema.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Català D'Oncologia-Hospital Germans Trias I Pujol</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susana Vives Polo</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institut Català D'Oncologia - Hospital Duran I Reynals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bellvitge</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Montserrat Arnan Sangerman</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital San Pedro de Alcántara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cáceres</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Juan Miguel Bergua Burgués</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía</name>
      <address>
        <city>Córdoba</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Josefina Serrano López</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Gran Canaria Dr. Negrín</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Palmas</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carlos Rodríguez Medina</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Lucus Augusti</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lugo</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Esperanza Lavilla Rubira</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Ramón Y Cajal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pilar Herrera Puente</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pilar Martínez Sánchez</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Central de Asturias</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oviedo</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Teresa Bernal del Castillo</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Del H.U. Virgen Del Rocío</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José Antonio Pérez Simón</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mar Tormo Díaz</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Y Politécnico La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rebeca Rodríguez Veiga</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Appelbaum FR, Gundacker H, Head DR, Slovak ML, Willman CL, Godwin JE, Anderson JE, Petersdorf SH. Age and acute myeloid leukemia. Blood. 2006 May 1;107(9):3481-5. Epub 2006 Feb 2.</citation>
    <PMID>16455952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juliusson G, Antunovic P, Derolf A, Lehmann S, Möllgård L, Stockelberg D, Tidefelt U, Wahlin A, Höglund M. Age and acute myeloid leukemia: real world data on decision to treat and outcomes from the Swedish Acute Leukemia Registry. Blood. 2009 Apr 30;113(18):4179-87. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-07-172007. Epub 2008 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19008455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dombret H, Seymour JF, Butrym A, Wierzbowska A, Selleslag D, Jang JH, Kumar R, Cavenagh J, Schuh AC, Candoni A, Récher C, Sandhu I, Bernal del Castillo T, Al-Ali HK, Martinelli G, Falantes J, Noppeney R, Stone RM, Minden MD, McIntyre H, Songer S, Lucy LM, Beach CL, Döhner H. International phase 3 study of azacitidine vs conventional care regimens in older patients with newly diagnosed AML with &gt;30% blasts. Blood. 2015 Jul 16;126(3):291-9. doi: 10.1182/blood-2015-01-621664. Epub 2015 May 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25987659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kantarjian HM, Thomas XG, Dmoszynska A, Wierzbowska A, Mazur G, Mayer J, Gau JP, Chou WC, Buckstein R, Cermak J, Kuo CY, Oriol A, Ravandi F, Faderl S, Delaunay J, Lysák D, Minden M, Arthur C. Multicenter, randomized, open-label, phase III trial of decitabine versus patient choice, with physician advice, of either supportive care or low-dose cytarabine for the treatment of older patients with newly diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2012 Jul 20;30(21):2670-7. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2011.38.9429. Epub 2012 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22689805</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grimwade D, Walker H, Harrison G, Oliver F, Chatters S, Harrison CJ, Wheatley K, Burnett AK, Goldstone AH; Medical Research Council Adult Leukemia Working Party. The predictive value of hierarchical cytogenetic classification in older adults with acute myeloid leukemia (AML): analysis of 1065 patients entered into the United Kingdom Medical Research Council AML11 trial. Blood. 2001 Sep 1;98(5):1312-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11520776</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fröhling S, Schlenk RF, Kayser S, Morhardt M, Benner A, Döhner K, Döhner H; German-Austrian AML Study Group. Cytogenetics and age are major determinants of outcome in intensively treated acute myeloid leukemia patients older than 60 years: results from AMLSG trial AML HD98-B. Blood. 2006 Nov 15;108(10):3280-8. Epub 2006 Jul 13.</citation>
    <PMID>16840728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tardi P, Johnstone S, Harasym N, Xie S, Harasym T, Zisman N, Harvie P, Bermudes D, Mayer L. In vivo maintenance of synergistic cytarabine:daunorubicin ratios greatly enhances therapeutic efficacy. Leuk Res. 2009 Jan;33(1):129-39. doi: 10.1016/j.leukres.2008.06.028. Epub 2008 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18676016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feldman EJ, Lancet JE, Kolitz JE, Ritchie EK, Roboz GJ, List AF, Allen SL, Asatiani E, Mayer LD, Swenson C, Louie AC. First-in-man study of CPX-351: a liposomal carrier containing cytarabine and daunorubicin in a fixed 5:1 molar ratio for the treatment of relapsed and refractory acute myeloid leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Mar 10;29(8):979-85. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.30.5961. Epub 2011 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21282541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lancet JE, Cortes JE, Hogge DE, Tallman MS, Kovacsovics TJ, Damon LE, Komrokji R, Solomon SR, Kolitz JE, Cooper M, Yeager AM, Louie AC, Feldman EJ. Phase 2 trial of CPX-351, a fixed 5:1 molar ratio of cytarabine/daunorubicin, vs cytarabine/daunorubicin in older adults with untreated AML. Blood. 2014 May 22;123(21):3239-46. doi: 10.1182/blood-2013-12-540971. Epub 2014 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>24687088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lancet JE, Uy GL, Cortes JE, et al. Final results of a phase III randomized trial of CPX-351 versus 7+3 in older patients with newly diagnosed high risk (secondary) AML. J Clin Oncol 34, 2016 (suppl; abstr 7000).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cheson BD, Bennett JM, Kopecky KJ, Büchner T, Willman CL, Estey EH, Schiffer CA, Doehner H, Tallman MS, Lister TA, Lo-Coco F, Willemze R, Biondi A, Hiddemann W, Larson RA, Löwenberg B, Sanz MA, Head DR, Ohno R, Bloomfield CD; International Working Group for Diagnosis, Standardization of Response Criteria, Treatment Outcomes, and Reporting Standards for Therapeutic Trials in Acute Myeloid Leukemia. Revised recommendations of the International Working Group for Diagnosis, Standardization of Response Criteria, Treatment Outcomes, and Reporting Standards for Therapeutic Trials in Acute Myeloid Leukemia. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Dec 15;21(24):4642-9. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2004 Feb 1;22(3):576. LoCocco, Francesco [corrected to Lo-Coco, Francesco].</citation>
    <PMID>14673054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SJ, Lindquist K, Segal MR, Covinsky KE. Development and validation of a prognostic index for 4-year mortality in older adults. JAMA. 2006 Feb 15;295(7):801-8. Erratum in: JAMA. 2006 Apr 26;295(16):1900.</citation>
    <PMID>16478903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Döhner H, Estey E, Grimwade D, Amadori S, Appelbaum FR, Büchner T, Dombret H, Ebert BL, Fenaux P, Larson RA, Levine RL, Lo-Coco F, Naoe T, Niederwieser D, Ossenkoppele GJ, Sanz M, Sierra J, Tallman MS, Tien HF, Wei AH, Löwenberg B, Bloomfield CD. Diagnosis and management of AML in adults: 2017 ELN recommendations from an international expert panel. Blood. 2017 Jan 26;129(4):424-447. doi: 10.1182/blood-2016-08-733196. Epub 2016 Nov 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27895058</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdman M, Gudex C, Lloyd A, Janssen M, Kind P, Parkin D, Bonsel G, Badia X. Development and preliminary testing of the new five-level version of EQ-5D (EQ-5D-5L). Qual Life Res. 2011 Dec;20(10):1727-36. doi: 10.1007/s11136-011-9903-x. Epub 2011 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21479777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Secondary AML</keyword>
  <keyword>High risk AML</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

