<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04231201</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P2019/596</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04231201</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aortic Stenosis Evaluated Via Modern Ballistocardiography and Seismocardiography</brief_title>
  <acronym>TAVI</acronym>
  <official_title>Aortic Stenosis: Evaluation of Severity Before and After Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation by Means of Ballistocardiography and Seismocardiography.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erasme University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erasme University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Calcific aortic stenosis (AS) (formerly &quot;senile&quot; or &quot;degenerative&quot;) is a frequent disease of
      heart valves and is characterized by a thickness and calcification of leaflets with a
      significant increase of the pressure gradient, defined as an aortic jet velocity of &gt; 2 m/s.
      Whenever the aortic jet velocity is &gt; 4 m/s, in association with an aortic valve area of &lt; 1
      cm2, the disease is classified as severe and cardiac outflow obstruction develops. AS affects
      1-2% of population aged of &gt; 65 years and 12% of those aged &gt; 75 years. Among those aged &gt; 75
      years, it is estimated that 3.5% has severe AS. With the aging of population, the prevalence
      of AS is expected to increase in the forthcoming years. Transcatheter Aortic Valve
      Implantation (TAVI) has been introduced in 2004 and consists in percutaneous replacement of
      the aortic valve. It is indicated in those patients with severe AS who cannot undergo
      surgical replacement because of high surgical risk. TAVI seems to be a good alternative to
      surgical intervention also for patients deemed at intermediate risk, especially if they are
      frail or aged. Ballistocardiography (BCG) consists of the measurement of the body's
      accelerations as a consequence of the recoil forces generated by the blood mass ejection at
      each cardiac contraction and recorded on the body's surface close to the subject's center of
      mass. Seismocardiography (SCG) records the heart-induced accelerations generated at each
      cardiac contraction and transmitted to the local chest surface. Thanks to specific algorithms
      applied to the SCG and BCG waves, it is possible to compute the kinetic energy (KE) and Power
      (P) of a single cardiac contractile cycle.

      The aims of our study are to demonstrate that: LVOT Vmax and LVOT VTI changes obtained with
      echocardiography can be estimated reliably throught BCG and SCG signals, before and after
      TAVI procedure; Pmax and KE computed from the BCG and SCG signals could predict the severity
      of the AS before the TAVI procedure.

      KE and P computed from non invasively recorded BCG and SCG waves may prove useful in the
      evaluation of AS severity and its evolution before and after TAVI procedure, respectively.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of cardiac kinetic energy before and after aortic valve replacement by the means of modern micro-accelerometers and gyroscopes, namely ballistocardiography (BCG) and seismocardiography (SCG).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Kinetic energy (1/2 mv^2, J) and its temporal integral are computed from the BCG and SCG signals before and after valvular replacement.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of cardiac Power before and after aortic valve replacement by the means of modern micro-accelerometers and gyroscopes, namely ballistocardiography (BCG) and seismocardiography (SCG).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Maximal power (F*v, J/s)* produced during a contractile cycle is computed from the BCG and SCG signals before and after valvular replacement.
* F= Force (mass*acceleration) (Kg*m/s^2) v= velocity (m/s)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of LV twist and global longitudinal strain before and after valvular replacement</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>From 2 dimensional speckle tracking imaging (2D-STI) echocardiography, LV twist (°) and global longitudinal strain (°) will be measured before and after valvular replacement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">135</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Stenosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patient population studied: patients with aortic stenosis planned to undergo TAVI
        procedure.

        Number of patients planned: since this is a pilot study, no formal simple size calculation
        can be done. The Cardiology department of the Erasme hospital perform an average of 3 TAVI
        procedure a month. Since the enrollment will take place from January to September 2023, a
        total of 135 patients will be enrolled. Because of a complication rate of 10% linked to the
        invasive procedure, we expect 100 patients will be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe aortic stenosis, planned to undergo TAVI procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concomitant heart valve disease other than AS

          -  C2 and D2 stages of AS according to the current definition (see table I for further
             details)

          -  Heart failure regardless to the etiology

          -  Arrhythmias

          -  Severe kidney disease

          -  Denied consent to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sofia Morra, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Erasme Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sofia Morra, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+3225555919</phone>
    <email>sofia.morra@erasme.ulb.ac.be</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nora Bahhdoh</last_name>
    <phone>+3225558351</phone>
    <email>Service.Rech-biomed@erasme.ulb.ac.be</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Erasme Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1070</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sofia Morra, MD, PhD fellow</last_name>
      <phone>+32 2 555 5919</phone>
      <email>sofia.morra@erasme.ulb.ac.be</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ballistocariodgraphy</keyword>
  <keyword>Seismocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>LV mechanics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

