<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04230746</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00224835</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04230746</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Antibiotics on Urinary Microbiome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Antibiotics on Urinary Microbiome: Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Planning to study urine microbiota at baseline and after administration of bactrim
      antibiotics in healthy volunteers. Will intermittently collect voided urine specimens for 16
      s DNA analysis over a period of 6 months after 2 weeks of bactrim or placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Urinary tract infections (UTI) are the most common type of human bacterial disease, prompting
      more than 10 million physician office visits annually at a healthcare cost of over $1 billion
      dollars. Treatment of UTI is typically empiric or culture-driven antibiotics which are
      associated with ever increasing bacterial resistance. Over the last decade, The Human
      Microbiome Project has established that even 'culture-negative' urine represents a diverse
      ecosystem of bacteria. Despite broad use of antibiotics to cure disease for the past 90
      years, the broader impact of antibiotics on typical flora are not well understood.
      Antibiotics are also commonly used as prophylaxis for surgical procedures in the urinary
      tract altering patient outcomes in unforeseen ways. Despite widespread utilization of
      antibiotics, the longitudinal impact on the dynamic intravesical environment remains
      completely unknown.

      Dysbiosis in the microbiome has been suggested as a causative agent in a wide range of
      disease: arthritis, metabolic disorders, neurologic disease, inflammatory bowel conditions,
      and cancer. Yet there remains a fundamental knowledge gap regarding the short and long-term
      effect of antibiotics on microbiota communities. Specifically within the urinary tract,
      variance in baseline commensal organisms have been associated with interstitial cystitis,
      overactive bladder, frequent symptomatic urinary tract infection and potentially cancer
      development. The study of microbiota reveal pathways and mechanisms that play important roles
      in immunological response and health but studies typically are limited to the gut.

      To address this knowledge gap, the investigators plan a placebo controlled randomized trial
      to test the longitudinal impact of 10 days of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the urinary
      microbiome in healthy adults. Data collection for individual participants will persist for a
      period of 6 months. The investigators hypothesize antibiotic administration contributes to a
      rise in bacterial resistance and directly leads to urine microbiome dysbiosis. The
      investigators further hypothesize the urinary microbiome does not return to baseline, with
      loss of certain bacteria permanent during the study period. While the investigators' study is
      groundbreaking and novel, the feasibility of the investigators' experimental plan has been
      previously demonstrated in the study of the salivary and gut microbiome. Ultimately the
      investigators anticipate even a single course of antibiotic treatment may increase the risk
      of bacterial resistance and lead to long-lasting shifts in the urinary microbiome. If
      confirmed, this knowledge will directly influence clinical decision making in antibiotic
      selection, duration, and utility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Planning to study the urine microbiota at baseline and after administration of bactrim antibiotics in healthy volunteers. Will intermittently collect voided urine specimens for 16 s DNA analysis over a period of 6 months after 2 weeks of bactrim or placebo.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Drug will be blinded to all.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Microbiome flora number of organisms</measure>
    <time_frame>At Baseline, Day 2, Day 5, Day 10, Day 30, and Day 180 of study</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of 16S rRNA gene amplicon data to determine number of varied organisms (genus and species).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Microbiome flora percentage distribution of organisms</measure>
    <time_frame>At Baseline, Day 2, Day 5, Day 10, Day 30, and Day 180 of study</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of 16S rRNA gene amplicon data to determine the percent distribution of organisms (microbiologic genus and species).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Microtia</condition>
  <condition>UTI</condition>
  <condition>Bacteriuria</condition>
  <condition>Antibiotic Resistant Infection</condition>
  <condition>Antibiotics Causing Adverse Effects in Therapeutic Use</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be recruited and enrolled. Participants will be surveyed regarding environmental, health, and behavioral practices. (Instrument 1) . Then a clean catch urine specimen will be collected. Participants will be provided with placebo to be taken twice daily. This will be considered day 0. Participants will then be instructed to take the study drug twice daily and return on Day 2, Day 5, Day 10, Day 30, and Day 180 for additional clean-catch urine specimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bactrim</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will be recruited and enrolled. Participants will be surveyed regarding environmental, health, and behavioral practices. (Instrument 1) . Then a clean catch urine specimen will be collected. Participants will be provided with Bactrim 800/120 to take twice daily. This will be considered day 0. Participants will then be instructed to take the study drug twice daily and return on Day 2, Day 5, Day 10, Day 30, and Day 180 for additional clean-catch urine specimen.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bactrim DS 800Mg-160Mg Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>To study effect on urinary microbiome</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bactrim</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bactrim, trimethoprim sulfamethoxazole, Septra, sulfatrim</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo oral tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>To study effect on urinary microbiome</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosed or suspected urinary tract infection in prior 6 months

          -  Treated with antibiotics for any reason in prior 6 months

          -  Allergy to sulfa

          -  Under 18

          -  Pregnant or planning to become pregnant in the next 12 months by self report (as is
             the clinical standard for prescribing this medication for suspected or proven UTI
             treatment)

          -  Use indwelling or intermittent urinary hardware or implant such as supra-pubic tube or
             catheter

          -  Neurogenic bladder

          -  Baseline renal insufficiency

          -  Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency

          -  Taking angiotensin converting enzyme

          -  Angiotensin receptor blocker

          -  Nursing

          -  HIV/AIDS

          -  On Immunosuppressant drugs

          -  On Chemotherapy/Immunotherapy

          -  Liver dysfunction

          -  On the following medications: DOFETILIDE, METHENAMINE &amp; LEVOMETHADYL; WARFARIN &amp;
             Methotrexate; GEMIFLOXACIN, DIGOXIN, PYRIMETHAMINE, CLASS IA ANTIARRHYTHMIC AGENTS
             (Quinidine, procainamide, disopyramide), TRICYCLIC ANTIDEPRESSANTS (amitriptyline,
             desipramine, doxepin, Imipramine, nortriptyline, amoxapine, clomipramine, maprotiline,
             trimipramine, and protriptyline), LEUCOVORIN CALCIUM.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew J Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrew J Cohen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>4105507739</phone>
    <email>acohen65@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kathy Beres</last_name>
    <phone>4105503341</phone>
    <email>kberes@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 11, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>antibiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>flora</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bacteriuria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Congenital Microtia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trimethoprim</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trimethoprim, Sulfamethoxazole Drug Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sulfamethoxazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

