<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04238806</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013.3/13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04238806</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Desflurane,Brain Natriuretic Peptide and Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Investigation of the Association Between Desflurane Inhalational Agent, Serum Brain Natriuretic Peptide (BNP) Levels and Clinical Outcomes During Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG) Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kartal Kosuyolu Yuksek Ihtisas Education and Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Trakya University Faculty of Medicine Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kartal Kosuyolu Yuksek Ihtisas Education and Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) operations with cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB),
      the use of desflurane continuously or intermittently may have effects on serum brain
      natriuretic peptide (BNP) levels. The aim is to investigate the association between
      desflurane, serum BNP values, and clinical outcomes during CABG operations. In a prospective,
      randomized, double-blinded study, desflurane inhalational anesthesia was administered either
      continuously or intermittently (Group 1; n=60 versus Group 2; n=62). The preoperative and
      postoperative BNP levels at 24, 48 and 72 hours after surgery were collected. Outcomes were
      recorded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: During coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) operations with cardiopulmonary
      bypass (CPB), the use of desflurane continuously or intermittently may have effects on serum
      brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) levels.

      Aim of the study: The aim is to investigate the association between desflurane, serum BNP
      values, and clinical outcomes during CABG operations.

      Material and methods: In a prospective, randomized, double-blinded study, desflurane
      inhalational anesthesia was administered either continuously or intermittently (Group 1; n=60
      versus Group 2; n=62). The preoperative and postoperative BNP levels at 24, 48 and 72 hours
      after surgery were collected. Outcomes were recorded. Randomization into two groups was
      performed using sealed envelopes. The sequentially numbered assignments of participants were
      concealed in these envelopes during the study. The patients enrolled in the study receive an
      allocation to a group after anesthesia induction by health care personnel after the opening
      of the envelope. The observers were blinded to the anesthetic protocol. Caregivers were not
      blinded, but they did not participate in data collection or data interpretation. Therefore,
      the study protocol is considered double-blinded, masked to observers. Inclusion criteria
      include; 18 to 75 years of age, body mass index of 25 to 31, ejection fraction≥50%. Exclusion
      criteria include; repeat cardiac surgery, emergent surgery, preoperative coagulation
      disorder, preoperative congestive heart failure, ejection fraction &lt;49%, preoperative renal
      dysfunction (serum creatinine&gt;1.3 mg/dL), dialysis, preoperative hepatic dysfunction (serum
      aspartate/alanine amino transferase&gt;40 U/L), preoperative electrolyte imbalance, history of
      pancreatitis or current corticosteroid treatment.The primary endpoint was to determine
      preoperative and postoperative BNP values 24, 48 and 72 hours after surgery. The secondary
      endpoint was the relation between BNP values and clinical outcomes such as; 1-Aortic
      cross-clamp time, 2-Cardiopulmonary bypass time, 3-The use of inotropic support,
      4-Intra-aortic balloon pump, 5-Duration of mechanical ventilation (&gt;48 hours), 6-Development
      of pneumonia, 7-Perioperative myocardial infarction, 8-Cerebrovascular event (stroke or
      transient ischemic attack), seizure, 9-Atrial fibrillation and other rhythm disturbances,
      10-Need for renal replacement therapy (RRT), 11-Reoperation secondary to bleeding,
      12-Intensive care unit stay (&gt;3 days), 13-Hospital stay and, 14-Thirty-day mortality.

      Statistical analysis. The sample size was calculated according to the comparison of serum BNP
      values in a previous study and a sample size of 58 patients per group would be required with
      80% power and the conventional 2-sided type 1 error of 5%. A multiple logistic regression
      analysis was performed to assess the predictive factors for weaning failure from mechanical
      ventilation, and the significance level was set at a p-value of less than 0.10 in the
      univariate model. To determine the best cut-off for preoperative BNP value to predict the
      development of prolonged mechanical ventilation, we calculated the area under the receiver
      operating characteristic curve.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>In a prospective, randomized, double-blinded study, desflurane inhalational anesthesia was administered either continuously or intermittently (Group 1; n=60 versus Group 2; n=62).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>The observers were blinded to the anesthetic protocol. Caregivers were not blinded, but they did not participate in data collection or data interpretation. Therefore, the study protocol is considered double-blinded, masked to observers.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum BNP values before the cardiac surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>One day before cardiac surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum BNP values were collected from a blood sample of each patient one day before cardiac surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum BNP values after the cardiac surgery at 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>After operation at 24 hours after cardiac surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum BNP values were collected from a blood sample of each patient after cardiac surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum BNP values after the cardiac surgery at 48 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>After operation at 48 hours after cardiac surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum BNP values were collected from a blood sample of each patient after cardiac surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum BNP values after the cardiac surgery at 72 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>After operation at 72 hours after cardiac surgery.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum BNP values were collected from a blood sample of each patient after cardiac surgery</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum BNP values before and after the cardiac surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>After collection of the data and during statistical analysis</time_frame>
    <description>The collected serum BNP values were compared with each other by repeated measure analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome aortic cross-clamp time</measure>
    <time_frame>During operative time period of cardiac surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and aortic cross-clamp time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome cardiopulmonary bypass time</measure>
    <time_frame>During operative time period of cardiac surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and cardiopulmonary bypass time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome use of inotropic support</measure>
    <time_frame>During operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and use of inotropic support</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome use of Intra-aortic balloon pump</measure>
    <time_frame>During operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and use of Intra-aortic balloon pump</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome duration of mechanical ventilation (&gt;48 hours)</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and duration of mechanical ventilation (&gt;48 hours)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome development of pneumonia</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and development of pneumonia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>During operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and perioperative myocardial infarction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome cerebrovascular event or seizure</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and cerebrovascular event (stroke or transient ischemic attack) or seizure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome atrial rhythm disturbances</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and atrial fibrillation and other atrial rhythm disturbances</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome ventricular rhythm disturbances</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and ventricular rhythm disturbances</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome renal replacement therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and need for renal replacement therapy (RRT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome reoperation</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and reoperation secondary to bleeding</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome intensive care unit stay</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and intensive care unit stay (&gt;3 days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and intensive care unit stay (&gt;3 days)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcome thirty-day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>After operative time period of cardiac surgery and during intensive care unit stay</time_frame>
    <description>A relation between serum BNP values and thirty-day mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">151</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Natriuretic Peptide</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Bypass Graft Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Cardiopulmonary Bypass</condition>
  <condition>Desflurane</condition>
  <condition>Outcome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Desflurane Continuous</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In Group 1 of 60 patients, desflurane inhalational agent was administered continuously during coronary artery bypass graft surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass. Anesthesia induction was administered to all patients with intravenous midazolam at a dose of 0.2 mg/kg, fentanyl at a dose of 5 to 10 µg/kg and rocuronium bromide at a dose of 0.1 mg. For maintenance, in Group 1 patients, desflurane inhalational agent was administered at an end-tidal concentration of 1 to 4% during the whole surgical procedure and intravenous maintenance midazolam at a dose of 0.03 mg/kg and fentanyl at a dose of 1 to 2 µg/kg every half an hour. In Group 1 of patients, during the whole surgical procedure, attention to keep mean arterial pressure above 50 mmHg was provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Desflurane Intermittent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In Group 2 of 60 patients, desflurane inhalational agent was administered intermittently during coronary artery bypass graft surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass. Anesthesia induction was administered to all patients with intravenous midazolam at a dose of 0.2 mg/kg, fentanyl at a dose of 5 to 10 µg/kg and rocuronium bromide at a dose of 0.1 mg/kg. For maintenance, in Group 2 patients, desflurane inhalational agent was administered at an end-tidal concentration of 1 to 4% before and after the cardiopulmonary bypass procedure as intermittently with the addition of intravenous maintenance midazolam at a dose of 0.03 mg/kg and fentanyl at a dose of 1 to 2 µg/kg every half an hour. In Group 2 of patients, during the whole surgical procedure, attention to keep mean arterial pressure above 50 mmHg was provided.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Desflurane Inhalational agent</intervention_name>
    <description>Desflurane inhalational agent administration during the whole cardiac surgical operation with cardiopulmonary bypass versus administration of desflurane inhalational agent before and after cardiopulmonary bypass during the whole period of cardiac surgical operation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Desflurane Continuous</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Desflurane Intermittent</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Suprane</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eighteen to seventy-five years of age,

          -  Body mass index values between twenty-five and thirty-one,

          -  Ejection fraction greater than or equal to 50%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Repeat cardiac surgery,

          -  Emergent surgery,

          -  Preoperative coagulation disorder,

          -  Preoperative congestive heart failure,

          -  Ejection fraction less than 49%,

          -  Preoperative renal dysfunction (serum creatinine value of greater than 1.3 mg/dL),

          -  Dialysis,

          -  Preoperative hepatic dysfunction (serum aspartate/alanine amino transferase values of
             greater than 40 U/L),

          -  Preoperative electrolyte imbalance,

          -  History of pancreatitis,

          -  Current corticosteroid treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gonul Sagiroglu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Trakya University, Faculty of Medicine, Edirne, Turkey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>De Hert SG, Cromheecke S, ten Broecke PW, Mertens E, De Blier IG, Stockman BA, Rodrigus IE, Van der Linden PJ. Effects of propofol, desflurane, and sevoflurane on recovery of myocardial function after coronary surgery in elderly high-risk patients. Anesthesiology. 2003 Aug;99(2):314-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12883404</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cuthbertson BH, Amiri AR, Croal BL, Rajagopalan S, Alozairi O, Brittenden J, Hillis GS. Utility of B-type natriuretic peptide in predicting perioperative cardiac events in patients undergoing major non-cardiac surgery. Br J Anaesth. 2007 Aug;99(2):170-6. Epub 2007 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17573389</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Karthikeyan G, Moncur RA, Levine O, Heels-Ansdell D, Chan MT, Alonso-Coello P, Yusuf S, Sessler D, Villar JC, Berwanger O, McQueen M, Mathew A, Hill S, Gibson S, Berry C, Yeh HM, Devereaux PJ. Is a pre-operative brain natriuretic peptide or N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide measurement an independent predictor of adverse cardiovascular outcomes within 30 days of noncardiac surgery? A systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Oct 20;54(17):1599-606. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.06.028. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19833258</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Uhlig C, Bluth T, Schwarz K, Deckert S, Heinrich L, De Hert S, Landoni G, Serpa Neto A, Schultz MJ, Pelosi P, Schmitt J, Gama de Abreu M. Effects of Volatile Anesthetics on Mortality and Postoperative Pulmonary and Other Complications in Patients Undergoing Surgery: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Anesthesiology. 2016 Jun;124(6):1230-45. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0000000000001120. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27065094</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yun KH, Jeong MH, Oh SK, Choi JH, Rhee SJ, Park EM, Yoo NJ, Kim NH, Ahn YK, Jeong JW. Preoperative plasma N-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide concentration and perioperative cardiovascular risk in elderly patients. Circ J. 2008 Feb;72(2):195-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18219153</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fox AA, Nascimben L, Body SC, Collard CD, Mitani AA, Liu KY, Muehlschlegel JD, Shernan SK, Marcantonio ER. Increased perioperative b-type natriuretic peptide associates with heart failure hospitalization or heart failure death after coronary artery bypass graft surgery. Anesthesiology. 2013 Aug;119(2):284-94. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e318299969c.</citation>
    <PMID>23695172</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Litton E, Ho KM. The use of pre-operative brain natriuretic peptides as a predictor of adverse outcomes after cardiac surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2012 Mar;41(3):525-34. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezr007. Epub 2011 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22345176</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hutfless R, Kazanegra R, Madani M, Bhalla MA, Tulua-Tata A, Chen A, Clopton P, James C, Chiu A, Maisel AS. Utility of B-type natriuretic peptide in predicting postoperative complications and outcomes in patients undergoing heart surgery. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 May 19;43(10):1873-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15145114</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Murad Junior JA, Nakazone MA, Machado Mde N, Godoy MF. Predictors of mortality in cardiac surgery: brain natriuretic peptide type B. Rev Bras Cir Cardiovasc. 2015 Mar-Apr;30(2):182-7. doi: 10.5935/1678-9741.20150008.</citation>
    <PMID>26107449</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lurati Buse GA, Koller MT, Burkhart C, Seeberger MD, Filipovic M. The predictive value of preoperative natriuretic peptide concentrations in adults undergoing surgery: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Anesth Analg. 2011 May;112(5):1019-33. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e31820f286f. Epub 2011 Mar 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21372274</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cuthbertson BH, Croal BL, Rae D, Gibson PH, McNeilly JD, Jeffrey RR, Smith WC, Prescott GJ, Buchan KG, El-Shafei H, Gibson GA, Hillis GS. N-terminal pro-B-type natriuretic peptide levels and early outcome after cardiac surgery: a prospective cohort study. Br J Anaesth. 2009 Nov;103(5):647-53. doi: 10.1093/bja/aep234. Epub 2009 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19713279</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Kartal Kosuyolu Yuksek Ihtisas Education and Research Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ayse Baysal</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Desflurane</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD sharing plan includes sharing of the Study Protocol, Statistical Analysis Plan, and Statistical Analysis of the study with researchers upon request via e-mail.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>The Study Protocol, the Clinical Study Report and the Statistical Analysis Plan are available after ClinicalTrials.gov registration.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>Accessible to all researchers</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

