<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT04238143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GARM-MSK-ALD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT04238143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adipose-Derived Biocellular Regenerative Therapy for Osteoarthritis</brief_title>
  <acronym>GARM-MSK-ALD</acronym>
  <official_title>Adipose-Derived Biocellular Regenerative Therapy in Treatment of Osteoarthritis (OA) and Associated Connective Tissue Degeneration and Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Healeon Medical Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Donna Alderman, DO</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Robert W. Alexander, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Terry, Glenn C., M.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Healeon Medical Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Use of Biocellular and cellular approaches to treatment of Osteoarthritis (OA),
      musculoskeletal aging processes, pain, and degenerative changes are to be studied with
      minimally invasive protocols, and non-pharmaceutical means to relieve OA and its associated
      issues. Traditional surgical interventions have not yielded convincing long-term outcomes,
      including total joint replacement surgeries and medical management of the supportive
      structures.

      This study is to use a person's own stem/stromal Cells (autologous) plus HD-PRP (important
      healing growth factors and signal molecules) in such cases of OA for long-term minimally
      invasive treatments. Baseline (existing) findings are documented, and thence tracked as to
      progress deemed to be result of the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoarthritis (OA) is one of the most common chronic health conditions and a leading cause
      of pain and disability in the world, with a substantial proportion of adults affected. It is
      estimated that symptomatic OA affects one in eight men and women in the US (27-31 million),
      In a global study of health conditions, osteoarthritis and musculoskeletal pain ranked in the
      top 4 percent of worldwide disabilities. OA is a complex, multifactorial disease, with much
      still to learn regarding mechanisms and progression. . The most commonly affected joints
      include the hip , knee , hand and foot , and spine. although OA can affect any joint. OA is
      linked to substantial economic costs estimated in developed countries to be between 1% and
      2.5% of GDP. With the rise in life expectancy, the prevalence of osteoarthritis is projected
      to increase further, resulting in a greater healthcare burden.

      Diagnosis is commonly accomplished via clinical examinations and subjective symptoms coupled
      with a variety of imaging protocols. These are an intrinsic portion of the protocols of this
      Trial, measuring both the safety and outcomes resulting from three basic approaches to
      provide both cellular and biocellular therapeutic approaches.

      The Trial consists of three separate approaches: 1). Use of guided biocellular therapy (tSVF
      + Platelet Rich Plasma); 2). Use of guided biocellular and cellular therapy (tSVF + Platelet
      Rich Plasma + cSVF concentrates); and, 3). Use of cSVF only via systemic deployment suspended
      in sterile Normal Saline IV solution. Patient's will be enrolled based on the approach
      considered the most likely to safely attain clinical improvement and compared to others of
      similar findings in the same musculoskeletal indications.

      Follow up and tracking to be extended over a two year period (minimum) following each
      treatment delivery. Those who do more than one site, or have a repeat treatment, will be
      followed on separate tracks to maintain the outcomes resulting from single versus double
      treatments. Management and voluntary enrollment will follow existing HIPPA (confidentiality)
      rules and regulations in place.

      Participants will be requested to report any and all Adverse Events or Severe Adverse Events
      (complications not anticipated within parameters of usual and customary side effects
      resulting from such therapies) as may potentially result from any treatment provided (not
      including the normal &quot;sequelae&quot; of procedures utilized.

      Cartilage loss remains the main pathologic features of OA, however OA is recognized to
      involve aging, inflammation and degenerative changes within the musculoskeletal joint,
      components, including pathologic changes in the bone, cartilage, and supportive soft tissues,
      As a natural process within aging and mechanical stresses, the ability of our homeostatic
      system to maintain a fully functional, pain free system, Weight bearing and repetitive trauma
      contribute to the demand for attempted repairs after use, it is common for OA to be found in
      multiple joints within the same individual over time and use.

      Another aspect of OA is that it has been shown to be present in multiple joints in the same
      individual, suggesting a systemic bone response to mechanical stresses. When OA is severe,
      the bone involvement can be detected on plain radiographs, but radiographs may not detect
      milder cases. And while radiographs remain the standard means of diagnosing OA severity ,
      these provide no information about the non‐bone aspects of OA pathophysiology. Studies
      demonstrate that diagnostic musculoskeletal ultrasound as a complementary imaging tool, along
      with radiography, may enable more accurate diagnostics for osteoarthritis.

      Treatments consist of harvesting (with microcannula) a small volume of tSVF to provide the
      needed stem/stromal cells found in large numbers around the small capillaries and blood
      vessels (needs typically 5-15 teaspoons). This tSVF is mixed with the patient's own
      concentrated platelets and guided for placement with use of a high resolution ultrasound for
      accurate placement. These elements are what are normally used in our bodies for maintaining
      (homeostasis) and repair (regenerative healing), with the advantage of accurate placement
      into the bone, soft tissues and joints involved in inflammatory or degenerative breakdown
      with pain and loss of function.

      Each patient will be carefully followed to measure progress and imaging which documents
      structural changes that may be realized with these treatments. Of most note, the avoidance or
      postponement of invasive and often difficult rehabilitation is realized.

      These procedures have been safely and successfully provided for approximately 15 years,
      however, without a large series and tracking over a period of years. We are seeking
      validation of the processes and elements which have been performed and reported in case
      reporting or small case series.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant with Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse and Severe Adverse Events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain Rating Scale (NPRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective Pain Rating</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from Baseline visual analog pain scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 6 months, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Reported Pain (1-10)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Ultrasound Images from Baseline Condition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>High Definition Ultrasonography Soft and Hard Tissues of Musculoskeletal Areas To Be Treated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knee Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (KOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Knee and OA Status for Pain and OA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change from Baseline of Pain and Arthritis In Knee and Hip</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hip Disability and OA Outcomes Survey (HOOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change from Baseline of Pain &amp; Function of Hip</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder, and Hand Score (DASH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change from Baseline of Pain, Range of Motion and Function All Areas</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Roland-Morris Back Pain Questionnaire (RMBPQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 months; 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change from Baseline of Pain, Function and Range of Motion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Foot and Ankle Ability Measure (FAAM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change from Baseline Pain, Function, Range of Motion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Foot and Ankle Disability Index (FADI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline; 6 Month; 1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Measure Change in Disability From Baseline Pain, Function, Range of Motion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <condition>Osteo Arthritis Knee</condition>
  <condition>Osteo Arthritis Shoulders</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis of Multiple Joints</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis, Hip</condition>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis - Ankle/Foot</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP Arm1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tissue Stromal Vascular Fraction (tSVF) + Platelet-Rich Plasma (PRP) Concentrate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP + cSVF Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tissue Stromal Vascular Fraction (tSVF) + Platelet-Rich Plasma (PRP) Concentrate + Cellular Stromal Vascular Fraction (cSVF)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline IV + cSVF Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cellular Stromal Vascular Fraction (cSVF); Sterile Normal Saline Intravenous (IV) Introduction</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tissue Stromal Vascular Fraction (tSVF) Arm 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Harvesting subcutaneous tSVF with sterile, disposable microcannula system</description>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP Arm1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRP Concentrate Arm 1</intervention_name>
    <description>Preparation of PRP Concentrate via sterile Terumo-Harvest System</description>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP Arm1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tissue Stromal Vascular Fraction (tSVF) Arm 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Harvesting subcutaneous tSVF with sterile, disposable microcannula system</description>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP + cSVF Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRP Concentrate Arm 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Preparation of PRP Concentrate via sterile Terumo-Harvest System</description>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP + cSVF Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cellular Stromal Vascular Fraction (cSVF) Arm 2</intervention_name>
    <description>Isolation-Concentration of cSVF via sterile enzymatic digestion (Liberase TM, Sterile Roche)</description>
    <arm_group_label>tSVF + PRP + cSVF Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cellular Stromal Vascular Fraction (cSVF) Arm 3</intervention_name>
    <description>Isolation-Concentration of cSVF via sterile enzymatic digestion (Liberase TM, Sterile Roche)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline IV + cSVF Arm 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sterile Normal Saline (IV Solution)</intervention_name>
    <description>Suspension of cSVF in 500 cc Sterile Normal Saline (IV Solution)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline IV + cSVF Arm 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented osteoarthritic inflammatory and/or degenerative changes in the joint or
             connective tissues of the knee, hip, shoulder, Achilles tendon, Sacroiliac Joint,
             wrist/hand, foot/ankle, or Plantar Fasciitis (PR);

          -  No systemic disorders which, in opinion of principal investigator, would disqualify
             from safely being able to undergo the determined procedures;

          -  Have the ability to understand and accept all items in Informed Consent Document;

          -  Have adequate perivascular and extracellular matrix donor tissues available;

          -  Mature enough to tolerate determined procedures and follow up instructions and
             complete post-treatment tracking responsibilities

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Systemic or psychological impairment which would preclude patient tolerance and
             understanding nature and extent of procedures and follow up tracking;

          -  Known active cancer, chemotherapy, or radiation therapy;

          -  Pregnancy;

          -  Active infections which would increase risk of patient to undergo treatment;

          -  High dose steroid users, or recipients of corticosteroids with a six month period
             before treatment date;

          -  Medication or Opiate addition, or in active treatment for drug rehabilitation;

          -  History of documented severe traumatic brain injuries;

          -  In the opinion of the principal investigator/provider, the patient's condition or
             medical issues which would not allow the individual to fully accomplish or complete
             the study requirements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hemwall Center for Orthopedic Regenerative Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91355</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regenevita LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stevensville</city>
        <state>Montana</state>
        <zip>59870</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliver, K., Alexander, RW. Combination of Autologous Adipose-Derived Tissue Stromal Vascular Fraction Plus High Density Platelet-Rich Plasma or Bone Marrow Concentrates in Achilles Tendon Tears. J. Prolotherapy; 5:e895-912, 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alexander, Robert W., Use of Disposable Microcannula System For Low Pressure Harvest, Preparation, and Placement of Small Volume Autologous Fat Grafting With Activated High Density Platelet-Rich Plasma (HD-PRP). Clin Cosm Invest Derm 6:91-102, 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albano JJ, Alexander RW. Autologous fat grafting as a mesenchymal stem cell source and living bioscaffold in a patellar tendon tear. Clin J Sport Med. 2011 Jul;21(4):359-61. doi: 10.1097/JSM.0b013e31821d0864.</citation>
    <PMID>21562415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin, K., Short Review on the advancement of osteoarthritis treatment with cell therapy. J. Regen Biol Med. (2020), 2(1): 1-7.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehranfar S, Abdi Rad I, Mostafav E, Akbarzadeh A. The use of stromal vascular fraction (SVF), platelet-rich plasma (PRP) and stem cells in the treatment of osteoarthritis: an overview of clinical trials. Artif Cells Nanomed Biotechnol. 2019 Dec;47(1):882-890. doi: 10.1080/21691401.2019.1576710. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>30887856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong Z, Chen J, Zhang S, Zhao C, Bi M, Chen X, Bi Q. Intra-articular injection of autologous adipose-derived stromal vascular fractions for knee osteoarthritis: a double-blind randomized self-controlled trial. Int Orthop. 2019 May;43(5):1123-1134. doi: 10.1007/s00264-018-4099-0. Epub 2018 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>30109404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alderman, D. Regenerative injection therapies for pain: traditional, platelet-rich plasma, and biocellular prolotherapy. text, 345, 2016.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alexander RW. Biocellular Regenerative Medicine: Use of Adipose-Derived Stem/Stromal Cells and It's Native Bioactive Matrix. Phys Med Rehabil Clin N Am. 2016 Nov;27(4):871-891. doi: 10.1016/j.pmr.2016.06.005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27788905</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nelson AE, Allen KD, Golightly YM, Goode AP, Jordan JM. A systematic review of recommendations and guidelines for the management of osteoarthritis: The chronic osteoarthritis management initiative of the U.S. bone and joint initiative. Semin Arthritis Rheum. 2014 Jun;43(6):701-12. doi: 10.1016/j.semarthrit.2013.11.012. Epub 2013 Dec 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24387819</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alderman, D, Alexander, RW, Stem Cell Prolotherapy In Regenerative Medicine: Background, Theory, and Protocols. J. Prolo 3(3): 689-708, 2011.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alexander, RW, Overview of Cellular Stromal Vascular Fraction (cSVF) &amp; Biocellular Uses of Stem/Stromal Cells &amp; Matrix (tSVF + HD-PRP) in Regenerative Medicine, Aesthetic Medicine, and Plastic Surgery. J Stem Cell Res Ther; S1003, 2019.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Burdett N, McNeil JD. Difficulties with assessing the benefit of glucosamine sulphate as a treatment for osteoarthritis. Int J Evid Based Healthc. 2012 Sep;10(3):222-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1744-1609.2012.00279.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22925619</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Thorlund JB, Juhl CB, Roos EM, Lohmander LS. Arthroscopic surgery for degenerative knee: systematic review and meta-analysis of benefits and harms. BMJ. 2015 Jun 16;350:h2747. doi: 10.1136/bmj.h2747. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26080045</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Katz JN, Brownlee SA, Jones MH. The role of arthroscopy in the management of knee osteoarthritis. Best Pract Res Clin Rheumatol. 2014 Feb;28(1):143-56. doi: 10.1016/j.berh.2014.01.008. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24792949</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alderman, D, Alexander, RW. Advances In Regenerative Medicine: High Density Platelet-Rich Plasma and Stem Cell Prolotherapy. J. Prac Pain Management, Oct: 49-60, 2011.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alexander, RW. Understanding Adipose-Derived Stromal Vascular Fraction (SVF) Cell Biology On The Basis of Perivascular Cell Components In Aesthetic &amp; Regenerative Medicine. J. Prolo, 4: e13777, 2012.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gallagher S, Heberger JR. Examining the interaction of force and repetition on musculoskeletal disorder risk: a systematic literature review. Hum Factors. 2013 Feb;55(1):108-24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23516797</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kuorinka I, Jonsson B, Kilbom A, Vinterberg H, Biering-Sørensen F, Andersson G, Jørgensen K. Standardised Nordic questionnaires for the analysis of musculoskeletal symptoms. Appl Ergon. 1987 Sep;18(3):233-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15676628</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2020</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2020</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Degenerative</keyword>
  <keyword>Joint Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid Arthritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Hip</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Complement Factor H</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

