<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03751280</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CPEA001A12201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03751280</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Efficacy of PEAR-004 in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Sham-Controlled Study of PEAR-004 as an Adjunct to Standard-of-care Treatment for Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study was to determine in patients currently being administered
      antipsychotic pharmacotherapy whether PEAR-004 could further reduce symptoms of schizophrenia
      as measured by the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS).

      The overall rationale for the study was to assess the first prescription digital therapeutic
      (PDT) in schizophrenia using a form of proven psychosocial intervention, cognitive behavioral
      therapy (CBT), to supplement standard of care with antipsychotic medications.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a randomized, sham-controlled, rater-blinded, parallel group trial. Overall, 112
      subjects were randomized 1:1 in to the following groups:

        -  Group A: Clinician-directed pharmacotherapy + PEAR-004

        -  Group B: Clinician-directed pharmacotherapy + sham app An up to 28-day screening period
           included standard screening assessments as defined in the assessment schedule. Eligible
           subjects were randomized on Day 1 into one of the treatment groups.

      Subjects in both groups continued to receive their clinician-directed standard-of-care
      treatment for schizophrenia, including pharmacotherapy. Subjects in Group A used PEAR 004 and
      subjects in Group B used a sham for a period of 12 weeks. Subjects returned to the clinic for
      outpatient visits at Week 4 (day 29), Week 8 (day 57), and Week 12 (day 85). At each visit,
      standard assessments were performed according to the assessment schedule, including PANSS,
      ISST-Plus, CGI, BMQ, MAP-SR, WHOQOL-BREF, BDI-II, ISI, and adverse events (AEs). A final
      follow-up visit was performed at Week 16 (day 115),
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85</time_frame>
    <description>Total PANSS score from baseline to day 85 or last visit 30 different schizophrenia symptoms scored from 1-7 total score of 30-210 is sum of 7-item positive scale, 7-item negative scale, and 16-item general psychopathology scale higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of dropout</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 115</time_frame>
    <description>Dropout rate</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in positive Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the Positive PANSS score from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit 7-item positive symptom scale, with score 1-7 on each item and a summed total range of 7-49 higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the general psychopathology Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the General Psychopathology PANSS score from baseline to day 29, day 57 and day 85 or last visit 16-item general psychopathology symptom scale, with score 1-7 on each item and a summed total range of 16-112 higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the negative Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the Negative PANSS score from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit 7-item negative symptom scale, with score 1-7 on each item and a summed total range of 7-49 higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Motivation and Pleasure Self-report (MAP-SR) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the Motivation and Pleasure self-report (MAP-SR) score from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit Includes questions about social pleasure, recreational or work pleasure, close relationships, and motivation and effort to engage in activities 15 questions with a score of 0-4, summed for a total range of 0-60 higher values represent a better outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 115</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events, serious adverse events, and adverse events leading to discontinuation throughout the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients with Vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs at baseline, day 85 or last visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>InterSePT Scale for Suicidal Thinking-Plus (ISST-Plus) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 29, 57, 85, and 115</time_frame>
    <description>InterSePT Scale for Suicidal Thinking-Plus (ISST-Plus) score at baseline, day 29, day 57, day 85, and day 115 or last visit Semi-structured interview to assess severity of suicidal ideation and behavior Part I: collects information on 7 days prior to visit; 13 items scored 0, 1, or 2 Part II: collects information since last visit Part III: global rating of status at time of interview; scored 0-5 for suicidality, with a higher score representing a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change on the World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL-BREF) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change on the World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL-BREF) scale from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit Includes questions about quality of life, health, or other areas of life 26 questions scored 1-5, for a raw score sum of 24-120 higher values represent a better outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Beck Depression Inventory, Second Ed. (BDI-II) total score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the Beck Depression Inventory, Second Edition (BDI-II) total score from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit 21-item questionnaire with each item scored 0-3 for a summed total of 0-63 higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage change in Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage change in PANSS score (within assigned treatment group) from baseline to day 29, day 57, and day 85 or last visit 30 different schizophrenia symptoms scored from 1-7 total score of 30-210 is sum of 7-item positive scale, 7-item negative scale, and 16-item general psychopathology scale higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Responders in total Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 85</time_frame>
    <description>Responders: defined as a reduction of at least 20% at day 85 or last visit in total PANSS score relative to baseline 30 different schizophrenia symptoms scored from 1-7 total score of 30-210 is sum of 7-item positive scale, 7-item negative scale, and 16-item general psychopathology scale higher values represent a worse outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who responded to Brief Medication Questionnaire (BMQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 29, 57, and 85 (last visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Brief Medication Questionnaire (BMQ) collects information about current schizophrenia medication use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">112</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PEAR-004</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible participants were to access PEAR-004 (an investigational digital therapeutic) on a mobile device (iOS and Android based) as needed to receive suggestions about coping strategies to overcome difficulties in daily life.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible participants were to access a sham control downloaded on a mobile device (iOS and Android based) as needed to delivering notifications prompting the participant to open the sham app, and then display a prescription timer for the remaining duration of app availability.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEAR-004</intervention_name>
    <description>PEAR-004 (an investigational digital therapeutic) or sham (control) was downloaded to the subject's phone and then the assigned application was unlocked using a prescription code provided by Pear Therapeutics. As this was a digital therapeutic device study, dose or mode of administration is not applicable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PEAR-004</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham</intervention_name>
    <description>PEAR-004 (an investigational digital therapeutic) or sham (control) was downloaded to the subject's phone and then the assigned application was unlocked using a prescription code provided by Pear Therapeutics. As this was a digital therapeutic device study, dose or mode of administration is not applicable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent must be obtained prior to participation in the study.

          -  Healthy male and female subjects 18 to 65 years of age, inclusive, and in good health
             as determined by medical history, physical examination, and vital signs at screening

          -  SCID-based DSM-5 diagnosis of schizophrenia and a total PANSS score &gt; 60

          -  Proficient in English at 5th grade reading level or higher, in the judgement of the
             investigator

          -  Capable of using a mobile device (compatible with PEAR-004) and using common
             applications, in the judgement of the investigator

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Major change in primary antipsychotic medication in the prior 4 weeks before screening
             (e.g., switching to a new agent or a dose adjustment within two weeks of
             randomization)

          -  Planning to move out of the geographic area within 3 months

          -  Unable to use English to participate in the consent process, the interventions or
             assessments

          -  Inability to comply with study procedures, due to severe medical conditions or
             otherwise

          -  Meet DSM-5 diagnosis for a current episode of major depression, mania, or hypomania in
             the past month

          -  Meet DSM-5 diagnosis for a current moderate or severe alcohol or cannabis use disorder
             in the past 2 months

          -  Meet DSM-5 diagnosis for a current substance use disorder (other than alcohol or
             cannabis) in the past 2 months

          -  Considered high risk for suicidal behavior based on ISST-Plus score at screening, or
             in the judgement of the investigator

          -  Previously participated in a clinical study involving PEAR-004
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Garden Grove</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92845</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrance</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90502</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maitland</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32751</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Rapids</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>49548</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 18, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Digital Therapeutic</keyword>
  <keyword>CBT</keyword>
  <keyword>smartphone app</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Novartis is committed to sharing with qualified external researchers, access to patient-level data and supporting clinical documents from eligible studies. These requests are reviewed and approved by an independent review panel on the basis of scientific merit. All data provided is anonymized to respect the privacy of patients who have participated in the trial in line with applicable laws and regulations.
This trial data availability is according to the criteria and process described on www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

