<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03754933</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PNP-002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01FD005746-01A1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>14271</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03754933</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Repeat Administration of Ad/PNP and Fludarabine Phosphate in Patients With Local Head/Neck Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1/2, Open-label Study Evaluating Safety of Repeat Administration of Ad/PNP-F-araAMP (Ad/PNP Administered Intratumorally Followed by Intravenous Fludarabine Phosphate) in Subjects With Recurrent, Local Head and Neck Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PNP Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PNP Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective: The primary objective of the study is to evaluate the safety of repeat
      administration of a dose level of Ad/PNP plus fludarabine phosphate (F-araAMP) which
      demonstrated anti-tumor activity in patients with advanced, locoregional head/neck cancer in
      a completed phase I study.

      Secondary Objective: The secondary objective is to evaluate the antitumor activity of repeat
      administration of Ad/PNP plus F-araAMP.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Mechanism of action. The study drug, Ad/PNP-F-araAMP (Fludarabine phosphate) consists of
           a nonreplicating adenoviral vector expressing the E. coli purine nucleoside
           phosphorylase (PNP) injected intratumorally followed by intravenous administration of
           F-araAMP. This combination generates 2-fluoroadenine (F-Ade) within the tumor resulting
           in focal chemotherapeutic activity.

           F-araAMP is an agent that is rapidly cleaved by plasma phosphatases to fludarabine,
           which is the primary circulating form of the drug and has activity against certain
           hematological malignancies, but not against solid tumors such as head and neck squamous
           cell carcinoma (HNSCC). Fludarabine (F-araA) is an adenosine analog and substrate for E.
           coli PNP, which cleaves the glycosidic bond of F-araA to generate F-Ade. The F-Ade
           metabolite has shown pronounced activity against human tumor xenografts in mice.

           Many refractory tumors are refractory precisely because they have a very low growth
           fraction, i.e., a relatively small percentage of tumor cells dividing at any particular
           point in time. In nonclinical studies, significant in vivo antitumor activity has been
           demonstrated by F-Ade generation from F-araAMP in tumors in which 2.5 to 10% of cells
           express the E. coli PNP gene. In addition, anti-tumor effect was seen in patients with
           advanced solid tumors (melanoma and head and neck cancer) in the higher dose cohorts
           during a Phase 1 study (see next section).

        2. Tumor response with Ad/PNP-F-araAMP in Phase 1 Study. The safety and efficacy of
           Ad/PNP-F-araAMP has been evaluated in a Phase 1 study, PNP-001. Four escalating dose
           levels were evaluated in 10 subjects with head and neck cancer and 2 subjects with
           melanoma; clinical activity was observed at the highest dose levels following 3
           intratumoral injections of Ad/PNP over 2 days and IV F-araAMP phosphate over 3 days. The
           overall response rate (CR+PR) was approximately 67% in the 2 highest dose cohorts,
           Cohorts 3 and 4. Results suggest a dose response effect. The duration of response in the
           injected tumor was limited, with 4 of 5 responding tumors having disease progression of
           the injected lesion prior to last follow-up on Day 56, suggesting that repeat
           administration should be evaluated. Ad/PNP + F-araAMP was well tolerated. No subject
           experienced a dose-limiting toxicity and none of the subjects discontinued study
           treatment. Overall, the activity and safety profile of Ad/PNP seen in the Phase 1 study
           supports further clinical evaluation of repeat administration of Ad/PNP (IT) and
           F-araAMP phosphate infusion for patients with HNSCC.

        3. Purpose of the Study. Based upon the tumor response seen with a single administration of
           the two highest dose levels of Ad/PNP-F-araAMP in the Phase 1 study, PNP plans to
           investigate the safety and assess anti-tumor activity of repeat cycles of injection of
           Ad/PNP + F-araAMP in patients with advanced head and neck cancer. Subjects in the study
           will have RECIST 1.1 measurable HNSCC which is amenable to local injection for which
           there is no effective curative or palliative treatment option. This study population was
           selected since results from this Phase 1/2 trial are intended to support the safety of
           repeat dosing in further clinical investigation.

        4. Study Design. The trial is designed as a single-arm study to evaluate the safety of
           repeat cycles of Ad/PNP and F-araAMP in patients with recurrent HNSCC with tumor(s)
           accessible for injection. Ad/PNP will be injected intratumorally twice on Day 1 and once
           on Day 2 followed by infusion of F-araAMP daily on Days 3, 4, and 5. Subjects will
           receive repeat administration of Ad/PNP-F-araAMP every 4 weeks (i.e., each cycle) for 5
           cycles or until injected tumor progresses, unacceptable toxicity occurs, no tumor is
           present for injection, or patient death. Tumor response in the injected tumor(s) will be
           assessed by physical examination as well as by radiographic imaging. All subjects will
           be monitored for adverse events during study participation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety as measured by the number of adverse events Grade 2 and above that are considered by investigator to be definitely, probably, or possibly related to study treatment, graded according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Effects v. 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 days</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events Grade 2 and above that are considered by investigator to be definitely, probably, or possibly related to study treatment will be collected from initial dose through 60 days after last dose of study drug. Outcome measure will be reported as the number of events for each dose group, and all safety events will be summarized with descriptive statistics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best Overall Response (ORR) per RECIST 1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>Best durable overall response (ORR) defined as CR or partial response determined by RECIST 1.1 persisting for at least 4 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) defined as time from first intratrumoral injection to date of progression or to death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of treatment response</measure>
    <time_frame>Six months</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of treatment response defined as time from first documentation of CR or PR until first occurrence of disease progression or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Recurrent Head and Neck Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ad/PNP + fludarabine phosphate, 5 cycles</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ad/PNP</intervention_name>
    <description>Ad/PNP is a replication defective adenoviral vector expressing E. coli Purine Nucleoside Phosphorylase</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ad/PNP + fludarabine phosphate, 5 cycles</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gedeptin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine Phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine phosphate is an anticancer agent currently used to treatment patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ad/PNP + fludarabine phosphate, 5 cycles</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provided Informed Consent

          2. Age ≥ 18 years

          3. Patients with histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of recurrent HNSCC
             for whom there is no curative treatment option. For the purposes of trial eligibility,
             HNSCC may include, in addition to the usual mucosal sites, cutaneous squamous cell
             primary sites and squamous cell carcinoma of unknown primary presenting with neck
             lymph nodal disease, and nasopharyngeal carcinoma.

          4. All standard or approved treatment options that would provide substantive palliation
             must have failed, been exhausted, or patient not eligible or willing to use them (for
             example neuropathy, nephropathy , or hearing loss precluding the use of cisplatin)

          5. Tumor mass (primary tumor and/or lymphadenopathy) technically suitable for IT
             injections (otolaryngologist will determine feasibility). Patients with nodal disease
             (or metastatic disease) that is needle accessible are eligible. Patients with
             additional tumors (including distant metastatic disease) beyond the IT injection
             accessible tumor(s) that are not accessible for intratumoral injection are eligible
             only if the patient has no other curative treatment option for the metastatic disease
             and treatment of local disease may provide the patient some benefit or palliation.

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of ≤ 2

          7. In the judgment of the Investigator, the patient has recovered sufficiently from any
             previous significant therapy side effects or toxicities prior to Ad/PNP
             administration.

          8. Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500 cells/ul; hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dl, platelets ≥
             100,000/ul

          9. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dl, or calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 60 ml/min

         10. Bilirubin ≤ upper limit of normal, alanine aminotransferase ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of
             normal and/or aspartate aminotransferase ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal, alkaline
             phosphatase ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal

         11. Prothrombin time (PT)/international normalized ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of
             normal

         12. Activated partial thromboplastin (aPTT) time ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal

         13. Female patients must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy at screening (pregnancy
             test is not required for patients with bilateral oophorectomy and/or hysterectomy or
             for those patients who are &gt; 1 year postmenopausal)

         14. All patients of reproductive potential must agree to use a medically acceptable form
             of contraception (eg, hormonal birth control, double-barrier method) or abstinence.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior history or current diagnosis of leukemia

          2. Have received any gene therapy products or oncolytic viral therapy

          3. Receiving allopurinol

          4. Received an investigational drug within 30 days prior to first injection of Ad/PNP

          5. Received radiation treatment &lt; 4 weeks prior to first injection of Ad/PNP, and does
             not have any RECIST 1.1 evaluable lesions that are outside the radiation field. (If
             the patient has RECIST 1.1 evaluable lesions outside the radiation field then they can
             be included.)

          6. Received chemotherapy (systemic anticancer treatment) &lt; 4 weeks prior to first
             injection of Ad/PNP and has not recovered from all the related side effects. (If the
             patients has recovered from related side effects or has reached a new baseline then
             can be included)

          7. Has significant baseline neuropathy (&gt; grade 2 based on CTCAE v4.0)

          8. Uncontrolled intercurrent disease (e.g., diabetes, hypertension, thyroid disease,
             active infection)

          9. Had within 6 months prior to enrollment: Myocardial infarction, cerebral vascular
             accident, uncontrolled congestive heart failure, significant liver disease, unstable
             angina

         10. Fever (temperature &gt; 38.1 degrees C orally)

         11. Receiving chronic systemic corticosteroids (&gt; 3 weeks) or any chronic
             immunosuppressive medications within 14 days prior to first injection of Ad/PNP.
             Subjects receiving short courses of corticosteroids are considered eligible for the
             study.

         12. Receiving anticoagulants other than those to maintain patency of venous lines

         13. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding

         14. History of HIV infection. No requirement for testing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>A Dimitrios Colevas, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Roan C Raymundo</last_name>
    <phone>650-721-4071</phone>
    <email>rcraymun@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Roan C Raymundo</last_name>
      <phone>650-721-4071</phone>
      <email>rcraymun@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>A Dimitrios Colevas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-724-9707</phone>
      <email>colevas@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker WB, Sorscher EJ. Use of E. coli Purine Nucleoside Phosphorylase in the Treatment of Solid Tumors. Curr Pharm Des. 2017 Nov 8. doi: 10.2174/1381612823666171109101851. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>29119917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenthal EL, Chung TK, Parker WB, Allan PW, Clemons L, Lowman D, Hong J, Hunt FR, Richman J, Conry RM, Mannion K, Carroll WR, Nabell L, Sorscher EJ. Phase I dose-escalating trial of Escherichia coli purine nucleoside phosphorylase and fludarabine gene therapy for advanced solid tumors. Ann Oncol. 2015 Jul;26(7):1481-7. doi: 10.1093/annonc/mdv196. Epub 2015 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25899782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 19, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fludarabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenovirus</keyword>
  <keyword>Head &amp; neck squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

