<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03758313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1173/2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03758313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-Invasive Monitoring of Partial Pressure of Carbon Dioxide in Mechanically Ventilated Preterm Infants</brief_title>
  <official_title>Non-Invasive Monitoring of Partial Pressure of Carbon Dioxide in Mechanically Ventilated Preterm Infants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tobias Werther</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In mechanically ventilated preterm infants, the ability to monitor carbon dioxide partial
      pressure (pCO2) values is indispensable. The gold standard for pCO2 measurement is from an
      arterial blood sample (paCO2). This has two drawbacks: firstly, it requires an arterial line
      and, secondly, it does not provide the clinicians with a continuous measurement. At present,
      two alternative pCO2 monitoring systems are available in the field of neonatal intensive care
      medicine: end-tidal CO2 (etCO2) capnography and transcutaneous CO2 (tcCO2) measurements. Both
      methods have disadvantages including potential technical errors as well as pathologies that
      may reduce reliability as a surrogate for blood gas analysis (BGA). In particular,
      conventional side-stream etCO2 capnography underestimates pCO2 in presence of a tube leakage,
      which is a common occurrence in ventilated preterm infants where only tubes without cuff are
      used. Distal etCO2 (detCO2) by means of a double lumen endo-tracheal tube may solve the
      problem of unreliable etCO2 values in the presence of tube leakage.

      The aim of this study is to compare the agreement, precision and repeatability of the distal
      etCO2-measurement technique described by Kugelman et al. with respect to paCO2 and tcCO2 in
      mechanically ventilated preterm infants. Since ventilation strategies and pCO2 limits may
      vary among different centers, this study helps to determine which non-invasive CO2 monitoring
      system (detCO2 or tcO2) is more suitable in terms of applicability and reliability in preterm
      infants at our neonatal intensive care units.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: In mechanically ventilated preterm infants, the ability to monitor carbon dioxide
      partial pressure (pCO2) values is indispensable. The gold standard for pCO2 measurement is
      from an arterial blood sample (paCO2). This has two drawbacks: firstly, it requires an
      arterial line and, secondly, it does not provide the clinicians with a continuous
      measurement. At present, two alternative pCO2 monitoring systems are available in the field
      of neonatal intensive care medicine: end-tidal CO2 (etCO2) capnography and transcutaneous CO2
      (tcCO2) measurements. Both methods have disadvantages including potential technical errors as
      well as pathologies that may reduce reliability as a surrogate for blood gas analysis (BGA).
      In particular, conventional side-stream etCO2 capnography underestimates pCO2 in presence of
      a tube leakage, which is a common occurrence in ventilated preterm infants where only tubes
      without cuff are used. Distal etCO2 (detCO2) by means of a double lumen endo-tracheal tube
      may solve the problem of unreliable etCO2 values in the presence of tube leakage.

      Several studies compared etCO2 and tcCO2 to paCO2, simultaneously. A comparison study of
      etCO2 and tcCO2 in a cohort of critically ill children did not reveal significant differences
      in the absence of severe pulmonary parenchymal disease. Tobias et al compared etCO2 and tcCO2
      in a cohort of pediatric intensive care patients with respiratory failure and found tcCO2
      measurements to be more accurate. In a cohort of ventilated newborns, tcCO2 monitoring was
      generally more precise than etCO2 during neonatal transport to monitor ventilation. In a more
      recent study restricted to a cohort of postsurgical neonates without lung disease, etCO2
      underestimated paCO2 more than tcCO2 but provided greater precision over paCO2, however it
      was less accurate at smaller tidal volumes. These studies have in common that the adapter of
      the pCO2 analyzer was attached in-line and proximal to the endotracheal tube.

      Aim of the study: The aim of this study is to compare the agreement, precision and
      repeatability of the distal etCO2-measurement technique described by Kugelman et al. with
      respect to paCO2 and tcCO2 in mechanically ventilated preterm infants. Since ventilation
      strategies and pCO2 limits may vary among different centers, this study helps to determine
      which non-invasive CO2 monitoring system (detCO2 or tcO2) is more suitable in terms of
      applicability and reliability in preterm infants at our neonatal intensive care units.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Carbon Dioxide in Mechanically Ventilated Preterm Infants</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>partial pressure of carbon dioxide</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Preterm Infant</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CO2 measurements</intervention_name>
    <description>Distal etCO2, tcCO2 and paCO2 values will be recorded simultaneously in ventilated preterm infants. We will measure etCO2 in a distal position using a double lumen tube connected to an external side-stream capnometer.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Mechanically Ventilated Preterm Infants
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants with a current body weight between 1000 g and 3000 g who require
             intubation.

          -  Signed informed consent from parents or legal guardians.

          -  Expected to provide at least three measurements of paCO2 and detCO2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants with known congenital anomalies of the heart and/or lung.

          -  Need for high frequency oscillation.

          -  Parents or legal guardians deny informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tobias Werther, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Medical University Vienna</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tobias Werther</last_name>
    <phone>+4314040067400</phone>
    <email>tobias.werther@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Pediatrics, Division of Neonatology, Pediatric Intensive Care and Neuropediatrics, Medical University of Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tobias Werther</last_name>
      <phone>+4314040067400</phone>
      <email>tobias.werther@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morley CJ, Davis PG, Doyle LW, Brion LP, Hascoet JM, Carlin JB; COIN Trial Investigators. Nasal CPAP or intubation at birth for very preterm infants. N Engl J Med. 2008 Feb 14;358(7):700-8. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa072788. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2008 Apr 3;358(14):1529.</citation>
    <PMID>18272893</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giannakopoulou C, Korakaki E, Manoura A, Bikouvarakis S, Papageorgiou M, Gourgiotis D, Hatzidaki E. Significance of hypocarbia in the development of periventricular leukomalacia in preterm infants. Pediatr Int. 2004 Jun;46(3):268-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15151541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Erickson SJ, Grauaug A, Gurrin L, Swaminathan M. Hypocarbia in the ventilated preterm infant and its effect on intraventricular haemorrhage and bronchopulmonary dysplasia. J Paediatr Child Health. 2002 Dec;38(6):560-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12410866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobias JD. Transcutaneous carbon dioxide monitoring in infants and children. Paediatr Anaesth. 2009 May;19(5):434-44. doi: 10.1111/j.1460-9592.2009.02930.x. Epub 2009 Feb 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19236597</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aliwalas LL, Noble L, Nesbitt K, Fallah S, Shah V, Shah PS. Agreement of carbon dioxide levels measured by arterial, transcutaneous and end tidal methods in preterm infants &lt; or = 28 weeks gestation. J Perinatol. 2005 Jan;25(1):26-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15496874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Molloy EJ, Deakins K. Are carbon dioxide detectors useful in neonates? Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2006 Jul;91(4):F295-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16790735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McDonald MJ, Montgomery VL, Cerrito PB, Parrish CJ, Boland KA, Sullivan JE. Comparison of end-tidal CO2 and Paco2 in children receiving mechanical ventilation. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2002 Jul;3(3):244-249.</citation>
    <PMID>12780964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmalisch G. Current methodological and technical limitations of time and volumetric capnography in newborns. Biomed Eng Online. 2016 Aug 30;15(1):104. doi: 10.1186/s12938-016-0228-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27576441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson CT, Breen PH. Carbon dioxide kinetics and capnography during critical care. Crit Care. 2000;4(4):207-15. Epub 2000 Jul 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11094503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu CH, Chou HC, Hsieh WS, Chen WK, Huang PY, Tsao PN. Good estimation of arterial carbon dioxide by end-tidal carbon dioxide monitoring in the neonatal intensive care unit. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2003 Apr;35(4):292-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12629627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amuchou Singh S, Singhal N. Dose end-tidal carbon dioxide measurement correlate with arterial carbon dioxide in extremely low birth weight infants in the first week of life? Indian Pediatr. 2006 Jan;43(1):20-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16465002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dargaville PA, Tingay DG. Lung protective ventilation in extremely preterm infants. J Paediatr Child Health. 2012 Sep;48(9):740-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1754.2012.02532.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22970667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keszler M, Nassabeh-Montazami S, Abubakar K. Evolution of tidal volume requirement during the first 3 weeks of life in infants &lt;800 g ventilated with Volume Guarantee. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2009 Jul;94(4):F279-82. doi: 10.1136/adc.2008.147157. Epub 2008 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19060010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nassabeh-Montazami S, Abubakar KM, Keszler M. The impact of instrumental dead-space in volume-targeted ventilation of the extremely low birth weight (ELBW) infant. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2009 Feb;44(2):128-33. doi: 10.1002/ppul.20954.</citation>
    <PMID>19061234</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hagerty JJ, Kleinman ME, Zurakowski D, Lyons AC, Krauss B. Accuracy of a new low-flow sidestream capnography technology in newborns: a pilot study. J Perinatol. 2002 Apr-May;22(3):219-25.</citation>
    <PMID>11948385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nangia S, Saili A, Dutta AK. End tidal carbon dioxide monitoring--its reliability in neonates. Indian J Pediatr. 1997 May-Jun;64(3):389-94.</citation>
    <PMID>10771861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh BS, Gilbert U, Singh S, Govindaswami B. Sidestream microstream end tidal carbon dioxide measurements and blood gas correlations in neonatal intensive care unit. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2013 Mar;48(3):250-6. doi: 10.1002/ppul.22593. Epub 2012 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22589000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahmoud RA, Proquitté H, Fawzy N, Bührer C, Schmalisch G. Tracheal tube airleak in clinical practice and impact on tidal volume measurement in ventilated neonates. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2011 Mar;12(2):197-202. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3181e89834.</citation>
    <PMID>20581731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmalisch G, Al-Gaaf S, Proquitté H, Roehr CC. Effect of endotracheal tube leak on capnographic measurements in a ventilated neonatal lung model. Physiol Meas. 2012 Oct;33(10):1631-41. Epub 2012 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>22986303</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Proquitté H, Krause S, Rüdiger M, Wauer RR, Schmalisch G. Current limitations of volumetric capnography in surfactant-depleted small lungs. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2004 Jan;5(1):75-80.</citation>
    <PMID>14697113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kugelman A, Golan A, Riskin A, Shoris I, Ronen M, Qumqam N, Bader D, Bromiker R. Impact of Continuous Capnography in Ventilated Neonates: A Randomized, Multicenter Study. J Pediatr. 2016 Jan;168:56-61.e2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.09.051. Epub 2015 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>26490126</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kugelman A, Zeiger-Aginsky D, Bader D, Shoris I, Riskin A. A novel method of distal end-tidal CO2 capnography in intubated infants: comparison with arterial CO2 and with proximal mainstream end-tidal CO2. Pediatrics. 2008 Dec;122(6):e1219-24. doi: 10.1542/peds.2008-1300. Epub 2008 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>19029196</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cassady G. Transcutaneous monitoring in the newborn infant. J Pediatr. 1983 Dec;103(6):837-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6417293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rennie JM. Transcutaneous carbon dioxide monitoring. Arch Dis Child. 1990 Apr;65(4 Spec No):345-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2110802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bendjelid K, Schütz N, Stotz M, Gerard I, Suter PM, Romand JA. Transcutaneous PCO2 monitoring in critically ill adults: clinical evaluation of a new sensor. Crit Care Med. 2005 Oct;33(10):2203-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16215371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dullenkopf A, Bernardo SD, Berger F, Fasnacht M, Gerber AC, Weiss M. Evaluation of a new combined SpO2/PtcCO2 sensor in anaesthetized paediatric patients. Paediatr Anaesth. 2003 Nov;13(9):777-84.</citation>
    <PMID>14617118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sørensen LC, Brage-Andersen L, Greisen G. Effects of the transcutaneous electrode temperature on the accuracy of transcutaneous carbon dioxide tension. Scand J Clin Lab Invest. 2011 Nov;71(7):548-52. doi: 10.3109/00365513.2011.590601. Epub 2011 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>21732731</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eberhard P. The design, use, and results of transcutaneous carbon dioxide analysis: current and future directions. Anesth Analg. 2007 Dec;105(6 Suppl):S48-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18048898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirata K, Nishihara M, Oshima Y, Hirano S, Kitajima H. Application of transcutaneous carbon dioxide tension monitoring with low electrode temperatures in premature infants in the early postnatal period. Am J Perinatol. 2014 May;31(5):435-40. doi: 10.1055/s-0033-1352485. Epub 2013 Aug 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23918520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aly S, El-Dib M, Mohamed M, Aly H. Transcutaneous Carbon Dioxide Monitoring with Reduced-Temperature Probes in Very Low Birth Weight Infants. Am J Perinatol. 2017 Apr;34(5):480-485. doi: 10.1055/s-0036-1593352. Epub 2016 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>27673754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karlsson V, Sporre B, Ågren J. Transcutaneous PCO2 Monitoring in Newborn Infants During General Anesthesia Is Technically Feasible. Anesth Analg. 2016 Oct;123(4):1004-7. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0000000000001462.</citation>
    <PMID>27464976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Restrepo RD, Hirst KR, Wittnebel L, Wettstein R. AARC clinical practice guideline: transcutaneous monitoring of carbon dioxide and oxygen: 2012. Respir Care. 2012 Nov;57(11):1955-62. doi: 10.4187/respcare.02011.</citation>
    <PMID>23107301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sivan Y, Eldadah MK, Cheah TE, Newth CJ. Estimation of arterial carbon dioxide by end-tidal and transcutaneous PCO2 measurements in ventilated children. Pediatr Pulmonol. 1992 Mar;12(3):153-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1641271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tobias JD, Meyer DJ. Noninvasive monitoring of carbon dioxide during respiratory failure in toddlers and infants: end-tidal versus transcutaneous carbon dioxide. Anesth Analg. 1997 Jul;85(1):55-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9212122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tingay DG, Stewart MJ, Morley CJ. Monitoring of end tidal carbon dioxide and transcutaneous carbon dioxide during neonatal transport. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2005 Nov;90(6):F523-6. Epub 2005 Apr 29.</citation>
    <PMID>15863489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tingay DG, Mun KS, Perkins EJ. End tidal carbon dioxide is as reliable as transcutaneous monitoring in ventilated postsurgical neonates. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2013 Mar;98(2):F161-4. doi: 10.1136/fetalneonatal-2011-301606. Epub 2012 Aug 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22887048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Kaam AH, De Jaegere AP, Rimensberger PC; Neovent Study Group. Incidence of hypo- and hyper-capnia in a cross-sectional European cohort of ventilated newborn infants. Arch Dis Child Fetal Neonatal Ed. 2013 Jul;98(4):F323-6. doi: 10.1136/archdischild-2012-302649. Epub 2012 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23241364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donner A, Eliasziw M. Sample size requirements for reliability studies. Stat Med. 1987 Jun;6(4):441-8.</citation>
    <PMID>3629046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller R, Büttner P. A critical discussion of intraclass correlation coefficients. Stat Med. 1994 Dec 15-30;13(23-24):2465-76.</citation>
    <PMID>7701147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walter SD, Eliasziw M, Donner A. Sample size and optimal designs for reliability studies. Stat Med. 1998 Jan 15;17(1):101-10.</citation>
    <PMID>9463853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McSwain SD, Hamel DS, Smith PB, Gentile MA, Srinivasan S, Meliones JN, Cheifetz IM. End-tidal and arterial carbon dioxide measurements correlate across all levels of physiologic dead space. Respir Care. 2010 Mar;55(3):288-93.</citation>
    <PMID>20196877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siobal MS. Monitoring Exhaled Carbon Dioxide. Respir Care. 2016 Oct;61(10):1397-416. doi: 10.4187/respcare.04919. Epub 2016 Sep 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27601718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fayoux P, Devisme L, Merrot O, Marciniak B. Determination of endotracheal tube size in a perinatal population: an anatomical and experimental study. Anesthesiology. 2006 May;104(5):954-60.</citation>
    <PMID>16645447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yildizdaş D, Yapicioğlu H, Yilmaz HL, Sertdemir Y. Correlation of simultaneously obtained capillary, venous, and arterial blood gases of patients in a paediatric intensive care unit. Arch Dis Child. 2004 Feb;89(2):176-80.</citation>
    <PMID>14736638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zavorsky GS, Cao J, Mayo NE, Gabbay R, Murias JM. Arterial versus capillary blood gases: a meta-analysis. Respir Physiol Neurobiol. 2007 Mar 15;155(3):268-79. Epub 2006 Aug 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16919507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bland JM, Altman DG. Agreement between methods of measurement with multiple observations per individual. J Biopharm Stat. 2007;17(4):571-82.</citation>
    <PMID>17613642</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>November 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">November 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 29, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tobias Werther</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

