<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02627443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCI-2015-02064</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-02064</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1563</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9948</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9948</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CM00099</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UM1CA186686</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02627443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carboplatin, Gemcitabine Hydrochloride, and ATR Kinase Inhibitor VX-970 in Treating Patients With Recurrent and Metastatic Ovarian, Primary Peritoneal, or Fallopian Tube Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Dose Escalation and Expansion Cohort of Carboplatin and Gemcitabine With or Without M6620 (VX-970) in First or Second Recurrence Platinum-Sensitive Epithelial Ovarian, Peritoneal, and Fallopian Tube Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of gemcitabine hydrochloride and
      ATR kinase inhibitor VX-970 and how well they work with carboplatin in treating patients with
      ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer that has come back (recurrent) and has
      spread to other places in the body (metastatic). Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as
      carboplatin and gemcitabine hydrochloride, work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor
      cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from
      spreading. ATR kinase inhibitor VX-970 may stop the growth of tumor cells by blocking some of
      the enzymes needed for cell growth. Giving ATR kinase inhibitor VX-970 with chemotherapy
      (carboplatin and gemcitabine hydrochloride) may work better in treating patients with
      ovarian, primary peritoneal, or fallopian tube cancer compared to chemotherapy alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Assess safety and tolerability of the combination therapy carboplatin, gemcitabine
      (gemcitabine hydrochloride) and M6620 (VX-970) (rad3-related [ATR] kinase inhibitor VX-970)
      in adult women with platinum sensitive recurrent high grade serous or high grade endometrioid
      ovarian, primary peritoneal or fallopian tube cancer. (Phase I Dose Escalation/Safety
      Lead-in) II. Determine the dose of the triple therapy to be used in the dose expansion cohort
      of the study. (Phase I Dose Escalation/Safety Lead-in) III. Confirm the safety at the maximum
      tolerated dose (MTD) for the addition of M6620 (VX-970) to carboplatin and gemcitabine in
      first or second recurrence of platinum sensitive high grade serous or endometrioid ovarian,
      primary peritoneal or fallopian tube carcinoma. (Expansion Cohort)

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine if the MTD for the combination of carboplatin, gemcitabine and M6620 (VX-970)
      improves the confirmed response rate in adult women with platinum sensitive recurrent high
      grade serous or high grade endometrioid ovarian, primary peritoneal or fallopian tube cancer.

      II. To determine the impact of the MTD on overall survival (OS), duration of response, and
      progression-free survival (PFS).

      INTEGRATED CORRELATIVE STUDY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Collection of specimens for biomarker studies to provide preliminary proof of mechanism.
      Assess, in an exploratory fashion, whether the combination of gemcitabine and carboplatin
      activates the ATR/CHK1 pathway at achievable concentrations and also whether M6620 inhibits
      the activated pathway.

      II. To determine whether increased deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) damage as assessed by two
      different multiplex assays correlates with response to combination therapy with M6620
      (VX-970).

      III. To determine whether mutations in homologous recombination repair genes correlate with
      response to combination therapy with M6620 (VX-970).

      IV. To ascertain modulation of ATR autophosphorylation and other pharmacodynamic readouts for
      ATR inhibition by M6620 (VX-970).

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of gemcitabine hydrochloride and ATR kinase
      inhibitor VX-970 followed by a phase II study.

      Patients receive carboplatin intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on day 1, gemcitabine
      hydrochloride IV over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8, and ATR kinase inhibitor VX-970 IV over 60
      minutes on days 2 and 9. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for 3 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 4, 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) (phase I dose escalation)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 28 days</time_frame>
    <description>The MTD in this study will be defined as the highest safely tolerated dose, up to a maximum of dose level 4, where at most 1 out of six patients experience a dose limiting toxicity (DLT) with the next higher dose having at least 2 DLTs in 3 or more patients. Will be reported descriptively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be summarized using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 5.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Confirmed response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From study entry to death from any cause, assessed up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>OS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>From first documented date of confirmed response (complete response [CR] or partial response [PR]), to the date at which progression is first documented, up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The duration of confirmed responses will be assessed using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to the first of either disease progression or death from any cause, up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Disease progression will be determined based on Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria. PFS will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the frequency of marker inhibition</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Semi-quantitative data will be used to compare the data between the treatment arms using boxplots and descriptive statistics.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) damage markers and mutation data with clinical endpoints (i.e. response, PFS, OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical and graphical techniques will be used to explore these relationships. For time-to-event endpoints, we will use Cox proportional hazards models, and for response data we will use Logistic regression models. In addition, we will use Fisher's exact tests to test the association between categorical marker data and response.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">31</enrollment>
  <condition>High Grade Ovarian Serous Adenocarcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Fallopian Tube Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Ovarian Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Metastatic Primary Peritoneal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Ovarian Endometrioid Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Fallopian Tube Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Ovarian Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Primary Peritoneal Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Fallopian Tube Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Ovarian Cancer AJCC v6 and v7</condition>
  <condition>Stage IV Primary Peritoneal Cancer AJCC v7</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive carboplatin IV over 30 minutes on day 1, gemcitabine hydrochloride IV over 30 minutes on days 1 and 8, and ATR kinase inhibitor VX-970 IV over 60 minutes on days 2 and 9. Cycles repeat every 21 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Berzosertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-Pyrazinamine, 3-(3-(4-((Methylamino)methyl)phenyl)-5-isoxazolyl)-5-(4-((1-methylethyl)sulfonyl)phenyl)-</other_name>
    <other_name>M 6620</other_name>
    <other_name>M6620</other_name>
    <other_name>VX 970</other_name>
    <other_name>VX-970</other_name>
    <other_name>VX970</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blastocarb</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplat</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatin Hexal</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatino</other_name>
    <other_name>Carboplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosin</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbosol</other_name>
    <other_name>Carbotec</other_name>
    <other_name>CBDCA</other_name>
    <other_name>Displata</other_name>
    <other_name>Ercar</other_name>
    <other_name>JM-8</other_name>
    <other_name>Nealorin</other_name>
    <other_name>Novoplatinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatin AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Paraplatine</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinwas</other_name>
    <other_name>Ribocarbo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dFdC</other_name>
    <other_name>dFdCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>Difluorodeoxycytidine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gemcitabine Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>dFdCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>Difluorodeoxycytidine Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>FF 10832</other_name>
    <other_name>FF-10832</other_name>
    <other_name>FF10832</other_name>
    <other_name>Gemcitabine HCI</other_name>
    <other_name>Gemzar</other_name>
    <other_name>LY-188011</other_name>
    <other_name>LY188011</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological Study</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (carboplatin, gemcitabine hydrochloride, VX-970)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed high grade serous or endometrioid ovarian, peritoneal or
             fallopian tube malignancy that is metastatic and for which curative measures do not
             exist; the histology can be confirmed from tissue that was taken at the time of
             diagnosis; a biopsy at the time of recurrence prior to enrollment on study is not
             required

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded for
             non-nodal lesions and short axis for nodal lesions) as &gt;= 20 mm (&gt;= 2 cm) with
             conventional techniques or as &gt;= 10 mm (&gt;= 1 cm) with spiral computed tomography (CT)
             scan, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or calipers by clinical exam

          -  Patients enrolled in the expansion cohort will be required to have archival tumor
             tissue available for analysis and be willing to have a tumor biopsy at baseline (after
             registration and prior to starting study treatment), at cycle 1 day 2 and at cycle 2
             day 2; patients must have platinum sensitive disease and be in their first or second
             platinum sensitive recurrence; platinum sensitive disease is defined as recurrence
             that occurred greater than six months after completion of their last line of platinum
             based therapy; no non-platinum regimens allowed; prior therapy with PARP inhibitors as
             well as bevacizumab is allowed

          -  No more than two prior platinum based regimens; one regimen is defined as the interval
             of treatment from start of platinum based doublet to finish of that treatment course
             for the initial therapy or for the recurrent disease episode; if the nonplatinum agent
             is altered due to any reason other than disease progression, it counts as one regimen;
             for example, if a patient started on carboplatin and paclitaxel but developed a taxol
             reaction and was switched to carboplatin and Abraxane, this counts as one prior
             regimen

          -  Children are excluded from this study, but will be eligible for future pediatric
             trials

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status =&lt; 2 (Karnofsky &gt;= 60%)

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 6 months

          -  Leukocytes &gt;= 3,000/mcL

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Total bilirubin within normal institutional limits

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase
             [SGOT])/alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT])
             =&lt; 2 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Creatinine within normal institutional limits OR creatinine clearance &gt;= 50
             mL/min/1.73 m^2 for patients with creatinine levels above institutional normal

          -  Negative serum pregnancy test result for females of child bearing potential

               -  Note: The effects of M6620 (VX-970) on the developing human fetus are unknown.
                  For this reason and because deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA)-damage response (DDR)
                  inhibitors as well as other therapeutic agents used in this trial may have
                  teratogenic potential, women of child-bearing potential must agree to use
                  adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence)
                  prior to study entry, for the duration of study participation, and 6 months after
                  completion of M6620 (VX-970) administration. Should a woman become pregnant or
                  suspect she is pregnant while she is participating in this study, she should
                  inform her treating physician immediately

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with platinum resistant disease or platinum sensitive disease that is past
             the first or second recurrence

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering
             the study or those who have not recovered from adverse events due to agents
             administered more than 4 weeks earlier, excluding alopecia; patients with treatment
             related effects, such as peripheral neuropathy, that are grade 1 or less are eligible

          -  Prior exposure to gemcitabine

          -  Patients who are receiving any other investigational agents

          -  Patients with known brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial
             because of their poor prognosis and because they often develop progressive neurologic
             dysfunction that would confound the evaluation of neurologic and other adverse events

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to M6620 (VX-970), carboplatin, gemcitabine or to these specific compounds

          -  M6620 (VX-970) is primarily metabolized by CYP3A4; therefore, concomitant
             administration with strong inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4 should be avoided. Because
             the lists of these agents are constantly changing, it is important to regularly
             consult a frequently-updated medical reference for a list of drugs to avoid or
             minimize use of. As part of the enrollment/informed consent procedures, the patient
             will be counseled on the risk of interactions with other agents, and what to do if new
             medications need to be prescribed or if the patient is considering a new
             over-the-counter medicine or herbal product

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because M6620 (VX-970) as a DNA-damage
             response (DDR) inhibitor may have the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient
             effects. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing
             infants secondary to treatment of the mother with M6620 (VX-970), breastfeeding should
             be discontinued if the mother is treated with M6620 (VX-970). These potential risks
             also apply to the other agents used in this study, such as carboplatin and gemcitabine

          -  Patients with Li Fraumeni syndrome are excluded from the study as M6620 (VX-970) is a
             DDR inhibitor

          -  Addition of bevacizumab to the treatment in this study is not allowed; if the treating
             physician feels that the addition of bevacizumab is in the best interest of the
             patient, the patient should be treated with an FDA approved regimen outside of the
             present study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrea E Wahner Hendrickson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center LAO</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Hospital in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea E. Wahner Hendrickson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea E. Wahner Hendrickson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>720-848-0650</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bradley R. Corr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida Health Science Center - Gainesville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Suspended</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32224-9980</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea E. Wahner Hendrickson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky/Markey Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40536</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>859-257-3379</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rachel W. Miller</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University/Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>313-576-9790</phone>
      <email>ctoadmin@karmanos.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ira S. Winer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weisberg Cancer Treatment Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Farmington Hills</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48334</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>313-576-9790</phone>
      <email>ctoadmin@karmanos.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ira S. Winer</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>855-776-0015</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrea E. Wahner Hendrickson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rutgers Cancer Institute of New Jersey</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Brunswick</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>732-235-8675</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eugenia Girda</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute (UPCI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>412-647-8073</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah E. Taylor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Site Public Contact</last_name>
      <phone>434-243-6303</phone>
      <email>PAS9E@virginia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Linda R. Duska</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 24, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fallopian Tube Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Ovarian Epithelial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystadenocarcinoma, Serous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

