<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01403246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLL0709</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01403246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chlorambucil + Lenalidomide and Lenalidomide Maintenance in Untreated Elderly With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I-II Multicenter Study to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of the Chlorambucil + Lenalidomide Combination and Lenalidomide Maintenance Therapy in Untreated Elderly Pts With CLL. EudraCT Number 2009-013415-35</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gruppo Italiano Malattie EMatologiche dell'Adulto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gruppo Italiano Malattie EMatologiche dell'Adulto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I multicenter, open label study in previously untreated and elderly patients
      (&gt; 60 years) with CLL: a non-comparative phase aimed at defining the MTD of lenalidomide
      given in combination with chlorambucil and the efficacy and safety of the lenalidomide and
      chlorambucil combination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All patients will receive six monthly courses of the chlorambucil (C) and lenalidomide (L)
      schedule consisting of 8 days of C (d1-d8) combined with L given daily until response
      assessment which will take place 12 weeks from the start (d+1) of course VI, while patients
      continue their treatment with lenalidomide daily.

      In the first phase of the induction phase of the study the dose of L given with C will be
      gradually escalated to reach the MTD.

      Patients who will achieve a response after 6 courses of CL induction phase -PR, CRi, CR

      The study was first designed to be a phase I-II trial, yet the second phase of the study was
      not conducted due to different reasons, among which: poor accrual and lack of interest.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Slow patient enrollment and new molecules for chronic lymphoid leukemia, have importantly
    reduced the interest of conducting the phase II of this study.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Dose Limiting Toxic Events (DLT) of Lenalidomide Given in Combination With Chlorambucil.</measure>
    <time_frame>At maximum 8 months from induction therapy start</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide with Chlorambucil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide; Chlorambucil</intervention_name>
    <description>MTD of lenalidomide given in combination with chlorambucil</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide with Chlorambucil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  CLL diagnosis according to the 2008 revised NCI criteria.

          -  Age &gt; 65 years or between 60 and 65 years if not suitable for fludarabine-based
             regimens according to the investigator's judgment.

          -  ECOG performance status of ≤2 at study entry.

          -  No previous treatment.

          -  Advanced stage or progressive CLL according to the 2008 revised NCI criteria.

          -  Disease-free of prior malignancies other than CLL for ≥3 years, with the exception of
             currently treated basal cell, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or carcinoma &quot;in
             situ&quot; of the cervix or breast.

          -  Able to take low molecular weight heparin or in alternative, low-fixed-dose warfarin
             or, in alternative, low-dose aspirin.

          -  Able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential(FCBP) must:

               -  Understands the potential teratogenic risk to the unborn child and the need for
                  effective contraception;

               -  Be capable of complying with effective contraceptive measures.

               -  Be informed and understand the potential consequences of pregnancy and the need
                  to notify her study doctor immediately if there is a risk of pregnancy.

               -  Understand the need to commence the study treatment as soon as study drug is
                  dispensed following a negative pregnancy test.

               -  Uderstand the need and accepts to undergo pregnancy testing based on the
                  frequency outlined in this protocol.

               -  Contraception.

               -  Females of childbearing potential (FCBP) enrolled in this protocol must agree to
                  use two reliable forms of contraception simultaneously or to practice complete
                  abstinence from heterosexual contact during the following time periods related to
                  this study: 1) for at least 28 days before starting study drug; 2) while
                  participating in the study; 3) dose interruptions; and 4) for at least 28 days
                  after study treatment discontinuation.

               -  The two methods of reliable contraception must include one highly effective
                  method and one additional effective (barrier) method. FCBP must be referred to a
                  qualified provider of contraceptive methods if needed. The following are examples
                  of highly effective and additional effective methods of contraception:

               -  Highly effective methods:

                    1. Intrauterine device (IUD)

                    2. Hormonal (birth control pills, injections, implants)

                    3. Tubal ligation

                    4. Partner's vasectomy

               -  Additional effective methods:

                    1. Male condom

                    2. Diaphragm

                    3. Cervical Cap

          -  Because of the increased risk of venous thromboembolism in patients with multiple
             myeloma taking lenalidomide and dexamethasone, combined oral contraceptive pills are
             not recommended. If a patient is currently using combined oral contraception the
             patient should switch to one of the effective method listed above. The risk of venous
             thromboembolism continues for 4 to 6 weeks after discontinuing combined oral
             contraception. The efficacy of contraceptive steroids may be reduced during
             co-treatment with dexamethasone.

          -  Implants and levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine systems are associated with an
             increased risk of infection at the time of insertion and irregular vaginal bleeding.
             Prophylactic antibiotics should be considered particularly in patients with
             neutropenia.

          -  Pregnancy testing.

          -  FCBP must have two negative pregnancy tests prior to starting study drug. The first
             pregnancy test must be performed within 10 to 14 days prior to the start of study drug
             and the second pregnancy test must be performed within 24 hours prior to the start of
             study drug.

          -  FCBP must agree to have a medically supervised pregnancy test every 4 weeks including
             4 weeks after the end of study treatment, except in the case of confirmed tubal
             sterilization. This requirement also applies to women of childbearing potential who
             practice complete and continued abstinence.

          -  Females must agree to abstain from breastfeeding during study participation and for at
             least 28 days after study drug discontinuation.

          -  Male patients must:

               -  Understand the potential teratogenic risk if engaged in sexual activity with a
                  pregnant female or a female of childbearing potential.

               -  Must practice complete abstinence or agree to use a condom during sexual contact
                  with a pregnant female or a female of childbearing potential while participating
                  in the study, during dose interruptions and for at least 28 days following study
                  drug discontinuation, even if he has undergone a successful vasectomy.

               -  If pregnancy or a positive pregnancy test does occur in the partner of a male
                  study patient during study participation, the investigator must be notified
                  immediately.

          -  Female and male patients:

               -  should be instructed never to give this medicinal product to another person and
                  to return any unused capsules to the study doctor at the end of treatment.

               -  Should not donate blood during therapy and for at least 28 days following
                  discontinuation of study drug.

               -  Male patients should not donate blood, semen or sperm during therapy or for at
                  least 28 days following discontinuation of study drug.

          -  Laboratory test results within these ranges:

               -  Serum creatinine ≤1.5 mg/dL and creatinine clearance ≥ 60mL/min

               -  Total bilirubin ≤1.5 mg/dL

          -  AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) ≤1.5 x ULN.

          -  All patients must be able to understand and voluntarily sign the informed consent
             form.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from signing the informed consent form.

          -  A CIRS score &gt; 6.

          -  Pregnant or Lactating Females.

          -  Known positive serology for HIV or active hepatitis B or C.

          -  Active infection requiring systemic anti-viral, antibiotic or anti-fungal therapy.

          -  History of tuberculosis within the last five years or recent exposure to tuberculosis
             equal to or less than 6 months.

          -  History of renal failure requiring dialysis.

          -  Known presence of alcohol and/or drug abuse.

          -  History of thrombosis, thromboembolism within one year.

          -  Hearth failure, arrhythmia.

          -  ≥ grade 2 neuropathy.

          -  Uncontrolled hyperthyroidism or hypothyroidism.

          -  Uncontrolled autoimmune hemolytic anemia or thrombocytopenia.

          -  One or more laboratory abnormalities:

          -  calculated creatinine clearance (Cockroft-Gault) &lt;60mL/min;

          -  electrolyte abnormalities according to the Cairo Bishop definition of laboratory TLS.

          -  GOT, GPT, γGT &gt; 1.5 x upper limit of normal value;

          -  serum bilirubin &gt;1.5 mg/dL.

          -  Lactose Intolerance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roberto Foà</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Umberto I - Dipartimento di Biotecnologie Cellulari ed Ematologia Cellulari</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesca Romana Mauro, Co-Coordinator</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Umberto I - Dipartimento di Biotecnologie Cellulari ed Ematologia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Spedali Civili</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Università di Catania - Cattedra di Ematologia - Ospedale &quot;Ferrarotto&quot;</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catania</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Pugliese Ciaccio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catanzaro</city>
        <zip>88100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Azienda Ospedaliera Pugliese Ciaccio - Presidio Ospedaliero A.Pugliese - Unità Operativa di Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catanzaro</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Ematologica - Università degli Studi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UO Centro Trapianti di Midollo - IRCCS Ospedale Maggiore Policlinico</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U.O. Ematologia Clinica - Azienda USL di Pescara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pescara</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Umberto I di Roma - Dipartimento di Biotecnologie Cellulari ed Ematologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roma</city>
        <zip>00161</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U.O. Ematologia, Azienda Ospedaliera Universitaria Senese</name>
      <address>
        <city>Siena</city>
        <zip>53100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SS.C. di Oncoematologia - Dipartimento di Medicina Clinica e Sperimentale - Azienda Ospedaliera - S. Maria Di Terni</name>
      <address>
        <city>Terni</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.gimema.it</url>
    <description>GIMEMA Foundation Webpage</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>February 23, 2016</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2018</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2019</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 12, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CLL</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>Chlorambucil</keyword>
  <keyword>No previous treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chlorambucil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Lenalidomide and Chlorambucil</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Study Group</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="9"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="72" lower_limit="67" upper_limit="81"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Italy</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Dose Limiting Toxic Events (DLT) of Lenalidomide Given in Combination With Chlorambucil.</title>
        <time_frame>At maximum 8 months from induction therapy start</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Study Group</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Dose Limiting Toxic Events (DLT) of Lenalidomide Given in Combination With Chlorambucil.</title>
          <units>Toxic events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>3 years and 3 months</time_frame>
      <desc>The adverse events in the present study report have been classified according to the CTCAE grading. These are included under the Serious Adverse Events, although the fields in the form do not allow to specify grading.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Study Group</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="6" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>PIs of participating centres may disclose their centre's results only after the main study publication has been released, so that a single centre experience can be compared to the study overall results and give a more appropriate view of the study.</restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Alfonso Piciocchi</name_or_title>
      <organization>GIMEMA</organization>
      <phone>+393203671224</phone>
      <email>a.piciocchi@gimema.it</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

