<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03567850</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>I 65518</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03567850</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Problem Solving Skills Training in Adult Cancer Survivors: Bright IDEAS-AC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Problem Solving Skills Training in Adult Cancer Survivors: Bright IDEAS-AC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this 2-year study will assess the acceptability and feasibility of offering
      Problem Solving Skills Therapy (PSST) to cancer survivors and their caregivers focusing on
      the highest risk patients with distress.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At Roswell Park Comprehensive Cancer Center, in collaboration with the University at Buffalo
      School of Public Health and Health Professions and the University of Rochester, we are
      looking for adult cancer patients to participate in our new project designed to facilitate
      recovery from cancer and help cancer survivors lead better, more productive lives. The ideal
      subjects are individuals who have completed treatment for stage I-III cancer and speak
      English. Participants will be randomized into two groups: 8 weekly 1-hour long sessions of
      problem solving skills therapy delivered by a trained therapist vs. care as usual. Bright
      IDEAS Adult Cancer (Bright IDEAS-AC) therapy will be delivered in the most patient-friendly
      way. Sessions will be face-to-face at the location of patient choice (hospital, clinic, or
      participant's home) or over the phone. A supportive other or caregiver is also invited to
      participate in this study. This project does not involve any experimental drugs and does not
      affect the regular care or patient relationship with doctor(s).

      At the time of enrollment, after 3 months and after 6 months, all participants in the
      intervention and control arms, as well as any participating supportive others/caregivers will
      be asked about their healthcare utilization since the last assessment including primary care,
      specialist and emergency department visits and any hospital stays. During the same three time
      points, both patients and supportive others/caregivers will be asked to fill in 4 short
      questionnaires assessing their problem solving skills, health status, mood and function
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 19, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 19, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Health of patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient on physical health using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - disease specific</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Health of Patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on problem solving skills,using the Social Problem-Solving Inventory-Revised (SPSI-R)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization of Patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At time of enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on their healthcare utilization since the last assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Health of patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient on physical health using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Disease Specific (FACT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Health of patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient on physical health using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy (FACT)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral health of patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on problem solving skills,using the Social Problem-Solving Inventory-Revised (SPSI-R)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Health of patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on problem solving skills,using the Social Problem-Solving Inventory-Revised (SPSI-R)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization of Patient</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on their healthcare utilization since the last assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare Utilization of Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>At 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>From all patients in the intervention and control arms, we will collect patient self-report data on their healthcare utilization since the last assessment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Colo-rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to the intervention arm will receive Problem Solving Skills Training (PSST) consisting of eight one-hour individual weekly sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Care As Usual Group (CAU): Participants randomized to the CAU group will be observed under naturalistic conditions. Both PSST and CAU participants and their clinicians (PCP and oncology providers) will be allowed to use any clinically appropriate medical and behavioral care without restriction (e.g., care management, rehabilitation, behavioral therapy, palliative care) or refer patients to social and community services (e.g., peer support, county cancer services program or aging services). The CAU participants will undergo the same evaluation protocol as the PSST group</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Problem solving Skills Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be encouraged to identify specific problems particularly relevant to them and to their family's situation (instead of providing them with standardized examples) to be discussed and &quot;solved&quot; during the PSST sessions. The eight sessions of PSST will be organized in a systematized, therapeutic manner. Session 1 will be face-to-face and devoted to rapport building and understanding relevant social and medical information. The therapist (RA) will introduce PSST and the Bright IDEAS paradigm, present worksheets to guide PSST homework assignments, and give an overview of subsequent sessions. Starting at session 2, participants will continue training over the phone, with the same general structure and format. In sessions 2-7, the therapist and patient, with a supportive other (SO) if available, will review the patient's identified problems and work on application of problem-solving strategies and skills learned earlier.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  stage I-III Colorectal Cancer, Breast, Bladder or Prostate Cancer

          -  meet the screening criteria for psychological distress (NCCN Distress &gt;2)

          -  be able to speak English

          -  have a 5-year survival rate of 50% or greater as deemed by their oncologist,
             surgeon,or other relevant attending physician (suggesting a reasonable rate of cure or
             prolonged medical survival with state-of-the-art medical care)

          -  be willing to provide written informed consent to participate in the study which
             includes several clinical evaluations, provide access to medical records/PCP, and
             allow all interviews and PSST therapy sessions to be audiotaped.

          -  Among patients treated in the urban centers, we will specifically target patients who
             live more than 40 miles away from the clinic as they are more likely to experience
             problems with access to care.

          -  Age 21 or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  a diagnosis of mental retardation,

          -  and/or acute suicidal behavior
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ekaternia Noyes, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ekaternia Noyes, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>716-829-5365</phone>
    <email>enoyes@buffalo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ekaterina Noyes</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 16, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

