<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03567200</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H17-01540</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03567200</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Girls United on the Move: A Unique Integrated Physical Activity and Psychosocial Program for At-risk Adolescent Girls</brief_title>
  <acronym>GUM</acronym>
  <official_title>A League of Their Own: Examining the Effectiveness of a Psycho-social and Sport Program Targeting At-risk Adolescent Girls</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to evaluate the effectiveness of a 9-week psycho-social and
      physical activity program aimed at improving body image, physical self-perceptions, and
      self-compassion for at-risk adolescent girls. In collaboration with the Elizabeth Fry
      Society, the GUM program will be delivered to at-risk adolescent girls within the Okanagan
      Region. Information will be gathered concerning program content and delivery, as well as
      insights into the participants' experiences with the program. These results will provide much
      needed information about whether programs integrating psychological, social, and physical
      components of health are beneficial for this population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Body dissatisfaction increases throughout adolescence; strong associations have been
      established between body image emotions and negative self--perceptions, reduced
      self-compassion, low self- esteem, and depression in adolescent girls. This is heightened in
      at--risk adolescent girls, including those of low socioeconomic status, who have experienced
      abuse and who have limited social support. As such, unique strategies aimed at reducing
      negative self--perceptions of one's physical self and improving self- compassion among
      at--risk adolescent girls are needed. Engagement in physical activity is one way in which
      adolescent girls may experience positive self--perceptions, enhanced body image emotions, and
      increased self--compassion, yet the research has primarily focused on girls who are already
      involved in organized physical activities (i.e., athletes). To address this need, the
      research team and representatives from the Central Okanagan Elizabeth Fry Society, a National
      charitable organisation dedicated to advancing the safety, legal rights, and economic
      security of women and children, have co--created the unique 9- week Girls United and on the
      Move (GUM) integrated program (psycho-social and physical activity) to improve physical
      self--perception, body image, and self--compassion among at--risk adolescent girls living in
      the Okanagan Region of British Columbia. This is particularly important in the Okanagan where
      there is a high number of adolescent girls from low income, abusive households, with many
      facing sexual exploitation and extreme despair, compared to other adolescent girls in British
      Columbia. Thus, the current aim is to implement and undertake a comprehensive evaluation of
      the program's effectiveness in terms of physical self--perceptions, body image,
      self--compassion, and commitment to and enjoyment of physical activity, in order to refine
      and deliver the program more widely.

      This 9- week, integrated program will be implemented in up to 8 middle schools throughout the
      Okanagan. It includes a 1.5 hour, weekly session held at local schools and facilitated by a
      trained researcher and registered social worker. These sessions include psycho-social
      components (e.g., understanding healthy relationships, building self--confidence) in addition
      to engaging in various physical activities (e.g., soccer, dance, and martial arts). At--risk
      adolescent girls from the participating schools will be identified and recruited by school
      counsellors. Each school group will include 10- to 12 participants, yielding a total sample
      of approximately 80-100.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 10, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 29, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Image</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing change from baseline to post-intervention (9-weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Physical Self-Description Questionnaire (PSDQ), which is a multidimensional tool used to measure physical self--perceptions, body image and self--concept. The purpose of the PSDQ is to see how people describe themselves physically.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Compassion</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing change from baseline to post-intervention (9-weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Self-Compassion Scale (SCS), which is a a valid and reliable 26--item scale that has previously been used in this population.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Self-Perceptions</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing change from baseline to post-intervention (9-weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Physical Self-Description Questionnaire (PSDQ), which is a multidimensional tool used to measure physical self--perceptions, body image and self--concept. The purpose of the PSDQ is to see how people describe themselves physically.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sport Enjoyment and Commitment</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessing change from baseline to post-intervention (9-weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Sport-Commitment Questionnaire, which is a 58-item questionnaire that addresses five components or sub-scales which are believed to impact sport commitment; this includes sport enjoyment, involvement alternatives, personal investments, social constraints, and involvement opportunities. Not only has this construct been shown to be very important in motivating youth in sport, but it also may indicate the positive affect to commitment in youth sport programs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant satisfaction and acceptability of the GUM program</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-Intervention (9-weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by conducting semi-structured interviews to gather information concerning program content and delivery, as well as insights into their experiences with the program.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">83</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single-Arm Feasibility</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>9-week, 1x/week, 90-minute face-to-face sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single-Arm Feasibility</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in each of the 8 participating groups (N=10-12 per group) are exposed to an integrated intervention program (integration of physical activity and psychosocial components). Each session is co-facilitated by a trained research staff member and a registered social worker, providing participants with the opportunity to engage in physical activity behaviours as well as discuss various psychosocial topics that are applicable to the participants interests. Physical activities include participating in group activities such as rock climbing, self-defence, yoga, etc. Psychosocial topics addressed include group discussions around cyber-bullying, sexual abuse and exploitation, gender issues, etc.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single-Arm Feasibility</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Girls United and On the Move (GUM) Intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who identify with experiencing challenges with personal or family lives.

          -  Must identify as female between the ages of 11-15 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No specific exclusion criteria, however, only girls that are specifically identified
             and invited to join GUM by the school guidance counsellors, at the participating
             middle schools, will be invited to participate in the research.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cristina Caperchione, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UBC Okanagan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kelowna</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V1V 1V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 2, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 4, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cristina Caperchione</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

