<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03567213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00167247</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03567213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation on the Cortical Communication (CortiCom) System</brief_title>
  <acronym>CortiCom</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigation on the Cortical Communication (CortiCom) System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The CortiCom system consists of 510(k)-cleared components: platinum PMT subdural cortical
      electrode grids, a Blackrock Microsystems patient pedestal, and an external NeuroPort Neural
      Signal Processor. Up to two grids will be implanted in the brain, for a total channel count
      of up to 128 channels, for six months. In each participant, the grid(s) will be implanted
      over areas of cortex that encode speech and upper extremity movement.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The successful adoption of brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) as assistive technologies (ATs)
      for disabled populations depends on the ability to elicit rapid, intuitive, and reliable
      control signals. To date, it is not known which sources of neural information provide the
      most natural and efficient means of control. This study will directly assess the efficacy of
      two sources of neural control signals, speech and motor cortex, for BCI control of software
      and devices using investigators' Cortical Communication (CortiCom) system.

      The CortiCom system consists of 510(k)-cleared components: platinum PMT subdural cortical
      electrode grids, a Blackrock Microsystems patient pedestal, and an external NeuroPort Neural
      Signal Processor. Up to two grids will be implanted in the brain, for a total channel count
      of up to 128 channels, for six months. In each participant, the grid(s) will be implanted
      over areas of cortex that encode speech and upper extremity movement.

      Investigators' study will be the first to investigate the efficiency and intuitiveness of two
      contrasting neural control strategies for BCI: Motor imagery and speech. As the first study
      to chronically and simultaneously record from human speech and motor regions, this study
      seeks to achieve the following:

        -  demonstrate the ability to decode intended upper extremity movements using information
           decoded from primary motor cortex arm/hand area;

        -  demonstrate the ability to decode intended speech from articulatory speech cortex; and

        -  determine the most effective and intuitive user strategies (e.g. imagined speech or
           imagined movement) and optimal neural sources for brain-computer interactions,

      The patient populations targeted in this study are amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS),
      brainstem stroke, locked-in syndrome (LIS), and tetraplegia. Individuals within these
      populations may have normal cortical function and cognition while suffering from motor or
      combined speech and motor deficits.

      Based on research by colleagues, as well as investigators' own experience working with
      participants affected by epilepsy implanted with high density electrocorticographic grids,
      investigators hypothesize that long-term recording of neural activity from the targeted
      cortical areas may provide a new communication channel for these clinical populations. The
      utilization of high-channel-count (up to 128 channel) ECoG grids, in combination with
      simultaneous coverage of speech and motor cortex, will enable investigations into the
      performance of speech-mediated and motor-mediated control efficacy as applied to a variety of
      end effectors, such as computers, tablets, headsets for virtual or augmented reality, smart
      lights, televisions, and assistive technologies. Additionally, eye-tracking may be utilized
      in combination with neural commands to improve target selection performance and ease.

      Through this study, investigators will assess the performance of speech- and motor-mediated
      control using chronic, high-channel count ECoG grid neural implants in pursuit of a
      high-performing, clinically beneficial BCI assistive technology.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to device explantation</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This study outcome will be considered successful if the device is not explanted during the 26-week period of the study. Explantation of the device prior to the completion of the 26-week period implies that the device is putting the subject at risk (e.g. through a serious infection at the implantation site) and therefore must be removed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success rate in controlling the brain computer interface, i.e. ratio of successful trials to total trials.</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>One or more participants demonstrates successful use of the CortiCom system in which motor and/or speech neural signals can be decoded to provide control signals for software and devices. Efficacy is assessed in terms of accuracy, i.e. how often the participant is able to select a desired target.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speed of brain-computer interface control, i.e. time to complete successful trials (in seconds).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>One or more participants demonstrates successful use of the CortiCom system in which motor and/or speech neural signals can be decoded to provide control signals for software and devices. Efficacy is therefore also assessed in terms of how long it takes to select the target.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Tetraplegia</condition>
  <condition>Locked-in Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Brainstem Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical implantation of the CortiCom system</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical implantation of CortiCom system</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of Cortical communication system, consisting of one or two Electrocorticography (ECoG) grids connected to a transcutaneous patient pedestal.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Surgical implantation of the CortiCom system</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of tetraplegia (quadriplegia), brainstem stroke , amyotrophic
             lateral sclerosis (ALS) or Locked-in Syndrome (LIS)

          -  Tetraplegia diagnosis, ALS diagnosis, stroke, or LIS etiology onset occurred at least
             one year prior to enrollment

          -  Complete or incomplete tetraplegia (quadriplegia), tetraparesis (quadriparesis), or
             severe ataxia. In addition, these motor impairments may be combined with severe
             motor-related speech impairment (dysarthria or anarthria), as in LIS.

          -  22-70 years

          -  Meeting surgical safety criteria, including surgical clearance by the participant's
             primary healthcare provider, study physicians, and any necessary consultants

          -  Ability to communicate reliably, such as through eye movement

          -  Willingness and ability to provide informed consent

          -  Screened by rehabilitation psychologist with a result showing that the participant has
             a stable psychosocial support system with caregiver capable of monitoring participant
             throughout the study

          -  Ability and willingness to travel up to 100 miles to study location up to three days
             per week for the duration of the study

          -  Ability to understand and comply with study session instructions

          -  Participant consents to the study and still wishes to participate at the time of the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Performance on formal neuropsychological testing that indicates significant
             psychiatric conditions or cognitive impairments that would interfere with obtaining
             informed consent or fully participating in study activities.

          -  Suicide attempt or persistent suicidal ideation within the past 12 months.

          -  Implanted devices that are incompatible with MRI, which may include pacemakers,
             cardiac defibrillators, spinal cord or vagal nerve stimulators, deep brain
             stimulators, and cochlear implants.

          -  History of substance abuse, narcotic dependence, or alcohol dependence in past 24
             months

          -  Medical conditions contraindicating surgery of a chronically implanted device (e.g.
             osteomyelitis, diabetes, hepatitis, any autoimmune disease/disorder, epilepsy, skin
             disorders causing excessive skin sloughing or poor wound healing, blood or cardiac
             disorder requiring chronic anti-coagulation)

          -  Other chronic, unstable medical conditions that could interfere with subject
             participation.

          -  Presence of pre-surgical findings in anatomical, functional, and/or vascular
             neuroimaging that makes achieving implant locations within desired risk levels too
             challenging (to be decided by neurological and neurosurgical team)

          -  Prior cranioplasty

          -  Inability to undergo MRI or anticipated need for an MRI during the study period

          -  Participants with active infections or unexplained fever

          -  Participants with other morbid conditions making the implantation of the recording
             elements unsafe; not limited to: significant pulmonary, cardiovascular, metabolic, or
             renal impairments making the surgical procedure unsafe

          -  Pregnancy (confirmation through blood test)

          -  Nursing an infant, planning to become pregnant, or not using adequate birth control

          -  Corrected vision poorer than 20/100

          -  HIV or AIDS infection

          -  Existing scalp lesions or skin breakdown

          -  Chronic oral or intravenous use of steroids or immunosuppressive therapy

          -  Active cancer within the past year or requires chemotherapy

          -  Uncontrolled autonomic dysreflexia within the past 3 months

          -  Hydrocephalus with or without an implanted ventricular shunt

          -  Participants in whom it is medically contraindicated to stop anti-coagulant
             medications during surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nathan E Crone, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Neurology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nathan E Crone, MD</last_name>
    <phone>410-955-6772</phone>
    <email>ncrone@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nathan E Crone, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-6772</phone>
      <email>ncrone@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nathan E Crone, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tetraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>ALS</keyword>
  <keyword>Locked-in Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Brainstem stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Computer Interface</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Hopkins</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Quadriplegia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Stem Infarctions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

