<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03561363</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-3-2012-129</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03561363</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of 6 Weeks Saturated and Polyunsaturated High-Fat Diets on Insulin Sensitivity and Health Parameters</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of 6 Weeks Saturated and Polyunsaturated High-Fat Diets on Insulin Sensitivity and Health Parameters</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Copenhagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Copenhagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the intervention is to gain insight into the long term effect of dietary fatty
      acid quality on insulin sensitivity and health parameters in healthy men.

      Whole body and peripheral insulin sensitivity were measured, together with analyses of plasma
      hormones and metabolites. The plasma proteome was also analyzed. Molecular adaptations in
      skeletal muscle and adipose tissue were subject for investigation. Furthermore, gut
      microbiota population number and diversity will be analyzed from faeces samples obtained
      before and after the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Two experimental diets with a high fat content (65 E% fat), enriched in either saturated or
      polyunsaturated fatty acids, were provided for 6 weeks to healthy men, in a randomized
      controlled intervention study with two arms.

      Healthy, untrained, non-obese male subjects (27-45 years) were included in the study. The
      experimental diets are eucaloric, and thus provided so the subjects remains weight stable.

      Before and after the intervention, two experimental days was conducted (2 experiments before
      and 2 experiments after the intervention).

      At pre-intervention, subjects completed a high-fat meal test and insulin sensitivity was
      measured by the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp. On both days, blood and tissue biopsies
      were obtained. These two experimental days were repeated at the end of the 6 weeks
      intervention.

      The hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp was combined with stable isotope infusion (deuterium
      labelled glucose) in order to measure hepatic glucose production. Before the clamp, a
      catheter is inserted into the femoral vein, to enable measurement of insulin stimulated
      glucose uptake across the leg. Biopsies are obtained by the needle biopsy method from the
      vastus lateralis muscle and peri-umbilical subcutaneous adipose tissue. Blood samples were
      analyzed for glucose, insulin, inflammatory markers, gut hormones, adipokines, plasma fatty
      acid composition, and lipoprotein profile. Indirect calorimetric was also applied to measure
      substrate oxidation during the experimental days.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in whole body and peripheral insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>Each subject completes a hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp at pre-intervention (week 0) and again after 6 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>This outcome will be evaluated with the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp, combined with the femoral arterio-venous balance technique</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in gut microbiota population number and diversity</measure>
    <time_frame>Faeces samples are obtained from each subject at pre-intervention (week 0), and after the intervention (week 6). Analyses will be performed when the last faeces sample is obtained.</time_frame>
    <description>Gut microbiota will be analyzed in faeces samples obtained from the subjects before and after the intervention (using 18s-RNA sequencing)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in molecular adaptations in skeletal muscle and adipose tissue induced by saturated and polyunsaturated fatty acids</measure>
    <time_frame>Biopsies are obtained at pre-intervention (week 0) and at week 6 after the intervention. Analyses will be performed when the last tissue biopsies are obtained.</time_frame>
    <description>Skeletal muscle and subcutaneous adipose tissue biopsies are obtained from each subject. Specific molecular analyses (western blotting and real time-PCR) are applied to tissue samples to assess changes in relevant genes and proteins.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Insulin Sensitivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saturated high-fat diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this intervention group, subjects ingest a saturated eucaloric high-fat diet (64 E%) with total fat content being similar to the polyunsaturated high-fat diet.
The diet is enriched in saturated fat (36 E%). The main saturated fatty acids in the diet are primarily palmitic acid (C16:0) and stearic acid (C18:0). The main food sources are milk products, high-fat meat and vegetables.
Carbohydrate comprise 20 E% and protein 15 E%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>polyunsaturated high-fat diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this intervention group, subjects ingest a polyunsaturated eucaloric high-fat diet (64 E%), with total fat content being similar to the saturated high-fat diet. The diet is enriched in polyunsaturated fat (32 E%). The main polyunsaturated fatty acids in the diet are primarily linoleic acid (C18:2 n-6) and alpha-linoleic acid (C18:3 n-3). The main food sources are vegetable oils, nuts and high-fat fish (e.g. salmon). Carbohydrate comprise 20 E% and protein 15 E%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High-fat diet</intervention_name>
    <description>The aim of the intervention is to evaluate whether insulin sensitivity and selected Health parameters is affected, when the intake of saturated fatty acids or polyunsaturated fatty acids are highly increased, even when subjects are in energy balance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saturated high-fat diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>polyunsaturated high-fat diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  healthy male subjects

          -  27-45 years

          -  BMI 22-31

          -  maximal oxygen uptake &lt;48 ml/kg/min

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  smokers

          -  use of medication

          -  parents with type-2 diabetes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>27 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bente Kiens, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dept. of Nutrition, Exercise and Sports, University of Copenhagen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vessby B, Uusitupa M, Hermansen K, Riccardi G, Rivellese AA, Tapsell LC, Nälsén C, Berglund L, Louheranta A, Rasmussen BM, Calvert GD, Maffetone A, Pedersen E, Gustafsson IB, Storlien LH; KANWU Study. Substituting dietary saturated for monounsaturated fat impairs insulin sensitivity in healthy men and women: The KANWU Study. Diabetologia. 2001 Mar;44(3):312-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11317662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Copenhagen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Annemarie Lundsgaard</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PostDoc. and principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>insulin sensitivity</keyword>
  <keyword>high-fat diet</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

