<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03563443</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CH-urology-bladder marker-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03563443</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genomic Imprinting Testing for Diagnosis of Bladder Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Genomic Imprinting Testing for Detection and Surveillance of Bladder Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Changhai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>LiSen imprinting diagnostic (LSID) Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Changhai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Urine analysis provide a promising non-invasive liquid biopsy for diagnosis of bladder
      cancer. Molecular biomarkers in urine may serve as important diagnostic and prognostic
      indicators for bladder cancer. Many alterations of genes and proteins have been identified in
      the urinary for diagnosis of bladder cancer. However, not all bladder cancer patients have
      the same alterations due to tumor heterogeneity. Thus, to reach satisfactory sensitivity and
      specificity a new diagnostic molecular alteration should exists ubiquitously in cancers.
      Numerous studies indicate that Loss of imprinting (LOI) exists ubiquitously in cancers and
      precede morphological changes. The investigators will conduct a prospective evaluation of a
      panel of LOI changes in urine test for detection and surveillance of bladder cancer patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the progression of tumor, molecular changes in both genomics and epigenomics occur
      prior to morphological changes in cells and tissues, therefore molecular biological test is
      more sensitive to detect cancer at early stage. Genomic imprinting is one kind of epigenetic
      regulation that controls gene expression. In detail, a copy of gene on the certain maternal
      or paternal allele is silenced through methylation, while the other acts normally. This kind
      of genes are named imprinting genes. Loss of imprinting and Copy number variation (LOI &amp; CNV)
      is epigenetic change that the silenced copy of an imprinting gene is activated through
      demethylation. Numerous studies indicate that LOI exists ubiquitously in cancers and precede
      morphological changes. In contrast, LOI rarely happens in normal somatic cells. Therefore,
      the methylation status of imprinting genes can act as a biomarker to detect and analyze the
      abnormal cells.

      The investigators will develop a couple of common LOI to establish a predictive diagnostic
      LOI panel in urine with optimal and robust efficacy in diagnosis of bladder cancer by
      analyzing LOI in urine from bladder cancer patients and control group that without any tumor
      in urinary system or other organs. Moreover, the changes of LOI in urine collected before and
      1 year after transurethral resection of non-muscle invasive bladder cancer (NIMBC) will also
      be monitored. External consistency validation will be performed on subsequent urine from
      patients and control participants collection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of urinalysis by LOI urine analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>In the middle of the study, an average of 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared positive&quot; with the LOI urine test among the patients suffered from bladder cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of urinalysis by LOI urine analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>In the middle of the study, an average of 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared negative&quot; with the LOI urine test among the patients who are without cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of sensitivity of urinalysis by LOI urine analysis to predict the recurrence of bladder cancer within 1 year after transurethral resection of NMIBC</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared positive&quot; with the LOI urine test after bladder cancer surgery among the patients being confirmed to have bladder cancer by cystoscopic examination and biopsy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of specificity of urinalysis by LOI urine analysis to predict the free of bladder cancer recurrence within 1 year after transurethral resection of NMIBC</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared negative&quot; with the LOI urine test after bladder cancer surgery among the patients being confirmed to have no bladder cancer recurrence by cystoscopic examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the sensitivity of the urine LOI analysis versus urine cytology</measure>
    <time_frame>In the middle of the study, an average of 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared positive&quot; with the LOI analysis versus patients &quot;declared positive&quot; with the urine cytology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the specificity of the urine LOI analysis versus urine cytology</measure>
    <time_frame>In the middle of the study, an average of 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients &quot;declared negative&quot; with the LOI analysis versus patients &quot; declared negative &quot; with the urine cytology</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Urine Marking</condition>
  <condition>Diagnoses Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bladder cancer patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Diagnosed bladder cancer patients who are being monitored will be the experimental group to develop the LOI panel, and subsequent cohort will be used to confirm the sensitivity and specificity of this urinary analysis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-cancer participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients being treated for other diseases but without any tumor or healthy participants will provide a negative control to provide data for developing the LOI diagnostic panel</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genomic Imprinting Testing</intervention_name>
    <description>The changes of LOI The obtained LOI from morning urine and tumor will be tested by LiSen imprinting diagnostic (LSID)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bladder cancer patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non-cancer participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Loss of imprinting and Copy number variation (LOI &amp; CNV) is epigenetic change that the
      silenced copy of an imprinting gene is activated through demethylation. Numerous studies
      indicate that LOI exists ubiquitously in cancers and precede morphological changes. In
      contrast, LOI rarely happens in normal somatic cells. Therefore, the methylation status of
      imprinting genes can act as a biomarker to detect and analyze the abnormal cast-off cells in
      urine.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients diagnosed with bladder cancer or participants in control group in Changhai
        Hospital from December 2017 till the end of this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - 1. Patients diagnosed with of bladder cancer by cystoscopy and biopsy. 2. Participants
        without any tumor disease and willing to attend the study by providing morning urine.

        3. Moring urine and available tumor tissue obtained by biopsy. 4. Male or female patients
        aged &gt;= 18 years. 5. Participants signed informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - 1. Age under 18 years 2. Individuals unwilling to sign the IRB-approved consent form and
        unwilling to follow the protocol to submit the serial urine for test after surgery 3.
        Comorbidities that will prohibit or make serial urine collection and cystoscopic
        examination difficult or impossible during follow up.

        4. Prior diagnosis of cancer except bladder cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chuangliang Xu, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Changhai Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shuxiong Zeng, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+86 18930568759</phone>
    <email>zengshuxiong@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Changhai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200433</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chuanliang Xu, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18930568759</phone>
      <email>drxuchuanliang@126.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yinghao Sun, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
      <email>sunyhsmmu@126.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jelinic P, Shaw P. Loss of imprinting and cancer. J Pathol. 2007 Feb;211(3):261-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17177177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haig D. Maternal-fetal conflict, genomic imprinting and mammalian vulnerabilities to cancer. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2015 Jul 19;370(1673). pii: 20140178. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2014.0178. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26056362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uribe-Lewis S, Woodfine K, Stojic L, Murrell A. Molecular mechanisms of genomic imprinting and clinical implications for cancer. Expert Rev Mol Med. 2011 Jan 25;13:e2. doi: 10.1017/S1462399410001717. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21262060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jirtle RL. Genomic imprinting and cancer. Exp Cell Res. 1999 Apr 10;248(1):18-24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10094809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Changhai Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zeng Shuxiong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D., Ph.D</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bladder Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Genomic imprinting</keyword>
  <keyword>Urine biomarker</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Surveillance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

