<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03562793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 17-032</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1712397218</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03562793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Communication and Activation in Pain to Enhance Relationships and Treat Pain With Equity</brief_title>
  <acronym>COOPERATE</acronym>
  <official_title>Communication and Activation in Pain to Enhance Relationships and Treat Pain With Equity (COOPERATE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chronic pain affects approximately 100 million Americans and 40-70% of Veterans, and amounts
      to over $600 billion/year in direct medical costs and lost worker productivity. Racial
      disparities in pain care are well-documented, within and outside VA. Minorities are more
      likely to be undertreated for pain, are subjected to more urine drug tests, and are referred
      for substance abuse evaluation more frequently than Whites. Minority patients also exhibit
      lower levels of engagement and active involvement in their healthcare, which leads to poorer
      communication with providers and poorer outcomes. COOPERATE is a randomized controlled trial
      testing an intervention to improve minority Veterans' active participation in their pain care
      by focusing on 2 essential skill sets: 1) goal-setting and prioritization, and 2)
      communication skills.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Chronic pain affects 40-70% of Veterans and amounts to over $600 billion/year in
      direct medical costs and lost worker productivity. Racial disparities in pain treatment have
      been extensively documented. Minority patients, including Veterans, are more likely to be
      undertreated for pain. Minority Veterans have pain documented less frequently, undergo more
      urine drug tests, and are more likely to be referred for substance abuse evaluation than
      White Veterans. Compounding these pain care disparities, minority Veterans exhibit lower
      levels of patient activation than Whites. Patient activation-having knowledge, confidence,
      and skills to manage health-is associated with better health experiences, self-management,
      and outcomes. Low activation is frequently manifested in poorer communication among minority
      patients. Minority patients are less likely to share their concerns with providers, ask
      questions, and prepare for their clinic visits. This poor communication is associated with
      lower quality care, poorer patient-provider relationships, and treatment non-adherence. The
      poorer communication experienced by minorities is exacerbated by the documented difficulties
      in patient-provider communication about chronic pain and its treatment-particularly where
      opioids are concerned.

      Objectives: COOPERATE (Communication and Activation in Pain to Enhance Relationships and
      Treat Pain with Equity) is a pragmatic randomized controlled trial of an intervention to
      improve patient activation and communication with providers for minority Veterans with
      chronic pain. COOPERATE focuses on 2 essential skill sets necessary to facilitate effective
      patient activation: 1) goal-setting and prioritization, and 2) communication skills.
      COOPERATE is delivered over the telephone in 6 sessions (4 weekly sessions followed by 2
      booster session) over a period of 12 weeks. The primary study outcome is patient activation.

      Methods: COOPERATE is a Hybrid Type 1 study, designed to test effectiveness while also
      examining implementation facilitators and barriers. COOPERATE will enroll 250 minority
      Veterans with chronic musculoskeletal pain from primary care clinics. Veterans will be
      randomized either to the COOPERATE intervention or to an attention control arm. For Aim 1 the
      investigators will test the effects of COOPERATE at 3 (primary end point), 6, and 9 months
      (sustained effects) on patient activation (primary outcome), communication self-efficacy,
      pain intensity and interference, and psychological functioning. In Aim 2, the
      pre-implementation aim, the investigators will use qualitative methods to understand
      facilitators and barriers to implementing COOPERATE. Guided by the RE-AIM framework, the
      investigators will interview a purposefully selected subsample of intervention Veterans, and
      clinicians from primary care and the chronic pain clinic, to better prepare for COOPERATE's
      implementation. Aim 3 is an exploratory aim to determine the effects of COOPERATE on
      important relational indicators of high-quality care: working alliance (with providers), and
      perceived discrimination in healthcare.

      Innovation: COOPERATE focuses on two important, yet frequently neglected, areas for
      improvement in minority health: patient activation and communication. This is especially
      important in chronic pain care, since numerous treatment options with a wide range of risks
      and benefits exist, and since minorities are offered fewer of these pain treatment options.
      Helping minority Veterans to become more active in their care is critical for improving
      chronic pain care. This is especially important in light of VA efforts such as the Opioid
      Safety Initiative, designed to improve safety for Veterans, but which also require engaged,
      active patients as Veterans must explore alternative pain treatments with their
      providers-treatments that are feasible for Veterans' individual lifestyles and consistent
      with their symptom priorities and treatment goals.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial with behavioral intervention.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Assessors will be blinded to treatment assignment when administering baseline outcome assessments.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Activation Measure (PAM). Construct: self-management self-efficacy (i.e., patient activation). 13-item patient activation measure assesses patient knowledge, skill, and confidence for self-management. Range 0 (lowest activation) - 100 (highest activation). Higher values are better outcomes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Communication Self-Efficacy (Perceived Efficacy in Patient-Physician Interactions--PEPPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Perceived Efficacy in Patient-Physician Interactions (PEPPI-5). Construct: patients' self-efficacy in obtaining medical info and getting most important concerns discussed with their doctors. Range 0 (lowest) - 50 (highest). Higher values are better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Intensity and Interference (Brief Pain Inventory)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Brief Pain Inventory (BPI). Construct: Pain Intensity and Interference. 11-item measure that assesses pain intensity and interference with activity. The Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) assesses two key domains-intensity and interference-recommended for pain studies and has been validated in primary care. The BPI is the average of pain intensity and pain interference scores. The pain intensity score is an average of 4 ratings of 0 (no pain) to 10 (pain as bad as you can imagine) for current, least, worst, and average pain in the past week. The pain interference score averages seven ratings, 0 (does not interfere) to 10 (interferes completely), of interference with general activity, mood, walking ability, normal work, relations with other people, sleep, and enjoyment of life. Lower scores are better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression (PHQ8)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ)-8. Construct: Depression. Validated 8-item measure assessing depression severity. Range 0 - 24. Lower scores are better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>GAD 7. Construct: Anxiety. Validated 7-item measure to assess anxiety. Range 0 - 21. Lower scores are better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Coping</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Coping Strategies Questionnaire. Construct: Pain coping. A 14-item measure of pain coping strategies. Range 0-84. Lower scores are better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Covariate--Working alliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Working Alliance Inventory (WAI). Construct: Patient-Provider Therapeutic Alliance--patient-provider agreement on treatment goals, collaboration, and mutual trust/liking. Range: 12-84. Higher scores are better outcomes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Covariate--patient-provider gender and race concordance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure race and gender concordance between patients and their primary care providers. This is not a scale.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Covariate--length of patient-provider relationship</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will ask patients how long they have been seeing their primary care provider. This is not a scale but a continuous measure of length of relationship.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">250</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COOPERATE Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention patients will focus on 1) goal clarification/prioritization; 2) communication skills. There are 6 total sessions delivered individually over 12 weeks: 4 sessions teaching skills (30 min each) and 2 booster sessions delivered once/month for the next 2 months. Intervention will be delivered by telephone.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Attention Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Veterans randomized to the control group will receive phone calls on the same schedule as intervention Veterans. During these phone calls, study staff will ask Veterans a series of questions about their pain, self-management activities, and any changes they have experienced since the last call. These phone calls are designed to control for attention only, and Veterans will not be offered specific information or advice about their pain or its management (with the exception of suggesting a doctor visit if warranted).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Communication and Activation in Pain to Enhance Relationships and Treat Pain with Equity (COOPERATE)</intervention_name>
    <description>. COOPERATE seeks to improve patient activation in minority Veterans with chronic pain by focusing on two major skill sets: 1) goal clarification and prioritization, and 2) communication skills (Table 1). By understanding, clarifying, and prioritizing goals, and having the skills to communicate their goals, priorities, and preferences to providers, Veterans will gain knowledge, confidence, and skills to be actively involved in managing their chronic pain. The intervention consists of 6 total sessions delivered individually over 12 weeks: 4 sessions focused on teaching skills related to goal clarification/prioritization and communication (30-minutes each), delivered weekly for the first 4 weeks, plus 2 booster sessions (20-25 minutes each) delivered once per month for the next 2 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>COOPERATE Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>COOPERATE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Black or African American Veteran

          -  Have musculoskeletal pain in the low back, cervical spine, or extremities (hip, knee,
             shoulder) for 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients will be excluded if electronic medical records indicate:

          -  a psychotic disorder diagnosis

          -  current substance use disorder

          -  severe medical conditions precluding participation (e.g., NY Heart Association Class
             III or IV heart failure), or if the eligibility
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marianne Sassi Matthias, PhD MS BA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Weiner, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(317) 988-2952</phone>
    <email>Michael.Weiner4@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Suthat Liangpunsakul, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(317) 988-2427</phone>
    <email>Suthat.Liangpunsakul@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Richard L. Roudebush VA Medical Center, Indianapolis, IN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202-2884</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Angela L Rollins, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(317) 988-4789</phone>
      <email>Angela.Rollins@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Linda A Collins, BS CRA</last_name>
      <phone>(317) 988-2722</phone>
      <email>linda.collins4@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam T Hirsh, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johanne Eliacin, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kevin L Rand, PhD MA</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marianne Sassi Matthias, PhD MS BA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Matthew J. Bair, MD MS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michelle P Salyers, MS PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>healthcare disparities</keyword>
  <keyword>communication</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

