<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03563807</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2018P000394</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03563807</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Golf Instruction Versus Tai Chi for People With Parkinson's Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility and Tolerability of Group Golf Instruction Versus Tai Chi for Patients With Moderate to Advanced Parkinson's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility and tolerability of golf
      instruction for participants with moderate to advanced Parkinson's disease (PD). Other forms
      of exercise have been shown to be beneficial for PD. Golf is a low impact sport that utilizes
      balance and strength. Currently, there are no data looking at the effects of golf on PD. This
      pilot study aims to test the effects of golf in the PD patient population, particularly its
      effect on balance. In this study, we will be comparing group golf instruction to group Tai
      Chi lessons (the gold standard balance exercise for patients with PD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately, 40-50 participants with Parkinson's Disease (H&amp;Y stage 2 to 3) will be
      enrolled in this study. Participants who provide informed consent will be randomized 1:1 to
      either group golf instruction or group Tai Chi classes. Participants will be evaluated before
      and after the intervention with a battery of cognitive, motor and balance assessments
      including the UPDRS, the Mini-BESTest of balance, and timed up and go tests. They will
      participate in classes twice weekly for 10 weeks which will be provided free of charge. At
      the end of the intervention period they will repeat the assessments. The primary outcomes of
      the study are feasibility and tolerability. The key secondary objectives are to measure the
      efficacy of golf instruction on measures of balance, risk of falls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A blinded rater will perform the Mini-BESTest of balance before and after the intervention</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of group golf instruction compared to Tai Chi</measure>
    <time_frame>Both interventions will continue for 10 weeks and subject participation rates will be recorded during this time.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who complete 10 weeks in the study will be measured using weekly attendance sheets. We will consider the intervention to be tolerable if the proportion of participants who withdraw consent prior to the end of the study is less than 40% with 80% confidence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of group golf instruction compared to Tai Chi</measure>
    <time_frame>Both interventions will continue for 10 weeks and any adverse events will be recorded during this time.</time_frame>
    <description>The frequency of treatment-related adverse events including falls will be summarized by treatment group and system organ class by CTCAE v 4.0</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Key Secondary objectives are to measure the efficacy of golf instruction compared to Tai Chi on measures of balance.</measure>
    <time_frame>Both interventions will continue for 10 weeks. The Mini-BESTest will be performed by a blinded rater before and after the intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>The Mini-BESTest will be used to measure balance before and after the intervention. The Mini-BESTest is scored from 0-28 where lower scores are better.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activities Specific Balance Confidence Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Both interventions will continue for 10 weeks. Participants will complete the questionnaire before and after the intervention period.</time_frame>
    <description>This is a self-reported measure of confidence in performing various ambulatory activities without falling. The scale is out of 100</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson Disease</condition>
  <condition>Movement Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Neuro-Degenerative Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Golf</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group golf lessons will be led by professional golf instructors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tai Chi</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group Tai Chi classes led by a certified Tai Chi instructor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Golf Instruction</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will participate in two weekly hour-long golf classes. Classes will be led by professional golf instructors that will work with individuals to teach participants how to play golf. This will include stretching, individual coaching, and working with participants to maximize their golf swing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Golf</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tai Chi Class</intervention_name>
    <description>Tai Chi is an ancient martial art that uses meditative movement to improve strength, flexibility, and balance. Subjects will participate in two weekly hour-long Tai Chi classes.The class will be led by a certified Tai Chi instructor and consist of approximately 12 people.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tai Chi</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult participants with a diagnosis of Parkinson's disease by a Movement Disorders
             specialist, H&amp;Y stage II-III in the &quot;On&quot; state treated with Parkinson's disease
             medications

          -  Participants must be capable of providing informed consent and complying with trial
             procedures including transportation to and from classes.

          -  Participants must be willing and able to participate in group exercise classes.

          -  Participants who are engaged in physical therapy or other exercise programs must be at
             a stable regimen for 60 days prior to the start of the study and must be willing to
             maintain their current regimen for the duration of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical evidence of unstable medical or psychiatric illness which would prevent them
             from engaging in exercise

          -  Participants who are already active golfers or currently active in Tai Chi would be
             excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mak MK, Wong-Yu IS, Shen X, Chung CL. Long-term effects of exercise and physical therapy in people with Parkinson disease. Nat Rev Neurol. 2017 Nov;13(11):689-703. doi: 10.1038/nrneurol.2017.128. Epub 2017 Oct 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29027544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li F, Harmer P, Fitzgerald K, Eckstrom E, Stock R, Galver J, Maddalozzo G, Batya SS. Tai chi and postural stability in patients with Parkinson's disease. N Engl J Med. 2012 Feb 9;366(6):511-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1107911.</citation>
    <PMID>22316445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gao KL, Hui-Chan CW, Tsang WW. Golfers have better balance control and confidence than healthy controls. Eur J Appl Physiol. 2011 Nov;111(11):2805-12. doi: 10.1007/s00421-011-1910-7. Epub 2011 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21416145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 8, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anne-Marie Alexandra Wills, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurodegenerative Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

