<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03563976</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU 122014-052</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03563976</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multiparametric Image Analysis and Correlation With Outcomes in Lung Cancer Screening and Early Stage Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multi Parametric Image Analysis and Correlation With Outcomes in Lung Cancer Screening and Early Stage Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Determine whether CT-based multiparametric analytical models may improve prediction of biopsy
      and treatment outcome in patients undergoing screening CT scan and/or treatment for early
      stage lung cancer
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The hypothesis is that multiparametric models that incorporate complex image information from
      screening CT scans will improve prediction of the outcome of subsequent lung biopsy, an
      invasive diagnostic procedure. In this project, we will construct an image feature-based
      multiparametric prognostic model for biopsy outcome from screening lung CT scans performed at
      our institution, and then validate it using theNLST imaging and clinical outcomes dataset.

      This study involves no treatment or invasive procedures. Investigator will review all charts
      of patients who were treated for early stage lung cancer with definitive radiation therapy at
      UTSW or Parkland Memorial hospital, diagnosed with a malignancy from January 1, 2004 to
      October 31, 2014, to compile demographic, diagnostic, therapeutic, outcome, and toxicity
      data. Investigator expect that this will include approximately 200 patient charts. This data
      will be analyzed statistically and used for future directed research. Investigator will also
      analyze an anonymized dataset of patients from the National Lung Cancer Screening Trial
      (NLST) provided by the National Cancer Institute (NCI)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 18, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 20, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>POTENTIAL BENEFITS:</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical Analyses will be performed for all subjects having received at least one fraction of radiation.The study will use the CTCAE version 4.0 for reporting of acute and late adverse events related to Lung will be reported by the physician through exam/assessment during research visit, encompassing events since last research visit. Research will collect and log lung related events for up to 10 years. Information gained from this study could lead to improved medical care for similar patients in the future.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Retrospective Study</intervention_name>
    <description>The medical charts are the subjects. The institutional charts will be identified by the use of definitive radiation therapy correlating with an early stage lung cancer diagnosis during the above time frame. The data from these charts will be entered into a password protected excel spreadsheet. The charts will be identified by name, medical record number, date of birth, and social security number. These are all patients treated by all hospitals and clinics affiliated with UTSW and Parkland. At the time of study, some of the patients will have expired but some will be alive and in the regional North Texas area. Thus, given the minimal risk nature of this retrospective chart review, we could not reasonably conduct this research with a full waiver of consent. The NLST external dataset is proved by the NCI, with no identifying characteristics.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Risk will be minimized by protecting patient data through the use of de-identification of
        patient identifiers and password protected data collection. The information will be given
        only to faculty members and statisticians involved in the research project. The information
        will include the parameters attached in the spreadsheet supplied with the IRB submission.
        The data will be disclosed only for analytical purposes.

        Confidentiality will be maintained by adhering to HIPAA guidelines. The location of the
        data will be maintained at the worksite of the PI and the research coordinator in the
        Moncrief Radiation Oncology Department on the North Campus at UTSW. Risks will be minimized
        by protecting patient data and using it only for research purposes for retrospective
        analysis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1) Patients that have been diagnosed with lung cancer, and are treated at Department of
        Radiation Oncology, UTSW.

        2Patients are greater than 18 years of age.

        3)Patients understand a written informed consent document and are willing to sign the
        consent form.

        4)The tumor must be ineligible for definitive surgical resection.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women who are pregnant or trying to get pregnant

          2. Children (under age of 18)

          3. The tumor must be ineligible for stereotactic body radiation therapy.

          4. Chemotherapy given within one week of study registration.

          5. Evidence of small cell histology.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UT Southwestern Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 25, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Early Stage Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

