<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03564132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CMUH106-REC2-148</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03564132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of Yi-Gan San in Children and Adolescents With Tourette's Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of Yi-Gan San in Children and Adolescents With Tourette's Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>China Medical University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>China Medical University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Yigansan was used in Ming dynasty by Xue Kai as a remedy for restlessness and agitation in
      children. We expect that the total YGTSS scores of Yigansan-treated subjects will be
      significantly reduced compared to that of placebo-treated subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tourette's disorder (TD) is a chronic, childhood-onset neuropsychiatric disorder. It is
      characterized by multiple motor and vocal tics, including involuntary or semivoluntary,
      sudden, brief, intermittent, repetitive movements or sounds. Yigansan was used in several
      clinical trials, like dementia, pervasive developmental disorder, schizophrenia and
      Huntington's disease, with good results. So the investigators choose Yigansan as a Chinese
      medicine formula in this study. After the participants signed the consent form, they have to
      stop taking any Chinese medicine or western medicine for treating Tourette's disorder for two
      weeks and then are randomly assigned to Yigansan group or placebo group. Our hypothesis is
      that Yigansan will be expected to improve motor tics and vocal tics, and YGTSS scores will
      decrease after 4-weeks treatments; secondary outcomes are measured by CGI-TS (Clinical Global
      Impression-Tourette Syndrome) scale and GTS-QOL (The Gilles de la Tourette syndrome-quality
      of life scale), and the investigators will also proceed the basic research of metabolomics
      and biochemistry(GOT、GPT、BUN、Creatinine、K+). In order to ensure the relationship of
      Tourette's disorder and allergic rhinitis, the investigators will detect IgE. Besides, the
      investigators will collect blood and urine from every child or adolescent when a participant
      visits our clinic at week 0 and week 4. In order to find these biomarkers related to TD, the
      investigators will use ELISA kits to detect and quantitate significantly changeable
      concentration of cytokines associated with YGTSS scores. In addition to specific cytokine
      targets, the investigators will also find these metabolites involved in TD between two groups
      before and after taking YGS. The serum and urine samples will be prepared and subjected to
      LC-MS/MS analysis. In summary of the experimental designs and expected results, the therapy
      and background information will be more clarified on the therapeutic efficacy and safety by
      Yigansan treatment for TD. Most importantly, this study will provide a kind of Chinese
      medicine formula to relieve such a disorder that most doctors feel difficult to treat.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline to Week 4 in Yale Global Tic Severity Scale (YGTSS) total tic score (TTS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week4</time_frame>
    <description>Ratings are 5 different dimensions on a scale of 0 to 5 for motor and vocal tics each, including number, frequency, intensity, complexity, and interference. The scores of TTS are from 0 to 50 and the scores of impairment are also from 0 to 50. Summation of TTS and impairment are YGTSS scores which will be the primary outcome measure in this trial.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Clinical Global Impressions Scale-Tourette's Syndrome (CGI-TS) Score at Week 4</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Response choices included: 0 = not assessed; 1 = normal, not at all ill; 2 = borderline mentally ill; 3 = mildly ill; 4 = moderately ill; 5 = markedly ill; 6 = severely ill; and 7 = among the most extremely ill patients. The change score was obtained from CGI-TS improvement scale assessment: 0 = not assessed, 1 = very much improved, 2 = much improved, 3 = minimally improved, 4 = no change, 5 = minimally worse, 6 = much worse, and 7 = very much worse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to Endpoint (Week 4) in Total YGTSS Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The YGTSS is used to rate the severity of symptoms (on a scale of 0 to 5 for 5 different dimensions, including number, frequency, intensity, complexity, and interference) of motor and vocal tics, and an impairment ranking. The Total YGTSS score is the summation of the severity scores of motor and vocal tics and also the ranking of impairment (range of 0 to 100).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical response is defined as &gt; 25% improvement from baseline to Week 4 in YGTSS TTS between 2 groups or a CGI-TS Change score of 1 [very much improved] or 2 [much improved] at Week 4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">154</enrollment>
  <condition>Tourette Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Tic Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yigansan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>2.5g of Yigansan granules by mouth, three times a day for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2.5g of Placebo(contained one-tenth Yigansan) granules by mouth, three times a day for 4 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yigansan</intervention_name>
    <description>Yigansan granules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yigansan</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YGS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>One-tenth concentration of Yigansan manufactured to mimic Yigansan granules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo (for Yigansan)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is a male or female child or adolescent, 6 to 17 years of age (inclusive)
             at the time of signing the informed consent/assent.

          2. The subject meets current DSM-V diagnostic criteria for Tourette's Disorder.

          3. The subject has a total score of ≥ 20 on the YGTSS at Screening and Baseline
             (randomization).

          4. Tic symptoms may cause impairment in the subject's normal routines, which include
             academic achievement, occupational functioning, social activities, and/or
             relationships.

          5. Females of childbearing potential (defined by menarche and not having undergone
             surgical sterilization/hysterectomy) must have a negative urine pregnancy test (when
             visiting our clinic at week 0 and week 4).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject presents with a clinical presentation and/or history that is consistent
             with another neurologic condition that may have accompanying abnormal movements. These
             include, but are not limited to:

             Transient Tic disorder/ Huntington's disease/ Parkinson's disease/ Sydenham's chorea/
             Wilson's disease/ Mental retardation/ Pervasive developmental disorder/ Traumatic
             brain injury/ Stroke/ Restless Legs Syndrome

          2. The subject has a history of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, or other psychotic
             disorder.

          3. Subjects who receive psychostimulants for the treatment of ADD/ADHD and who have
             developed and/or had exacerbations of the tic disorder after the initiation of
             stimulant treatment.

          4. Subjects who ever participated in any Chinese medicine or western medicine trial
             within 30 days.

          5. Subjects requiring cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) for Tourette's Disorder during
             the trial period.

          6. The inability to swallow Chinese herbal medicine.

          7. Female subjects who have been pregnant.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cheng-Hao Huang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>China Medical University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cheng-Hao Huang</last_name>
    <phone>886-4-22052121</phone>
    <phone_ext>1391</phone_ext>
    <email>d12628@mail.cmuh.org.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>404</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheng-Hao Huang, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>886-4-22052121</phone>
      <phone_ext>1391</phone_ext>
      <email>d12628@mail.cmuh.org.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>I-Ching Chou</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ching-Liang Hsieh</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ming-Yu Wang</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Der-Yen Lee</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jankovic J. Tourette's syndrome. N Engl J Med. 2001 Oct 18;345(16):1184-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11642235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen SC, Leckman JF, Bloch MH. Clinical assessment of Tourette syndrome and tic disorders. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 2013 Jul;37(6):997-1007. doi: 10.1016/j.neubiorev.2012.11.013. Epub 2012 Dec 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23206664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang S, Qi F, Li J, Zhao L, Li A. Effects of Chinese herbal medicine Ningdong granule on regulating dopamine (DA)/serotonin (5-TH) and gamma-amino butyric acid (GABA) in patients with Tourette syndrome. Biosci Trends. 2012 Aug;6(4):212-8.</citation>
    <PMID>23006968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhao L, Li AY, Lv H, Liu FY, Qi FH. Traditional Chinese medicine Ningdong granule: the beneficial effects in Tourette's disorder. J Int Med Res. 2010 Jan-Feb;38(1):169-75.</citation>
    <PMID>20233526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim YH, Son CG, Ku BC, Lee HW, Lim HS, Lee MS. Herbal medicines for treating tic disorders: a systematic review of randomised controlled trials. Chin Med. 2014 Feb 7;9(1):6. doi: 10.1186/1749-8546-9-6.</citation>
    <PMID>24507013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu M, Xiao GH, Zhang JM, Zhang X, Ma B, Wang SX, Zhou YB, Zhang JY. Clinical research into Qufeng Zhidong Recipe used to treat 31 children with tic disorder. J Tradit Chin Med. 2010 Sep;30(3):163-70.</citation>
    <PMID>21053620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chou IC, Lin HC, Lin CC, Sung FC, Kao CH. Tourette syndrome and risk of depression: a population-based cohort study in Taiwan. J Dev Behav Pediatr. 2013 Apr;34(3):181-5. doi: 10.1097/DBP.0b013e3182829f2b.</citation>
    <PMID>23572168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zheng Y, Zhang ZJ, Han XM, Ding Y, Chen YY, Wang XF, Wei XW, Wang MJ, Cheng Y, Nie ZH, Zhao M, Zheng XX. A proprietary herbal medicine (5-Ling Granule) for Tourette syndrome: a randomized controlled trial. J Child Psychol Psychiatry. 2016 Jan;57(1):74-83. doi: 10.1111/jcpp.12432. Epub 2015 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26072932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eddy CM, Rickards HE, Cavanna AE. Treatment strategies for tics in Tourette syndrome. Ther Adv Neurol Disord. 2011 Jan;4(1):25-45. doi: 10.1177/1756285610390261.</citation>
    <PMID>21339906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takeyoshi K, Kurita M, Nishino S, Teranishi M, Numata Y, Sato T, Okubo Y. Yokukansan improves behavioral and psychological symptoms of dementia by suppressing dopaminergic function. Neuropsychiatr Dis Treat. 2016 Mar 15;12:641-9. doi: 10.2147/NDT.S99032. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27042075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyaoka T, Furuya M, Horiguchi J, Wake R, Hashioka S, Thoyama M, Murotani K, Mori N, Minabe Y, Iyo M, Ueno S, Ezoe S, Hoshino S, Seno H. Efficacy and safety of yokukansan in treatment-resistant schizophrenia: a randomized, multicenter, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2015;2015:201592. doi: 10.1155/2015/201592. Epub 2015 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25954314</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyaoka T, Furuya M, Horiguchi J, Wake R, Hashioka S, Tohyama M, Mori N, Minabe Y, Iyo M, Ueno S, Ezoe S, Murotani K, Hoshino S, Seno H. Efficacy and safety of yokukansan in treatment-resistant schizophrenia: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial (a Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale, five-factor analysis). Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2015 Jan;232(1):155-64. doi: 10.1007/s00213-014-3645-8. Epub 2014 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24923986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Yigansan</keyword>
  <keyword>YGTSS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tourette Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

