<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03567252</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>44215</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P42ES007380</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03567252</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tanglewood to Table: A Walking Farmer's Market Group and Control</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tanglewood to Table: A Walking Farmer's Market Group and Control</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dawn Brewer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Kentucky</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This program encourages community members to walk approximately 1 mile to the Whitesburg
      Farmers Market each Thursday or Saturday. The study aims to determine if walking to the
      market to receive vouchers improve health outcomes beyond controls who receive nutrition
      education.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the summer of 2018, community members of Whitesburg, Kentucky (KY) were recruited to join
      the Tanglewood to Table walking program, and community members of Harlan, KY were invited to
      serve as controls. Each Thursday or Saturday, participants report whether or not they walked
      the 1 mile trail to the farmers market, how many steps the walked in the previous 7 days and
      they reported which fruits and vegetables they consumed the previous week. The control group
      will receive nutrition education handouts. The program is from June 2018 - January 2019.
      Participants complete questionnaires about fruit and vegetable consumption and physical
      activity. Participants also provided physical and biological measurements. Recruiting for the
      2018 Walking Program will begin in May.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 21, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 21, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be compared between walking and non-walking groups to assess dietary behavior.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fruit Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey indicating the total servings of fruit consumed (possible answers range from 1 serving in 3 months to 3 servings per day). Survey will be measured at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months. Data will be presented as average servings of fruit per group over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vegetable Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey indicating the total servings of vegetables consumed (possible answers range from 1 serving in 3 months to 3 servings per day). Survey will be measured at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months. Data will be presented as average servings of vegetables per group over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in understanding of plant-based nutrients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked a question demonstrating their understanding of the importance of ingesting plant-based nutrients at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are yes, no, or not sure. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that understood the importance of plant-based nutrients over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in believing in the benefits of plant-based nutrients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked a question demonstrating their appreciation of plant-based nutrients at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are yes, no, or not sure. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that understood the importance of plant-based nutrients over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in believing in the preventative effects of plant-based nutrients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked a question demonstrating their beliefs of plant-based nutrients at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are yes, no, or not sure. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that understood the importance of plant-based nutrients over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in believing in the role of a healthy diet in protecting health from pollutants</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked a question demonstrating their beliefs that a healthy diet might protect health from environmental pollutants at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are yes, no, or not sure. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that understood the importance of a healthy diet over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge of which foods contain phytonutrients</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked a question about which foods contain phytonutrients at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are meat, dairy, plant foods, all foods, or don't know. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that correctly identified plant foods over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in knowledge of environmental pollutants</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to identify environmental pollutants from a list at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months into the study. Possible answers are polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), mercury, nitrites, all of those, none of those, or don't know. Data will be presented as the percent of participants in each group that correctly identified all of those over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in days of vigorous exercise in the last week</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked a number of days of the last 7 days that they participating in vigorous activity including the following: heavy lifting, digging, aerobics, or fast bicycling or other. Data will be presented as the average number of days of vigorous activity compared between groups over time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in days of moderate exercise in the last week</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked a number of days of the last 7 days that they participating in moderate activity including the following: light lifting, bicycling or other. Data will be presented as the average number of days of moderate activity compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in time spent in vigorous exercise in the last week</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked how much time in hours and minutes over the last 7 days that they participated in vigorous activity including the following: heavy lifting, digging, aerobics, or fast bicycling or other. Data will be presented as the average number of minutes or hours of vigorous activity compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in time spent in moderate exercise in the last week</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked how much time in hours and minutes over the last 7 days that they participated in moderate activity including the following: lifting, bicycling or other. Data will be presented as the average number of minutes or hours of moderate activity compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in time spent walking</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked how many days over the last 7 days that they walked for at least 10 minutes. Data will be presented as the average number of minutes or hours of walking per day compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in time spent sitting</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months where they will be asked how many days over the last 7 days that they spent sitting. Data will be presented as the average number of minutes or hours of sitting per day compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dark green vegetable consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they eat at least 1.5 cups of dark green vegetables per week. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to consume dark green vegetables compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in red and orange vegetable consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they eat at least 5.5 cups of red and orange vegetables per week. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to consume red and orange vegetables compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fruit and vegetable consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they eat at least 5 cups of fruits and vegetables per week. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to consume fruits and vegetables compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fruit consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they eat at least 2 cups of fruits per week. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to consume fruits compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in walking 1 mile per day</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they walk at least 1 mile per day. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to walk 1 mile per day compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in leisure time and physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them if they get about 30 minutes of leisure time/recreational physical activity or exercise every day. Answers will include no, and I do not intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 6 months, No, but I intend to in the next 30 days, Yes, I have been but for less than 6 months, and Yes I have been for the past 6 months. Data will be presented as the average intention to get 30 minutes of exercise every day compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in general health</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them to state if they consider their health to be poor, fair, good, very good, or excellent. Data will be presented as the average ranking of individual health compared between groups over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in participation in program</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will complete a survey at baseline, 4 months, and 8 months that will ask them why they decided to participate in the program. Data will be presented as the average reason for participating over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total steps taken per day</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 4 months and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants in the walking group will be issued pedometers to measure the total number of steps taken per day. Data will be collected weekly for the duration of the study. Data presented as the average number of steps per day.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">157</enrollment>
  <condition>Dietary Habits</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Walking Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will join an established walking group and travel by foot 1 kilometer to a local Farmer's Market. They will also receive handouts about nutrition information and nutritional choices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-Walking Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will have no walking requirement. They will receive handouts about nutrition information and nutritional choices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Walking Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will walk 1 kilometer to a Farmer's Market.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Walking Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Over 18 years

          -  non-pregnant

          -  moderate to good health (able to walk approximately 1 mile)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  under 18 years

          -  pregnant

          -  poor health (unable to walk approximately 1 mile)

          -  institutionalized adults

          -  impaired consent capacity

          -  prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dawn Brewer, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Kentucky</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Kentucky</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 25, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Kentucky</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dawn Brewer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Appalachia</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>It depends on the quality of data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Informed Consent Form</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>No</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>Yes</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>July 31, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/52/NCT03567252/ICF_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

