<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03561922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RI-FI-2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03561922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact on Daily Life of Patients Using the Subretinal Implant RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact on Daily Life of Patients Using the Subretinal Implant RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Retina Implant AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Retina Implant AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to assess the impact of the subretinal implant RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS on
      the patient's daily life, using validated activities of daily living and questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to assess the impact of the subretinal implant RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS on
      the patient's daily life. In addition, the study will provide additional information about
      the safety and efficacy of the CE-certified RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS. In several studies it
      has been shown that patients who received this subretinal implant regain visual function to a
      certain extent and that its use is safe. So far, all assessments of patients with the RETINA
      IMPLANT Alpha AMS have been done in a controlled environment within the scope of
      interventional studies where the benefit in daily life has been assessed anecdotally only.
      Currently, there is no standard method available for an objective assessment of the impact of
      such devices in daily life of these patients. Hence, the aim of this study is to further
      assess the impact in daily life with a combination of already validated and newly developed
      assessments and questionnaires.

      This study adheres to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Manufacturer of the investigational device has ceased all business activities
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 4, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 5, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 5, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional vision</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline vs. 12 months after implantation</time_frame>
    <description>Instrumental Activities of Daily Living assessed at baseline (prior to implantation) versus one year after implantation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vision Related Quality of Life - Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 1, 2.5, 4, 6, 9 and 12 months after implantation (and for longterm review after 18 and 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A validated patient reported outcome questionnaire, IVI-VLV, assessed at baseline versus one year after implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Function - Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at baseline and 1, 2.5, 4, 6, 9 and 12 months after implantation (and for longterm review after 18 and 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A validated patient reported outcome questionnaire, ULV-VFQ, assessed at baseline versus one year after implantation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Number, nature and severity of device-related and implantation-related adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of implant-mediated visual function</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Computer test assessed with implant on versus off</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Retinal Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Inherited Retinal Dystrophy Primarily Involving Sensory Retina</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants receive the subretinal device RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of the subretinal RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</description>
    <arm_group_label>RETINA IMPLANT Alpha AMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 to 78

          2. Willing and able to give written informed consent

          3. Hereditary retinal degeneration of the outer retinal layer i.e. photoreceptors (rods &amp;
             cones)

          4. Pseudophakia or aphakia in the eye to be implanted

          5. Retinal vessels with remaining perfusion, despite pathological condition

          6. Layering of inner retina in the central region present, as shown by Optical Coherence
             Tomography (OCT)

          7. Thickness of the retina sufficient for subretinal surgery as shown by OCT

          8. Inner retina still functional (proven e.g. by light perception or electrically evoked
             phosphenes (EEP))

          9. Blindness in both eyes, (no light perception or light perception only)

         10. Visual acuity sufficient for reading normal print in earlier life, optically corrected

         11. Period of appropriate visual functions at least 12 years / lifetime

         12. Willing and able to perform study assessments and training during the full time period
             of 12 months

         13. Motivation to get the best possible results through training and realistic
             expectations about these as assessed in screening interview

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. OCT shows significant retina edema and/or scar tissue within target region for implant

          2. Heavy clumped pigmentation at posterior pole or on the planned route of the
             implantation

          3. atrophy of optic nerve or ganglion cells degeneration

          4. Any other ophthalmologic disease with relevant effect upon visual function (e.g.
             glaucoma, optic neuropathies, trauma, diabetic retinopathy, retinal detachment)

          5. Deep amblyopia reported earlier in life on eye to be implanted

          6. Systemic conditions that might imply considerable risks with regard to the surgical
             interventions and anesthesia (e.g. cardiovascular/pulmonary diseases, severe metabolic
             diseases)

          7. Acute and severe neurological and/or psychiatric diseases

          8. Hyperthyroidism or hypersensitivity to iodine

          9. Hypersensitivity to fluorescent dye

         10. Women who are pregnant or nursing, or women of childbearing potential who are not
             willing to use a medically acceptable means of birth control for the duration of the
             study or women unwilling to perform a pregnancy test before entering the study

         11. Participation in another interventional clinical study within the past 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>78 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicolas Leveziel, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire (CHU) de Poitiers, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierre-André Duval, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clinique Saint Jean, Montpellier, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Saint Jean</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <state>Hérault</state>
        <zip>34093</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire La Milétrie de Poitiers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Poitiers</city>
        <state>Vienne</state>
        <zip>86021</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.retina-implant.de</url>
    <description>Retina Implant AG Sponsor homepage</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stingl K, Schippert R, Bartz-Schmidt KU, Besch D, Cottriall CL, Edwards TL, Gekeler F, Greppmaier U, Kiel K, Koitschev A, Kühlewein L, MacLaren RE, Ramsden JD, Roider J, Rothermel A, Sachs H, Schröder GS, Tode J, Troelenberg N, Zrenner E. Interim Results of a Multicenter Trial with the New Electronic Subretinal Implant Alpha AMS in 15 Patients Blind from Inherited Retinal Degenerations. Front Neurosci. 2017 Aug 23;11:445. doi: 10.3389/fnins.2017.00445. eCollection 2017.</citation>
    <PMID>28878616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards TL, Cottriall CL, Xue K, Simunovic MP, Ramsden JD, Zrenner E, MacLaren RE. Assessment of the Electronic Retinal Implant Alpha AMS in Restoring Vision to Blind Patients with End-Stage Retinitis Pigmentosa. Ophthalmology. 2018 Mar;125(3):432-443. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2017.09.019. Epub 2017 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29110946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Retinal Degeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>Artificial Vision</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal Prosthesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Subretinal Implant</keyword>
  <keyword>Inherited Retinal Dystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Vision Restoration</keyword>
  <keyword>Bionic Eye</keyword>
  <keyword>Bionic Vision</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinitis Pigmentosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Artificial Retina</keyword>
  <keyword>Retina Implant</keyword>
  <keyword>Cone-Rod Dystrophy</keyword>
  <keyword>Choroideremia</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinopathia Pigmentosa</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinal Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Dystrophies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>If data are shared, this will only be done in a pseudonymized manner.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

