<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03568487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201712089RINC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03568487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Scapula Adaption in Overhead Athletes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Scapula Adaption in Overhead Athletes: Novel Scapulometer Development, Scapula Movement Adaption and Intensive Scapula-focused Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Previous studies have proposed various ways to assess scapular dyskinesis, but they were
      impractical in clinical setting or the validity was questioned. The novel scapulometer we
      developed can measure the prominence of scapular medial border and inferior angle. We would
      like to examine its reliability and validity in subjects with symptomatic scapular
      dyskinesis. The long-term, high-intensity, unilateral loading may cause overhead athletes to
      develop adaptive changes in shoulder kinematics, range of motion (ROM) and strength in the
      dominant arm. We hypothesized that these changes may be related to scapular dyskinesis.
      According to the previous studies, we expect electromyography (EMG) biofeedback training can
      help improve the ratio of muscle activation of scapular muscle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fifty subjects of scapular dyskinesis will be classified and recruited from overhead players
      (baseball, basketball, tennis, volleyball, and so on) at high schools and through local
      Internet media. All participants and their legal guardians will provide written informed
      assent and consent, respectively, and the study will be approved by the Ethics Committee
      Institutional Review Board. Since intervention may be specific to pattern of scapular
      dyskinesis, pattern of scapular dyskinesis in control group will match the pattern of
      scapular dyskinesis in the intervention group. Twenty-five subjects per group is based on a
      minimal revenant difference of a self-reported functional questionnaire between intervention
      and control (Struyf et al., 2013; Andersen et al., 2014). Participants will be recognized as
      elite players in their age categories. Subjects will be excluded if they have a history of
      shoulder pain or injury. Players will supply their player characteristics, including years of
      sports practice, weekly sports and conditioning exposure and type of sports. Players'
      standing height, sitting height, and body mass will be measured and used with the chronologic
      age to estimate their biological age according to the assessments of skeletal age, dental
      age, and secondary sex characteristics (Baxter et al., 2005). A clinical trial with a blinded
      assessor will be conducted. The subject takes a form (with a letter A or B) indicating
      allocation to either groups (scapula-focused approach versus control) from a closed envelop.
      For the scapula-approached group, pattern of scapular dyskinesis will be assessed. Then
      subjects in B control group will meet pattern-matched criteria related to pattern assessment
      of scapula-focused group. More subjects may be recruited for the control group to meet
      pattern-matched criteria of scapula-approached group. A list with subject numbers and the
      group allocation that results from this matched-control procedure will be stored in a sealed
      envelope. Only the therapist has direct access to the allocation list. In this way, subjects
      are allocated to either intervention or control group comprised of 25 subjects in each group.
      Both groups will be treated by the same therapist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of range of motion after 4-week training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>Passive interior rotation ROM and exterior rotation ROM of the glenohumeral joint will be assessed bilaterally using a hand-held standard universal goniometer. The player will lay supine with the humerus abducted to 90 degrees and elbow flexed to 90 degrees. The fulcrum of the goniometer is set at the olecranon process.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of muscle strength after 4-week training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>The maximal isometric strength of 8 shoulder-scapula complex muscles will be assessed bilaterally using a handheld dynamometer. Each test will be performed twice, with a 30-second rest period between tests. The largest strength value for each muscle will be used for statistical analyses, normalized to body weight (in kilograms), and expressed as a percentage for inter individual comparison.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of shoulder complex kinematics after 4-week training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>The Polhemus 3Space FASTRAK system (Polhemus Inc., Colchester, VT, USA) will be used to record shoulder complex kinematics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of muscular activities after 4-week training</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>Bipolar surface electromyographic (EMG) electrodes will be placed over the upper trapezius (UT), middle trapezius (MT), lower trapezius (LT), and serratus anterior (SA) of the dominant shoulder to record muscular activities.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forward shoulder posture (acromial distance)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>The measurement of the distance between the posterior border of the acromion and the table (acromial distance) is performed in supine. In this position, the assessor measured the distance between the most posterior aspect of the posterior border of the acromion and the table bilaterally.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pectoralis minor muscle length</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 4-week training</time_frame>
    <description>The distance from the fourth rib to the coracoids process will be measured with FASTRAK system with accuracy of 0.08 cm. This distance (in centimeter) is divided by the subjects height and multiplied by 100. This results in a pectoralis muscle length index (PMI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Scapular Dyskinesis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intensive scapula-focused approach</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensive scapula-focused approach</intervention_name>
    <description>scapula-focused approach with exercises, 3 x 20 min training per week for 4 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intensive scapula-focused approach</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>not have any physical training but is encouraged to stay active as usual.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  (1) with scapular dyskinesis

          -  (2) overhead players (baseball, basketball, tennis, volleyball, and so on) at high
             schools

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  if they have a history of shoulder pain or injury
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jiu-Jenq Lin, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>02-33668126</phone>
    <email>jiujlin@ntu.edu.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>scapular dyskinesis</keyword>
  <keyword>EMG biofeedback</keyword>
  <keyword>scapulometer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dyskinesias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

