<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03564223</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18DD02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRAS Project ID: 238932</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03564223</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Great Ormond Street Hospital Top Child and Adolescent Health Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Great Ormond Street Hospital Top Child and Adolescent Health Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institute of Child Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institute of Child Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Great Ormond Street Hospital (GOSH) Top child and adolescent health problems study aims
      to identify the top health concerns that parents/guardians and paediatricians in a tertiary
      hospital have for young people in England. 400 parents or guardians attending GOSH
      outpatients and 200 Paediatricians working at GOSH will be asked to rank a list of 30 child
      health concerns and results compared. Analysis will be done by demographics as well.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The GOSH Top child and adolescent health problems study aims to identify the top health
      concerns that parents/guardians and paediatricians in a tertiary hospital have for young
      people in England. The study will be surveying parents/guardians and paediatricians at Great
      Ormond Street Hospital (GOSH), asking them to review and give their impressions from a list
      of thirty common child and adolescent health issues. Analysis of responses will provide a
      list of problems that are most important and determine if respondents feel that the NHS
      England is adequately addressing these problems.

      The project was designed with public partnership. We conducted literature reviews, and
      adopted with permission, a survey instrument used by the C.S. Mott Children's Hospital
      National Poll in Michigan, USA. We asked some parents to list child and adolescent health
      problems that they deem most important. A consensus meeting with experts was held, to select
      the thirty most common and important public health issues for young people in England, from
      which the study will identify problems with the highest concern. This project and its
      intended outcomes will span medical, nursing, research and voluntary services that will
      improve child and adolescent healthcare provision the UK.

      The State of Child Health (SoCH) Report 2017 highlights indicators of child health problems
      across the four nations of the United Kingdom. There are some polls that were conducted in
      Australia and USA, investigating the top concerns for child health problems and thus
      providing a framework onto which to find solutions. The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
      through its National Child Health Poll established that that excessive screen time was the
      greatest parental concern, and that the top ten concerns related to modern lifestyle, mental
      health and child safety. Similarly, the C.S. Mott Children's Hospital National Poll on
      children's health selected a national sample of adults to identify health topics that are a
      &quot;big problem&quot; for children and teenagers. The 2017 report identified bullying/cyberbullying
      as the greatest concern. However there is no available evidence about studies being conducted
      in the United Kingdom to find out what parents/guardians and paediatricians report as the top
      child and adolescent health problems.

      The information would be valuable to the health professionals at the point of care, as well
      as the national healthcare system. This study analyses information from groups on both the
      supply and demand side of child and adolescent healthcare. Understanding the different
      perceptions of child and adolescent health problems between healthcare professionals and
      parents/guardians can lead to improved follow-up care and compliance with advice. Information
      from this study can be used as a basis for the establishment of a UK national poll that would
      further investigate public concerns for child health.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Top 10 Child Health Concerns</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Ranking of Top Child Health Concerns by Parents and Paediatricians, which will obtained by asking both groups to state on a 5-point Likert scale whether they strongly agree to strongly disagree on the significance of each of 30 child health concerns.
This will enable determination of top 10 child health concerns</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adequacy of NHS perceptions</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Parents and Paediatricians are asked to decide if they think the NHS is adequately addressing adolescent and child health issues, on a 5-point Likert scale, from 'strongly agree' to 'strongly disagree'</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of Top 3 information sources for parents and paediatricians</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Parents and Paediatricians are asked to list their top three information sources, and these will be analysed to determine the three most common sources of information for each group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Child Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Parents</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parents/Guardians</arm_group_label>
    <description>Parents/Guardians aged over 18, attending Great Ormond Street Hospital Outpatients.
Intervention: Administer questionnaire to review and decide on significance of each of 30 child health concerns</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paediatricians</arm_group_label>
    <description>Paediatricians working at Great Ormond Street Hospital NHS Foundation Trust.
Intervention: Administer questionnaire to review and decide on significance of each of 30 child health concerns</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Parents/guardians attending GOSH OPD (nA)

          -  Target Population = Yearly OPD attendance = 308,457

          -  Confidence Level is 95%

          -  Margin of error = 5%

          -  Target Sample Size = 384, approximately 400

          -  Sampling will be matched to attendance proportions in the six OPD areas - Cheetah,
             Manta ray, Rhino, Zebra, Hare and Hippo.

        Paediatricians (nB)

          -  Target population = 400 Paediatricians at GOSH

          -  Confidence Level is 95%

          -  Margin of error = 5%

          -  Target Sample Size = 197, approximately 200

          -  There will be no power calculation done. No statistical testing will be conducted
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents/Guardians attending GOSH NHS Foundation Trust Outpatients

          -  Paediatricians practicing at GOSH

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents/Guardians and Paediatricians outside the GOSH or NHS England

          -  Children aged under 18 years old

          -  Inpatients

          -  Parents/Guardians who cannot communicate in English and do not have an interpreter

          -  Participants who have previously responded to the questionnaire

          -  Outpatient coordinator or Nurse in Charge feels that the potential participant may be
             vulnerable, or have complex issues.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vikram Palit</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Great Ormond Street Hospital Institute of Child Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vikram Palit</last_name>
    <phone>07884228149</phone>
    <email>v.palit@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Lee D Hudson</last_name>
    <phone>07775123574</phone>
    <email>l.hudson@ucl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Ormond Street Institute of Child Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 1EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vikram Palit</last_name>
      <phone>07884228149</phone>
      <email>v.palit@ucl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Lee D Hudson</last_name>
      <phone>07775123574</phone>
      <email>l.hudson@ucl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Webby E Phiri</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://mottpoll.org/tags/top-10-child-health-concerns</url>
    <description>C.S. Mott Poll for Top Child Health Concerns</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.rchpoll.org.au/polls/top-10-child-health-problems/</url>
    <description>Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne Child Health Poll</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garbutt JM, Leege E, Sterkel R, Gentry S, Wallendorf M, Strunk RC. What are parents worried about? Health problems and health concerns for children. Clin Pediatr (Phila). 2012 Sep;51(9):840-7. doi: 10.1177/0009922812455093. Epub 2012 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22843294</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Parental concerns</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Paediatrician Concerns</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is currently no plan made to share IPD. This project is part of an educational project for the fulfillment of an MSc. Paediatrics and Child Health at University College London.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol and Statistical Analysis Plan</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>Yes</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>June 4, 2018</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/23/NCT03564223/Prot_SAP_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

