<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03566095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-69004-20401</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03566095</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Voices for Food: Food Policy Councils, Food Security and Healthy Food Choices</brief_title>
  <acronym>VFF</acronym>
  <official_title>Voices for Food: Utilizing Food Policy Councils to Bridge the Gap Between Food Security and Healthy Food Choices</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>South Dakota State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michigan State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Nebraska Lincoln</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Purdue University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Missouri-Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>South Dakota State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effectiveness of coaching and Voices for Food materials on
      establishing Food Policy Councils (FPCs) and using guided client choice in rural food
      pantries to improve food security and diet quality among food pantry clients, and to improve
      the food environment in rural, midwestern food pantries. Half of the communities received
      coaching and the Voices for Food kit, the other half only received the Voices for Food kit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Community coaching is a a strategy that helps community leaders plan for and overcome
      challenges to community development. Interventions at the community level are most effective
      when they are conceived and led by locals. Community coaches can aid the local community in
      the development of FPCs in rural communities. FPCs have the potential to improve the
      nutritional quality of available food, and connect a diverse network of food system
      stakeholders from the public, private and nonprofit sectors, which includes local food
      pantries. Food pantry users are food insecure and avoid hunger by consuming low cost and
      shelf stable food items. Guided client choice is a system of distribution that can be
      employed in food pantries and supported by FPCs. Guided client-choice is a model of
      distribution in which pantry clients choose the foods they would like from the pantry based
      upon family size and is formatted based upon USDA MyPlate. Guided client choice has been
      shown to meet the needs of the pantry client base better than the traditional model of
      distribution often found in food pantries. Food pantries have the opportunity to meet the
      nutritional needs of the food insecure population.

      Voices for Food is a multi-leveled socio-ecological, longitudinal, matched treatment and
      comparison study to develop food policy councils (FPCs), and improve food security and diet
      quality in rural communities. Voices for Food was conducted in 24 rural, high poverty
      counties in South Dakota, Indiana, Missouri, Michigan, Nebraska and Ohio. Counties were
      assigned to a treatment (n=12) or comparison (n=12) group.

      Intervention activities focus on three key components that impact food security: 1) community
      coaching by Extension Educators/field staff, 2) FPC development, and 3) development of a
      MyChoice (guided client choice) food pantry. Community coaching, along with the Voices for
      Food kit was only provided to treatment counties. Comparison communities only received the
      Voices for Food kit. Evaluation components focus on three levels of the intervention: 1)
      Community (FPCs), 2) Food Pantry Organization and Food Environment, and 3) Pantry Client &amp;
      Families. Participants in this study were community stakeholders, food pantry directors,
      staff/volunteers and food pantry clients. Pantry food access/availability including pantry
      food quality and quantity, household food security and pantry client dietary intake are
      dependent variables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All data were collected from both treatment an comparison communities at the same time points.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants were not aware of their status as a treatment or comparison community.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The United States Household Food Security Survey Module</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in food security of food pantry clients. Individuals will be classified as very low food secure, low food secure, marginal food secure and high food secure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthy Eating Index (HEI) Score</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Change in diet quality of food pantry clients. The Automated Self-Administered 24-hour (ASA24®) Dietary Assessment Too allows for calculation of the Healthy Eating Index score, which is a measure of diet quality.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Policy Council Implementation Form</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Food Policy Council Implementation Form is a study developed assessment tool that assesses the degree of food policy council implementation. The Food Council Implementation Form documents changes occurring within the Food Policy Council.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Pantry MyChoice Observation Tool</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Food Pantry MyChoice Observation Tool is a study developed assessment tool that assesses the degree of MyChoice (guided client choice) implementation. The tool documents the extent to which key components of the MyChoice food pantry model are physically in place at the pantry and part of the food, food display, and distribution process.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1735</enrollment>
  <condition>Food Security</condition>
  <condition>Nutritive Value</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Coaching and Voices for Food Kit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The treatment communities received community coaching from an Extension Professional or Educator in the use of the Voices for Food kit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Voices for Food Kit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The comparison community received the Voices for Food kit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coaching and Voices for Food Kit</intervention_name>
    <description>Community Coaching and Voices for Food Kit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Coaching and Voices for Food Kit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Voices for Food Kit</intervention_name>
    <description>Voices for Food Kit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Voices for Food Kit</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Food Pantry Clients must be current clientele by visiting the participating food
             pantry at least once in the last year, English-speaking.

          -  Food Pantry Directors must be 18 years or older (19 if in Nebraska), English-speaking
             and a director of a participating food pantry.

          -  Food Pantry Staff/Volunteers must be 18 years or older (19 if in Nebraska),
             English-speaking and a staff/volunteer of a participating food pantry.

          -  Community Stakeholders must be 18 years or older (19 if in Nebraska), English-speaking
             and reside in the participating community.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 18 years old (19 if in Nebraska)

          -  Non English- speaking
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Suzanne Stluka, PhD, RD, LN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>South Dakota State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heather Eicher- Miller, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Purdue University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Henne, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Michigan State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Donna Mehrle, MPH, RD, LD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Missouri-Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Franzen-Castle, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Nebraska Lincoln</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dan Remley, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rural</keyword>
  <keyword>Food Policy Councils</keyword>
  <keyword>Food Pantry</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Coaching</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is not a plan to make IPD available.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

