<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03568383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12041</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03568383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Protecting Households On Exposure to Newly Diagnosed Index Multidrug-Resistant Tuberculosis Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PHOENIx MDR-TB</acronym>
  <official_title>Protecting Households On Exposure to Newly Diagnosed Index Multidrug-Resistant Tuberculosis Patients (PHOENIx MDR-TB)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Otsuka Pharmaceutical Development &amp; Commercialization, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the efficacy and safety of 26 weeks of delamanid
      (DLM) versus 26 weeks of isoniazid (INH) for preventing confirmed or probable active
      tuberculosis (TB) during 96 weeks of follow-up among high-risk household contacts (HHCs) of
      adults with multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) (index cases). High-risk HHCs are those
      with HIV or non-HIV immunosuppression, latent TB infection, and young children below the age
      of 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will compare the efficacy and safety of 26 weeks of delamanid (DLM) versus 26
      weeks of isoniazid (INH) for preventing confirmed or probable active tuberculosis (TB) during
      96 weeks of follow-up among high-risk household contacts (HHCs) of adults with
      multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) (index cases). High-risk HHCs are those with HIV or
      non-HIV immunosuppression, latent TB infection, and young children below the age of 5 years.

      If at least one HHC within a household (HH) is found to be eligible, the HH will be
      randomized to one of the following:

      Arm A: DLM daily for adults, adolescents, and children, given for 26 weeks.

      Arm B: INH daily for adults, adolescents, and children, given for 26 weeks AND pyridoxine
      (vitamin B6) daily for adults, adolescents, and children, given for 26 weeks.

      All high-risk HHCs in the same HH will receive the same randomized regimen.

      All participants will be in the study for 96 weeks. At study entry, index cases will undergo
      a medical history review and sputum collection. HHCs will have study visits at study entry
      and at Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 26, 36, 48, 60, 72, 84, and 96. Visits may include physical
      examinations; blood, urine, and sputum collection; electrocardiograms (ECGs); and
      questionnaires and assessments. Forty HHCs under the age of 5 taking DLM will undergo an
      intensive PK visit at Week 8.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 18, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 18, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants with confirmed or probable active TB at any time between Day 0 and the week 96 study visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>TB diagnoses will be reviewed by the independent outcomes review committee to assess whether the HHC had TB, if it was confirmed or probable TB, and if it was MDR-TB.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants who permanently discontinue randomized study drug (DLM or INH) due to a treatment-related adverse event</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Requiring discontinuation as defined in the protocol, or in the opinion of the site investigator is a treatment-limiting adverse event.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants with confirmed active MDR-TB at any time between Day 0 and the week 96 study visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 96</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants who died from any cause at any time between Day 0 and 96 weeks of follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Deaths will be reviewed by the independent outcomes review committee to assess whether the HHC had TB at the time of death, possibly undiagnosed, and relatedness of the death to TB.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants who died from any cause at any time between Day 0 and 96 weeks of follow-up, or with confirmed or probable active TB at any time between Day 0 and the week 96 study visit</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 96</time_frame>
    <description>Deaths and TB diagnoses will be reviewed by the independent outcomes review committee to assess whether the HHC had TB at the time of death, possibly undiagnosed, and relatedness of the death to TB; and whether the HHC had TB, if it was confirmed or probable TB, and if it was MDR-TB.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of participants with a Grade 3 or higher adverse event during the period receiving randomized study drug (DLM or INH)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured through Week 26</time_frame>
    <description>If a HHC has a Grade 3 or higher adverse event prior to starting randomized study drug, then the same event will only be considered during follow-up if the grade worsens.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5610</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis, MDR</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Delamanid (DLM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HHCs will receive delamanid (DLM) for 26 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Isoniazid (INH)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HHCs will receive isoniazid (INH) and pyridoxine (vitamin B6) for 26 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delamanid (DLM)</intervention_name>
    <description>Adults and children ≥30 kg: delamanid 200 mg orally once daily.
Children ≥2.5 kg to &lt;30 kg: weight-band dosing orally once daily as per the study protocol. As children gain weight, their DLM dose should be adjusted, typically every month or as the visit schedule permits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Delamanid (DLM)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Isoniazid (INH)</intervention_name>
    <description>Adults and children ≥24 kg: INH 300 mg orally once daily.
Children ≥2.5 kg to &lt;24 kg: INH weight-band dosing orally once daily as per the study protocol. As children gain weight, their INH dose should be adjusted.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Isoniazid (INH)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pyridoxine (vitamin B6)</intervention_name>
    <description>All HHCs in Arm B must receive pyridoxine (vitamin B6) with each dose of INH based on the current local dosing guidelines. For children up to 3 years of age and nursing women, pyridoxine will be given as per local standard of care. Pyridoxine is not supplied through the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Isoniazid (INH)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        INDEX CASE

          -  Men and women age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  Pulmonary MDR-TB defined as:

               -  Confirmation of rifampin/rifampicin (RIF) resistance and INH resistance by

               -  adequate source documentation (including date of testing, test methodology, and
                  test results) of RIF and INH resistance from a licensed/nationally approved*
                  referral program, OR

               -  if either or both results are unknown or not adequately documented (as noted
                  above), then confirmation must be obtained using a DAIDS-approved laboratory that
                  operates according to Good Clinical Laboratory Practices (GCLP) guidelines and
                  participates in an appropriate external quality assurance (EQA) program.

               -  *NOTE: The term &quot;licensed/nationally approved&quot; refers to a laboratory that has
                  been certified or licensed by an oversight body within that country and approved
                  for RIF and/or INH resistance testing.

               -  NOTE: Pre-XDR and XDR TB are not exclusionary. See the A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx MOPS
                  for study-approved molecular and phenotypic methods.

          -  Started MDR-TB treatment within the past 90 days.

          -  Ability and willingness of the index case to provide informed consent to access the HH
             and approach HH members for evaluation.

          -  HH of index case has at least one reported HHC.

        HOUSEHOLD CONTACTS

        If any member(s) of the HH is/are not eligible or do not want to participate, all other
        eligible TB contacts within the HH can still participate.

          -  Currently lives or lived in the same dwelling unit or plot of land and shares or has
             shared the same housekeeping arrangements as the index case and who reports exposure
             within 90 days prior to the index case starting MDR-TB treatment. Also, shared greater
             than 4 hours of indoor airspace with the index case during any one-week period prior
             to the index case starting MDR-TB treatment.

          -  HHCs must be in one of the following high-risk groups:

               -  All children 0 to less than 5 years old at the time of enrollment, regardless of
                  LTBI or HIV status;

               -  Adults, adolescents, and children greater than or equal to 5 years of age who are
                  LTBI test positive (either TST-positive (greater than or equal to 5 mm) or
                  IGRA-positive), and whose HIV status is negative, indeterminate, or unknown, and
                  who are not non-HIV immunosuppressed;

               -  NOTE: Both TST and IGRA testing are required for screening unless TST testing is
                  not available due to global shortages or in-country supply challenges, but only
                  one positive test is required for eligibility.

               -  Adults, adolescents, and children greater than or equal to 5 years of age who are
                  HIV-infected or are non-HIV immunosuppressed (defined as receiving anti-tumor
                  necrosis factor (TNF) treatment, or being solid organ or hematologic transplant
                  recipients), regardless of LTBI test status.

          -  HIV-1 infection status must be documented as positive, negative, indeterminate or
             unknown for all HHCs. Unknown status includes those who previously tested HIV negative
             but the test was performed more than one year ago. HIV testing will be offered to all
             HHCs with negative of unknown status. For adults (18 years and older), HIV-1 infection
             must be documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or chemiluminescence
             immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit at any time prior to study entry and confirmed by a
             licensed Western blot or a second antibody test by a method other than the initial
             rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by HIV-1 antigen or plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load greater
             than 1000 copies/mL. Two or more plasma HIV-1 RNA viral loads of greater than 1,000
             copies/mL are also acceptable as documentation of HIV infection. More information is
             available on this criterion in the protocol.

          -  The following specific laboratory values for infants, children, and adults obtained
             within 30 days prior to study entry by any DAIDS-approved non-US laboratory.

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 750 cells/mm^3

               -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 7.4 g/dL

               -  Platelet count greater than or equal to 50,000/mm^3

               -  Creatinine less than or equal to 2 × upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Potassium level greater than or equal to 3.0 mEq/L

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (SGOT) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (SGPT)
                  less than or equal to 3 × ULN

               -  Total bilirubin less than or equal to 2.5 × ULN (Note: if on atazanavir (ATV),
                  total bilirubin greater than 2.5 x ULN is permitted if direct bilirubin less than
                  or equal to 2.5 × ULN)

               -  Albumin greater than 3 g/dL

               -  NOTE: Participants with results from other laboratory tests that are outside the
                  normal range may be eligible for the study, at the discretion of the site
                  investigator, if not considered to be an obstacle to entry.

          -  For females of reproductive potential, negative serum or urine pregnancy test within 7
             days prior to study entry by any DAIDS-approved non-US laboratory that operates in
             accordance with GCLP and participates in appropriate external quality assurance
             programs.

               -  NOTE: Reproductive potential is defined as:

               -  Girls who have reached menarche or

               -  Women who have had menses within the past 12 consecutive months and who do not
                  have an FSH greater than 40 IU/L or

               -  Women who have had menses within the past 24 consecutive months if an FSH
                  measurement is not available

               -  Women who have not undergone surgical sterilization (e.g., hysterectomy, or
                  bilateral oophorectomy, or bilateral salpingectomy).

               -  Female participants who are participating in sexual activity that could lead to
                  pregnancy must agree to use one reliable form of contraceptive (i.e., hormonal
                  contraceptive, condoms, IUD, diaphragm with spermicide, or cervical cap with
                  spermicide) while receiving study treatments.

               -  NOTE: Female participants who are not of reproductive potential, as defined
                  above, or whose male partner(s) have undergone successful vasectomy with
                  documented azoospermia or have documented azoospermia for any other reason, are
                  eligible without requiring the use of contraceptives. Participant-reported
                  history is acceptable documentation of menopause, hysterectomy, bilateral
                  oophorectomy, or bilateral salpingectomy.

          -  For infants (0 to 1 year of age), weight greater than or equal to 2.5 kg at screening.

          -  Ability and willingness of participant or legally-authorized representative (legal
             guardian or biological parent) to provide informed consent or assent as appropriate.

          -  Chest radiograph without evidence of active TB performed within 70 days prior to study
             entry for HHCs greater than or equal to 2 years of age and within 30 days prior to
             study entry for HHCs less than 2 years of age.

          -  QTcF interval less than or equal to 460 ms within 30 days prior to study entry as
             confirmed by the central ECG reading center.

          -  Enrollment of the HHC within 30 days after the index case is enrolled. In the event
             that a HHC is suspected of having TB, then this window for enrollment may be extended
             from within 30 days to within 70 days to allow for TB testing of the HHC.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        INDEX CASE

          -  Has previously enrolled into the A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx trial as an index case or HHC,
             or is a member of a HH which has previously enrolled into the A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx
             trial.

        HOUSEHOLD CONTACTS

          -  Current confirmed or probable or possible pulmonary or extrapulmonary TB, based on the
             following criteria: the current ACTG Diagnosis Appendix 100 for adults and for
             children of greater than or equal to 15 years of age; or the modified pediatric TB
             definitions for children less than 15 years of age as described in the
             A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx MOPS.

          -  Receipt of more than 30 cumulative days of INH, rifamycin, fluoroquinolone, or DLM in
             the 90 days prior to study entry.

          -  History of or current liver cirrhosis at any time prior to study entry.

          -  Evidence of acute hepatitis, such as abdominal pain, nausea and vomiting, jaundice,
             dark urine, and/or light stools within 90 days prior to study entry.

          -  Peripheral neuropathy greater than or equal to Grade 2 within 90 days prior to study
             entry according to the DAIDS Table for Grading the Severity of Adult and Pediatric
             Adverse Events (DAIDS AE Grading Table), corrected Version 2.1, July 2017.

          -  Known allergy/sensitivity or any hypersensitivity to components of study drugs or
             their formulation.

          -  Current cardiovascular disorder that is clinically relevant in the opinion of the site
             investigator, including but not limited to heart failure, coronary heart disease,
             second or third degree atrioventricular (AV) block, prolongation of the QRS complex
             over 120 ms (in both male and female participants), arrhythmia, or tachyarrhythmia.

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements.

          -  Serious illness requiring systemic treatment including parenteral therapy (e.g.,
             antibiotics) and/or hospitalization within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Currently receiving other medication with potential for adverse drug-drug
             interactions, including QT prolongation. Please see the study protocol for a list of
             prohibited medications.

          -  Taken an investigational drug or vaccine within 30 days prior to study entry.

          -  Has a clinical condition that in the site investigator's opinion would interfere with
             study participation.

          -  Has enrolled into a TB vaccine or TB preventive therapy or TB therapeutic trial,
             including the A5300B/I2003B/PHOENIx trial, in the two years prior to study entry.

          -  Not expected to be able to complete 96 weeks of study follow-up (e.g., seasonal or
             migrant workers or students who may not stay in the area).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gavin Churchyard, MBBCh MMed FRCP FCP(SA) PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Aurum Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amita Gupta, MD, MHS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions, Center for Clinical Global Health Education</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anneke Hesseling, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Stellenbosch</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan Swindells, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Nebraska</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gaborone CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gaborone</city>
        <state>South-East District</state>
        <country>Botswana</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tebogo J. Kakhu</last_name>
      <phone>267-3931353</phone>
      <email>tkakhu@bhp.org.bw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Instituto de Pesquisa Clinica Evandro Chagas (IPEC) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rio de Janeiro</city>
        <zip>21040-360</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra W. Cardoso, Ph.D., M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>55-21-22707064</phone>
      <email>sandra.wagner@ipec.fiocruz.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GHESKIO Institute of Infectious Diseases and Reproductive Health (GHESKIO - IMIS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port-au-Prince</city>
        <zip>HT-6110</zip>
        <country>Haiti</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandy N. Nerette, M.D.</last_name>
      <email>snerette@gheskio.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Les Centres GHESKIO Clinical Research Site (GHESKIO-INLR) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Port-au-Prince</city>
        <zip>HT-6110</zip>
        <country>Haiti</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cynthia Riviere, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>509-22222241</phone>
      <email>criviere@gheskio.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Byramjee Jeejeebhoy Medical College (BJMC) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pune</city>
        <state>Maharashtra</state>
        <zip>411001</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nishi Suryavanshi, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>91-98-23248979</phone>
      <email>nishi@jhumitpune.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chennai Antiviral Research and Treatment (CART) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chennai</city>
        <state>Tamil Nadu</state>
        <zip>600113</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Faith E. Samson</last_name>
      <phone>91-44-39106811</phone>
      <email>beulah@cartcrs.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Moi University Clinical Research Center (MUCRC) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Eldoret</city>
        <state>Rift Valley</state>
        <zip>30100</zip>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Priscilla C. Cheruiyot</last_name>
      <phone>254-532060850</phone>
      <email>pcchepkorir@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Socios En Salud Sucursal Perú CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>15001</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bruno Martel</last_name>
      <phone>51-1-945230659</phone>
      <email>bmartel_ses@pih.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barranco CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>15063</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis A. Limo, D.D.S., MPH</last_name>
      <phone>51-1-2067800</phone>
      <phone_ext>210</phone_ext>
      <email>llimo@impactaperu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>San Miguel CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>32-15088</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Milagros L. Sabaduche, RGN</last_name>
      <phone>51-1-5521600</phone>
      <phone_ext>644</phone_ext>
      <email>msabaduche@impactaperu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>De La Salle Health Science Institute Angelo King Medical Research Center (DLSHSI-AKMRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cavite</city>
        <zip>4114</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maricelle S. Gler</last_name>
      <phone>63-9178230431</phone>
      <email>tarcelasg@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Soweto ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <state>Gauteng</state>
        <zip>1862</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Debra Peters</last_name>
      <phone>27-119899700</phone>
      <email>petersd@phru.co.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wits Helen Joseph Hospital CRS (Wits HJH CRS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <state>Gauteng</state>
        <zip>2092</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anne Reyneke</last_name>
      <phone>27-11-2768817</phone>
      <email>areyneke@witshealth.co.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durban International Clinical Research Site CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durban</city>
        <state>Kwa Zulu Natal</state>
        <zip>4052</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rosie Mngqibisa, MB ChB, M.B.B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>27-31-2611093</phone>
      <email>mngqibisa@ecarefoundation.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PHRU Matlosana CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Klerksdorp</city>
        <state>North West Province</state>
        <zip>2574</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tumelo Moloantoa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>27-18-4653751</phone>
      <email>moloantoat@phru.co.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rustenburg CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rustenburg</city>
        <state>North West Province</state>
        <zip>0300</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tania Adonis</last_name>
      <phone>27-87-1351587</phone>
      <email>tadonis@auruminstitute.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Task Applied Science (TASK) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape Province</state>
        <zip>7530</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christelle v. Niekerk</last_name>
      <phone>27-21-9171044</phone>
      <email>christelle@task.org.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cape Town Lung Institute (UCTLI) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape Province</state>
        <zip>7700</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Catrien Drinkwater</last_name>
      <phone>27-21-4066850</phone>
      <email>catrien.drinkwater@uct.ac.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South African Tuberculosis Vaccine Initiative (SATVI) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape Province</state>
        <zip>7705</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris Hikuam</last_name>
      <phone>27-21-4066228</phone>
      <email>chris.hikuam@uct.ac.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kilimanjaro Christian Medical Centre (KCMC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moshi</city>
        <country>Tanzania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Boniface N. Njau, B.S., M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>255-75-4933559</phone>
      <email>bnneneu@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siriraj Hospital ,Mahidol University NICHD CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <state>Bangkoknoi</state>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Watcharee Lermankul</last_name>
      <phone>66-2-4197000</phone>
      <phone_ext>5695</phone_ext>
      <email>watchareeped@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thai Red Cross AIDS Research Centre (TRC-ARC) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pathumwan</city>
        <state>Bangkok</state>
        <zip>10330</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Parawee Thongpaeng</last_name>
      <phone>662-6523040</phone>
      <phone_ext>106</phone_ext>
      <email>parawee.t@hivnat.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chiangrai Prachanukroh Hospital NICHD CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chiang Mai</city>
        <zip>50100</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pra-ornsuda Sukrakanchana</last_name>
      <phone>66-81-7468858</phone>
      <email>Pra-ornsuda.Sukrakanchana@phpt.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joint Clinical Research Centre (JCRC)/Kampala Clinical Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra Rwambuya, M.P.H.</last_name>
      <phone>256-772-779283</phone>
      <email>dxr23@case.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MU-JHU Research Collaboration (MUJHU CARE LTD) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carolyne P. Onyango, MB ChB, M.S.</last_name>
      <phone>256-414-541044</phone>
      <email>carolonyango@mujhu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Milton Park CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milton Park</city>
        <state>Harare</state>
        <country>Zimbabwe</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Rachel Mahachi, M.Sc., R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>263-24-2701356</phone>
      <email>rmahachi@uzchs-ctrc.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Botswana</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Haiti</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Kenya</country>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>Philippines</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Tanzania</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>Uganda</country>
    <country>Zimbabwe</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 17, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tuberculosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Multidrug Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Household Contact</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Multidrug-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyridoxal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B 6</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isoniazid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data that underlie results in the publication, after deidentification.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Beginning 3 months following publication and available throughout period of funding of the AIDS Clinical Trials Group by NIH.</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>With whom?
Researchers who provide a methodologically sound proposal for use of the data that is approved by the AIDS Clinical Trials Group.
For what types of analyses?
To achieve aims in the proposal approved by the AIDS Clinical Trials Group.
By what mechanism will data be made available?
Researchers may submit a request for access to data using the AIDS Clinical Trials Group &quot;Data Request&quot; form at: https://actgnetwork.org/about-actg/templates-and-forms. Researchers of approved proposals will need to sign an AIDS Clinical Trials Group Data Use Agreement before receiving the data.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

