<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03563846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>G28-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03563846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Standard Meal on the Pharmacokinetic Profile of RP-G28 in Healthy Adult Male and Female Subjects</brief_title>
  <acronym>RP</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective, Open-Label, Randomized, Two-Period, Two-Sequence, Crossover Study Comparing RP-G28 Administered in the Fasted State and the Effect of a Standard Meal on the Pharmacokinetic Profile of RP-G28 in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ritter Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ritter Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized, open-label, 2-period, 2-sequence, crossover study to evaluate the effect of a
      standard meal on the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of orally administered RP-G28.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This randomized, open-label, 2-period, 2-sequence, crossover study is designed to evaluate
      the effect of a standard meal on the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of orally administered
      RP-G28, which is being developed for the treatment of lactose intolerance. The study consists
      of a screening visit (during the interval from Day -21 to Day -3), baseline/check-in to the
      clinical research unit (Day -2 to Day -1), 2 treatment periods (Day 1 and Day 3), a 48-hour
      washout between doses, check-out from the clinical research unit (Day 4), and 1 follow-up
      phone call conducted 7 to 10 days after the final dose of the study drug (i.e., during the
      interval from Day 10 to Day 13). The duration of subject study participation is approximately
      5 weeks. Plasma samples for PK analysis will be taken at specified timepoints from 24 hours
      prior to each dose through 24 hours after each dose.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 13, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 13, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 extrapolated to infinity</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 2 and 1 pretreatment; Day 1 post-treatment, Day 1-3 washout, Day 3 and 4 post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Assess systemic exposure of RP-G28 when administered in the fed and fasted state</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>2, 3, 2 and 1 days pretreatment; 1 - 13 days post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events will be continuously monitored throughout the entire study, including follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum chemistry</measure>
    <time_frame>21 and 3 days pretreatment; day 4 post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Albumin, alkaline phosphatase, alanine aminotransferase, aspartate aminotransferase, blood urea nitrogen, calcium, chloride, carbon dioxide, creatinine, total bilirubin, gamma glutamyl transferase, glucose, lactic dehydrogenase (lactate dehydrogenase), phosphorus, potassium, sodium, total cholesterol, total protein, uric acid, and vitamin D.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematology</measure>
    <time_frame>21 and 3 days pretreatment; day 4 post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects with abnormal laboratory values will be flagged and summarized separately</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinalysis</measure>
    <time_frame>2, 3, 2 and 1 days pretreatment; day 1 and 3 post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of subjects with abnormal laboratory values will be flagged and summarized separately</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Lactose Intolerance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RP-G28 administered in the fasted state</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RP-G28, 15 g dissolved in water, administered in the fasted state</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RP-G28 administered in the fed state</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RP-G28, 15 g dissolved in water, administered immediately following the consumption of a standard non-dairy meal</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RP-G28</intervention_name>
    <description>RP-G28 is a purified galacto-oligosaccharide (GOS) product</description>
    <arm_group_label>RP-G28 administered in the fasted state</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>RP-G28 administered in the fed state</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>galactic-oligosaccharide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Healthy male and female subjects between 18 and 60 years of age

          2. Subjects with body weights greater than or equal to 50 kg and a body mass index (BMI)
             between 18 kg/m2 and 32 kg/m2

          3. Female subjects of childbearing potential and males and their female partner(s) of
             childbearing potential must agree to use 2 forms of contraception, 1 of which must be
             a barrier method, during the study and for 30 days after the end of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating females or male partners of females who are pregnant or
             lactating.

          2. Subjects with any history of clinically significant bronchopulmonary, cardiovascular,
             cerebrovascular, hematologic, renal, hepatic, neurological, psychiatric, metabolic, or
             endocrine (eg, diabetes or thyroid disease) disease/disorder.

          3. Use of prescription or over-the-counter (OTC) drugs, including vitamins and herbal or
             dietary supplements within 2 weeks (4 weeks for enzyme inducers including St. John's
             Wort) or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer), prior to the baseline/check-in visit,
             unless in the opinion of the investigator, prior use of the medication will not
             interfere with the study procedures or compromise subject safety.

          4. Subjects with sustained supine or semi-supine systolic blood pressure of &lt; 90 or &gt; 140
             mm Hg and supine or semi-supine diastolic blood pressure of &lt; 50 or &gt; 90 mm Hg at the
             screening or baseline/check-in visits.

          5. Subjects with a resting heart rate of &lt; 45 or &gt; 100 beats per minute at the screening
             or baseline/check in visits.

          6. Subjects with any clinically relevant deviation from normal during the physical
             examination, including vital signs at the screening or baseline/check-in visits.

          7. Subjects with a known history of hypercalcemia, hyperparathyroidism, or
             hypervitaminosis D.

          8. Use of calcium or vitamin D supplements (prescription or OTC) within 2 weeks prior to
             the baseline/check-in visit.

          9. Subjects with a history of allergic reactions or hypersensitivities to
             galacto-oligosaccharides or any significant drug-related or food-related allergy (such
             as anaphylaxis or hepatotoxicity).

         10. Regular use of probiotics, antacids, histamine type 2 (H2)-receptor blockers, proton
             pump inhibitors, or any medications that may alter the normal gastric environment
             and/or motility, or use of such medications within 2 weeks prior to the
             baseline/check-in visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul G Pearson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Ritter Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Syneos Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lactose Intolerance</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

