<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03563664</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RIF-Danazol</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03563664</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Danazol on Endometrial αvβ3 Integrin Expression in Patients With Unexplained Recurrent Implantation Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Danazol on Endometrial αvβ3 Integrin Expression in Patients With Unexplained Recurrent Implantation Failure - A Self-controlled Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ain Shams University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigates the presence of a possible link between treatment with danazol and
      expression of endometrial αvβ3 integrin which might allow tailoring of danazol treatment to
      the subset of repeated IVF/ET failure that might benefit most from it.

      38 eligible ovulatory women were recruited aged 20 - 38 years with unexplained recurrent
      implantation failure (RIF). Timed suction endometrial biopsy was obtained from participants
      during the implantation window of the pretreatment cycle, followed by immunohistochemical
      staining for endometrial αvβ3 integrin expression, scored using H-score.

      Participants were treated with danazol (Danol® 200mg capsules, Sanofi, Guildford, UK) in
      daily dosage of 400 mg for 12 weeks. Post-treatment suction endometrial biopsy was obtained
      during the implantation window following the first ovulation after danazol treatment and
      endometrial αvβ3 integrin expression was compared to the pretreatment cycle.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>38 ovulatory patients with unexplained recurrent implantation failure were recruited. Endometrial αvβ3 integrin expression (using immunohistochemically stained endometrial biopsy) was compared before and after treatment with danazol.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>H-score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stained sections were evaluated by the same pathologist for the intensity of brownish cytoplasmic and membranous staining of the endometrial components using the semi-quantitative scoring system originally described by Budwit-Novotny et al., H-score [6], calculated using the formula H-score=∑▒〖P_i (i+1)〗 where i is the staining intensity valued as 0, absent; 1+, weak, but detectable above control; 2+, moderate and 3+, strong; and Pi is the percentage of epithelial cells stained with each intensity (varying from 0 to 100%)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Unexplained Infertility</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>38 ovulatory patients with unexplained recurrent implantation failure were recruited. Pre-treatment endometrial biopsy and immunohistochemical examination for endometrial αvβ3 integrin expression (using immunohistochemically stained endometrial biopsy) was done. After treatment with danazol (Danol® 200mg capsules, Sanofi, Guildford, UK) in daily dosage of 400 mg for 12 weeks, post-treatment endometrial biopsy and immunohistochemical examination was repeated and compared with previous results.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-treatment endometrial biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Timed suction endometrial biopsy was obtained from participants via Wallach Endocell® 908014A endometrial cell sampler timed during the implantation window of the pretreatment cycle; followed by immunohistochemical staining using immunoperoxidase staining incorporating avidin-biotin complex (ABC) method.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Danazol</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants were treated with danazol (Danol® 200mg capsules, Sanofi, Guildford, UK) in daily dosage of 400 mg for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Post-treatment endometrial biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Post-treatment suction endometrial biopsy was obtained during the implantation window following the first ovulation after danazol treatment, timed, processed and stained as described previously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: 20-38 yrs

          -  Unexplained recurrent implantation failure (RIF), defined as failure to achieve an
             intrauterine gestational sac recognized by ultrasonography after transfer of at least
             four good-quality embryos (defined as those with four or five blastomeres on day 2,
             seven or more cells on day 3, ≤ 20% anucleated fragments and absence multinucleated
             blastomeres) in a minimum of three fresh or frozen IVF cycles after exclusion of other
             causes of RIF (as depicted by normal transvaginal ultrasonography, hysteroscopy,
             hysterosalpingography, laparoscopic findings, male and female karyotypic examination,
             endocrinological profile during ovarian stimulation and negative anti-cardiolipin
             antibody IgM/IgG, lupus anticoagulant, thrombophilia screening (including protein C,
             protein S, anti thrombin III and factor V leiden) and normal male semen analysis as
             depicted by 2010 WHO criteria for semen analysis and sperm DNA fragmentation testing).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Anovulation

          -  Contraindications to treatment with danazol (including chronic liver disease,
             congestive heart failure, dyslipidemia or history/current thrombo-embolic disease)

          -  Medical comorbidities (e.g. autoimmune disorders, diabetes mellitus, etc)

          -  Patients who underwent induction of ovulation / received hormonal treatment during the
             previous three months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>38 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mohamed Samy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M Samy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ain SHams Maternity Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <state>Abbaseya</state>
        <zip>002</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2018</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>mohammed mahmoud samy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Lecturer in Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Danazol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

