<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03562468</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MB-1801</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03562468</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study by ChromaDex to Assess the Effects of TRU NIAGEN on Cognitive Function, Mood and Sleep in Older Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Crossover Study to Assess the Effects of Nicotinamide Riboside on Cognitive Function, Mood and Sleep in Older Adult Men and Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ChromaDex, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Midwest Center for Metabolic and Cardiovascular Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ChromaDex, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The sponsor of this study is ChromaDex, Inc. This is a double-blind, randomized, crossover
      study to investigate the effects of 300 mg/d and 1000 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside)
      compared to a placebo control on cognitive function, mood and sleep in men and women over 55
      years of age. The trial is managed by Midwest Center for Metabolic and Cardiovascular
      Research.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 13, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 26, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 26, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Treatments will be administered daily as 4 capsules in a double-blind, randomized, crossover manner for three 8-week treatment periods. Each subject will receive one placebo and two active treatments in a crossover design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study site will be provided placebo and TRU NIAGEN capsules, each labeled with the protocol number, blinded product code, expiration date, batch number, the statement &quot;For Investigational Use Only&quot; and a space to write the subject's initials, screen and date dispensed.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary comparison will be the low dose (300 mg/d nicotinamide riboside) condition to the placebo condition for the change from baseline to the end of each relevant treatment period.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome variable will be the difference between treatments in the change from baseline (defined as visit 2 value for each of the three treatment periods) in executive function measured with the CNS Vital Signs test battery, using the standard score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Function</condition>
  <condition>Mood</condition>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will be randomly assigned to receive placebo for an 8-week treatment period. Subjects will be instructed to take two capsules (placebo) in the morning with breakfast and two capsules (placebo) in the evening with dinner. At the end of each 8-week treatment period subjects will crossover to the next treatment group until all three treatment periods have been completed at 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) 300 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will be randomly assigned to receive 300 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) for an 8-week treatment period. Subjects will be instructed to take two capsules of TRU NIAGEN in the morning with breakfast and two capsules of TRU NIAGEN in the evening with dinner. At the end of each 8-week treatment period subjects will crossover to the next treatment group until all three treatment periods have been completed at 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) 1000 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each subject will be randomly assigned to receive 1000 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) for an 8-week treatment period. Subjects will be instructed to take two capsules of TRU NIAGEN in the morning with breakfast and two capsules of TRU NIAGEN in the evening with dinner. At the end of each 8-week treatment period subjects will crossover to the next treatment group until all three treatment periods have been completed at 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>300 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside)</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment with 300 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) will be administered daily as 4 capsules in a double-blind, randomized, crossover manner for three 8-week treatment periods. Each subject will receive one placebo and two active treatments in a crossover design. The two active treatments are 300 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) and 1000 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside).</description>
    <arm_group_label>TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) 300 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Niagen, the active ingredient in TRU NIAGEN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1000 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside)</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment 1000 mg/day of TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) will be administered daily as 4 capsules in a double-blind, randomized, crossover manner for three 8-week treatment periods. Each subject will receive one placebo and two active treatments in a crossover design. The two active treatments are 300 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) and 1000 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside).</description>
    <arm_group_label>TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) 1000 mg/day</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Niagen, the active ingredient in TRU NIAGEN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment with placebo capsules will be administered daily as 4 capsules in a double-blind, randomized, crossover manner for three 8-week treatment periods. Each subject will receive one placebo and two active treatments in a crossover design. The two active treatments are 300 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside) and 1000 mg/d TRU NIAGEN (nicotinamide riboside).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is male or female, ≥55 years of age.

          2. Subject has a BMI of 18.50 to 34.99 kg/m2.

          3. Subject has a score of ≥80 on executive function at screening. One re-test will be
             allowed for subjects who require additional instruction on the CNS VS test battery.

          4. Subject is willing to maintain usual diet and physical activity patterns.

          5. Subject has no plans to change smoking habits during the study period.

          6. Subject is willing to limit alcohol consumption to no more than one serving of alcohol
             per day (1 drink = 12 oz beer, 5 oz wine, or 1.5 oz hard liquor) and will abstain from
             consuming 2 h prior to retiring for the evening for the duration of the study.

          7. Subject is willing to limit consumption of caffeine-containing
             beverages/foods/products to no more than 400 mg daily, with all caffeine consumption
             occurring prior to 6 pm.

          8. Subject is willing to fast (8 - 15 h, target 10 h, water only) prior to each clinic
             visit.

          9. Subject has no difficulties swallowing capsules.

         10. Subject is willing and able to attend all clinic visits.

         11. Subject understands the study procedures and signs forms documenting informed consent
             to participate in the study and authorization for release of relevant protected health
             information to the study Investigator and is willing to complete study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Individual has history or presence of a clinically significant (in the opinion of the
             Investigator) psychiatric disorder or neurologic disease including epilepsy,
             cerebrovascular disturbance or traumatic injury.

          2. Individual has a history of diagnosed clinical depression in the prior 2 years, or a
             score ≥20 (defined as moderate-to-severe depression) on the Beck Depression
             Inventory-II administered at visit 1 (week -1).

          3. Individual is currently diagnosed with dementia and/or has a score &lt;24 on the Mini
             Mental State Questionnaire administered at visit 1 (week -1).

          4. Uncorrected abnormal vision that in the opinion of the Investigator would impair the
             subject's ability to complete the computerized testing (including but not limited to
             nearsightedness, farsightedness, and color blindness).

          5. Individual has a clinically important active endocrine, cardiovascular, renal,
             hepatic, pulmonary, pancreatic, neurologic or biliary disorder.

          6. Individual has a history of a cardiovascular event or revascularization procedure
             within 6 months of visit 1 (week -1).

          7. Individual has a diagnosis of type I diabetes mellitus. Type 2 diabetes mellitus is
             excluded if the individual has experienced initiation of or a dosage change in
             diabetes medication(s) within 2 months of visit 1 (week -1), or has significant
             co-morbidities as determined by the study physician.

          8. Insulin for the treatment of Type I or Type 2 diabetes mellitus is exclusionary.

          9. Individual has uncontrolled hypertension (systolic blood pressure ≥160 mm Hg and/or
             diastolic blood pressure ≥100 mm Hg).

         10. Individual has a recent history (prior 5 years) or the presence of cancer other than
             non-melanoma skin cancer.

         11. Individual has a history or presence of a chronic pain condition requiring regular use
             of opioid therapy.

         12. Individual has a recent history or strong potential for drug or alcohol abuse defined
             as &gt;14 drinks per week (1 drink = 12 oz beer, 5 oz wine, or 1 ½ oz distilled spirits).

         13. Individual has a history of unconventional sleep patterns (e.g., night shift) or
             chronic insomnia (at least 3 d/week over the past month), a diagnosed sleep disorder,
             or a chronic medical condition with the potential to impact energy/fatigue levels.

         14. Individuals taking any form of niacin &gt;25 mg/d and any use of nicotinamide riboside
             within 2 weeks of visit 1 (week -1).

         15. Individual is a heavy consumer of caffeinated beverages (&gt;400 mg/d within 2 weeks of
             visit 1).

         16. Individual has a history of using psychotropic medications (including antidepressants
             and tranquilizers), stimulant medications, and/or narcotics within 4 weeks of visit 1
             (week -1).

         17. Individual has used sleep aid medications, supplements, and/or products, including
             antihistamines, within 2 weeks of visit 1 (week -1) A washout prior to screening is
             allowed).

         18. Individual has a known allergy to any ingredients in the study products.

         19. Individual is pregnant, planning to be pregnant during the study period, lactating, or
             is of childbearing potential and is unwilling to commit to use of a medically approved
             form of contraception throughout the study period.

         20. Subject has an active infection or has used antibiotics within 5 d of any clinic
             visit. For those with an active infection and/or using antibiotics, subjects must wait
             at least 5 d after the infection resolves or antibiotic use is complete. The test
             period will be extended for completion in these cases.

         21. Subject has been exposed to any non-registered drug product within 30 d of visit 1
             (week -1).

         22. Individual has a condition the Investigator believes would interfere with his or her
             ability to provide informed consent, comply with the study protocol, which might
             confound the interpretation of the study results or put the person at undue risk.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MB Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boca Raton</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33487</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nicotinamide riboside</keyword>
  <keyword>NAD</keyword>
  <keyword>TRU NIAGEN</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nicotinic Acids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

