<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03999398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OLL-242381</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03999398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short and Long-term Results of PCI in no Touch Vein-graft.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short and Long-term Results of PCI in no Touch Vein-graft:a Comparison With the Standard One.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Region Örebro County</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karlstad Central Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Region Örebro County</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery disease is one of the biggest health issue worldwide.The treatment, in a
      large part of the patients, implicates a so called bypass-operation, that consists in to
      connect new vascular conduits (grafts) beyond the narrowed coronary vessels to improve the
      blood supply to the heart. One of the graft that is commonly used is the saphenous vein from
      the leg. The disadvantage of the saphenous vein graft is the predisposition to early
      obstruction. The international literature shows the following grades of occlusion: 15% in the
      first year and 40% after 10 year.

      At the Cardio-Thoracic Clinic of the University hospital of Örebro has been developed a new
      method to harvest the saphenous vein together with the surrounding fat-tissue. This
      technique, called no-touch technique, has the advantage to reduce the damages to the vein
      during the harvesting, showing a substantially reduced risk for future occlusion (5% after 18
      months and 10% after 8,5 years).

      The aim of the PhD project is to evaluate the results of the no-touch technique in compare to
      the conventional technique for the venous graft harvesting. The focus of the study is to
      analyse all the operated patients in our clinic who underwent a post-operative coronary
      angiography do to angina pectoris (heart pain). All the patients who received a stent during
      the post-operative angiography will be analysed in detail and one will compare the occlusion
      grade and the rate of major adverse cardiac events (MACE).

      This study is the first and the only one in the world that will examine the long-term results
      of the no-touch technique in particular after the stenting of the venous graft.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a observational retrospective with registered-based data. The register used is
      Swedeheart which is the national Swedish intervention-related quality register for
      cardiological interventions (such as percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI)) and cardiac
      surgical procedures that are performed every year in Sweden.

      After the approval of the Regional ethical review board in Uppsala (Sweden), one could review
      all the subjects that received a PCI in a venous graft between January the 1st, 2006 and June
      the 30th, 2017 either at the Angiographic unit of the University Hospital of Orebro or at the
      Angiographic unit of the Hospital of Karlstad. All the participants has been previously
      operated at the Cardiothoracic department of the University hospital of Orebro with a
      coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) procedure, with one type of vein graft (no-touch) or
      the other (standard) According to the restrictions that Regional ethical review board of
      Uppsala imposed, only those that gave a written consensus or that were death at the moment of
      the data extraction, could be included in the study.

      All the relevant data for the study that are missed in the quality register, are extrapolated
      by the clinical registers of the two hospital involved (Orebro and Karlstad).

      Once finished the data extraction and review, the data will be statistically analysed in term
      of short and long term results; and an advanced comparison between the two different type of
      venous graft involved. This is to show if there is a significant difference between the two
      techniques also after a PCI procedure (already proven clinical different between the two
      technique in favour of the no-touch one by numerous studies).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Major adverse cardiac event (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>after the percutaneous coronary intervention (until December the 31th 2017)</time_frame>
    <description>adverse cardiac event (mortality (cardiac) + myocardial infarction + target vessel revascularisation)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In-stent restenosis</measure>
    <time_frame>after the percutaneous coronary intervention (until December the 31th 2017)</time_frame>
    <description>stenosis or occlusion of the stent implanted during the percutaneous coronary intervention procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>after the percutaneous coronary intervention (until December the 31th 2017)</time_frame>
    <description>overall mortality after the procedure</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">216</enrollment>
  <condition>Percutaneous Coronary Intervention</condition>
  <condition>Saphenous Vein</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Bypass</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No-touch</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants that operated at the time of the coronary artery bypass grafting with a &quot;no-touch&quot; venous graft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants that operated at the time of the coronary artery bypass grafting with a &quot;conventional&quot; venous graft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants are treated with a PCI and stent implantation in a venous graft (previously implanted during the CABG operation)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No-touch</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Previously: coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All the subjects that previously were operated with a coronary artery bypass grafting at
        the Cardiothoracic department of the University hospital of Orebro (from the 1990 until
        2017) and that underwent a percutaneous coronary intervention in a venous graft between
        January the 1st, 2006 and June the 30th, 2017.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants previously operated with a coronary artery bypass grafting at the
             Cardiothoracic department of the University hospital of Orebro

          -  Participants that underwent a percutaneous coronary intervention in a venous graft

          -  Given the informed consensus or dead at the moment of the data extraction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not given the informed consensus
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gabriele Ferrari, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Region Örebro Län</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kärl-Thoraxkliniken; University Hospital of Örebro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Örebro</city>
        <zip>70185</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.researchweb.org/is/fourol/project/242381</url>
    <description>link of the original (Swedish) project plan</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Souza D. A new no-touch preparation technique. Technical notes. Scand J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 1996;30(1):41-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8727856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Souza DS, Dashwood MR, Tsui JC, Filbey D, Bodin L, Johansson B, Borowiec J. Improved patency in vein grafts harvested with surrounding tissue: results of a randomized study using three harvesting techniques. Ann Thorac Surg. 2002 Apr;73(4):1189-95.</citation>
    <PMID>11996262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Souza DS, Johansson B, Bojö L, Karlsson R, Geijer H, Filbey D, Bodin L, Arbeus M, Dashwood MR. Harvesting the saphenous vein with surrounding tissue for CABG provides long-term graft patency comparable to the left internal thoracic artery: results of a randomized longitudinal trial. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2006 Aug;132(2):373-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16872965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samano N, Bodin L, Karlsson J, Geijer H, Arbeus M, Souza D. Graft patency is associated with higher health-related quality of life after coronary artery bypass surgery. Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg. 2017 Mar 1;24(3):388-394. doi: 10.1093/icvts/ivw372.</citation>
    <PMID>28040753</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samano N, Geijer H, Liden M, Fremes S, Bodin L, Souza D. The no-touch saphenous vein for coronary artery bypass grafting maintains a patency, after 16 years, comparable to the left internal thoracic artery: A randomized trial. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2015 Oct;150(4):880-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2015.07.027. Epub 2015 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>26282605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bourassa MG. Fate of venous grafts: the past, the present and the future. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1991 Apr;17(5):1081-3.</citation>
    <PMID>2007707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campeau L, Enjalbert M, Lespérance J, Bourassa MG, Kwiterovich P Jr, Wacholder S, Sniderman A. The relation of risk factors to the development of atherosclerosis in saphenous-vein bypass grafts and the progression of disease in the native circulation. A study 10 years after aortocoronary bypass surgery. N Engl J Med. 1984 Nov 22;311(21):1329-32.</citation>
    <PMID>6333635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzgibbon GM, Kafka HP, Leach AJ, Keon WJ, Hooper GD, Burton JR. Coronary bypass graft fate and patient outcome: angiographic follow-up of 5,065 grafts related to survival and reoperation in 1,388 patients during 25 years. J Am Coll Cardiol. 1996 Sep;28(3):616-26.</citation>
    <PMID>8772748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hindnavis V, Cho SH, Goldberg S. Saphenous vein graft intervention: a review. J Invasive Cardiol. 2012 Feb;24(2):64-71. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22294536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldman S, Zadina K, Moritz T, Ovitt T, Sethi G, Copeland JG, Thottapurathu L, Krasnicka B, Ellis N, Anderson RJ, Henderson W; VA Cooperative Study Group #207/297/364. Long-term patency of saphenous vein and left internal mammary artery grafts after coronary artery bypass surgery: results from a Department of Veterans Affairs Cooperative Study. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Dec 7;44(11):2149-56.</citation>
    <PMID>15582312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee MS, Park SJ, Kandzari DE, Kirtane AJ, Fearon WF, Brilakis ES, Vermeersch P, Kim YH, Waksman R, Mehilli J, Mauri L, Stone GW. Saphenous vein graft intervention. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Aug;4(8):831-43. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2011.05.014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21851895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehilli J, Pache J, Abdel-Wahab M, Schulz S, Byrne RA, Tiroch K, Hausleiter J, Seyfarth M, Ott I, Ibrahim T, Fusaro M, Laugwitz KL, Massberg S, Neumann FJ, Richardt G, Schömig A, Kastrati A; Is Drug-Eluting-Stenting Associated with Improved Results in Coronary Artery Bypass Grafts? (ISAR-CABG) Investigators. Drug-eluting versus bare-metal stents in saphenous vein graft lesions (ISAR-CABG): a randomised controlled superiority trial. Lancet. 2011 Sep 17;378(9796):1071-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61255-5. Epub 2011 Aug 26. Erratum in: Lancet. 2012 Jan 14;379(9811):122.</citation>
    <PMID>21872918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stone GW, Goldberg S, O'Shaughnessy C, Midei M, Siegel RM, Cristea E, Dangas G, Lansky AJ, Mehran R. 5-year follow-up of polytetrafluoroethylene-covered stents compared with bare-metal stents in aortocoronary saphenous vein grafts the randomized BARRICADE (barrier approach to restenosis: restrict intima to curtail adverse events) trial. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Mar;4(3):300-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2010.11.013.</citation>
    <PMID>21435608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 24, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 24, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 24, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 24, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Region Örebro County</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Gabriele Ferrari</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Saphenous Vein</keyword>
  <keyword>No-touch</keyword>
  <keyword>Percutaneous Coronary Intervention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>starting 6 months after publication</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>All the individual data that can be shared according the Regional ethical review board rules. Those data will be share a specific upon request in order to contribute to other researchers own works (that want to compare their results with ours) or in case of meta-analysis.</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

