<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03995082</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-2562.cc</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03995082</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Breast Cancer Patient Engagement With Patient Reported Outcome Measure Survey</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Study of Breast Cancer Patient Engagement With Patient Reported Outcome Measure Survey Results</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research protocol is to measure Patient Reported Outcome Measures (PROMs)
      in breast cancer patients. PROM results will be provided to patients and providers and the
      investigators will evaluate the relationship between patient engagement with PROM results and
      patient and clinicopathologic variables, utilization of supportive and hospital services, and
      patient satisfaction with patient-provider communication.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PROM Survey The BREAST-Q survey will be utilized to evaluate PROMs at the designated survey
      time points. The investigators will utilize the mastectomy and breast conserving therapy
      pre-operative and post-operative modules dependent on the type of surgery each patient
      chooses. The BREAST-Q survey has questions that pertain to the following domains: 1.
      Satisfaction with breasts, 2. Psychosocial well-being, 3. Physical well-being, 4. Sexual
      well-being, 5. Adverse effects of radiation, and 6. Patient experience with the health care
      team. Scores for each domain are scored with an equivalent Rasch transformed score (range
      0-100). These scores can then be tracked over time. In addition to the BREAST-Q modules, the
      investigators will ask 3 open ended questions. These questions will allow patients to share
      concerns or outcomes at each time point in an effort to identify currently unmeasured
      outcomes that are important to patients.

      Timing of Surveys For patients having surgery first: At the pre-operative visit, patients
      will be provided the pre-operative module. The post-operative modules will then be
      administered via email or in the clinic at the post-operative visit (~2 weeks after surgery),
      and then at 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months after surgery. After one year,
      patients will be surveyed annually.

      For patients receiving neoadjuvant chemotherapy, surveys will be administered every 3 months
      during the pre-operative period. The post-operative modules will then be administered via
      email or in the clinic at the post-operative visit (~2 weeks after surgery), and then at 3
      months, 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months after surgery. After one year, patients will be
      surveyed annually.

      Patients will be randomized to receive the results of PROM surveys graphed over time
      (experimental group) or to not receive the results of the PROM surveys (normative control
      group). Results of the BREAST-Q surveys will be available to providers for all patients.

      Statistical Analyses Study data will be collected in a prospective database using the CCTSI
      RedCap database, with which the breast cancer program has extensive experience. The database
      will include demographic information, clinicopathologic data, surgical details, neoadjuvant
      and adjuvant treatments, and the equivalent Rasch transformed scores for each PROM metric at
      all recorded time points.

      Descriptive statistics will be utilized to characterize the patient population and patient
      engagement with PROMs. Univariate and multivariate analyses will be used to evaluate
      demographic and clinicopathologic variables and variations in PROMs across the course of
      treatment. The study endpoints will be evaluated with the following statistical methods:
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 30, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>BREAST Q patient satisfaction with breast surgeon domain</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with patient-provider communication using the BREAST Q satisfaction with breast surgeon domain. The domain is scored from 0 to 100 points with more points representing higher patient satisfaction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BREAST Q Patient reported outcome measure survey domains including: Satisfaction with breasts, psychosocial well being, physical well being, sexual well being, and effects of radiation domains.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Validated BREAST Q survey domains. All domains are scored 0 to 100 points. Higher points represent a better outcome. The subscales will not be used to create a total score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare utilization including the use of social work services, psycho-oncology services, oncology fitness service, nutrition service, and urgent/emergent services including visits to urgent care or the emergency room.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants using supportive services will be scored as yes or no if the patient used the specific service or did not use the service.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Currently unmeasured patient reported outcomes using open ended questions</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will use open ended questions to identify currently unmeasured patient reported outcomes. Responses will be evaluated as qualitative data using descriptive coding to identify themes. Expected common themes include financial concerns, concerns about caring for family or imposing on family, fertility concerns, etc. The questions will include: &quot;what are your top 3 concerns&quot;, &quot;what are you most worried about going forward&quot;, &quot;how could the healthcare team better help you&quot;, &quot;if you could start your treatment over what would you have done differently.&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">370</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive the results from the PROM survey in graphical form each time they complete a survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normative Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>These patients will complete the PROM surveys, but will not be presented with the results of the survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Reported Outcome Measure Survey result feedback</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive a graph of their results from the PROM survey each time they complete a survey</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        We will target all patients with a new diagnosis of breast cancer who present to the breast
        multi-disciplinary clinic.

        Inclusion:

          -  Adult (18 years of age or more)

          -  Female

          -  Patients with breast cancer

          -  Patients who can independently complete surveys

        Exclusion

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Male

          -  Patients who cannot independently complete surveys
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Tevis</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Tevis</last_name>
    <phone>3037242731</phone>
    <email>sarah.tevis@ucdenver.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Tevis</last_name>
      <email>sarah.tevis@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Tevis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cherry Creek Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80206</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sarah Tevis, MD</last_name>
      <phone>608-692-0836</phone>
      <email>sarah.tevis@cuanschutz.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Tevis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lone Tree Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lone Tree</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 22, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 22, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

