<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03994692</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>omfs 3-3-3</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03994692</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Patient Satisfaction Using Autogenous Inlay (Sandwich) Eminoplasty Versus Patient Specific Poly Ether-ether Ketone (PEEK) Onlay Implant</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Patient Satisfaction Using Autogenous Inlay (Sandwich) Eminoplasty Versus Patient Specific Poly Ether-ether Ketone (PEEK) Onlay Implant in Treatment of Chronic Condylar Dislocation A Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cairo University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>El-Galaa Military Medical Complex</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cairo University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the study:

      The aim is minimize morbidity in treatment of TMJ dislocation. Hypothesis: Alternate
      hypothesis that treatment tmj dislocation with PEEK eminoplasty will be more efficient than
      using autogenous inlay technique

      PICO:

      Problem (P): patients with un pleasant painful dislocated tmj Intervention (I): eminoplasty
      with patient specific poly ether-ether ketone (PEEK) onlay implant Control Group (C):
      autogenous inlay (sandwich) eminoplasty Outcome (O): patient Satisfaction, dislocation
      treatment (normal range of mouth opening), less morbidity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the study:

      The aim is minimize morbidity in treatment of TMJ dislocation. Hypothesis: Alternate
      hypothesis that treatment tmj dislocation with PEEK eminoplasty will be more efficient than
      using autogenous inlay technique

      PICO:

      Problem (P): patients with un pleasant painful dislocated tmj Intervention (I): eminoplasty
      with patient specific poly ether-ether ketone (PEEK) onlay implant Control Group (C):
      autogenous inlay (sandwich) eminoplasty Outcome (O): patient Satisfaction, dislocation
      treatment (normal range of mouth opening), less morbidity.

      8. Trial design: Type: Parallel, two arm, randomized clinical trial. Allocation ratio: 1:1
      Superiority framework

      III. Methods A) Participants, interventions &amp; outcomes 9. Study settings: Diagnosis in
      outpatient clinic of Oral and Maxillofacial surgery at the faculty of dentistry, Cairo
      University, Urban area, Cairo Governorate, Egypt.

      The surgery will be in O.R rooms or in the outpatient clinic of the same faculty.

      11. Interventions

      Control Group:

      Patient preparation The operation can be performed under general anesthesia. mental nerve
      blocks will be given and infiltration for hemostasis.

      After allowing adequate time for vasoconstrictor effects to take place, the incision is
      initiated in a layered approach through the labial mucosa and is continued through the
      mentalis muscles and periosteum.

      Exposure of the symphyseal bone is undertaken using periosteal elevators and the mental
      nerves are visualized bilaterally.

      The roots of the incisors and canines should be localized and bone cuts should be made at
      least 5 mm inferior to the root apices.

      The roots of canines can impede the operation and limit the size of graft. Similarly, the
      surgeon should stay at least 5 mm away from the inferior border of the symphysis and the
      mental foramina.

      Bone cuts can be made with a bur or reciprocating saw under copious saline irrigation. When
      the desired bone cuts have been completed, thin straight or curved osteotomes are then used
      to deliver the graft Hemostasis can be achieved using resorbable hemostatic agents or fibrin
      glue. Long-lasting local anesthetic, e.g. bupivacaine, can be applied to the area to achieve
      longer analgesia.

      The wound closure is done in two layers with a resorbable suture for the muscle layer and
      fast-resorbing suture for the mucosa.

      Flexible skin tape can be used on the chin for 3-5 days to reduce swelling and prevent wound
      dehiscence.

      Layered Endural approach to TMJ making wedge in eminence by mallet &amp; chisel (green stick
      fracture), then wedging piece of chin graft to increase the height of the eminence creating
      an obstacle to treat dislocation by manipulation of patient mandible intra operative.

        -  Functional mandibular movements were reproduced to confirm absence of subluxation and
           checked for interference and any required adjustments made.

        -  A multilayer closure of the incisions will be accomplished using Vicryl sutures (88).

      Intervention group ; CT scan will be done with the following criteria;

      bony window for facial bones, axial cuts, minimal slice thickness, minimal intervals between
      the cuts, guantry tilt equals zero and finally DICOM files on CD .then, Using cad cam
      software (mimics 15) , the virtual design and surgery will be done.

      Patient Preparation;

        -  All surgeries will be performed under general anaesthesia (naso-endotracheal intubation)

        -  Then the entire periarticular region and overlying skin will be infiltrated by 2%
           lidocaine (20 ml lidocaine + adrenalin 1%) via a 25 gauge needle as an additional
           anaesthesia.

        -  Benzyl penicillin 2 MIU in combination with dicloxacillin 1 g will be administered
           intravenously as prophylactic antibiotics.

        -  A line is drawn between the lateral eyebrow and tragus. The articular fossa and condylar
           head is located 10 mm anterior to the tragus and 2-5 mm below this line.

        -  The temporofacial branch has relatively a constant course and vector being on a line
           located 0.5 cm below the tragus of the ear, in the direction of the eyebrow and passing
           1.5 cm above the lateral eyebrow. Just anterior to the condylar head where the articular
           eminence will be identified by palpation and marked.

      The TMJ will be exposed using the endural incision line and the articular eminence will be
      identified

        -  To locate the articular eminence precisely, tissue must be exposed layer by layer until
           the articular eminence is located. Then, a tunnel will be formed using blunt dissection
           so that the front wall of the articular capsule can be exposed completely.(89-90-91 )

        -  The patient specific PEEK eminence will be inserted and secured with two to three
           pre-planed screws .

        -  Functional mandibular movements were reproduced to confirm absence of subluxation and
           checked for interference and any required adjustments made.

        -  A multilayer closure of the incisions will be accomplished using Vicryl sutures.

      For both groups masseter muscle scarification through intra oral approach will be done with
      post-operative intermaxillary fixation using ivy loops

      Post-operative instructions:

      According to Oral Maxillo-fac Surg Clin North Am (Quinn PD, 2000):

      The following postoperative protocol will be used for patients of both groups:

        -  Broad-spectrum antibiotics (penicillin V 1 g, or clindamycin 600 mg) and non-steroidal
           anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) will be prescribed for 1 week.

        -  The patients will be told to stay on a soft diet for 5 days and encouraged to resume a
           normal diet as soon as possible.

        -  Physiotherapy will start on postoperative day 1, and patients will be encouraged to
           increase the exercise program as soon as possible.

        -  Patients will be advised to continue physiotherapy for at least 1 year and possibly
           longer.

        -  Cone Beam CT (CBCT) imaging will be performed at the first follow-up visit in order to
           visualize the position of the patient specific titanium eminence, as well as the
           position of the retention screws and their relationships to the surrounding vital
           structures following surgery.

      Visit: (every month till 4 month after operation) For group I: Regular follow up with
      measuring maximum inter incisal distance with a caliper , check normal mandibular movement &amp;
      other problems like pain ,discomfort &amp; swelling For group II: Regular follow up with
      measuring maximum inter incisal distance with a caliper , check normal mandibular movement &amp;
      other problems like pain ,discomfort &amp; swelling
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 20, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 20, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized control trial
trials will be carried out in hospital of oral &amp; maxillofacial department at faculty of oral and dental medicine of Cairo university
equal randomization participants with equal probabilities for intervention
positive controlled , both groups receiving treatment
parallel group study , each group of patient receive single treatment simultaneously</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>because the two intervention in this trial are clearly different and easily recognized by participant and investigator , neither investigators nor participant can be blinded</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction: Question</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 month after operation</time_frame>
    <description>Questioning the patient about if there is any dislocation or any limitation to mandibular movement</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal Incisal Opening</measure>
    <time_frame>follow up for 4 month</time_frame>
    <description>measured with Caliper</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>during operation</time_frame>
    <description>measured with time calculation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post operative pain: VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>follow up for 2 weeks up to 4 month</time_frame>
    <description>measured with visual analogue scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7</enrollment>
  <condition>Mandibular Dislocation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PEEK eminoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CT scan with bony window for facial bones and DICOM files on CD .then, Using cad cam software (mimics 15) , the virtual design and surgery will be done.
under general anathesia The TMJ will be exposed using the endural incision line and the articular eminence will be identified then blunt dissection so that the front wall of the articular capsule can be exposed completely.
The patient specific PEEK eminence will be inserted and secured with two to three pre-planed screws .
Functional mandibular movements were reproduced to confirm absence of subluxation and then closure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>autogenous onlay grafting eminoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>under general anesthesia , chin graft was taken Layered Endural approach to TMJ making wedge in eminence by mallet &amp; chisel (green stick fracture), then wedging piece of chin graft to increase the height of the eminence creating an obstacle to treat dislocation by manipulation of patient mandible intra operative.
- Functional mandibular movements were reproduced to confirm absence of subluxation then closure</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PEEK eminoplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>making obstacle at eminence using patient specefic PEEK device</description>
    <arm_group_label>PEEK eminoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>poly ether - ether ketone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>autogenous onlay grafting eminoplasty</intervention_name>
    <description>making obstacle at eminence using chin graft</description>
    <arm_group_label>autogenous onlay grafting eminoplasty</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>grafting eminoplasty</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  - Patient with recurrent dislocation with maximum inter incisal opening over 55mm

          -  Long-standing dislocation of the TMJ involving both fixation for more than 3 weeks and
             the failure of manual reduction

          -  Failure of conservative strategies such as orientation to self-limit jaw movement and
             the use of a chin-cap or bandage

          -  Both sexes

          -  Age between 18 and 48 years.

          -  Highly motivated patients.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Post-menopausal females with osteoporosis

          -  Patient with uncontrolled systemic disease

          -  pregnancy

          -  psychological disorders, drug or alcohol dependency

          -  Known allergies or sensitivities to dental materials, including PEEK, Titanium or
             general anesthetic agents

          -  Inability to return for follow up visits.

          -  Refusal of participation from the patient
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>mohamed mounir, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>faculty of oral and dental medecine cairo university</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>mustafa gamal abdel kawy, B.D.S</last_name>
    <phone>01004519806</phone>
    <email>mustafa.gamal@dentistry.cu.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>mustafa gamal abdel kawy, B.D.S</last_name>
    <phone>01021287358</phone>
    <email>hero0105590840@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>1-Mayer L. Recurrent dislocation of the jaw. J Bone Joint Surg1933;15:22Y25 2- Van der Kwast WA. Surgical management of bilateral habitual luxation of the mandible. Int J Oral Surg 1978;7:329Y332 3- Gosserez M, Dautrey J. Osteoplastic bearing for the treatment of temporomandibular luxations. In: Oral Surgery Transactions of 2nd Congress of Int Assoc Oral Surg Copenhagen. 1967:261Y264 4- Lindemann A. Die chirurgische behandlung der erkrankungen des kiefergelenkes. Z Stoma 1925;23:395Y 406 5- Iizuka T, HNdaka H, Murakami K, et al. Chronic recurrent anterior luxation of the mandible. Int J Oral Maxillofac Surg 1988; 17:170Y172</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>El-Galaa Military Medical Complex</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>mustafa gamal abdel kawy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>resident of oral &amp; maxillofacial surgery department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PEEK eminoplasty ,autogenous inlay (sandwich) eminoplasty</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Dislocations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ether</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

