<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03995030</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NYMC 181</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03995030</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Massively Parallel Sequencing to Identify Microbiological Organisms in Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid</brief_title>
  <official_title>Massively Parallel Sequencing to Identify Microbiological Organisms in Bronchoalveolar Lavage Fluid in Children, Adolescents and Young Adults Post Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York Medical College</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York Medical College</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients who are post hematopoietic stem cell transplantation who require a bronchoalveolar
      lavage (BAL) for standard clinical car will have extra fluid collected and sent for massively
      parallel sequencing to see if it is as sensitive for detecting a microbial pulmonary
      infection compared to standard cultures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      5.1 Subjects will undergo bronchoscopy and BAL based on clinical indications. Techniques and
      equipment will be per current clinical practice at Westchester Medical Center (WMC). The
      bronchoscope is usually introduced either via an artificial airway (endotracheal tube or
      laryngeal mask airway). The lavage is performed with sterile normal saline. The site of
      performing the lavage is selected based on radiologic or clinical data and on the appearance
      of the airways during the bronchoscopy. The typical volume of the lavage is 3 aliquots of 1
      ml/kg each, with a max of 20 ml per aliquot.

      5.2 When 10 ml or more of BAL fluid is received by the WMC laboratory, the BAL fluid will be
      divided by the WMC laboratory for all physician ordered clinical laboratory tests and for
      massively parallel sequencing research tests. This will ensure that sufficient BAL material
      is available for all clinical tests.

      5.3 The BAL fluid for research will be held by the WMC laboratory and picked up by research
      personnel for processing at New York Medical College Genomics Core Facility.

      5.4 The research portion will be further divided for isolation of viral, bacterial, and
      fungal nucleic acid isolation. A control sample of fluid used for the BAL will be prepared in
      parallel. Bacterial/fungal DNA and viral DNA and RNA will be isolated. Whole genome
      sequencing libraries will be generated and sequenced in batches on the Illumina MiSeq.

      FASTQ files will be demultiplexed and then aligned to microbial genomes using Phylosift.11
      DNA sequences present in both the patient and control samples will be discarded as
      contaminant. The preponderant organism(s) identified will be matched to the results of the
      culture based techniques used to verify the culture independent results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 15, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage concordance between massively paralleled sequencing (MPS) and standard microbiological technique results.</measure>
    <time_frame>10 days</time_frame>
    <description>Children, adolescents and young adult (CAYA) hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) subjects with clinical symptoms/indications will undergo bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL), with samples from those with sufficient BAL fluid yield (&gt;10ml) undergoing both massively paralleled sequencing and standard microbiological technique comparison.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Infection</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>massively paralleled sequencing</intervention_name>
    <description>Whole genome sequencing libraries will be generated and sequenced in batches on the Illumina MiSeq. FASTQ files will be demultiplexed and then aligned to microbial genomes using Phylosift.</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Extra BAL fluids will be sent to for massively parallel sequencing research tests at New York
      Medical College Genomics Core Facility.

      The research portion will be further divided for isolation of viral, bacterial, and fungal
      nucleic acid isolation. A control sample of fluid used for the BAL will be prepared in
      parallel. Bacterial/fungal DNA and viral DNA and RNA will be isolated. Whole genome
      sequencing libraries will be generated and sequenced in batches on the Illumina MiSeq.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients less than 30 years old who have had a hematopoietic stem cell transplantation and
        require a BAL for clinical diagnosis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  Patient age &lt; 30 years

          -  Recipient of an autologous or allogeneic stem cell transplant in the previous 365 days

          -  Requires a bronchoalveolar lavage for clinical indications

          -  Signed consent Exclusion criteria

          -  Lack of signed informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremy Rosenblum, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York Medical College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Will submit manuscript for peer-reviewed publication.</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Clinical Study Report (CSR)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>submit for publication Q4 2019</ipd_time_frame>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

