<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03992534</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19QC5168</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03992534</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The FLIP-1 Study: Vaginal Lactobacillus Supplementation in Women at High Risk of Preterm Birth</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility, Safety, Tolerance and Assessment of LACTIN-V Use in a Cohort of Pregnant Women at Risk of Preterm Birth</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Imperial College Healthcare NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preterm birth (PTB) is the primary cause of infant death worldwide. It has been shown that a
      vaginal microbiota deplete in Lactobacillus species is a risk factor for preterm labour.
      Conversely a vaginal microbiota dominated by Lactobacillus crispatus appears to be protective
      for these adverse outcomes. A wide range of 'over the counter' Lactobacillus spp. containing
      products targeted at 'vaginal health' and formulated for vaginal administration are
      available, but most of them do not contain vaginal species of Lactobacillus. The primary aim
      of this study is to determine whether vaginal supplementation with L. crispatus CTV-05 is
      associated with colonisation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pregnant women at Queen Charlotte's and Chelsea Hospital and St Mary's Hospital London who
      are defined as being at a higher than background risk for preterm labour will be recruited
      into this study. Women at risk of pre-term labour will include those with either previous
      LLETZ, previous preterm birth, previous second trimester pregnancy loss or a combination of
      these indications.

      As part of this interventional study, subjects will be offered supplementation with L.
      crispatus CTV-05. The preparation of LACTIN-V is administered vaginally using a specially
      designed applicator.

      The primary aim of this study is to determine whether vaginal supplementation with L.
      crispatus CTV-05 is associated with colonisation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 16, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of participants that demonstrate a change in vaginal colonisation during and following LACTIN-V use.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Microbiological effects of LACTIN-V by laboratory analysis, next generation sequencing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of participants with treatment related adverse events following LACTIN-V supplementation in pregnant women at high risk of preterm birth.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked about adverse events during clinical review and the safety profile will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of patients using LACTIN-V that go on to experience preterm birth, PPROM or cervical shortening.</measure>
    <time_frame>2-4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical outcomes of participants will be analysed, in accordance with colonisation results</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Preterm Labor</condition>
  <condition>Preterm Birth</condition>
  <condition>Preterm Premature Rupture of Membrane</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Incompetence</condition>
  <condition>Miscarriage in Second Trimester</condition>
  <condition>Miscarriage in Third Trimester</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LACTIN-V</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Name of Product: LACTIN-V (Lactobacillus crispatus CTV-05)
Dosage: LACTINV is a powder formulation of Lactobacillus crispatus CTV-05 provided in a prefilled vaginal applicator at a dose of 2 x 10^9 CFU of L. crispatus CTV-05. Route of Administration: LACTIN-V powder is administered vaginally using a specially designed applicator.
Formulation: LACTIN-V is supplied as a pre-filled, single-use applicator. Each applicator contains LACTIN-V powder at a dose of 2 x 10^9 CFU. The LACTIN-V powder formulation contains L. crispatus CTV-05 and a preservation matrix containing inactive excipients of non-animal origin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LACTIN-V</intervention_name>
    <description>Vaginal supplementation with L. crispatus CTV-05.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LACTIN-V</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactobacillus crispatus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women at risk of preterm labour

          -  Women referred to the prematurity clinic

          -  Women with previous LLETZ (large loop excision of the transformation zone)

          -  Women with previous preterm birth

          -  Women with previous second trimester loss

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV positive women

          -  Women who are unable to provide informed consent

          -  Women aged &lt;18

          -  Women receiving antibiotic treatment within 1 week of recruitment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Pregnant women</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Phillip Bennett, BSc PhD MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Phillip Bennett, BSc PhD MD</last_name>
    <phone>+442075942176</phone>
    <email>p.bennett@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David MacIntyre, BSc PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+442075942195</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Reproductive Developmental Biology, Hammersmith Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W12 0UQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Erna Bayar, MBBS BSc (Hons) MSc FHEA</last_name>
      <email>e.bayar@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>MacIntyre DA, Chandiramani M, Lee YS, Kindinger L, Smith A, Angelopoulos N, Lehne B, Arulkumaran S, Brown R, Teoh TG, Holmes E, Nicoholson JK, Marchesi JR, Bennett PR. The vaginal microbiome during pregnancy and the postpartum period in a European population. Sci Rep. 2015 Mar 11;5:8988. doi: 10.1038/srep08988.</citation>
    <PMID>25758319</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brown RG, Marchesi JR, Lee YS, Smith A, Lehne B, Kindinger LM, Terzidou V, Holmes E, Nicholson JK, Bennett PR, MacIntyre DA. Vaginal dysbiosis increases risk of preterm fetal membrane rupture, neonatal sepsis and is exacerbated by erythromycin. BMC Med. 2018 Jan 24;16(1):9. doi: 10.1186/s12916-017-0999-x.</citation>
    <PMID>29361936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kindinger LM, Bennett PR, Lee YS, Marchesi JR, Smith A, Cacciatore S, Holmes E, Nicholson JK, Teoh TG, MacIntyre DA. The interaction between vaginal microbiota, cervical length, and vaginal progesterone treatment for preterm birth risk. Microbiome. 2017 Jan 19;5(1):6. doi: 10.1186/s40168-016-0223-9.</citation>
    <PMID>28103952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kindinger LM, MacIntyre DA, Lee YS, Marchesi JR, Smith A, McDonald JA, Terzidou V, Cook JR, Lees C, Israfil-Bayli F, Faiza Y, Toozs-Hobson P, Slack M, Cacciatore S, Holmes E, Nicholson JK, Teoh TG, Bennett PR. Relationship between vaginal microbial dysbiosis, inflammation, and pregnancy outcomes in cervical cerclage. Sci Transl Med. 2016 Aug 3;8(350):350ra102. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.aag1026.</citation>
    <PMID>27488896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stapleton AE, Au-Yeung M, Hooton TM, Fredricks DN, Roberts PL, Czaja CA, Yarova-Yarovaya Y, Fiedler T, Cox M, Stamm WE. Randomized, placebo-controlled phase 2 trial of a Lactobacillus crispatus probiotic given intravaginally for prevention of recurrent urinary tract infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2011 May;52(10):1212-7. doi: 10.1093/cid/cir183. Epub 2011 Apr 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21498386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ravel J, Gajer P, Abdo Z, Schneider GM, Koenig SS, McCulle SL, Karlebach S, Gorle R, Russell J, Tacket CO, Brotman RM, Davis CC, Ault K, Peralta L, Forney LJ. Vaginal microbiome of reproductive-age women. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2011 Mar 15;108 Suppl 1:4680-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1002611107. Epub 2010 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>20534435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 28, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Preterm labour</keyword>
  <keyword>Preterm delivery</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaginal microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Next generation sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>Lactobacillus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obstetric Labor, Premature</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Spontaneous</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fetal Membranes, Premature Rupture</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Incompetence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rupture</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Informed Consent Form (ICF)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>Data will be available within 6 months of study completion</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>as study protocol</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

