<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03992898</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Survival Study Cohort(SSC001)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03992898</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nomogram Analysis for HBV Related Acute-on-chronic Liver Failure</brief_title>
  <official_title>Establishment and Validation of Prognostic Nomograms for HBV-related Acute-on-Chronic Liver Failure in South of China</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sun Yat-sen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sun Yat-sen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute-on-chronic liver failure (ACLF) is an acute deterioration of chronic liver diseases,
      which progresses rapidly, with a mortality rate of more than 50%.MELD score is used to
      evaluate the patients' condition. However, MELD score only concerned about the variables of
      total bilirubin, international normalize ratio (INR) and creatinine which is not enough to
      access ACLF patients' condition accurately.

      Scholars of US and China suggested to divided ACLF patients into 3 subgroups base on the
      different &quot;chronic liver disease&quot; . Type A ACLF patients have chronic liver disease without
      cirrhosis. Type B ACLF patients with compensated cirrhosis, while type C ACLF patients with
      decompensated cirrhosis. Currently, no studies have assessed the prognosis of different types
      of ACLF patients, especially for HBV-related ACLF patients.

      Investigators conducted a retrospective study which enrolls HBV-related ACLF patients between
      January 2010 and March 2018 in the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University.
      Clinical data, survival time and information regarding liver transplantation after enrolment
      were collected. A nomogram was formulated based on the results of multivariable Cox
      regression analysis. The performance of the nomogram was evaluated by the concordance index
      (C-index) and assessed by comparing nomogram-predicted vs observed Kaplan-Meier estimates of
      survival probability, and bootstraps with 1000 resamples were applied to these activities.
      Comparisons between the nomogram, MELD Score，MELD-Na Score and CTP Score in the entire
      population were performed and were tested by the C-index. A larger C-index indicated more
      accurate prognostic stratification.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute-on-chronic liver failure (ACLF) is an acute deterioration of chronic liver diseases,
      which progresses rapidly, with a mortality rate of more than 50%. Liver transplantation is
      the only therapy that has been proven beneficial, but the number of liver donor is limited.
      MELD score is used to evaluate the patients' condition before transplantation to decide who
      is in greatest need. However, MELD score only concerned about the variables of total
      bilirubin, international normalize ratio (INR) and creatinine. Other important valuables such
      as age, hepatic encephalopathy, and indexes of infection (e.g. white blood cell counts) were
      excluded. Many studies showed that application of MELD score only is not enough to access the
      liver failure patients' condition accurately.

      Both APASL and Chinese Society of Infectious Disease considered the &quot;chronic liver disease&quot;
      included chronic liver disease with/without cirrhosis. Scholars of US and China suggested to
      divided ACLF patients into 3 subgroups base on the different &quot;chronic liver disease&quot; . Type A
      ACLF patients have chronic liver disease without cirrhosis. Type B ACLF patients with
      compensated cirrhosis, while type C ACLF patients with decompensated cirrhosis. Currently, no
      studies have assessed the prognosis of different types of ACLF patients, especially for
      HBV-related ACLF patients.

      Investigators conducted a retrospective study which enrolls HBV-related ACLF patients between
      January 2010 and March 2018 in the Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University.
      Clinical data of demographic data, admission causes, cirrhosis complications, and
      precipitating events associated with acute decompensation or severe liver injury, laboratory
      measurements (e.g., serum albumin, sodium, alanine aminotransferase, aspartate
      aminotransferase, total bilirubin, INR and creatinine levels), mean arterial pressure, HBV
      infection biomarkers, HBV-DNA levels, antiviral treatment for HBV (nucleoside analogues,
      including lamivudine, adefovir, entecavir, telbivudine and tenofovir, within 6 months prior
      to and during hospitalisation), and prognosis would be collected. Survival time and
      information regarding liver transplantation after enrolment were also collected. A nomogram
      was formulated based on the results of multivariable Cox regression analysis. The performance
      of the nomogram was evaluated by the concordance index (C-index) and assessed by comparing
      nomogram-predicted vs observed Kaplan-Meier estimates of survival probability, and bootstraps
      with 1000 resamples were applied to these activities. Comparisons between the nomogram, MELD
      Score, MELD-Na Score and CTP Score in the entire population were performed and were tested by
      the C-index. A larger C-index indicated more accurate prognostic stratification.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>survival status</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be follow-up for 90 days until death or received liver transplantation. And survival days of each patients will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2739</enrollment>
  <condition>Liver Failure</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic hepatitis cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort, patients were defined as type A acute-on-chronic liver failure (ACLF) patients who have chronic liver disease but without cirrhosis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cirrhosis cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>In this cohort, patients were defined as type B and type C ACLF patients with cirrhosis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No special intervention was suitable for this observational study</intervention_name>
    <description>Investegators divided patients into 3 corhort according to the liver condition at enrollment (i.e. chronic liver disease, compemsated cirrhosis, decompensated cirrhosis). All patients received standard medical treatment, including nutritional supplementation; administration of human serum albumin, fresh frozen plasma, antivirus treatment and appropriate treatment for complications. No special intervention was suitable for this observational study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic hepatitis cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cirrhosis cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The investigators will enroll a retrospective cohort of HBV related acute-on-chronic liver
        failure patients who were admitted to The Third affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen
        University from January 2010 to March 2018.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years; Serum total bilirubin ≥ 10 mg/dl; International normalized ratio≥1.5
             or prothrombin activity &lt;40%; Complicated within 4 weeks by ascites and/or
             encephalopathy; Positive serum hepatitis B surface antigen for more than 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Drug induce liver diseases; Autoimmune liver diseases; Alcohol or drug abusers
             (average alcohol consumption &gt;40g/d for men, &gt;20g/d for women); Liver diseases caused
             by metabolic factors; Superinfection with hepatitis A, C, D, E viruses; Infected by
             HIV virus; Pregnancy or lactation; Liver failure caused by recurrence of hepatitis b
             after transplantation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bingliang Lin, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Third Affiliated Hospital, Sun Yat-Sen University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guangzhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510630</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lin B, Pan CQ, Xie D, Xie J, Xie S, Zhang X, Wu B, Lin C, Gao Z. Entecavir improves the outcome of acute-on-chronic liver failure due to the acute exacerbation of chronic hepatitis B. Hepatol Int. 2013 Jun;7(2):460-7. doi: 10.1007/s12072-012-9415-y. Epub 2013 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26201778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duseja A, Choudhary NS, Gupta S, Dhiman RK, Chawla Y. APACHE II score is superior to SOFA, CTP and MELD in predicting the short-term mortality in patients with acute-on-chronic liver failure (ACLF). J Dig Dis. 2013 Sep;14(9):484-90. doi: 10.1111/1751-2980.12074.</citation>
    <PMID>23692973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng Y, Qi X, Tang S, Deng H, Li J, Ning Z, Dai J, Hou F, Zhao J, Wang R, Guo X. Child-Pugh, MELD, and ALBI scores for predicting the in-hospital mortality in cirrhotic patients with acute-on-chronic liver failure. Expert Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2016 Aug;10(8):971-80. doi: 10.1080/17474124.2016.1177788. Epub 2016 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27070325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moreau R, Jalan R, Gines P, Pavesi M, Angeli P, Cordoba J, Durand F, Gustot T, Saliba F, Domenicali M, Gerbes A, Wendon J, Alessandria C, Laleman W, Zeuzem S, Trebicka J, Bernardi M, Arroyo V; CANONIC Study Investigators of the EASL–CLIF Consortium. Acute-on-chronic liver failure is a distinct syndrome that develops in patients with acute decompensation of cirrhosis. Gastroenterology. 2013 Jun;144(7):1426-37, 1437.e1-9. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2013.02.042. Epub 2013 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23474284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jalan R, Pavesi M, Saliba F, Amorós A, Fernandez J, Holland-Fischer P, Sawhney R, Mookerjee R, Caraceni P, Moreau R, Ginès P, Durand F, Angeli P, Alessandria C, Laleman W, Trebicka J, Samuel D, Zeuzem S, Gustot T, Gerbes AL, Wendon J, Bernardi M, Arroyo V; CANONIC Study Investigators; EASL-CLIF Consortium. The CLIF Consortium Acute Decompensation score (CLIF-C ADs) for prognosis of hospitalised cirrhotic patients without acute-on-chronic liver failure. J Hepatol. 2015 Apr;62(4):831-40. doi: 10.1016/j.jhep.2014.11.012. Epub 2014 Nov 22. Erratum in: J Hepatol. 2015 Jul;63(1):291.</citation>
    <PMID>25463539</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Silva PE, Fayad L, Lazzarotto C, Ronsoni MF, Bazzo ML, Colombo BS, Dantas-Correa EB, Narciso-Schiavon JL, Schiavon LL. Single-centre validation of the EASL-CLIF consortium definition of acute-on-chronic liver failure and CLIF-SOFA for prediction of mortality in cirrhosis. Liver Int. 2015 May;35(5):1516-23. doi: 10.1111/liv.12597. Epub 2014 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24840673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jalan R, Yurdaydin C, Bajaj JS, Acharya SK, Arroyo V, Lin HC, Gines P, Kim WR, Kamath PS; World Gastroenterology Organization Working Party. Toward an improved definition of acute-on-chronic liver failure. Gastroenterology. 2014 Jul;147(1):4-10. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2014.05.005. Epub 2014 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24853409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luo Y, Xu Y, Li M, Xie Y, Gong G. A new multiparameter integrated MELD model for prognosis of HBV-related acute-on-chronic liver failure. Medicine (Baltimore). 2016 Aug;95(34):e4696. doi: 10.1097/MD.0000000000004696.</citation>
    <PMID>27559979</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shi KQ, Cai YJ, Lin Z, Dong JZ, Wu JM, Wang XD, Song M, Wang YQ, Chen YP. Development and validation of a prognostic nomogram for acute-on-chronic hepatitis B liver failure. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2017 Feb;32(2):497-505. doi: 10.1111/jgh.13502.</citation>
    <PMID>27490495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 2, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 2, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 6, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sun Yat-sen University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lin Bingliang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatic Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>End Stage Liver Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute-On-Chronic Liver Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

