<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03994120</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>190114</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>19-N-0114</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03994120</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modulating the Hippocampal and Striatal Memory Networks With rTMS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Modulating the Hippocampal and Striatal Memory Networks With rTMS</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      People have 2 memory systems. One helps them learn skills and the other helps them learn
      facts. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) uses electronic currents to
      activate brain cells. This can make small changes in how brain systems operate. Researchers
      will use rTMS to change how memory systems work and to see if changing one system causes the
      other to change too. This could help find ways to improve learning and memory in people with
      memory disorders.

      Objective:

      To learn how different memory systems work with each other.

      Eligibility:

      Healthy adults ages 18-40 who are not pregnant

      Design:

      Potential participants will be screened with a neurological exam if they haven t had one from
      NINDS in the past 2 years. They may have urine tests.

      Eligible participants will have 5-10 visits at NIH. Each visit will last 1-6 hours. Visits
      1-4 will each take place 1 day apart.

      At visit 1, participants will have an MRI and take memory tests. For MRI, they will lie on a
      table that slides in and out of a cylinder that takes pictures of their brain. They will also
      have rTMS. For rTMS, a metal coil is held on their scalp. Brief electrical currents pass
      through the coil.

      At visits 2 and 3, participants will have rTMS.

      At visit 4, participants will have an MRI and do memory tests.

      About a week later, participants will have visit 5. They will have an MRI and do memory
      tests. Participants may be asked to have more visits if any technical problems occur.
      Participants involvement will last 2 weeks.

      ...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      The Behavioral Neurology Unit studies the human brain systems underlying learning and
      adaptation with the ultimate goal of finding interventions to make these processes more
      efficient. We are interested in whether repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS)
      can alter functional connectivity (FC) and behavioral efficiency in two memory networks in
      the brain: the hippocampal network, which supports the storage and retrieval of recallable
      facts, concepts, and events, and the striatal network, which supports the storage and
      retrieval of skills and habits. Additionally, because these networks interact behaviorally
      and can interfere with each other, an important question is whether neuromodulation of one
      network changes connectivity and efficiency in the other network. Pilot data from our group
      suggest that exogenous stimulation of one network causes it to expand its range of FC and
      co-opt resources from the other, which is a potential mechanism for the observed behavioral
      interaction. This study is designed to test a) whether rTMS- modulates within-network FC and
      memory supported by that network, and b) whether this also causes FC and behavioral changes
      in the other network.

      Study population: Healthy Volunteers

      Design

      This study contains four between-subjects experiments and is a mixed inter-/intra subject
      design. Experiment 1 will use nominally excitatory stimulation targeting the hippocampal
      network to increase FC within the hippocampal network. We also expect to increase FC between
      the hippocampal and striatal networks, increased declarative memory, and a possible decrease
      in procedural, learning. Experiment 2 will use excitatory stimulation targeted to the
      striatal network. We expect this to cause stronger within- network FC in the striatal
      network, increased FC between the hippocampus and the striatal network and concomitant
      behavioral effects. Experiments 3 and 4 will be similar except that we will target nominally
      inhibitory stimulation to these networks and look for the inverse results. FC will be
      measured under resting and task-activated conditions and active rTMS will be compared to
      vertex sham.

      Outcome measures

      The primary outcome measure is the change in FC produced by rTMS within the targeted network.
      Between-network FC changes and corresponding memory changes will be secondary outcomes.
      Exploratory measures will include correlations between individual cognitive differences
      (questionnaires and NIH Toolbox scores), and our primary and secondary outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 26, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2029</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2029</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional Connectivity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hrs.</time_frame>
    <description>Pre-to-Post rTMS differences in rsFC and tbFC within the targeted memory network</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Memory Task Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Outcomes include percentage of correct/optimal responses and reaction time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Normal Behavioral Patterns</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motor Cortex rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Motor Cortex rTMS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PPC rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PPC rTMS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>vertex rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>vertex rTMS</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTMS</intervention_name>
    <description>Altering the connectivity of trans-synaptic pathways</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motor Cortex rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PPC rTMS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>vertex rTMS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18-40 (inclusive)

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Any current major neurological or psychiatric disorder such as (but not limited to)
             stroke, Parkinson disease, Alzheimer disease, schizophrenia or major depression

          -  History of seizure

          -  Medications acting on the central nervous system, such as those that lowers the
             seizure threshold such as neuroleptics, beta lactams, isoniazid, metronidazole;
             benzodiazepines, tricyclic or other antidepressants; or prescription stimulants.

          -  Ferromagnetic metal in the cranial cavity or eye, implanted neural stimulator,
             cochlear implant, or ocular foreign body

          -  Implanted cardiac pacemaker or auto-defibrillator or pump

          -  Non-removable body piercing

          -  Claustrophobia

          -  Inability to lie supine for 2 hours

          -  Pregnancy, or plans to become pregnant during the study.

          -  Members of the NINDS BNU

          -  Subjects that received rTMS under protocol 17-N-0055 are excluded in order avoid
             learning effects from previously being exposed to the same behavioral tasks

          -  Subjects who have contraindications to MRI (we will follow the NMR Center guidelines
             for MR safety). Some of the exclusions are:

               -  Have non-MRI compatible metal in the body, such as a cardiac pacemaker, brain
                  stimulator, shrapnel, surgical metal, clips in the brain or on blood vessels,
                  cochlear implants, artificial heart valves or ferromagnetic fragments in the eye
                  or oral cavity as these make having an MRI unsafe.

               -  Unable to lie flat on the back for the expected length of the experiment (2
                  hours).

               -  Have an abnormality on the brain imaging or neurologic examination not related to
                  the diagnosis.

               -  Non-removable body piercing or

               -  Pregnancy (urine pregnancy test)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric M Wassermann, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia M Fioriti</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 402-6921</phone>
    <email>cynthia.fioriti@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2019-N-0114.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 29, 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Memory Systems</keyword>
  <keyword>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Efficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>Hippocampal and Striatal Memory Networks</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

