<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03996499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TRIPLESTRESS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03996499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Myocardial Perfusion, Coronary Flow Reserve and Kinetic Analysis During Dobutamine Stress Echocardiography</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIPLESTRESS</acronym>
  <official_title>Myocardial Perfusion, Coronary Flow Reserve and Kinetic Analysis During Dobutamine Stress Echocardiography</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stress echocardiography is a screening test for coronary heart disease that already has good
      sensitivity and specificity (both around 70%). This examination is mainly offered to stable
      patients, consulting externally, in order to detect ischemic heart disease in the same way as
      would a myocardial scintigraphy or MRI stress. This examination is an echocardiographic
      modality consisting in visualizing and analyzing the modifications of the contraction of the
      cardiac muscle during a stress constituted by an effort or by injection of certain drugs.
      Stress echocardiography is performed by injection of drugs to reproduce the conditions of the
      effort. The products used to perform this examination are initially an intravenous infusion
      of dobutamine, atropine whose effect is to increase the heart rate, and in a second time, an
      intravenous infusion of beta-blockers or a bradycardic calcium channel blocker at the end of
      the procedure whose effect is to slow down the heart rate.

      The use of echographic contrast medium, allowing a better visibility, is recommended for the
      realization of a stress ultrasound, since the echogenicity is judged insufficient on two
      segments (segmentation of the left ventricle in 17 segments).

      The analysis of dobutamine stress echocardiography currently relies solely on the analysis of
      segmental kinetics, namely the quality of the thickening of the endocardium. When segmental
      kinetics are abnormal, patients benefit from a coronary CT scan or coronary angiography to
      visualize all the coronary arteries and to check whether there is a narrowing of the
      arteries.

      Moreover, stress echocardiography performed using a contrast medium makes it possible to
      analyze two other indices in addition to segmental kinetics.

      Thus, the second parameter that can be analyzed corresponds to the Coronary Flow Reserve
      measurement, thanks to the easy identification of the Doppler flow in the anterior
      interventricular at rest and peak of dobutamine. The coronal reserve is well validated with
      adenosine, but much less well known under dobutamine.

      The third parameter that can be analyzed is myocardial perfusion. By using appropriate
      settings, it is possible to see the microbubbles in the thickness of the myocardium. These
      bubbles are then destroyed by an ultrasonic flash of high mechanical index. This results in
      the destruction of all intra-myocardial bubbles. The analysis of the myocardial perfusion is
      based on the rate of reappearance of these bubbles (through the coronary arteries) at rest
      and peak stress. In case of significant stenosis or coronary occlusion, there is a delay or
      complete absence of perfusion in the territory concerned.

      Joint analysis of segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion has already
      been described with adenosine, but not with dobutamine. Studies in the literature suggest
      that the analysis of coronary reserve on the one hand, and myocardial perfusion on the other
      hand would increase the sensitivity and specificity of the examination. In addition, other
      studies suggest that among the tests considered normal for segmental kinetics analysis, there
      are patients with myocardial perfusion abnormality and / or coronary reserve abnormality that
      strike (s) on prognosis (alteration of the coronary microcirculation).

      This is why it seems interesting to compare the results of these 3 indices obtained during
      stress echocardiography under dobutamine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 20, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 24, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The course of the examination corresponds to the welcome of the patient, the search for contraindications and the performance of the stress ultrasound. During this stress ultrasound, the 3 indices (segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion) will be analyzed. The duration of the ultrasound is not lengthened (examination time: 20 minutes).
The evaluation of the myocardial perfusion is carried out thanks to the use of the &quot;flash&quot;, modality not being part of the usual care.
Indeed, during the examination, the power of the probe will be increased to evaluate the myocardial perfusion. The bubbles of the contrast medium are destroyed by applying a &quot;flash&quot;, that is to say a transient increase in the power of the ultrasonic beam. Systole after systole, on a recorded loop, the filling rate of the myocardium, which depends on the myocardial blood flow, is analyzed. The evaluation of the infusion is visual and qualitative.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of the combined analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>This is to measure the sensitivity of segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion compared to simple segmental kinetic analysis alone to detect coronary artery disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of the combined analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>This is to measure the specificity of segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion compared to simple segmental kinetic analysis alone to detect coronary artery disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Year 2</time_frame>
    <description>This is to measure rate of cardiovascular mortality, hospitalization for acute coronary syndromes or emergency coronary revascularization in patients with negative examination on 1, 2 or 3 index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stress echocardiography</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The course of the examination corresponds to the welcome of the patient, the search for contraindications and the performance of the stress ultrasound. During this stress ultrasound, the 3 indices (segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion) will be analyzed. The duration of the ultrasound is not lengthened (examination time: 20 minutes).
The evaluation of the myocardial perfusion is carried out thanks to the use of the &quot;flash&quot;, modality not being part of the usual care.
Indeed, during the examination, the power of the probe will be increased to evaluate the myocardial perfusion. The bubbles of the contrast medium are destroyed by applying a &quot;flash&quot;, that is to say a transient increase in the power of the ultrasonic beam. Systole after systole, on a recorded loop, the filling rate of the myocardium, which depends on the myocardial blood flow, is analyzed. The evaluation of the infusion is visual and qualitative.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Stress echocardiography</intervention_name>
    <description>The course of the examination corresponds to the welcome of the patient, the search for contraindications and the performance of the stress ultrasound. During this stress ultrasound, the 3 indices (segmental kinetics, coronary reserve and myocardial perfusion) will be analyzed. The duration of the ultrasound is not lengthened (examination time: 20 minutes).
The evaluation of the myocardial perfusion is carried out thanks to the use of the &quot;flash&quot;, modality not being part of the usual care.
Indeed, during the examination, the power of the probe will be increased to evaluate the myocardial perfusion. The bubbles of the contrast medium are destroyed by applying a &quot;flash&quot;, that is to say a transient increase in the power of the ultrasonic beam. Systole after systole, on a recorded loop, the filling rate of the myocardium, which depends on the myocardial blood flow, is analyzed. The evaluation of the infusion is visual and qualitative.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stress echocardiography</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient whose age ≥ 18 years

          -  Patient referred for stress echography in the context of a cardiovascular assessment
             or for suspicion of coronary disease

          -  Patient whose echogenicity requires the use of an ultrasound contrast product
             (SONOVUE®) according to European Society of Cardiology recommendations

          -  Patient affiliated with a health insurance plan

          -  Francophone patient

          -  Patient able to give free, informed and written oral consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  People in emergency situations (recent acute coronary syndromes) who can not express
             their prior consent

          -  Patient with an allergy to any of the products used

          -  Patient for whom it is impossible to obtain a theoretical maximum frequency (continued
             beta-blocker treatment, chronotropic insufficiency)

          -  Pregnant woman

          -  Patient under tutorship or curatorship

          -  Patient deprived of liberty
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe P GARCON, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint Joseph</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>GARCON Philippe, MD</last_name>
    <phone>0144127693</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>pgarcon@hpsj.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Helene BEAUSSIER, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0144127883</phone>
    <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
    <email>crc@hpsj.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Paris Saint-Joseph</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Helene BEAUSSIER, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>0144127883</phone>
      <phone_ext>+33</phone_ext>
      <email>crc@hpsj.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

