<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03999892</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00194122</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50MH115842</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03999892</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adapted ACHIEVE Curriculum for Community Mental Health Settings</brief_title>
  <official_title>ACHIEVE-D Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In light of the obesity epidemic in persons with serious mental illness (SMI), there is an
      urgent need to scale-up behavioral interventions that have demonstrated efficacy in the
      clinical trial setting such as the intervention in the National Institute of Mental Health
      (NIMH)-funded Achieving Healthy Lifestyles in Psychiatric Rehabilitation (ACHIEVE) trial. To
      increase ease of adoption and sustained implementation of ACHIEVE in community mental health
      programs, the format needs to be adapted for delivery by community mental health staff. Based
      on the investigators' experience conducting the ACHIEVE trial, this study team had modified
      the ACHIEVE intervention into a new ACHIEVE curriculum appropriate for community mental
      health settings. Therefore, the investigators will pilot test 8 weeks of this curriculum in a
      community-based psychiatric rehabilitation program (PRP) to determine whether this format is
      acceptable to participating PRP consumers with SMI as well as PRP staff and peer leaders.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prevalence of obesity is significantly elevated and a leading cause of preventable death in
      people with serious mental illness (SMI) through its effects on other cardiovascular disease
      (CVD) risk factors and CVD. Behavioral interventions targeting changes in diet and exercise
      need to be tailored to the needs of people with SMI, such as memory impairment and limited
      executive function. The NIMH-funded Achieving Healthy Lifestyles in Psychiatric
      Rehabilitation (ACHIEVE) trial tested a behavioral weight-loss intervention for persons with
      SMI and demonstrated clinically significant weight loss. In light of the obesity epidemic in
      persons with SMI, there is an urgent need to scale-up interventions like ACHIEVE. To increase
      ease of adoption and sustained implementation of ACHIEVE in community mental health programs,
      the format needs to be adapted for delivery by community mental health staff. Based on the
      investigators' experience conducting the ACHIEVE trial, this study team had modified the
      ACHIEVE intervention into a new ACHIEVE curriculum appropriate for community mental health
      settings. Therefore, the investigators will pilot test 8 weeks of this curriculum in a
      community-based psychiatric rehabilitation program (PRP) to determine whether this format is
      acceptable to participating PRP consumers with SMI as well as PRP staff and peer leaders.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 24, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Consumer satisfaction with ACHIEVE curriculum as assessed by two open-ended questions at focus group discussion</measure>
    <time_frame>One week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will ask two open-ended questions during a focus group discussion with consumers to determine their satisfaction with the curriculum. Responses will be categorized into various levels of satisfaction.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Consumer attitudes towards the ACHIEVE curriculum as assessed by five open-ended questions at focus group discussion</measure>
    <time_frame>One week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will ask five open-ended questions during a focus group discussion with consumers to determine their attitudes towards the curriculum and its components. Responses will be categorized into various attitudes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Staff attitudes towards the ACHIEVE curriculum as assessed by seven open-ended questions at focus group discussion</measure>
    <time_frame>One-week post-intervention</time_frame>
    <description>We will ask seven open-ended questions during a focus group discussion with staff to determine their attitudes towards the curriculum and its components. Responses will be categorized into various attitudes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Mental Disorders, Severe</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Consumers with SMI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Consumers with serious mental illness who attend a psychiatric rehabilitation program (PRP) will participate in a group-based diet and physical activity program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Staff at PRP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Staff and peer leaders who work at a psychiatric rehabilitation program (PRP) will observe sessions of a group-based diet and physical activity program for consumers with SMI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ACHIEVE</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will test two modules of the adapted video-assisted curriculum format of 45 to 60-minute multipurpose classes, which will include a segment on group weight management (~20-30 minutes) and group exercise (~20-30 minutes). Within each module, the group weight management topic varies by week, and within each week the content of the three weight management groups builds gradually and is purposely repeated. Within each module, the group exercise classes will focus on mild to moderate intensity aerobic exercise using an exercise video. In this pilot study, a trained study interventionist will deliver the ACHIEVE-D curriculum.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Consumers with SMI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Staff at PRP</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  aged 18 or older

          -  consumers at Prologue psychiatric rehabilitation program

          -  expected to be in the rehabilitation program for at least 6 months after enrollment

          -  able to attend the intervention classes 3 days per week

          -  able and willing to give informed consent and participate in the intervention

          -  have a body mass index (BMI) over 25 kg/m2

          -  be interested in losing weight

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  any underlying medical conditions that could seriously reduce life expectancy, ability
             to participate in the study, or for which dietary change or physical activity may be
             contraindicated and/or require medical supervision by a physician (e.g.,
             medication-dependent diabetes mellitus, cancer or malignant tumor, lung disease
             requiring supplemental oxygen, dementia or cognitive impairment, consumption of more
             than 14 drinks per week, eating disorders, angina, or diagnosis in the last 12 months
             of myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, transient ischemic attack or
             stroke, liver disease or kidney disease)

          -  women who are pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  individuals with an inability to walk to participate in exercise class as demonstrated
             by walking up and down 2 flights of stairs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gail Daumit</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Daumit GL, Dickerson FB, Wang NY, Dalcin A, Jerome GJ, Anderson CA, Young DR, Frick KD, Yu A, Gennusa JV 3rd, Oefinger M, Crum RM, Charleston J, Casagrande SS, Guallar E, Goldberg RW, Campbell LM, Appel LJ. A behavioral weight-loss intervention in persons with serious mental illness. N Engl J Med. 2013 Apr 25;368(17):1594-602. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1214530. Epub 2013 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23517118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 27, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

