<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03990714</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HUTorrecardenas</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03990714</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intracorporeal Vs Extracorporeal Anastomosis in Laparoscopic Right Hemicolectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>IVEA</acronym>
  <official_title>Intracorporeal Vs Extracorporeal Anastomosis in Patients Undergoing Laparoscopic Right Hemicolectomy: a Multicenter Randomized Clinical Trial (The IVEA-study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor- Investigator MD Ángel Reina Duarte. HUTorrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator BA Francisco Rubio Gil. HU Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator MD Elisabet Vidaña Márquez. HU Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator MD Juan Manuel García Torrecillas. HU Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator Rocío Torres Fernández. HU Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator MD Almudena Moreno Serrano. Hospital Inmaculada. Huercal-Overa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator MD Pedro Moya Forcén. HU Torrecárdenas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sponsor-Investigator MD Jorge Alejandro Benavides Buleje. HU Reina Sofía</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Torrecárdenas</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective. The aim of this study was to evaluate short-term outcomes of performing
      intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis in laparoscopic right hemicolectomy for
      right colon neoplasm. Background. Despite advances in laparoscopic approach in colorectal
      surgery and the clear benefit of this approach over open surgery, the technical difficulty in
      performing intracorporeal anastomosis causes certain groups continue performing it
      extracorporeally in right colon surgery.

      Methods. This study was a prospective multicenter randomized trial with two parallel groups
      being done intracorporeal anastomosis (IA) or extracorporeal anastomosis (EA) in laparoscopic
      right hemicolectomy for right colon neoplasm, carried out between January 2016 and December
      2018.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Right hemicolectomy using a minimally invasive technique allows for an earlier recovery, with
      less postoperative pain and less hospital stay. After right hemicolectomy, the ileocolic
      anastomosis is not performed &quot;naturally&quot; as is habitually done in low anterior resections or
      sigmoidectomies. There is, therefore, no standardization in the reconstruction technique,
      with two possibilities: intracorporeal and extracorporeal anastomosis.

      The intracorporeal anastomosis allows proper visualization of it, ensuring adequate
      conformation (absence of rotation or traction), in addition allowing the closure of the mesos
      and avoiding the possible appearance of internal hernia, also allowing to choose the location
      and length of the incision necessary for the extraction of the piece. On the other hand, it
      is a difficult technique that requires high training in advanced laparoscopy.

      The extracorporeal anastomosis is performed by extracting both ends (terminal ileum and
      transverse colon) through the incision through which the piece is obtained, and the
      anastomosis is performed. It does not require, therefore, an important training in
      intracorporeal sutures. On the contrary, it forces to make the abdominal incision in the area
      that allows the extraction of said ends. In obese patients it can be difficult since the
      mesos are short and do not allow their extraction easilywith ,so sometimes, it forces
      excessive traction. In addition, intestinal rotations during the anastomosis may go
      unnoticed.

      Although there are currently defenders of both techniques, the extracorporeal anastomosis is
      currently the most performed in our environment and will be used as a reference treatment in
      the present study.

      Numerous studies have been published comparing both techniques. A very recent meta-analysis,
      including 12 non-randomized comparative studies with 1492 patients, concluded that
      intracorporeal anastomosis is associated with less morbidity and a reduction in hospital
      stay, suggesting a faster recovery. To date, no well-designed, prospective, randomized and
      randomized study exists in the literature. We believe it is necessary, therefore, to carry
      out a project that compares both surgical techniques in the treatment of right colon cancer
      and assess which is associated with a lower postoperative morbidity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The IVEA-study is a prospective multicenter randomized trial with two parallel groups being done IA or EA in laparoscopic right hemicolectomy for right colon neoplasia.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In patients with right colon cancer, laparoscopic right hemicolectomy with intracorporeal anastomosis presents less perioperative morbidity than extracorporeal anastomosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare perioperative morbidity between laparoscopic right hemicolectomy with intracorporeal anastomosis versus extracorporeal anastomosis within 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical time</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours</time_frame>
    <description>o evaluate the difference in surgical time between right hemicolectomy with intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Quantify, by means of the Visual-Analogue Scale (VAS: is determined by measuring the distance (mm) on the 10-cm line between the &quot;no pain&quot; anchor and the patient's mark, providing a range of scores from 0-100. A higher score indicates greater pain intensity. Based on the distribution of pain VAS scores in post- surgical patients who described their postoperative pain intensity as none, mild, moderate, or severe, the following cut points on the pain VAS have been recommended: no pain (0-4 mm), mild pain(5-44 mm), moderate pain (45-74 mm), and severe pain (75-100 mm)), postoperative pain 24 hours after surgery and the day of hospital discharge, and determine which of the two laparoscopic right hemicolectomy techniques produces less pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dehiscence</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate and compare the rate of anastomotic dehiscence in both groups of anastomoses up to 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the infection rate of the surgical site in both groups up to 30 days after surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>180 days</time_frame>
    <description>o compare the difference of days of hospital stay in both groups of anastomoses.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">168</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Surgery</condition>
  <condition>Anastomotic Leak</condition>
  <condition>Colectomy</condition>
  <condition>Laparoscopy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intracorporeal anastomosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The specimen was preferentially extracted via a small Pfannenstiel-type incision with the protection of an Alexis Wound Protector (Applied Medical, Rancho Santa Margarita, California, USA). The incision for the extraction of the right colon is sutured in two layers by absorbable suture. The ileum was held by the assistant to prevent rotation of its mesentery. A stay suture was applied 10 cm proximal and distal to the stapled ends of the terminal ileum and colon, respectively, and then held by the assistant. An enterotomy and colotomy were made sharply at the antimesenteric corner of the staple lines. An isoperistaltic side-to-side anastomosis was fashioned with a 60-mm laparoscopic stapler. A 2-0 double-barbed suture was used to close the enterocolotomy, in two planes (the first submucosal, and the second sero-serous). The mesenteric defect and the mesocolon after the construction of either type of anastomosis were not closed. Drains were not used routinely.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Extracorporeal anastomosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mobilized colon was externalized preferentially via a transverse or midline incision with the protection of an Alexis Wound Protector (Applied Medical, Rancho Santa Margarita, California, USA). A stay suture was applied 10 cm proximal and distal to the stapled ends of the terminal ileum and colon. An enterotomy and colotomy were made sharply at the antimesenteric corner of the staple lines. An isoperistaltic side-to-side anastomosis was fashioned with a 60-mm laparoscopic stapler. A 2-0 double-barbed suture was used to close the enterocolotomy, in two planes (the first submucosal, and the second sero-serous). The mesenteric defect and the mesocolon after the construction of either type of anastomosis were not closed.The incision for the extraction of the right colon and the realization of the anastomosis is sutured in two layers by absorbable suture. Drains were not used routinely.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Right hemicolectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>It is the resection of the right colon by a tumor and the reconstruction by an ileocolic anastomosis: intracorporeal or extracorporeal</description>
    <arm_group_label>Extracorporeal anastomosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intracorporeal anastomosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients had to be 18 years of age or over, to be programmed for laparoscopic
             surgery for right colon neoplasm and provide a signed written consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients who do not meet all the inclusion criteria were excluded. The other
             exclusion criteria included the need for emergency surgery, renal failure defined by
             haemodialysis, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis, T4 tumor invading adjacent organs,
             synchronous colorectal neoplasm, metastasis or carcinomatosis at diagnosis, bowel
             obstruction, psychiatric disorders or contraindication for laparoscopic approach.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manuel Ferrer-Marquez</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Colorectal Surgeon</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Ward E, Hao Y, Xu J, Thun MJ. Cancer statistics, 2009. CA Cancer J Clin. 2009 Jul-Aug;59(4):225-49. doi: 10.3322/caac.20006. Epub 2009 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>19474385</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bilimoria KY, Palis B, Stewart AK, Bentrem DJ, Freel AC, Sigurdson ER, Talamonti MS, Ko CY. Impact of tumor location on nodal evaluation for colon cancer. Dis Colon Rectum. 2008 Feb;51(2):154-61. doi: 10.1007/s10350-007-9114-2. Epub 2008 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18172729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le Voyer TE, Sigurdson ER, Hanlon AL, Mayer RJ, Macdonald JS, Catalano PJ, Haller DG. Colon cancer survival is associated with increasing number of lymph nodes analyzed: a secondary survey of intergroup trial INT-0089. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Aug 1;21(15):2912-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12885809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobs M, Verdeja JC, Goldstein HS. Minimally invasive colon resection (laparoscopic colectomy). Surg Laparosc Endosc. 1991 Sep;1(3):144-50.</citation>
    <PMID>1688289</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colon Cancer Laparoscopic or Open Resection Study Group, Buunen M, Veldkamp R, Hop WC, Kuhry E, Jeekel J, Haglind E, Påhlman L, Cuesta MA, Msika S, Morino M, Lacy A, Bonjer HJ. Survival after laparoscopic surgery versus open surgery for colon cancer: long-term outcome of a randomised clinical trial. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Jan;10(1):44-52. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(08)70310-3. Epub 2008 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>19071061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hazebroek EJ; Color Study Group. COLOR: a randomized clinical trial comparing laparoscopic and open resection for colon cancer. Surg Endosc. 2002 Jun;16(6):949-53. Epub 2002 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>12163961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jayne DG, Guillou PJ, Thorpe H, Quirke P, Copeland J, Smith AM, Heath RM, Brown JM; UK MRC CLASICC Trial Group. Randomized trial of laparoscopic-assisted resection of colorectal carcinoma: 3-year results of the UK MRC CLASICC Trial Group. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Jul 20;25(21):3061-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17634484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lacy AM, García-Valdecasas JC, Delgado S, Castells A, Taurá P, Piqué JM, Visa J. Laparoscopy-assisted colectomy versus open colectomy for treatment of non-metastatic colon cancer: a randomised trial. Lancet. 2002 Jun 29;359(9325):2224-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12103285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy GD, Heise C, Rajamanickam V, Harms B, Foley EF. Laparoscopy decreases postoperative complication rates after abdominal colectomy: results from the national surgical quality improvement program. Ann Surg. 2009 Apr;249(4):596-601. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31819ec903.</citation>
    <PMID>19300230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu Q, Jin C, Hu T, Wei M, Wang Z. Intracorporeal Versus Extracorporeal Anastomosis in Laparoscopic Right Colectomy: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. J Laparoendosc Adv Surg Tech A. 2017 Apr;27(4):348-357. doi: 10.1089/lap.2016.0485. Epub 2016 Oct 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27768552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Milone M, Elmore U, Di Salvo E, Delrio P, Bucci L, Ferulano GP, Napolitano C, Angiolini MR, Bracale U, Clemente M, D'ambra M, Luglio G, Musella M, Pace U, Rosati R, Milone F. Intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis. Results from a multicentre comparative study on 512 right-sided colorectal cancers. Surg Endosc. 2015 Aug;29(8):2314-20. doi: 10.1007/s00464-014-3950-7. Epub 2014 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25414066</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ricci C, Casadei R, Alagna V, Zani E, Taffurelli G, Pacilio CA, Minni F. A critical and comprehensive systematic review and meta-analysis of studies comparing intracorporeal and extracorporeal anastomosis in laparoscopic right hemicolectomy. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2017 May;402(3):417-427. doi: 10.1007/s00423-016-1509-x. Epub 2016 Sep 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27595589</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shapiro R, Keler U, Segev L, Sarna S, Hatib K, Hazzan D. Laparoscopic right hemicolectomy with intracorporeal anastomosis: short- and long-term benefits in comparison with extracorporeal anastomosis. Surg Endosc. 2016 Sep;30(9):3823-9. doi: 10.1007/s00464-015-4684-x. Epub 2015 Dec 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26659237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carnuccio P, Jimeno J, Parés D. Laparoscopic right colectomy: a systematic review and meta-analysis of observational studies comparing two types of anastomosis. Tech Coloproctol. 2014 Jan;18(1):5-12. doi: 10.1007/s10151-013-1029-4. Epub 2013 May 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23686680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morpurgo E, Contardo T, Molaro R, Zerbinati A, Orsini C, D'Annibale A. Robotic-assisted intracorporeal anastomosis versus extracorporeal anastomosis in laparoscopic right hemicolectomy for cancer: a case control study. J Laparoendosc Adv Surg Tech A. 2013 May;23(5):414-7. doi: 10.1089/lap.2012.0404.</citation>
    <PMID>23627922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feroci F, Lenzi E, Garzi A, Vannucchi A, Cantafio S, Scatizzi M. Intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis after laparoscopic right hemicolectomy for cancer: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Colorectal Dis. 2013 Sep;28(9):1177-86. doi: 10.1007/s00384-013-1651-7. Epub 2013 Feb 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23371336</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee KH, Ho J, Akmal Y, Nelson R, Pigazzi A. Short- and long-term outcomes of intracorporeal versus extracorporeal ileocolic anastomosis in laparoscopic right hemicolectomy for colon cancer. Surg Endosc. 2013 Jun;27(6):1986-90. doi: 10.1007/s00464-012-2698-1. Epub 2013 Jan 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23299132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cirocchi R, Trastulli S, Farinella E, Guarino S, Desiderio J, Boselli C, Parisi A, Noya G, Slim K. Intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis during laparoscopic right hemicolectomy - systematic review and meta-analysis. Surg Oncol. 2013 Mar;22(1):1-13. doi: 10.1016/j.suronc.2012.09.002. Epub 2012 Oct 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23116767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Oostendorp S, Elfrink A, Borstlap W, Schoonmade L, Sietses C, Meijerink J, Tuynman J. Intracorporeal versus extracorporeal anastomosis in right hemicolectomy: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Surg Endosc. 2017 Jan;31(1):64-77. doi: 10.1007/s00464-016-4982-y. Epub 2016 Jun 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27287905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wong JT, Abbas MA. Laparoscopic right hemicolectomy. Tech Coloproctol. 2013 Feb;17 Suppl 1:S3-9. doi: 10.1007/s10151-012-0931-5. Epub 2012 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23250636</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 16, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario Torrecárdenas</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Manuel Ferrer Márquez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Right hemicolectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>Intracorporeal anastomosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Extracorporeal anastomosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anastomotic Leak</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>Proyect</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://drive.google.com/file/d/1EEFxi3XpaRW12IAzVctIrrOSo6EKi70_/view?usp=sharing</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>A project that compares both surgical techniques in the treatment of right colon cancer and assess which is associated with a lower postoperative morbidity</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <provided_document_section>
    <provided_document>
      <document_type>Study Protocol</document_type>
      <document_has_protocol>Yes</document_has_protocol>
      <document_has_icf>No</document_has_icf>
      <document_has_sap>No</document_has_sap>
      <document_date>January 1, 2016</document_date>
      <document_url>https://ClinicalTrials.gov/ProvidedDocs/14/NCT03990714/Prot_000.pdf</document_url>
    </provided_document>
  </provided_document_section>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

