<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03995849</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UHN REB 18-5370</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03995849</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Motion of Kids on Radiation Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Paediatric and Adolescent Radiotherapy Without Anaesthesia Using Audio-Visual Distraction - Are the Patients Moving?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Health Network, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Health Network, Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      At Princess Margaret Cancer Centre, a comprehensive approach to help children stay still
      during radiation treatment (RT) such as audio-visual distraction (television) is routinely
      used. These techniques help reduce the need for sedation or general anaesthesia to keep
      children still to avoid the chance of missing the tumour during RT. This approach has not
      been systematically evaluated to determine its effectiveness at reducing movement of children
      receiving RT. The purpose of the study is to measure the movement of children between the
      beginning and the end of RT to see how much they moved during treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cone beam CT (CBCT) is a low-dose imaging technique routinely used at Princess Margaret
      Cancer Centre to check the position of patients before RT. Using CBCT, the doctor is able to
      reduce the amount of tissues that receive RT because patients can be set-up with greater
      accuracy to only target the tumour and not harm the surrounding healthy tissue. In this
      study, children will receive one CBCT scan before starting RT as part of standard approach.
      Then after RT, another CBCT scan will be used to measure movement between the beginning and
      end of RT. The information gathered from this study will benefit other patients and cancer
      centres in the future, who can learn from these methods of using audio-visual distraction so
      that children have minimal or no motion for a more precise delivery of radiation during
      cancer treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 29, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients that move between pre- and post-RT CBCT acquisitions without anaesthesia.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the proportion of patients with adequate immobilization by measuring motion between pre- and post-RT CBCT acquisitions for patients treated without anaesthesia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative intra-fraction motion of patients treated with RT without anaesthesia.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To quantitatively determine intra-fraction motion of patients treated with RT without anaesthesia</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Factors associated with intra-fraction patient motion.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate factors associated with intra-fraction patient motion, thus facilitating creation of individualized, patient-specific planning target volumes (PTV)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perturbations in delivered treatment dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To calculate perturbations in delivered treatment dose using dose-accumulation upon on-treatment CBCT images</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Observational Study</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cone Beam CT Scan</intervention_name>
    <description>In this study, children will receive one CBCT scan before starting RT as part of standard approach. Then after RT, another CBCT scan will be used to measure movement between the beginning and end of RT.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Paediatric patients receiving an existing multi-faceted approach to reduce anaesthesia use
        in paediatric and adolescent radiotherapy (RT)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient (paediatric or adolescent) age 18 or under receiving RT without anaesthetic or
             procedural sedation (anaesthetic gas or intravenous sedative medication)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving oral midazolam or ketamine are ineligible

          -  Patient is receiving total body irradiation without CBCT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Derek Tsang, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre, University Health Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Derek Tsang, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-2121</phone>
    <email>Derek.Tsang@rmp.uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tatiana Ritchie, BSc, MRT(T)</last_name>
    <phone>416-946-4501</phone>
    <phone_ext>8812</phone_ext>
    <email>Tatiana.Ritchie@rmp.uhn.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Margaret Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Derek Tsang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>4169464501</phone>
      <phone_ext>2121</phone_ext>
      <email>Derek.Tsang@rmp.uhn.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anghelescu DL, Burgoyne LL, Liu W, Hankins GM, Cheng C, Beckham PA, Shearer J, Norris AL, Kun LE, Bikhazi GB. Safe anesthesia for radiotherapy in pediatric oncology: St. Jude Children's Research Hospital Experience, 2004-2006. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2008 Jun 1;71(2):491-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2007.09.044. Epub 2008 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>18207663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott MT, Todd KE, Oakley H, Bradley JA, Rotondo RL, Morris CG, Klein S, Mendenhall NP, Indelicato DJ. Reducing Anesthesia and Health Care Cost Through Utilization of Child Life Specialists in Pediatric Radiation Oncology. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2016 Oct 1;96(2):401-405. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2016.06.001. Epub 2016 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27475669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khurmi N, Patel P, Koushik S, Daniels T, Kraus M. Anesthesia Practice in Pediatric Radiation Oncology: Mayo Clinic Arizona's Experience 2014-2016. Paediatr Drugs. 2018 Feb;20(1):89-95. doi: 10.1007/s40272-017-0259-8.</citation>
    <PMID>28786083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owusu-Agyemang P, Grosshans D, Arunkumar R, Rebello E, Popovich S, Zavala A, Williams C, Ruiz J, Hernandez M, Mahajan A, Porche V. Non-invasive anesthesia for children undergoing proton radiation therapy. Radiother Oncol. 2014 Apr;111(1):30-4. doi: 10.1016/j.radonc.2014.01.016. Epub 2014 Feb 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24560754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seiler G, De Vol E, Khafaga Y, Gregory B, Al-Shabanah M, Valmores A, Versteeg D, Ellis B, Mustafa MM, Gray A. Evaluation of the safety and efficacy of repeated sedations for the radiotherapy of young children with cancer: a prospective study of 1033 consecutive sedations. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2001 Mar 1;49(3):771-83.</citation>
    <PMID>11172961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Létourneau D, Wong JW, Oldham M, Gulam M, Watt L, Jaffray DA, Siewerdsen JH, Martinez AA. Cone-beam-CT guided radiation therapy: technical implementation. Radiother Oncol. 2005 Jun;75(3):279-86.</citation>
    <PMID>15890424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guerreiro F, Seravalli E, Janssens GO, van de Ven CP, van den Heuvel-Eibrink MM, Raaymakers BW. Intra- and inter-fraction uncertainties during IGRT for Wilms' tumor. Acta Oncol. 2018 Jul;57(7):941-949. doi: 10.1080/0284186X.2018.1438655. Epub 2018 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>29457751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yin FF, Wang Z, Yoo S, Wu QJ, Kirkpatrick J, Larrier N, Meyer J, Willett CG, Marks LB. Integration of cone-beam CT in stereotactic body radiation therapy. Technol Cancer Res Treat. 2008 Apr;7(2):133-9.</citation>
    <PMID>18345702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richmond ND, Pilling KE, Peedell C, Shakespeare D, Walker CP. Positioning accuracy for lung stereotactic body radiotherapy patients determined by on-treatment cone-beam CT imaging. Br J Radiol. 2012 Jun;85(1014):819-23. doi: 10.1259/bjr/54341099.</citation>
    <PMID>22665927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 24, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 5, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

