<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03990506</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PiXLKC-I</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03990506</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Photorefractive Intrastromal Crosslinking (PiXL) for the Treatment of Progressive Keratoconus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Epi-off and Epi-on Photorefractive Intrastromal Crosslinking (PiXL) for Progressive Keratoconus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Umeå University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Avedro, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Umeå University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy, safety and postoperative ocular
      discomfort by comparing individually customized Photorefractive intrastromal crosslinking
      (PiXL) for progressive Keratoconus. The study compares two different protocols, PiXL with
      corneal epithelium debridement (Epi-off) and PiXL without epithelium debridement in high
      oxygen environment (Epi-on), with the hypothesis that Epi-on gives less postoperative ocular
      discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed as a prospective, single-masked intraindividually comparing randomized
      controlled trial involving participants of both genders aged 18-35 years with Keratoconus
      planned for routine corneal crosslinking at the Department of Ophthalmology, Umeå University
      Hospital, Umeå, Sweden. The study includes 30 participants with bilateral Keratoconus,
      receiving Epi-off PiXL (n=30) in one eye and Epi-on PiXL in high oxygen environment (n=30) in
      the fellow eye. The participants are randomized utilizing a list of unique random numbers
      between 1 and 30; an even number will be treated with Epi-on in the right eye; an uneven
      number will receive Epi-on in the left eye; the fellow eye will be treated with Epi-off. All
      patients are informed about the procedures before consenting to participate in the study.

      At baseline, before treatment, each eye is examined with slit-lamp microscopy, subjective
      refraction, determination of uncorrected (UCVA), low contrast visual acuity at 2.5 percentage
      contrast and 10 percentage contrast and best corrected (BSCVA) visual acuities using the
      LogMAR fast protocol and intraocular pressure (IOP) using Goldmann applanation tonometry.
      Under standardized, mesopic light conditions each eye is evaluated by keratometry readings
      and central corneal thickness, extracted from Schemipflug camera measurements, Pentacam HR®
      (Oculus, Inc. Lynnwood, WA).

      Central corneal endothelial photographs are taken with the Topcon SP-IP specular microscope
      (Topcon Europe B.V., Capelle a/d Ijssel, the Netherlands) and total ocular wavefront is
      measured with iTrace (Tracey Technologies, Inc.).

      Ocular discomfort is subjectively evaluated in each eye by a specific visual analogous rating
      scale at 4h, 8h, 12h, 24h and thereafter daily up to 1 week postoperatively.

      All the above mentioned examinations are repeated at 1, 3, 6, 12 and 24 months after
      treatment. At 1 day and 1 week after treatment, solely UCVA, Auto refractor measurements,
      slit-lamp examination are evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, single-masked intraindividually comparing randomized controlled trial. Participants will be randomized to receive Epi-off PiXL in one eye and Epi-on PiXL in the other, which is masked to the participant. The participant can choose to treat in eye at a time or both eyes during the same visit.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>The participants are not aware which eye will receive the Epi-off PiXL treatment and which eye will receive the Epi-on PiXL treatment.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in uncorrected visual acuity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in distance uncorrected visual acuity, LogMAR units</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in keratometry readings</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Kmean (average), K1 (flat meridian), K2 (steep meridian) and Kmax (steepest radius of curvature) assessed with the Pentacam HR Scheimpflug camera, Diopters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Ocular Discomfort Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>4 hours, 8 hours, 1 day, 2 days, 3 days, 4 days, 5 days, 6 days and 7 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in Ocular Discomfort Scores, Visual Analog Score (0 (no discomfort) - 10 (maximum discomfort))</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in refraction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Refractive errors assessed with Pentacam HR Schempflug Camera and iTrace, Diopters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in spherical equivalent</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in spherical equivalent on subjective distance refraction, Diopters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in corneal endothelial cell density</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Change from baseline in central corneal endothelial cell density, cells/mm2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Keratoconus</condition>
  <condition>Corneal Crosslinking</condition>
  <condition>Corneal Biomechanics</condition>
  <condition>Corneal Densitometry</condition>
  <condition>Scheimpflug Photography</condition>
  <condition>Corneal Disease</condition>
  <condition>Eye Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epi-on PiXL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Photorefractive intrastromal corneal crosslinking without epithelium debridement during humidified high oxygen flow.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Epi-off PiXL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Photorefractive intrastromal corneal crosslinking with epithelium debridement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epi-on PiXL</intervention_name>
    <description>Photorefractive intrastromal crosslinking (PiXL) After local anaesthetics, the keratoconus cornea is soaked in Riboflavin by repeated topical application during 10 minutes. For masking purposes, epithelial debridement is simulated by moving a scraping instrument in front of the cornea. A Riboflavin soaked sponge is used to lightly disrupt the epithelium tight junctions, without epithelium debridement. The cornea is illuminated with PiXL under 16:40 minutes during continuously delivery of humidified high oxygen via specific oxygen goggles. The UV-dosage is individually customized based upon Kmax; for &lt; 45 Diopters (D) 7.2J/cm2 is used; for 45-50D 10J/cm2 is used; for &gt; 50D 15 J/cm2 is used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epi-on PiXL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Epi-Off PiXL</intervention_name>
    <description>Photorefractive intrastromal crosslinking (PiXL) After local anaesthetics, the corneal epithelium is debrided and the keratoconus cornea is soaked in Riboflavin by repeated topical application during 10 minutes. The cornea is then illuminated with individually customized PiXL under 16:40 minutes. The UV-dosage is individually customized based upon Kmax; for &lt; 45D 7.2J/cm2 will be used; for 45-50D 10J/cm2 will be used; for &gt; 50D 15 J/cm2 will be used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Epi-off PiXL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients planned for corneal crosslinking.

          -  Progressive keratoconus documented with Scheimpflug photography using the Pentacam
             Scheimflug camera and/or repeated subjective refraction and keratometry.

          -  A keratoconus diagnosis based on the Amsler-Krumeich grading and the &quot;Total Deviation&quot;
             KC quantification value from the &quot;Belin-Ambrosio enhanced ectasia&quot; measurements of the
             Pentacam Scheimpflug camera, and an altered red reflex and/or an irregular cornea seen
             as distortion of the keratometric mires.

          -  Minimum corneal thickness of 400 µm at the thinnest point after epithelial removal.

          -  18-35 years of age

          -  No ocular abnormalities except keratoconus

          -  No previous ocular surgery

          -  No cognitive insufficiency interfering with the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age under 18 or over 35

          -  Any corneal abnormalities except keratoconus

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Previous ocular surgery

          -  Cognitive insufficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anders Behndig, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+46707827536</phone>
    <email>anders.behndig@umu.se</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Clinical Sciences/Ophthalmology, Umeå University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Umeå</city>
        <zip>901 85</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anders Behndig, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46707827536</phone>
      <email>anders.behndig@umu.se</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 20, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Umeå University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anders Behndig</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Keratoconus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Corneal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

