<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03999775</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>84908/2017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03999775</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Calcium and Vitamin D Supplementation With and Without Collagen Peptides in Postmenopausal Women With Osteopenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect on Bone Biomarkers and Bone Mineral Density and Tolerability of Calcium and Vitamin D Supplementation With and Without Collagen Peptides in Postmenopausal Women With Osteopenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ioannis K. Triantafyllopoulos, MD,MSci,PhD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Osteoporosis is undoubtedly one of the most common diseases affecting older individuals with
      debilitating consequences. Osteopenia, defined as T-score between -1 and -2.5, has also been
      associated with increased risk of osteoporotic fractures and the associated morbidity and
      mortality. Prompt diagnosis, prevention and treatment of both osteopenia and osteoporosis are
      essential in order to minimize future fracture risk. The mainstay of treatment of osteopenia
      and osteoporosis includes dietary changes, regular weight-bearing exercises, calcium and
      vitamin D supplementation and pharmacologic treatment mainly with antiresorptive or anabolic
      agents. Collagen peptides (CPs), also called collagen hydrolysates produced by hydrolysis of
      collagen, have also been shown to have high oral bioavailability and could have a place as a
      treatment option.

      Type I collagen comprises approximately 95% of the entire collagen content of bone. Bone
      matrix, unlike other connective tissues, possesses the unique ability to become calcified.
      Spindle or plate-shaped crystals of hydroxyapatite are found between and around collagen
      fibers, oriented in the same direction as collagen fibers are. Nowadays, it is
      well-documented that type I collagen molecules are involved in the mechanical properties of
      bone. Collagen peptide compounds seem to exert their beneficial effect on bone by affecting
      bone remodeling and mineralization of the bone matrix, promoting the proliferation and
      differentiation of pre-osteoblasts while reducing the maturation of osteoclasts. Several
      preclinical studies performed in mice and rats support this notion and also suggested that
      orally administrated CPs increased bone mineral density (BMD), as well as the compositional
      and the biodynamic characteristics of vertebrae. Human studies in postmenopausal women have
      also yielded positive results with increased BMD and blood biomarkers after 6 months and 1
      year of oral administration.

      The aim of the present randomized prospective study was to examine and compare the efficacy,
      as represented by the changes in bone biomarkers procollagen type I N-terminal propeptide
      (P1NP) and C-terminal telopeptide of collagen I (CTX), and bone mineral density and the
      tolerability of supplementation of calcium, vitamin D with and without bioactive CPs for a
      year in postmenopausal women with osteopenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 14, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 20, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 20, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of %-changes of P1NP and CTX levels from baseline to 3 months of supplementation between the two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint of the study was the comparison of %-changes of P1NP and CTX levels from baseline to 3 months of supplementation between the two groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of P1NP and CTX levels within groups and comparison of the adverse effects (tolerability), and/or the adherence to treatment between the two groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary endpoints were the change of P1NP and CTX levels following the 3-month calcium and vitamin D supplementation with and without collagen peptides supplement, the comparison of adverse effects (tolerability), and/or the adherence to treatment between the two groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteopenia</condition>
  <condition>Postmenopausal Osteopenia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium, vitamin D and bioactive collagen peptides supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm, all patients received a sachet containing 5mg bioactive collagen peptides, 500 mg calcium lactate and 400 IU vitamin D3 per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium and vitamin D supplement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this arm, all patients received a chewable tablet containing 500 mg calcium carbonate and 400 IU vitamin D3 per day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcium, vitamin D and bioactive collagen peptides supplement</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium, vitamin D and bioactive collagen peptides supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calcium and vitamin D supplement</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Calcium and vitamin D supplement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Postmenopausal women

          -  T-score in the osteopenic range (-1.0 &gt; T-score &gt; -2.5) at either the lumbar spine
             (LS) or femur as measured by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DXA)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  T-score in the osteoporotic range (T-score &lt; -2.5) at any site

          -  Patients receiving supplements of calcium and/or vitamin D at that time or during the
             last year

          -  Patients receiving medications known to positively or negatively affect bone turnover
             or BMD at that time or during the last 3 years (e.g. antiresorptive agents,
             oestrogens, systemic corticosteroids), or

          -  Secondary cause of osteoporosis (e.g. alcohol abuse, thyrotoxicosis etc)

          -  Patients who did not attend to their follow-up appointment and consequently had only
             the baseline measurements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Postmenopausal osteopenia</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 1, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National and Kapodistrian University of Athens</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ioannis K. Triantafyllopoulos, MD,MSci,PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Orthopaedics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Collagen peptides</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone turnover markers</keyword>
  <keyword>Calcium supplement</keyword>
  <keyword>Postmenopausal women</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Metabolic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

