<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03994939</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PAWOS000011-01-00</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03994939</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Families Talking Together (FTT) in Texas</brief_title>
  <acronym>FTT</acronym>
  <official_title>The National Campaign - FTT: A Family-based Teen Pregnancy Prevention Program in Texas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Power to Decide</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Healthy Futures of Texas</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rio Grande Valley Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Power to Decide</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Power to Decide, The National Campaign to Prevent Teen and Unplanned Pregnancy, partnered
      with the Center for Latino Adolescent and Family Health at New York University's Silver
      School of Social Work, Healthy Futures of Texas, and the Rio Grande Valley Council to
      implement Families Talking Together (FTT), an evidence-based teen pregnancy prevention
      program in Texas. This was a randomized clinical trial of a parent-based sexual and
      reproductive health intervention (SRH) to foster parent-adolescent communication about sex
      among Latino adolescents. The FTT intervention focuses on the parenting practices that are
      important to supporting healthy adolescent sexual behavior. As part of the intervention,
      families also received a module on the Affordable Care Act (ACA) to influence greater
      linkages to health care.The study was conducted with 634 parent-adolescent dyads in Willacy,
      Starr, Hidalgo, and Cameron counties in South Texas. Parent-adolescent dyads completed a
      baseline survey and were allocated to either an experimental or control group. Participating
      dyads completed follow-up surveys 3 and 9 months' post-baseline assessment. The proposed
      outcomes of the study were increased adolescent report of parent-adolescent communication
      about sex, decrease in sexual risk behaviors (e.g., sexual debut) as well as increased health
      care insurance enrollment among Latino families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study was a two-arm parallel RCT designed to test the efficacy of a teen pregnancy
      prevention program conducted in the Rio Grande Valley from 2013-2018. Parent-adolescent dyads
      were randomly assigned to either a passive control group that received no intervention or an
      experimental group which received the promotor delivered family-based SRH prevention program
      Families Talking Together (FTT) with an added Affordable Care Act (ACA) module.
      Parent-adolescent dyads completed baseline, immediate post-baseline (3 months) and delayed
      (9-month) follow-up assessments.

      A combination of venue-based and area sampling methods was used in 4 Rio Grande Valley
      counties to recruit Latino adolescents and their parents residing in colonias for study
      participation. The 4 counties (Willacy, Starr, Hidalgo, Cameron) were chosen due to well
      documented SRH disparities among youth.Trained recruitment promotores attended local
      community health fairs, shopping malls, supermarkets, etc. where large numbers of resident
      families could be engaged. During these events, recruitment promotores made initial contact
      with potentially eligible youth and their families in order to screen for study inclusion
      criteria. In addition, recruiters went door-to-door in targeted communities conducting active
      outreach and engagement of families directly within their homes. Eligible families were
      informed that they were being asked to participate in a research project seeking to improve
      access to SRH programming for adolescents and that participation would require, at minimum,
      participating in a survey now as well as after 3 and 9 months. We obtained informed assent
      and parental consent for all adolescents participating in the study. Parents provided their
      consent to participate.Refusal bias data was collected as part of the screening process.
      Refusal data suggested no significant differences between those families declining to
      participate and those agreeing to be part of the study.

      Adolescents and their parents completed baseline, immediate post-baseline (3 months), and
      delayed follow-up (9 months) assessments using self-administered surveys in either English or
      Spanish, based on preference. Prior to initiation of the RCT, surveys were pilot tested to
      ensure conceptual clarity and linguistic appropriateness. To ensure confidentiality, parents
      and adolescents completed questionnaires separately. A social desirability scale was included
      in the measurement protocol to assess the extent to which participant responses reflect
      social desirability bias.

      A computer random number generation program was used to create a randomly permutated scheme
      that assigned specific subject identification numbers to either the experimental or passive
      control group in a one-to-one ratio. An allocation sequence was generated by the principal
      investigator. Each experimental/control group allocation sequence was placed in a sealed
      envelope which remained concealed until after participants had enrolled into the study. After
      the baseline was completed, the sealed envelope was opened with the family's allocation tied
      to their specific ID. Data collectors administering the immediate and delayed follow-up
      surveys were blinded to the condition of participants.

      Parents randomized to the experimental group received the Families Talking Together (FTT)
      intervention, an evidence-based program designed to increase parent-adolescent communication
      about sex in order to delay sexual debut and prevent negative SRH outcomes in young
      adolescents (aged 10 to 14). The FTT intervention has been delivered with efficacy in
      multiple settings, including schools and clinics. FTT is also identified by the United States
      Department of Health and Human Services and the Office of Adolescent Health (OAH) as a high
      quality, effective prevention program. The FTT intervention consisted of two components.
      Intervention component 1 was comprised of two FTT intervention sessions between a parent and
      the bilingual and bicultural promotor trained to deliver FTT in either English or Spanish.
      Intervention sessions were delivered to parents in their home or a mutually agreed upon
      private location in the community. Intervention component 2 was comprised of written
      supplemental materials that promotores used to guide each intervention session. Written
      materials included a family FTT workbook and a short story entitled 'Victor and Maria.'

      During each intervention session, promotores reviewed the intervention materials and
      instructed parents how to structure conversations about delaying sexual debut and the use of
      contraception with their adolescent. At three and 9 months post-baseline, adolescents in the
      experimental and control groups completed follow-up surveys administered by data collectors.

      To examine group differences in parent-adolescent communication variables, ordinary least
      squares (OLS) regression was used. To ensure baseline equivalence between the two arms of the
      RCT, demographic and outcome variables were compared at baseline between the intervention and
      control groups. In order to assess the generalizability of results across traditional and
      robust methods of analysis, all analyses were repeated with bootstrapping. Additionally,
      outlier and specification-error for each analysis was conducted.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Two-arm parallel RCT designed to test the efficacy of a teen pregnancy prevention program conducted in the Rio Grande Valley from 2013-2018. Parent-adolescent dyads were randomly assigned to either a passive control group that received no intervention or an experimental group which received the promotor delivered family-based SRH prevention program Families Talking Together (FTT) with added Affordable Care Act (ACA) module.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>A computer random number generation program was used to create a randomly permutated scheme that assigned specific subject identification numbers to either the experimental or passive control group in a one-to-one ratio. An allocation sequence was generated by the principal investigator. Each experimental/control group allocation sequence was placed in a sealed envelope which remained concealed until after participants had enrolled into the study. After the baseline was completed, the sealed envelope was opened with the family's allocation tied to their specific ID. Data collectors administering the immediate and delayed follow-up surveys were blinded to the condition of participants.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parent-Adolescent Communication about Sex and Contraception</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 9 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Report of parent-adolescent communication about delay of sex and contraceptive use</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parent-Adolescent Communication about HIV/STDs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 9 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Report of parent-adolescent communication about HIV/STIs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sexual Risk Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 9 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Report of decrease in frequency of sex and/or increased condom use</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health Care Insurance Enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 and 9 months post-baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Report of health care insurance enrollment among Latino families</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">634</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexual Risk Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Received Families Talking Together (FTT) intervention, an evidence-based program designed to increase parent-adolescent communication about sex in order to delay sexual debut and prevent negative sexual and reproductive health outcomes in adolescents age 10-14. The FTT intervention consisted of two components. Component 1 was comprised of 2 FTT intervention sessions between a parent and bilingual/bicultural promotor trained to deliver FTT in English or Spanish. These sessions highlighted adverse health consequences of sex to motivate parents to communicate with their adolescent and provided guidance to parents on communication strategies. Component 2 was comprised of written supplemental materials that promotores used to guide each intervention session. Experimental condition families will complete all measurement assessments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents randomized to the control group did not receive any intervention sessions and only completed assessment questionnaires.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Families Talking Together (FTT)</intervention_name>
    <description>FTT is an evidence-based program designed to increase parent-adolescent communication about sex in order to delay sexual debut and prevent negative SRH outcomes in young adolescents (aged 10 to 14). The FTT intervention has been delivered with efficacy in multiple settings, including schools and clinics (Guilamo-Ramos et al., 2011a; Guilamo-Ramos et al., 2011b).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Self-identify as Latino

          -  At least one a parent present in home, defined as a biological or non-biological
             primary caregiver

          -  Resident of target geographic community (Willacy, Starr, Hidalgo, or Cameron) in the
             Rio Grande Valley

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Self-identify as non-Latino

          -  Lack of parent or caregiver in home during recruitment

          -  Resident of non-target community in the Rio Grande Valley
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gillian Sealy, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Power to Decide, The National Campaign to Prevent Unplanned Pregnancy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guilamo-Ramos V, Bouris A, Jaccard J, Gonzalez B, McCoy W, Aranda D. A parent-based intervention to reduce sexual risk behavior in early adolescence: building alliances between physicians, social workers, and parents. J Adolesc Health. 2011 Feb;48(2):159-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2010.06.007.</citation>
    <PMID>21257114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guilamo-Ramos V, Jaccard J, Dittus P, Bouris A, Gonzalez B, Casillas E, Banspach S. A comparative study of interventions for delaying the initiation of sexual intercourse among Latino and black youth. Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2011 Dec;43(4):247-54. doi: 10.1363/4324711. Epub 2011 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22151512</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Office of Adolescent Health. (2017). Families Talking Together (FTT). Retrieved from http://www.hhs.gov/ash/oah/oah-initiatives/tpp_program/db/programs/ebp-ftt.html.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 20, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 20, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 20, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 21, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sexual and reproductive health</keyword>
  <keyword>Promotores de Salud</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent-adolescent communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Health care insurance enrollment</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

