<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03990584</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10840098-604.01.01-E34148</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03990584</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Irrigation Activation on Clinical Outcomes of Root Canal Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Irrigation Activation on Clinical Outcomes of Root Canal Treatment in Posterior Teeth With Chronic Apical Periodontitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istanbul Medipol University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istanbul Medipol University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates postoperative pain and radiographic healing of asymptomatic posterior
      teeth with chronic apical periodontitis following root-canal treatment performed using
      different methods of irrigation activation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim: To evaluate postoperative pain and radiographic healing of asymptomatic posterior teeth
      with chronic apical periodontitis following root-canal treatment performed using different
      methods of irrigation activation.

      Methodology: In this prospective clinical trial, root-canal treatment was performed on 162
      posterior teeth with chronic apical periodontitis. After routine canal preparation, patients
      were assigned to either a control group treated using conventional needle irrigation (CNI)
      without activation or to one of 3 treatment groups, each of which was treated using a
      different activation protocol during the final irrigation [manual dynamic irrigation (MDI),
      passive ultrasonic irrigation (PUI), sonic irrigation (SI)]. All treatment was completed in a
      single visit. Patients provided self-assessments of the severity of postoperative pain at
      24h, 48h and 7 days using a modified 4-step visual analogue scale (VAS). Patients were
      recalled at 12 months for clinical and radiographic examinations. Periodontal healing was
      evaluated using a periapical index (PAI), with scores of 1 or 2 considered to represent
      treatment success and scores of 3, 4, or 5 to represent treatment failure. Data were analyzed
      using one-way ANOVA and Kruskal-Wallis tests, with differences of P &lt; 0.05 considered
      statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change from baseline postoperative pain at 1 week</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours, 48 hours and 1 week postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Pain was measured using a modified visual analogue scale (VAS) with 4 levels, as follows: 1, no pain; 2, slight pain (mild discomfort, no treatment needed); 3, moderate pain (pain required analgesics for relief); 4, severe pain (pain and/or swelling not relieved by simple analgesics and required unscheduled visit). Patients were provided forms and asked to record preoperative pain as well as pain at 24 hours, 48 hours and 1 week postoperatively, and to note down the number of analgesics taken. Patients returned their completed forms at their 1-week follow-up visits.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>change from baseline periapical index at 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>Clinical and radiographic examinations were performed on the 1 day of treatment,1 day after treatment and 1 year after treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Periapical tissue was evaluated using a 5-point periapical index (PAI) (Ørstavik et al. 1986) and scored as follows: 1: Normal periapical structures; 2: Small changes in bone structures; 3: Changes in bone structure with some mineral loss; 4: Periodontitis with well-defined radiolucent area; 5: Severe periodontitis with exacerbating features. If scores varied among roots in the same tooth, the highest score was recorded for that tooth. Similarly, if scores varied between observers for the same tooth, the higher score was recorded.
Treatment was considered successful if the patient had no discomfort, no percussion/palpation pain, no sinus tract, no mobility or associated soft-tissue swelling, and a PAI score of ≤ 2. Treatment was considered a failure if the patient could not perform normal masticatory functions, experienced discomfort and percussive pain upon examination, and/or had a PAI score of ≥ 3 .</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Periapical Periodontitis</condition>
  <condition>Root Canal Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>three irrigation activation methods</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Manual dynamic irrigation was performed using a well-fitting gutta-percha cone inserted to WL with in-and-out vertical strokes of 5 mm at a rate of approximately 100 strokes per minute in order to hydrodynamically displace the irrigant.
Passive ultrasonic irrigation was performed using a non‐cutting size 25 file attached to a piezoelectric ultrasonic unit.
Sonic irrigation was performed using an EndoActivator sonic handpiece (Dentsply Tulsa Dental Specialties, Tulsa, OK, USA). A suitable-size activator tip was selected and loosely placed at 2 mm from working length, and the device was operated at 10,000 cycles/min using a pumping action to move the tip to produce vertical strokes of 2-3 mm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional needle irrigation (control)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Conventional needle irrigation was performed with short, in-and-out vertical strokes of 2-3 mm at a rate of approximately 100 strokes per minute.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>three irrigation activation methods</intervention_name>
    <description>passive ultrasonic irrigation, sonic irrigation, manual dynamic irrigation</description>
    <arm_group_label>three irrigation activation methods</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>passive ultrasonic irrigation (Irrisafe; Satelec Acteon, Mérignac, France), sonic irrigation (Dentsply Tulsa Dental Specialties, Tulsa, OK, USA), manual dynamic irrigation (Kerr Dental, USA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional needle irrigation</intervention_name>
    <description>conventional needle irrigation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional needle irrigation (control)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  a non-contributory medical history

          -  must have an asymptomatic, necrotic premolar or molar with periapical lesions of &gt; 2.0
             x 2.0 mm around one or both roots

          -  must be diagnosed as chronic apical periodontitis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those with clinical symptoms (acute pain)

          -  have periapical radiolucency of &gt;5 mm

          -  no previous endodontic treatment

          -  no severe periodontal disease in the related tooth

          -  non-restorable tooth

          -  use of any analgesics within the previous 3 days or antibiotics within the previous
             month
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seyda Ersahan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul Medipol University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Medipol University, Faculty of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <state>Esenler</state>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrabi SM, Kumar A, Zia A, Iftekhar H, Alam S, Siddiqui S. Effect of passive ultrasonic irrigation and manual dynamic irrigation on smear layer removal from root canals in a closed apex in vitro model. Journal of Investigative and Clinical Dentistry 5: 188-93, 2014. Akerblom A, Hasselgren G. The prognosis for endodontic treatment of obliterated root canals. Journal of Endodontics 14: 565-7, 1998. Attar S, Bowles WR, Baisden MK, Hodges JS, McClanahan SB. Evaluation of pretreatment analgesia and endodontic treatment for postoperative endodontic pain. Journal of Endodontics 34: 652-5, 2008. Brito PR, Souza LC, Machado de Oliveira JC et al. Comparison of the effectiveness of three irrigation techniques in reducing intracanal Enterococcus faecalis populations: an in vitro study. Journal of Endodontics 35: 1422-7, 2009. Brynolf I (1967) A histological and roentgenological study of the periapical region of human upper incisors. Odontologisk Revy 18, 1-176.1-176. Cameron JA (1988) The effect of ultrasonic endodontics on the temperature of the root canal wall. Journal of Endodontics 14, 554-8. Card SJ, Sigurdsson A, Ørstavik D, Trope M . The effectiveness of increased apical enlargement in reducing intracanal bacteria. Journal of Endodontics 28: 779-83, 2002. de Gregorio C, Estevez R, Cisneros R, Heilborn C, Cohenca N . Effect of EDTA, sonic, and ultrasonic activation on the penetration of sodium hypochlorite into simulated lateral canals: an in vitro study. Journal of Endodontics 35: 891-5, 2009. de Gregorio C, Estevez R, Cisneros R, Paranjpe A, Cohenca N . Efficacy of different irrigation and activation systems on the penetration of sodium hypochlorite into simulated lateral canals and up to working length: an in vitro study. Journal of Endodontics 36: 1216-1221, 2010. Desai P, Himel V .Comparative safety of various intracanal irrigation systems. Journal of Endodontics 35: 545-9, 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istanbul Medipol University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>seydaersahan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Clinical Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic apical periodontitis</keyword>
  <keyword>irrigation activation methods</keyword>
  <keyword>periapical index</keyword>
  <keyword>postoperative pain</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Periodontitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Periapical Periodontitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>After its publication in a journal, we want to share our data</ipd_description>
    <ipd_info_type>Study Protocol</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_info_type>Statistical Analysis Plan (SAP)</ipd_info_type>
    <ipd_time_frame>After its publication in a journal, we want to share our data</ipd_time_frame>
    <ipd_access_criteria>postoperative pain scores periapical and panoramic radiographs and radiographic findings clinical findings</ipd_access_criteria>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

