<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03992326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHUV-DO-0012-SolTIL_2018</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03992326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adoptive Transfer Of Autologous Tumor-Infiltrating Lymphocytes in Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase Ib Study To Assess The Feasibility And Safety Of Adoptive Transfer Of Autologous Tumor-Infiltrating Lymphocytes In Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Single center, single arm phase Ib trial to test the feasibility and safety of Tumor-
      Infiltrating Lymphocyte-Adoptive Cell Therapy (TIL-ACT) combined with low-dose irradiation in
      patients with advanced or metastatic solid tumors. The trial is based on lymphodepleting
      chemotherapy followed by low dose irradiation (LDI), and then ACT utilizing ex vivo expanded
      TILs in combination with high dose IL-2 (optional, depending on patient's tolerance). LDI
      will be administered once to metastatic lesions using tomotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objective of the trial is to define the feasibility and safety of TIL-ACT in combination
      with low-dose irradiation (LDI) in patients with advanced or metastatic solid tumors.

      Study treatment will begin with intravenous (IV) non-myeloablative (NMA) lymphodepleting
      chemotherapy composed by fludarabine and cyclophosphamide. Both treatments will be started on
      the same day. Fludarabine will be administered for five days, and cyclophosphamide for two
      days. Low-dose irradiation (LDI) will be then administered once, to up to 20 measurable tumor
      lesions using tomotherapy.

      TIL infusion will be performed intravenously followed by high dose IL-2 administration every
      eight hours, for a maximum of eight doses. Supportive care will be given as needed during the
      whole treatment period.

      Patients achieving a stable disease, partial response or complete response after TIL-ACT
      treatment will then enter a follow-up period for 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 31, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2025</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of TIL-ACT in combination with LDI - successful Rapid Expansion Protocol (REP): Number of patients for whom TIL cultures</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated for each patient at day 0. After day 0 of the last patient, the number of patients with successful TIL-ACT infusion will be calculated.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients for whom TIL cultures after REP achieve the required cell number and release criteria to start TIL-ACT infusion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of TIL-ACT in combination with LDI - successful infusion: Number of patients receiving a complete TIL-ACT infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated for each patient at day 0, up to 60 mins after start of TIL-ACT infusion. At day 0 of the last patient, the number of patients with successful TIL-ACT infusion will be calculated.</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients receiving a complete TIL-ACT infusion (planned NMA chemotherapy, planned LDI and at least partial TIL infusion; no minimum IL-2 required)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity of TIL-ACT and LDI</measure>
    <time_frame>Treatment limiting toxicity (TLT) period: from chemotherapy start until Day30</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with adverse events as assessed by CTCAE version 5.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Achievement of complete response, partial response or stable disease</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Best overall response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS) for TIL-ACT</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from start of NMA chemotherapy until objective tumor progression (using RECIST criteria) or death if not documented progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Time from start of NMA chemotherapy until death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumor, Adult</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-myeloablative lymphodepleting chemotherapy (cyclophosphamide and fludarabine), Low Dose Irradiation (LDI), Tumor Infiltrating Lymphocyte (TIL)-Adoptive Cell Therapy (ACT), Interleukin-2 (IL-2).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TIL</intervention_name>
    <description>Adoptive transfer of Autologous Tumor-Infiltrating Lymphocytes</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cyclophosphamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Cyclophosphamide will be administered as an intravenous (IV) infusion for two days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Fludarabine will be administered as an intravenous (IV) infusion for five days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interleukin-2</intervention_name>
    <description>After TIL infusion, IL-2 (optional) will be started as a bolus administration every eight hours, for a maximum of eight doses.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Low-dose irradiation (1Gy) will be administered using tomotherapy to up to 20 measurable tumor lesions once before TIL infusion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TIL-ACT + LDI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with locally advanced (not radically treatable) or metastatic solid tumors
             with the below cancer types, who progressed after at least one standard therapy for
             advanced disease, or for whom such therapy was proven to be intolerable, or is
             considered inappropriate. Prior immunotherapy is allowed.

               1. Breast cancer: irrespective of hormone receptor, Human epidermal growth factor
                  receptor 2 (HER2) status or molecular subtype.

               2. Non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC): irrespective of histological or molecular
                  subtypes.

               3. Ovarian cancer: patients with high-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC).

               4. Colon cancer: irrespective of molecular subtype.

               5. Other solid tumor: Patients with any other histology (any molecular subtype) with
                  the exception of primary brain tumors, as well as cutaneous, mucosal, and
                  ocular/uveal melanoma.

          2. Patients who have previously undergone tumor resection or biopsy and for whom pre-REP
             TILs are already available and adequate for further REP expansion. The following
             conditions have to be met:

             a. The Manufacturing facility / sponsor representative confirms that adequate pre-REP
             material (in quantity and quality) is available to move to REP.

          3. At least one lesion accessible to biopsy for translational research (TR) at baseline
             and D30, without putting the patient at unusual risk. Every effort should be made to
             obtain a fresh tumor biopsy upon enrolment, if previous collection of tissue is judged
             insufficient for study translational endpoints. The following exceptions are accepted
             for the baseline biopsy:

             a. Tumor material was properly collected for all protocol translational endpoints
             during harvesting surgery or biopsy for the TIL production (pre-REP) and no
             intercurrent anticancer therapy has been administered since that surgery or last
             biopsy. If patient has been treated with any antitumor therapy that may have altered
             the tumor microenvironment at the estimation of the PI, a repeat biopsy should be
             performed.

          4. Male or female age ≥ 18 to ≤ 70 years at the time of informed consent. Patients aged
             &gt;70 will be evaluated by the investigator, and decision will be made according to
             patient's status, upon agreement with the PI.

          5. Clinical performance status of Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) of 0 to 2.

          6. Life expectancy of greater than 12 weeks.

          7. Radiologically measurable disease (as per RECIST v1.1).

               1. Modified RECIST should be used for mesothelioma.

               2. Prostate Cancer Working Group 3 (PCWG3) criteria should be used for prostate
                  cancer

          8. Patients with brain metastases are eligible after discussion and agreement with the
             PI, provided there are no more than 3 residual metastases, that all metastases have
             been treated with stereotactic radiation therapy or gamma knife therapy and are
             asymptomatic. Lesions should be stable for at least 1 month, as determined by CT or
             MRI evaluation after treatment and should not require steroids.

             Note: Patients presenting between three and five treated and inactive brain metastases
             can be considered for enrollment, after discussion and agreement with the PI.

          9. Adequate serology defined by the following laboratory results obtained during
             screening period (within 17 days prior registration).

               1. Seronegative for HIV infection (anti-HIV-1/-2)

               2. Seronegative for hepatitis B infection (HBsAg, total anti-hepatitis B core
                  antigen (HBc), anti-HBs). Exception is made in case of documented prior
                  vaccination. Patients with past or resolved hepatitis B infection (defined as
                  having a negative hepatitis B surface antigen HBsAg test and a positive anti-HBc
                  antibody test) are eligible, if Hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA test is negative.

               3. Seronegative for hepatitis C infection (anti-HCV): if a patient has positive
                  anti-HCV antibody, a negative HCV RNA need to be obtained to register the
                  patient.

         10. Hematology

               1. Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.0 x 10^9 cell/L without the support of granulocyte
                  colony stimulating factor (G-CSF).

               2. Platelet count ≥ 100 x10 ^9 cell/L

               3. Hemoglobin ≥ 80 g/L. Subjects may be transfused to reach this cut-off.

         11. Coagulation

             a. International normalization ratio (INR) ≤1.5 times the upper limit of normal (x
             ULN) unless the subject is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as INR/PT and
             partial thromboplastin time (PTT) is within therapeutic range of intended use of
             anticoagulants.

             i) Exception: for patients with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC), the INR may be up to
             2.2, as long as the Child-Pugh score is A6 maximum.

             b. PTT or activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) ≤ 1.5 x ULN unless the subject
             is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as INR/PT and PTT/aPTT is within
             therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants.

         12. Chemistry:

               1. Serum Alanine transaminase (ALT)/Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ to 3 x ULN i)
                  Exception: ALT/AST considered related to liver metastasis ≤ to 5 x ULN ii)
                  Exception: for patients with HCC serum ALT/AST ≤ to 5 x ULN

               2. Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x ULN i) Exception: in patients with Gilbert's syndrome who
                  must have a total bilirubin ≤2.5 x ULN ii) Exception: total bilirubin considered
                  related to liver metastasis ≤3 x ULN iii) Exception: for patients with HCC total
                  bilirubin ≤2.3 x ULN, as long as the Child-Pugh score is A6 maximum

               3. Creatinine clearance by Cockcroft-Gault formula ≥ 40 ml/min

         13. Adequate cardiovascular function, with documented left ventricular ejection fraction
             (LVEF) ≥ 45%. This parameter must be documented within 12 weeks before registration

         14. Adequate respiratory function with forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) ≥ 50%
             predicted, forced vital capacity (FVC) ≥ than 50% predicted and diffusing capacity of
             lung for carbon monoxide (DLCO) ≥ than 50% predicted corrected. Patients with lung
             cancer or mesothelioma and values slightly under these limits (but &gt;30% of predicted)
             can be enrolled after discussion and approval by the trial chair. These parameters
             must be documented within 12 weeks before registration

         15. At the time the patient receives the NMA chemotherapy regimen (D-7):

               1. ≥28 days must have elapsed from any chemotherapeutic cytotoxic drug

               2. ≥28 days must have elapsed from bevacizumab, aflibercept and other
                  anti-angiogenic antibodies

               3. ≥28 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is shorter) must have elapsed from a
                  non-cytotoxic drug including but not limited to trastuzumab, pertuzumab, and
                  other molecular targeted therapy (such as tyrosine kinase inhibitors), etc… i)
                  Note: In case of probable tumor flare upon stopping of the non-cytotoxic drug,
                  the investigator may decide to shorten this delay, upon agreement of the trial
                  chair, in a case-by-case approach.

               4. ≥21 days must have elapsed from the last antibody therapy that could affect an
                  anti-cancer immune response, including but not limited to anti-CTLA4,
                  anti-Programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1)), anti-Programmed death-ligand 1
                  (PD-L1), anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor Receptor Superfamily, member 4 (OX-40), or
                  anti-Lymphocyte-activation gene 3 (LAG3) antibody therapy or their combination

               5. Exceptions: denosumab and biphosphonates are permitted

               6. Exceptions: androgen-deprivation therapy (ADT) for prostate cancer and hormonal
                  therapy for breast cancer are permitted (and will be administered as SOC).

         16. Patients' toxicities from previous therapies must have recovered to at least grade 1
             according to NCI CTCAE v5.0, except for toxicities described below, as long as they do
             not put at risk the patient's condition and do not require systemic immunosuppressive
             steroids at immunosuppressive doses, including but not limited to:

               -  Fatigue

               -  Alopecia

               -  Skin disorders

               -  Stable neuropathy

               -  Endocrinopathies requiring replacement treatment Note: For other medical
                  conditions, or for any other toxicity with a higher grade but controlled by
                  adequate treatment, prior discussion and agreement with the trial chair is
                  mandatory.

             Note: Patients may have undergone surgical procedures within the past 3 weeks, as long
             as all toxicities have recovered to grade 1 or less.

         17. For women of childbearing potential (WOCBP: sexually mature women who have not
             undergone a hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy, have not been naturally
             post-menopausal for at least 12 consecutive months or have a serum
             follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) &lt; 40 milli-international units per milliliter
             (mIU/ml):

               1. Agreement to follow instructions for method(s) of contraception for the couple
                  from screening until month 6 post start of NMA chemotherapy of the study.

               2. Negative pregnancy test (urine or serum) during screening.

         18. For men participating in the trial and their female partners: agreement to follow
             instructions for method(s) of contraception for the couple from screening until month
             6 post start of NMA chemotherapy of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with an active second malignancy, except for

               1. non-melanoma skin cancer that has been apparently cured or successfully resected

               2. carcinoma in situ as long as they have been adequately treated

               3. Any malignancy that can be adequately managed expectantly without compromising
                  prognosis, and after PI agreement..

             Patients who have a history of malignancy are not considered to have an active
             malignancy if they have completed therapy since at least 2 years and are considered by
             their treating investigator to be at ≤ 30% risk for relapse.

          2. Patients with known peritoneal metastases who have a recent history of intermittent
             bowel obstruction (even partial), unless such obstruction has been resolved. Agreement
             with the Trial Chair is mandatory.

          3. Patients with leptomeningeal carcinomatosis

          4. History of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis or evidence of active pneumonitis (any
             origin)

          5. History of recent myocardial infarction or unstable angina, either within six months
             of enrolment

          6. Documented Child-Pugh score of B or C for hepatocellular carcinoma patients with known
             underlying liver dysfunction

          7. Active severe systemic infections within four weeks prior to beginning of NMA
             chemotherapy.

          8. Patient requiring regular systemic immunosuppressive therapy (for example for organ
             transplantation, chronic rheumatologic disease); all immunosuppressive medications
             including but not limited to steroids, mycophenolate mofetil, azathioprine,
             methotrexate, thalidomide, and anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-alpha agents must have
             been discontinued within the last two weeks prior to starting NMA chemotherapy.

               1. Note: Use of inhaled or topical steroids or corticosteroid use for radiographic
                  procedures is permitted

               2. Note: The use of physiologic corticosteroid replacement therapy is permitted.

          9. History of severe immediate hypersensitivity reaction to any of the agents used in
             this study.

         10. History of immediate hypersensitivity reaction to aminoglycosides (e.g. gentamicin or
             streptomycin).

         11. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding because of the potentially dangerous effects
             of the treatment on the fetus or infant.

         12. Subjects for whom there are concerns that they will not reliably comply with the
             requirements for contraception should not be enrolled into the study.

         13. Any serious underlying medical condition that could interfere with study medication
             and potential adverse events.

         14. Any mental or other impairment that may compromise compliance with the requirements of
             the study.

         15. Patient participation in any other study currently receiving treatment. If the patient
             is in the follow-up period, he/she may be enrolled, as far as the elapsed time since
             the last previous treatment administration and the preparative regimen (NMA
             chemotherapy) is respected according to Inclusion Criteria n°15).

         16. Participation in a research project using radiation sources exceeding an effective
             dose of 5 millisievert (mSv) with no direct benefit within the 12 last months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Coukos, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lana Kandalaft, Pharm D, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+41213147823</phone>
    <email>do.ion.ref@chuv.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUV Oncology Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lausanne</city>
        <state>Vaud</state>
        <zip>1011</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>George Coukos</last_name>
      <phone>+41213140627</phone>
      <email>do.ion.ref@chuv.ch</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2020</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2020</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2020</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire Vaudois</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>George Coukos, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

