<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03992313</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANRS 12384</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03992313</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Versus Facility-based Services to Improve the Screening of Active HCV Infection in Cambodia</brief_title>
  <acronym>Cam-C</acronym>
  <official_title>Community Versus Facility-based Services to Improve the Screening of Active HCV Infection in Cambodia: a Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>French National Institute for Health and Medical Research-French National Agency for Research on AIDS and Viral Hepatitis (Inserm-ANRS)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Health Sciences, Phnom Penh, Cambodia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hopital Paul Brousse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fondation Mérieux</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>French National Institute for Health and Medical Research-French National Agency for Research on AIDS and Viral Hepatitis (Inserm-ANRS)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Principal objective is to compare the effectiveness of a community-based intervention to
      a facility-based intervention to improve the combined-testing uptake (Antibody + RNA) of HCV
      infection among general population aged more than 40 years old in Cambodia

      Secondary objectives :

        -  To compare the HCV antibody testing uptake between the 2 arms for the eligible
           population

        -  To compare the active case detection rate between the 2 arms for the eligible population

        -  To compare the linkage to care between the 2 arms for those with active infection

        -  To compare the cost-effectiveness of the two strategies
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Methodology: two-arms cluster-randomized controlled trial. Clusters are defined as a group of
      50 households

      Expected enrolment : 4500 patients in 80 clusters located in 2 provinces (Kompong Cham and
      Siem Reap)

      Intervention

      Arm 1: Facility-based testing intervention Community Health Workers (CHWs) will provide
      information inside their groups on the possibility to be tested in health centers for HCV
      infection. HCV screening will be done using the SD Bioline HCV RDT on a finger stick
      capillary whole blood. Results will be available in 15 minutes. In case of positive HCV RDT,
      an immediate blood sample collection will be done in health center and sent to Provincial
      Hospital to perform HCV RNA using GenXpert viral load assay on plasma. Results will be sent
      back to the health center that will be in charge to give result to the participant and to
      refer to care in case of active infection.

      Arm 2: Community-based testing intervention After a dedicated training, CHWs will do the SD
      Bioline HCV RDT on a finger stick capillary whole blood directly in the village of
      participants. In case of positive HCV RDT, 5 blood spots will be collected immediately on DBS
      and sent to Phnom Penh for HCV RNA extraction and amplification (Omunis). Results will be
      sent back to the referral health center of each cluster and CHWs will be in charge to give
      result to the participant and to refer to care in case of active infection.

      Treatment phase For positive HCV RNA, a rapid consultation will be planned. The baseline
      assessment will include questionnaires (risk behaviours and socio-economic status), clinical
      exam, blood sampling and liver ultrasound. Symptomatic cirrhotic patients will be referred to
      a National Hospital in Phnom Penh in a hepatology unit. For the others patients, DAA
      treatment using sofosbuvir and daclatasvir combination for 12 weeks will be proposed, after
      checking the result of creatinine and the possible drug-drug interactions. All adverse events
      will be assessed by the investigator and documented regardless of the possible causality with
      the concomitant treatments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Combined-testing uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of persons tested for HCV RDT AND HCV RNA and aware of their status among the total number of persons eligible residing in the region where the intervention takes place (measured and compared between the 2 arms)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HCV antibody testing uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>number of persons tested for HCV RDT and aware of their status among the total number of persons eligible residing in the region where the intervention takes place (measured and compared between the 2 arms)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Active case detection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>defined as the number of persons with HCV active infection (positive HCV Ab and positive HCV RNA) and results given and explained among the total number of persons eligible residing in the region where the intervention takes place (measured and compared between the 2 arms)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Linkage to care</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>the number of persons with at least one consultation in the Provincial Hospital among the estimated total number of persons with active infection residing in the region where the intervention takes place (measured and compared between the 2 arms)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>the number of people initiating HCV treatment among the total number of persons with active infection linked to care (measured for the total population and not compared)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Liver-related morbidity and mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with decompensated cirrhosis, HCC (measured for the total population and not compared)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained virologic response 12</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with sustained virologic response 12 weeks after discontinuation of treatment (SVR12) (measured for the total population and not compared)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment failure</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with treatment failure defined as absence of SVR12 or missing HCV-RNA at 12 weeks post-treatment (PT12) due to treatment discontinuation for AEs or death (measured for the total population and not compared)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4500</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Testing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Facility-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community Health Workers (CHWs) will provide information inside their groups on the possibility to be tested in health centers for HCV infection. HCV screening will be done using the SD Bioline HCV RDT on a finger stick capillary whole blood. Results will be available in 15 minutes. In case of positive HCV RDT, an immediate blood sample collection will be done in health center and sent to Provincial Hospital to perform HCV RNA using GenXpert viral load assay on plasma. Results will be sent back to the health center that will be in charge to give result to the participant and to refer to care in case of active infection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Community-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>After a dedicated training, CHWs will do the SD Bioline HCV RDT on a finger stick capillary whole blood directly in the village of participants. In case of positive HCV RDT, 5 blood spots will be collected immediately on DBS and sent to Phnom Penh for HCV RNA extraction and amplification (Omunis). Results will be sent back to the referral health center of each cluster and CHWs will be in charge to give result to the participant and to refer to care in case of active infection.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community-based HCV rapid test</intervention_name>
    <description>HCV rapid tests will be done in the village</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Facility-based HCV rapid test</intervention_name>
    <description>HCV rapid tests will be done in the health center</description>
    <arm_group_label>Facility-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plasmatic HCV viral load</intervention_name>
    <description>HCV viral load will be done in provincial hospital on plasma using GenXpert</description>
    <arm_group_label>Facility-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DBS HCV viral load</intervention_name>
    <description>HCV viral load will be done in Phnom Penh by DBS using Omunis kit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Community-based testing intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All persons aged more than 40 years old

          -  Residing in the study area

          -  Informed consent obtained with oral information given and explained and the consent
             form signed by the participant and the nurse hired by the study at the latest the time
             of the RDT realization

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known positive HCV status with previous HCV treatment

          -  Severe disease present at inclusion involving life threatening

          -  Concurrent participation in any other clinical study without written agreement of the
             two study teams
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vonthanak Saphonn, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Saglik Bilimleri Universitesi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Charles Duclos-Vallee, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Paul Brousse hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sansothy Neth, MD</last_name>
    <phone>85561898668</phone>
    <email>nsothy@uhs.edu.kh</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Olivier Segeral, MD</last_name>
    <phone>85512479313</phone>
    <email>olivier_segeral@uhs.edu.kh</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>June 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 18, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 18, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 18, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 18, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

