<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03999723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-18040929</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03999723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combining Active and Passive DNA Hypomethylation</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVI-3</acronym>
  <official_title>Combining Active and Passive DNA Hypomethylation: A Multicentre, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Phase II Study of the Efficacy and Safety of Oral Vitamin C in Combination With Azacitidine in Higher-Risk MDS, CMML-2 and Low-Blast Count AML</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kirsten Grønbæk</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Van Andel Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Karolinska University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Skane University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oslo University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Helsinki</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Royal Sussex County Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Southern California</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Copenhagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zealand University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aalborg University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Odense University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Technical University of Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aarhus University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicentre, randomized, parallel-group, placebo-controlled, double-blind phase 2
      study of the efficacy and safety of oral vitamin C supplement in combination with azacitidine
      in patients with higher-risk MDS, CMML-2 and low-blast count AML. The primary purpose is to
      investigate if oral vitamin C supplementation to azacitidine, compared with azacitidine +
      placebo, can increase the effectiveness of epigenetic therapy in patients with higher-risk
      myeloid malignancies, who are not candidates for allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation. Hence hereby, the investigators wish to clarify whether the standard of care
      in patients being treated with azacitidine should be changed by routinely adding oral vitamin
      C.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      EVI-3 is a phase 2 international, multicentre, randomized, parallel-group,
      placebo-controlled, double-blind study of the efficacy and safety of oral vitamin C
      supplement in combination with azacitidine (AZA) in patients with higher-risk myeloid
      malignancies with or without mutations in genes recurrently affected in myeloid malignancies.
      Treatment allocation is in 1:1 ratio by block randomization stratified by clinical site.
      Study entry is staggered. Patients are randomized to either oral vitamin C 1000 mg daily or
      placebo from start of AZA treatment until end of study (EOS) or until AZA treatment is
      discontinued at the discretion of the treating physician, whichever occurs earlier. The
      accrual time is estimated to 36 months and 6 months follow-up, thus, maximum treatment
      duration will be approximately 42 months. A total of 182 patients is planned for enrollment.

      Study visits are scheduled at baseline, after 1st AZA treatment cycle, after 6 AZA treatment
      cycles, and, if AZA treatment is continued, at EOS or end of AZA treatment. Evaluations at
      study visits include bone marrow investigation, peripheral blood tests, patient-reported
      outcome measures and adverse events. Bone marrow aspirate and peripheral blood will be
      collected for biobank at each study visit.

      All patients will undergo follow-up once yearly from EOS. Follow-up will include information
      on survival and disease progression from myelodysplastic syndrome (MDS) or chronic
      myelomonocytic leukemia (CMML) to acute myeloid leukemia (AML), if diagnosed following a
      clinical indication for a bone marrow test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 11, 2019</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A multicentre, randomized, parallel-group, placebo-controlled, double-blind phase 2 study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Double-blind masking (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, (some) Outcomes Assessors)</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of azacitidine (AZA) therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of AZA therapy in patients randomized to AZA + oral vitamin C (arm A) compared to patients randomized to AZA + placebo (arm B) assessed at end of study (EOS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events and serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number and ratio of patients with a (serious) adverse event in arm A vs. arm B assessed from the time of administration of intervention (day 1, AZA cycle 1 = D1/C1) to EOS. Total number of adverse events and serious adverse events and the number per year from D1/C1 to EOS in arm A vs. arm B. Number of patients discontinuing the intervention and discontinuation rate in arm A vs. arm B from D1/C1 to EOS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival in months in arm A vs. arm B calculated from the time of randomization to EOS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of overall response and rates of individual responses (as according to international consensus criteria), including best response, in arm A vs. arm B after 6 AZA cycles and at EOS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-reported outcome (PRO) measures</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in PRO measures including health-related quality of life scores (EORTC QLQ-C30 and Hematological Malignancy (HM)-PRO) from baseline to end of 1st AZA cycle, after 6 AZA cycles and EOS, if AZA treatment ongoing, respectively, in arm A vs. arm B. Numerical PRO scores after the 1st AZA cycle and after 6 AZA cycles (and EOS), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variant allele frequency (VAF) of mutated clones</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in VAF of mutated clones (in percentage points and in percentage) in bone marrow mononuclear cells from baseline to end of 6th AZA cycle and to end of treatment (if occurring before EOS) in arm A vs. arm B. Number and ratio of patients with appearance of new mutations between baseline and end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment) in arm A vs. arm B. Total number of new mutations in arm A vs. arm B from baseline to end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global 5-hydroxymethylcytosine (5-hmC)/5-methylcytosine (5-mC)</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in global 5-hmC/5-mC in bone marrow CD34+ cells from baseline to end of 1st AZA cycle, end of 6th AZA cycle and end of treatment (if occurring before EOS), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B. Global 5-hmC/5-mC in bone marrow CD34+ cells at end of 1st AZA cycle and end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Site specific 5-hmC/5-mC</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in 5-hmC/5-mC at specific loci at promoters/enhancers/long terminal repeats (LTRs) or at other regulatory genomic regions of tumor suppressors, oncogenes, genes involved in hematopoietic development or human endogenous retrovirus (HERV) in bone marrow CD34+ cells from baseline to end of 1st AZA cycle, end of 6th AZA cycle and end of treatment (if occurring before EOS), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B. Site specific 5-hmC/5-mC in bone marrow CD34+ cells at end of 1st AZA cycle and end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gene expression</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in expression of genes involved in viral defense pathways, cell differentiation and tumor suppression in bone marrow CD34+ cells from baseline end of 1st AZA cycle, end of 6th AZA cycle and end of treatment (if occurring before EOS), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B. Expression of genes involved in viral defense pathways, cell differentiation and tumor suppression in bone marrow CD34+ cells at end of 1st AZA cycle and end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mRNA expression of HERV and HERV specific T-cell responses</measure>
    <time_frame>0-42 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in levels of mRNA expression of HERV in bone marrow CD34+ cells and HERV specific T-cell responses from baseline to end of 1st AZA cycle, end of 6th AZA cycle and end of treatment (if occurring before EOS), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B. Levels of HERV mRNA in bone marrow CD34+ cells and HERV specific T-cell responses at end of 1st AZA cycle and end of 6th AZA cycle (and end of treatment), respectively, in arm A vs. arm B.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">182</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral vitamin C (ascorbic acid) will be given in a dose of 1000 mg daily (two capsules of 500 mg once daily) starting day 1 in the 1st azacitidine (AZA) cycle (D1/C1) and continuing until discontinuation of AZA or end of study, whichever occurs earlier.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will be administered orally as two capsules once daily that look and taste identical to the capsules containing vitamin C. Treatment will start day 1 in the 1st azacitidine (AZA) cycle (D1/C1) and continuing until discontinuation of AZA or end of study, whichever occurs earlier. The content of the placebo capsules is glucose monohydrate, potato starch, gelatin, magnesium stearate and talc.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin C</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral vitamin C (ascorbic acid) 1000 mg daily will be administered from day 1 in the 1st AZA cycle (D1/C1) and continued until discontinuation of AZA or EOS as combination treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vitamin C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ascorbic acid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules (two capsules once daily) will be administered from day 1 in the 1st AZA cycle (D1/C1) and continued until discontinuation of AZA or EOS.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Patients eligible for treatment with azacitidine with one of the following diagnoses
        according to World Health Organization 2016:

          -  MDS Higher-risk MDS according to the IPSS-R, i.e., intermediate- to very high-risk
             (IPSS-R score &gt; 3)

          -  CMML CMML with 10-29 percent marrow blasts without myeloproliferative disorder

          -  AML AML with 20-30 percent blasts (low-blast count AML)

        Note: Patients with therapy-related MDS are eligible if they have not received radiation or
        chemotherapy for six months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients eligible for allogeneic stem cell transplantation

          -  Prior therapy with hypomethylating agents

          -  Any matter constituting an exclusion criterion for treatment with azacitidine

          -  Patients receiving other active cancer treatment, including investigational agents,
             with the exception of hydroxyurea for white blood cell control and granulocyte
             colony-stimulating factor

          -  History of allergic reactions to ascorbic acid

          -  History of kidney or urinary tract stones requiring intervention within the past year

          -  Lack of ability to understand the information given, or lack of willingness to sign a
             written informed consent document

          -  Unwillingness to comply with the protocol

          -  Unwillingness to discontinue any and all use of vitamin C medication/supplementation
             including multivitamin at least 3 days (but preferably longer) prior to inclusion and
             baseline sampling

          -  Planned azacitidine treatment after allogeneic stem cell transplantation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirsten Grønbæk, Prof., MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stine Ulrik Mikkelsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amalie Bach Nielsen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kirsten Grønbæk, Prof., MD</last_name>
    <phone>+45 35 45 60 86</phone>
    <email>kirsten.groenbaek@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Astrid Østergaard Mortensen, BSc, Nurse</last_name>
    <phone>+45 35 45 60 80</phone>
    <email>astrid.oestergaard.mortensen.01@regionh.dk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aalborg University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aalborg</city>
        <zip>9100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marianne Tang Severinsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 97666745</phone>
      <email>m.severinsen@rn.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kirsten Grønbæk, Prof., MD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 35 45 60 86</phone>
      <email>kirsten.groenbaek@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Astrid Østergaard Mortensen, BSc, Nurse</last_name>
      <email>astrid.oestergaard.mortensen.01@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stine Ulrik Mikkelsen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amalie Bach Nielsen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herlev University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2730</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bo Kok Mortensen, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 38686483</phone>
      <email>bo.kok.mortensen@regionh.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Klas Raaschou-Jensen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+45 23221586</phone>
      <email>Klas.Raaschou-Jensen@rsyd.dk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aaronson NK, Ahmedzai S, Bergman B, Bullinger M, Cull A, Duez NJ, Filiberti A, Flechtner H, Fleishman SB, de Haes JC, et al. The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30: a quality-of-life instrument for use in international clinical trials in oncology. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1993 Mar 3;85(5):365-76.</citation>
    <PMID>8433390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goswami P, Oliva EN, Ionova T, Else R, Kell J, Fielding AK, Jennings DM, Karakantza M, Al-Ismail S, Lyness J, Collins GP, McConnell S, Langton C, Al-Obaidi MJ, Oblak M, Salek S. Paper and electronic versions of HM-PRO, a novel patient-reported outcome measure for hematology: an equivalence study. J Comp Eff Res. 2019 May;8(7):523-533. doi: 10.2217/cer-2018-0108. Epub 2019 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>31037971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2019</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2019</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 27, 2019</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 17, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kirsten Grønbæk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, MD, DMSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin C</keyword>
  <keyword>Ascorbic acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Azacitidine</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypomethylating agents</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelomonocytic, Juvenile</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ascorbic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

