<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on July 28, 2020</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03022578</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016-0443</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2018-01286</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-0443</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA016672</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03022578</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laser Interstitial Thermal Therapy and Lomustine in Treating Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma or Anaplastic Astrocytoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Laser Interstitial Thermal Therapy (LITT) in Recurrent Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well laser interstitial thermal therapy and lomustine work in
      treating patients with glioblastoma or anaplastic astrocytoma that has come back. Using laser
      to heat the tumor cells may help to kill them. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as lomustine,
      work in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by
      stopping them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Giving laser interstitial
      thermal therapy and lomustine may work better in treating patients with glioblastoma or
      anaplastic astrocytoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Determine the disease control rate at 6 months in patients with recurrent glioblastoma or
      isocitrate dehydrogenase (IDH)-wildtype anaplastic astrocytoma treated with Laser
      Interstitial Thermal Therapy (LITT) at recurrence, followed by salvage chemotherapy.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Estimate overall survival (OS) of patients with recurrent glioblastoma, or isocitrate
      dehydrogenase (IDH)-wildtype anaplastic astrocytoma treated with LITT at tumor recurrence,
      followed by salvage chemotherapy.

      II. Estimate time to progression (TTP) of patients with recurrent glioblastoma, or isocitrate
      dehydrogenase (IDH)-wildtype anaplastic astrocytoma that are treated with LITT at tumor
      recurrence, followed by salvage chemotherapy.

      III. Analyze volumetric data consisting of thermal damage threshold lines and overall tumor
      volume to determine any role of 'extent of ablation' in outcomes (OS and/or TTP).

      IV. Characterize the safety profile of LITT followed by treatment with lomustine chemotherapy
      in the recurrent disease setting, using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events
      (CTCAE) version 4.0.

      V. Assess the long-term steroid requirements following LITT, compared to historical controls.

      VI. Determine the radiographic evolution of LITT-treated glioblastoma over time, using
      conventional magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) (T1 pre and post-contrast images, T2-weighted
      images [T2WI], fluid attenuating inversion recovery [FLAIR] images) and advanced brain tumor
      imaging (ABTI) [magnetic resonance (MR) perfusion [dynamic susceptibility contrast (DSC),
      dynamic contrast enhancement (DCE) and arterial spin labeling (ASL)], MR-diffusion, and MR
      spectroscopy), to include quantitative tumor metrics (volumetric extent of ablation and
      Response Assessment in Neuro-Oncology [RANO] criteria).

      VII. Analyze health care utilization as measured by length of hospital stay following LITT
      (including inpatient rehabilitation care).

      VIII. Evaluate patients' functional status (using the Karnofsky performance score [KPS] and
      the occurrence of symptoms [using the MD Anderson Symptom Inventory-Brain Tumor Module
      (MDASI-BT[English])] self-reporting tool), and correlate to disease progression and tolerance
      to treatment.

      EXPLORATORY OBJECTIVES:

      I. Identify correlative tumor and peripheral blood molecular markers that impact outcomes,
      etc, and identify inflammatory/immunologic markers to assess neoantigen expression, etc, if
      sufficient tissue is available.

      II. Identify and characterize changes in tumor tissue following LITT, by analyzing and
      comparing pre- and post-procedure tissue samples, if sufficient tissue is available.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients undergo LITT at baseline and receive lomustine orally (PO) on day 1. Treatment with
      lomustine repeats every 42 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or
      unaccepted toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up every 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>N/A</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Simon's optimal two-stage design will be employed to evaluate the effect of the study regimen on disease control rate at 6 months. Will be estimated along with 95% confidence intervals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, such as mean, standard deviation, median, and range for continuous variables, frequency and proportion for categorical variables. Correlation will be assessed among continuous variables using Pearson or Spearman correlation coefficient, whichever is appropriate. Association between categorical variables will be examined by Chi-Squared test or Fisher's exact test when appropriate. Wilcoxon rank-sum test or Kruskal-Wallis test will be used to examine the difference on continuous variables between or among patient's characteristic groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, such as mean, standard deviation, median, and range for continuous variables, frequency and proportion for categorical variables. Correlation will be assessed among continuous variables using Pearson or Spearman correlation coefficient, whichever is appropriate. Association between categorical variables will be examined by Chi-Squared test or Fisher's exact test when appropriate. Wilcoxon rank-sum test or Kruskal-Wallis test will be used to examine the difference on continuous variables between or among patient's characteristic groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biomarkers in peripheral blood and tumor tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, such as mean, standard deviation, median, and range for continuous variables, frequency and proportion for categorical variables. Correlation will be assessed among continuous variables using Pearson or Spearman correlation coefficient, whichever is appropriate. Association between categorical variables will be examined by Chi-Squared test or Fisher's exact test when appropriate. Wilcoxon rank-sum test or Kruskal-Wallis test will be used to examine the difference on continuous variables between or among patient's characteristic groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory/immunologic profile</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, such as mean, standard deviation, median, and range for continuous variables, frequency and proportion for categorical variables. Correlation will be assessed among continuous variables using Pearson or Spearman correlation coefficient, whichever is appropriate. Association between categorical variables will be examined by Chi-Squared test or Fisher's exact test when appropriate. Wilcoxon rank-sum test or Kruskal-Wallis test will be used to examine the difference on continuous variables between or among patient's characteristic groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method and the comparison between or among patient's characteristic groups will be evaluated by log-rank test. The Cox regression model may be applied to assess the effect of covariates of interest on OS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be estimated using the Kaplan-Meier method and the comparison between or among patient's characteristic groups will be evaluated by log-rank test. The Cox regression model may be applied to assess the effect of covariates of interest on TTP.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized by frequency tables.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term steroid requirements</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will be summarized by frequency tables.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MD Anderson Symptom Inventory-Brain Tumor Module (MDASI-BT) data</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will summarize the MDASI-BT at each time point using descriptive statistics and evaluate the change of MDASI-BT over time and its correlation with response and/or treatment tolerance using linear mixed models, where random effects will be used to account for within-subject correlations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>IDH Family Wildtype</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Anaplastic Astrocytoma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent Glioblastoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (LITT, lomustine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients undergo LITT at baseline and receive lomustine PO on day 1. Treatment with lomustine repeats every 42 days for up to 6 cycles in the absence of disease progression or unaccepted toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laser Interstitial Thermal Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo LITT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (LITT, lomustine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LITT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lomustine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (LITT, lomustine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>1-(2-Chloroethyl)-3-cyclohexyl-1-nitrosourea</other_name>
    <other_name>1-Nitrosourea, 1-(2-chloroethyl)-3-cyclohexyl-</other_name>
    <other_name>Belustin</other_name>
    <other_name>Belustine</other_name>
    <other_name>CCNU</other_name>
    <other_name>Cecenu</other_name>
    <other_name>CeeNU</other_name>
    <other_name>Chloroethylcyclohexylnitrosourea</other_name>
    <other_name>Citostal</other_name>
    <other_name>Gleostine</other_name>
    <other_name>Lomeblastin</other_name>
    <other_name>Lomustinum</other_name>
    <other_name>Lucostin</other_name>
    <other_name>Lucostine</other_name>
    <other_name>N-(2-Chloroethyl)-N''-cyclohexyl-N-nitrosourea</other_name>
    <other_name>Prava</other_name>
    <other_name>RB-1509</other_name>
    <other_name>WR-139017</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically-proven, recurrent supratentorial grade IV
             glioblastoma (or grade III IDH-wildtype anaplastic astrocytoma), for which a complete
             surgical resection is unsafe due to location, shape, or size of the tumor. Diagnosis
             of recurrence will be established by biopsy and frozen section immediately prior to
             initiating LITT procedure. If findings on frozen section are not consistent with
             recurrence (glioblastoma or recurrent IDH-wildtype anaplastic astrocytoma), decision
             to proceed with LITT procedure will be at the discretion of the neurosurgeon (only
             patients with histologically-proven recurrent tumor will be evaluable for efficacy).

          -  All patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of this study. Patients must have signed an authorization for
             the release of their protected health information. Patients must be registered prior
             to treatment on study.

          -  Patients must have a Karnofsky performance score (KPS) &gt; 60.

          -  Patients must have received standard of care therapy with chemoradiation with
             temozolomide followed by adjuvant chemotherapy with temozolomide. Patients may have
             received one additional chemotherapy regimen (other than lomustine) in addition to
             adjuvant temozolomide prior to study entry (patients at either first or second
             recurrence are eligible).

          -  In the context of this clinical trial, a lesion suitable for LITT is single,
             enhancing, supratentorial, at least 2 cm from inner table of skull over the
             hemispheric convexity, and &gt; 1 cm, but &lt; 4 cm in cross-sectional dimension, including
             thalamic tumor (=&lt; 3 cm).

          -  Patients must have stable cardiovascular, neurovascular and neurological status, and
             be considered surgical candidates, as determined by any relevant pre-operative
             assessments, at the neurosurgeon's discretion.

          -  Patients must not be receiving concurrent anti-tumor treatment and must have recovered
             from toxicity of prior treatment. Minimum interval required: 1) &gt; 6 weeks following
             nitrosourea chemotherapy; 2) &gt; 4 weeks after recovering from any non-nitrosourea drug
             or systemic investigational agent; 3) &gt; 2 weeks after receiving any non-cytotoxic
             anti-tumor drug; 4) &gt; 4 weeks after receiving radiation therapy (&gt; 12 weeks following
             upfront concurrent chemoradiation); 5) &gt; 2 weeks following Optune device use.

          -  Patients must not have previously undergone an intracranial LITT procedure.

          -  White blood cell (WBC) &gt; 3,000/ul (performed within 14 days (+ 3 working days) prior
             to registration)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt; 1,500/mm^3 (performed within 14 days (+ 3 working
             days) prior to registration)

          -  Platelet count of &gt; 100,000/mm^3 (may be reached by transfusion) (performed within 14
             days (+ 3 working days) prior to registration)

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 10 gm/dl (may be reached by transfusion) (performed within 14 days (+ 3
             working days) prior to registration)

          -  Serum glutamic-oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) and bilirubin &lt; 2 times upper limit of
             normal (ULN) (erformed within 14 days (+ 3 working days) prior to registration)

          -  Creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL (performed within 14 days (+ 3 working days) prior to
             registration)

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative B-Human chorionic gonadotropin
             (HCG) documented within 7 days prior to registration and must agree to practice
             adequate contraception as defined below. Non-childbearing potential (i.e.,
             physiologically incapable of becoming pregnant), includes any female who has had:

               -  A hysterectomy

               -  A bilateral oophorectomy

               -  A bilateral tubal ligation

               -  Is post-menopausal: Subjects not using hormone replacement therapy (HRT) must
                  have experienced total cessation of menses for &gt;= 1 year and be greater than 45
                  years in age, OR, in questionable cases, have a follicle stimulating hormone
                  (FSH) value &gt; 40 mIU/mL and an estradiol value &lt; 40 pg/mL (&lt; 140 pmol/L).

          -  Subjects using HRT must have experienced total cessation of menses for &gt;= 1 year and
             be greater than 45 years of age OR have had documented evidence of menopause based on
             FSH and estradiol concentrations prior to initiation of HRT.

          -  Childbearing potential includes any female who has had a negative serum pregnancy test
             within 7 days of study registration, and agrees to use adequate contraception.
             Acceptable contraceptive methods, when used consistently and in accordance with both
             the product label and the instructions of the physician, are as follows:

               -  Complete abstinence from sexual intercourse for 14 days before starting
                  treatment, through the treatment, and for at least 1 month after the last dose of
                  temozolomide

               -  Oral contraceptive, either combined or progestogen alone. A second barrier method
                  is required during the first month of treatment with oral contraceptives

               -  Injectable progesterone

               -  Implants of levonorgestrel

               -  Estrogenic vaginal ring

               -  Percutaneous contraceptive patches

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS) with a documented failure
                  rate of less than 1% per year

               -  Male partner sterilization (vasectomy with documentation of azoospermia) prior to
                  the female subject's entry into the study, and this male is the sole partner for
                  that subject

               -  Double barrier method: condom and an occlusive cap (diaphragm or cervical/vault
                  caps) with a vaginal spermicidal agent (foam/gel/film/cream/suppository). Female
                  participants who are lactating should discontinue nursing prior to the first dose
                  of temozolomide and should refrain from nursing throughout the treatment period
                  and for 42 days following the last dose of lomustine.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must not have received prior treatment with bevacizumab.

          -  Patients must not have had prior treatment of glioblastoma with stereotactic
             radiosurgery, brachytherapy, or carmustine-impregnated wafers (Gliadel).

          -  Patients must not have symptoms attributed to mass effect of the tumor (despite
             corticosteroid treatment) that would be better treated with debulking surgery, or
             wherein surgical debulking in the first 30 days following LITT procedure would be
             anticipated for symptom management.

          -  Patients unable to undergo MRI are not eligible.

          -  Patients with progression of multifocal tumors or tumors involving the posterior fossa
             (brainstem and cerebellum) will be excluded, as will patients where the anticipated
             treatment margin will be within 5 mm of critical intracranial structures (e.g.,
             primary branches of cerebral vessels, dural sinuses, hypophysis or cranial nerves).

          -  Patients may not have undergone previous treatment with lomustine.

          -  Patients must not have any significant medical illnesses that in the investigator's
             opinion cannot be adequately controlled with appropriate therapy or would compromise
             the patient's ability to tolerate this therapy.

          -  Patients with a history of any other cancer (except non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in-situ of the cervix), unless in complete remission and off of all therapy
             for that disease for a minimum of 3 years are ineligible.

          -  Patients must not have active infection or serious intercurrent medical illness.

          -  Patients must not be pregnant/breast feeding and must agree to practice adequate
             contraception.

          -  Patients must not have uncontrolled hypertension (systolic &gt;180 mm hg or diastolic &gt;
             100 mg Hg), angina pectoris, cardiac dysrhythmia, or recent (within 6 weeks)
             intracranial hemorrhage.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barbara J O'Brien</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Barbara J. O'Brien</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-2883</phone>
    <email>bjobrien@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>M D Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Barbara J. O'Brien</last_name>
      <phone>713-792-2883</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Barbara J. O'Brien</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2019</verification_date>
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2019</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2019</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2019</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Astrocytoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lomustine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

